<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Networked SIS Epidemics with Awareness</title>
				<funder ref="#_qVHXqSW">
					<orgName type="full">ARO</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">KAUST</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-07-12">12 Jul 2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Keith</forename><surname>Paarporn</surname></persName>
							<email>kpaarporn@gatech.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Georgia Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30332</postCode>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<region>GA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ceyhun</forename><surname>Eksin</surname></persName>
							<email>ceyhuneksin@gatech.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Georgia Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30332</postCode>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<region>GA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Georgia Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<region>GA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Joshua</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Weitz</surname></persName>
							<email>jsweitz@gatech.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Georgia Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<region>GA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">School of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Georgia Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<region>GA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jeff</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Shamma</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Georgia Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30332</postCode>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<region>GA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Computer, Electrical and Mathematical Sciences and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">King Abdullah University of Science and Technology (KAUST)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Thuwal Kingdom</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Networked SIS Epidemics with Awareness</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-07-12">12 Jul 2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1607.02502v2[cs.SI]</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T00:52+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We study an SIS epidemic process over a static contact network where the nodes have partial information about the epidemic state. They react by limiting their interactions with their neighbors when they believe the epidemic is currently prevalent. A node's awareness is weighted by the fraction of infected neighbors in their social network, and a global broadcast of the fraction of infected nodes in the entire network. The dynamics of the benchmark (no awareness) and awareness models are described by discrete-time Markov chains, from which mean-field approximations (MFA) are derived. The states of the MFA are interpreted as the nodes' probabilities of being infected. We show a sufficient condition for existence of a "metastable", or endemic, state of the awareness model coincides with that of the benchmark model. Furthermore, we use a coupling technique to give a full stochastic comparison analysis between the two chains, which serves as a probabilistic analogue to the MFA analysis. In particular, we show that adding awareness reduces the expectation of any epidemic metric on the space of sample paths, e.g. eradication time or total infections. We characterize the reduction in expectations in terms of the coupling distribution. In simulations, we evaluate the effect social distancing has on contact networks from different random graph families (geometric, Erdős-Renyi, and scale-free random networks).</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Mathematical models of epidemic spreading over networks have been extensively studied. Models characterize how the spatial features induced by network structure affects epidemic spread ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>). The simplest formulation for such processes is the susceptible-infected-susceptible (SIS) model, where an individual is either infected or susceptible to infection. In such models, there is a threshold determining whether the epidemic eradicates quickly or persists for a long time. Specifically, δ/β &gt; λ max (A) (β is the disease transmission rate, δ the healing rate, and λ max (A) the largest eigenvalue of the network adjacency matrix) is a sufficient condition for the disease to eradicate exponentially fast. The opposite strict inequality is a necessary condition for the disease to persist for a long period of time. The steady state in this regime is often referred to as the endemic or metastable state. How to devise control strategies in this regime is both an important research and policy question.</p><p>A commonly studied control strategy is budgeted vaccine allocation, where the administration of vaccines among central nodes in the network optimally inhibits the epidemic of Saudi Arabia jeff.shamma@kaust.edu.sa <ref type="bibr">([8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>). In these situations, a central authority selects individuals to vaccinate and hence is required to have knowledge of the network structure. In game-theoretic settings, individuals decide for themselves whether or not to vaccinate based on an assessment of risks and benefits ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>). However, these models do not account for social behavior during the course of an epidemic, which can significantly slow epidemic spread without the aid of vaccines.</p><p>With the widespread availability of social media and news outlets on the internet and television, individuals may be wellinformed about the current state of ongoing epidemics and how to take precautionary measures to avoid getting sick. In the recent 2009 H1N1 Influenza pandemic, people responded to public service announcements by increasing the frequency of washing hands, staying at home when they or loved ones were sick, or avoiding large public gatherings <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. In the recent Ebola outbreak in West Africa, a combination of quarantining and sanitary burial methods were shown to significantly reduce the rate of virus spread <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. These precautions and social distancing actions effectively limit epidemic spread. Individuals' distancing actions depend on the extent of how informed they are. The dissemination and exchange of information influences the public's behavior, affecting the course of the epidemic itself, in turn affecting the public's behavior again <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. This feedback loop allows epidemic spreading to coevolve with human social behavior, inducing complex dynamics.</p><p>Recent research effort has focused on understanding the complexities that arise when incorporating human behavioral elements into existing models of epidemic spreading. A review of the recent literature can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. Such models present general challenges for characterizing decentralized and dynamic protection measures and also capture a realistic aspect of disease spread in society. When individuals take social distancing actions based on the level of information they have, they reduce contact with others and the epidemic prevalence reduces significantly ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>). They can become aware of the epidemic by communicating with their social contacts or by a global broadcast ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>). Other actions include switching one's contact links, giving rise to a coevolving network <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. Endowing individuals with local prevalence-based awareness highlights the role of network effects ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>).</p><p>In this work, we study a networked SIS process with dynamically distributed information and social distancing actions. The information the agents receive comes from their social contacts and a global broadcast about the current state of the epidemic. An agent's social distancing action reduces its contact network interactions, the magnitude of which depends on how informed it is. We prove awareness reduces the endemic level, but cannot improve the epidemic threshold for persistence. In addition, we provide a stochastic comparison analysis between the awareness and benchmark (without awareness) processes using a coupling technique. This establishes an inequality between expectations of certain epidemic metrics (e.g. eradication time, cumulative infected), as well as the closed-form difference. We are also interested in studying which combinations of network structure and awareness are most effective. The results extend prior work by the same authors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, where the mean-field approximation and coupling technique were initially studied.</p><p>The paper is organized as follows. In Section II, we describe a networked SIS epidemic process in discrete time, which we modify by incorporating a dynamic form of agent awareness and social distancing. In Section III, we introduce mean-field approximations on the probabilities of infection and prove the epidemic threshold for persistence with distancing remains the same as without. Section IV provides a stochastic comparison analysis between the benchmark and awareness Markov chains through a coupling technique. In Section V, we explore through simulations which random graph families are effective at restricting epidemic spread and prevalence when social distancing is a factor. Section VI gives concluding remarks. Proofs of some of the results are given in the Appendix. Notation: Z + = N ∪ {0} is the set of nonnegative integers. The all zeros and all ones vector in R n is written 0 n and 1 n , respectively. For x, y ∈ R n we write x y if x i ≤ y i for all i, and x ≺ y if x i &lt; y i . To isolate a particular coordinate i, we write</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">x = (x -i , x i ) ∈ R n , where x -i = {x j : j = i} ∈ R n-1 .</formula><p>P(E) is the power set of some set E. The complement of the set E is written E c . In probabilistic settings, we write χ E (•) as the indicator on the event E, i.e. χ E (x) = 1 if x ∈ E and zero otherwise.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. NETWORKED SIS MODELS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Benchmark SIS Model</head><p>We introduce a model of epidemic spread which we refer to as the benchmark model (studied in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, and Section 5 of <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>). Consider the set of nodes N = {1, . . . , n} interconnected by a set of edges E C . Epidemic spread occurs in discrete time steps t = 0, 1, . . . over the undirected graph G C = (N , E), whose n × n adjacency matrix is defined for any i, j ∈ N , as</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">[A C ] ij = 1 if (i, j) ∈ E C</formula><p>and 0 otherwise. The graph G C is called the contact network. An agent i ∈ N is either susceptible to the disease or infected by it. The epidemic states are defined as Ω {0, 1} n . For any s ∈ Ω and i ∈ N , either s i = 0, meaning agent i is susceptible, or s i = 1, meaning it is infected. A susceptible node i can contract the disease from neighboring agents in the contact network, N C i {j ∈ N : (i, j) ∈ E C }. When agent i is susceptible in the epidemic state is s ∈ Ω (s i = 0), its probability of getting infected in the next time step due to an interaction with its neighbor j ∈ N C i is given by βs j where β ∈ (0, 1) is the transmission probability of the disease. Hence, an individual can only contract the disease from an infected neighbor. Agent i interacts with each of its neighbors independently. Therefore, i's probability of not becoming infected in the next time step is Consequently, the probability i becomes infected is</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">p i 00 (s) 1 -p i 01 (s). (<label>1</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">s i = 1 s i = 0 δp i 00 1 -δp i</formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">p i 01 (s) 1 - j∈N C i (1 -βs j )<label>(2)</label></formula><p>If i is infected in state s (s i = 1), it becomes susceptible in the next time step with probability δp i 00 (s), where δ ∈ (0, 1) is the healing probability. Thus, for an infected node to become susceptible, it must heal and not get re-infected by its neighbors. Agent i's transition probabilities are summarized in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>, and described by P i : Ω × {0, 1} → [0, 1] defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">If s i = 0, P i (s, 0) = p i 00 (s) P i (s, 1) = p i 01 (s)<label>(3)</label></formula><p>If</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">s i = 1, P i (s, 0) = δp i 00 (s) P i (s, 1) = 1 -δp i 00 (s)<label>(4)</label></formula><p>For each i ∈ N and s ∈ Ω, the P i define the benchmark SIS Markov chain over Ω by the 2 n × 2 n transition matrix K with elements K(s, s )</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">n i=1 P i (s, s i ), ∀s, s ∈ Ω<label>(5)</label></formula><p>This chain has one absorbing state, the all-susceptible state o {0} n .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Awareness SIS Model</head><p>We modify the benchmark model to take into account the agents' awareness of the current epidemic state. The information agent i receives comes from two sources: the proportion of infected neighbors in its local social network and a global broadcast of the proportion of infected nodes in the entire network. The social network is a graph G I = (N , E I ) with the same nodes as G C but with different edges, representing the nodes' social communication links. The set of i's neighbors in G I is written N I i . The information is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">µ i (s) α |N I i | j∈N I i s j + 1 -α n n j=1 s j , ∀s ∈ Ω<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where α ∈ [0, 1] is a parameter that governs the trust nodes place in information from their social contacts. Consequently, node i reduces its interactions with its physical neighbors through the social distancing action</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">a i (s) 1 -µ i (s),<label>(7)</label></formula><p>which reduces its susceptible-to-infected probability (2) to</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">p i 01,d (s) 1 - j∈N C i (1 -βa i (s)s j ).<label>(8)</label></formula><p>We similarly define p i 00,d (s) 1p i 01,d (s). An infected agent's probability of recovering becomes δp i 00,d (s). Note for all s ∈ Ω, p i 01,d (s) ≤ p i 01 (s). Combined with the social distancing behaviors a i , the local awareness spread dynamics in (6) make the effect of user behavior on its infection probability endogenous to the benchmark chain model through a negative feedback loop. We define the P d i analogously to (3) and (4):</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">If s i = 0, P d i (s, 0) = p i 00,d (s) P d i (s, 1) = p i 01,d (s)<label>(9)</label></formula><p>If</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">s i = 1, P d i (s, 0) = δp i 00,d (s) P d i (s, 1) = 1 -δp i 00,d (s)<label>(10)</label></formula><p>Thus, the P d i define the distancing Markov chain over Ω by the transition matrix K d with elements</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">K d (s, s ) n i=1 P d i (s, s i ), ∀s, s ∈ Ω<label>(11)</label></formula><p>whose unique absorbing state is also o, the all-susceptible state. The feedback between social distancing actions and epidemic states is illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>.</p><p>Remark 1. Our model of awareness captures the different ways an agent may receive information about an ongoing epidemic from the media. Large media corporations and public health institutions such as the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) and the World Health Organization (WHO) often report an estimated total number of people infected nationwide or globally at a given time, and this information is disseminated amongst the population. Information is also exchanged through one's personalized social links, which can range beyond a person's geographic location. Thus, a node's awareness is composed of a linear combination of both sources of information, as given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. MEAN-FIELD APPROXIMATIONS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Derivation</head><p>We derive a mean-field approximation (MFA) of the Markovian dynamics described in the previous section. The MFA is a deterministic, discrete-time dynamic system with an ndimensional state space [0, 1] n , which is interpreted to be each node's probability of being infected at any given time.</p><p>Here, we write s t ∈ Ω as the epidemic state at time t = 0, 1, . . .. Indeed, consider the node-level stochastic state transition update</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">s t+1 i = s t i B(1 -δp i 00,d (s t )) + (1 -s t i )B(p i 01,d (s t ))<label>(12</label></formula><p>) of the distancing chain where B(λ) denotes a Bernoulli random variable with parameter λ ∈ [0, 1]. For shorthand, we write x t i Pr(s t i = 1) for the probability node i is infected at time t. Taking the probability of both sides equaling one,</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">x t+1 i = Pr(B(1 -δp i 00,d (s t )) = 1|s t i = 1)Pr(s t i = 1) + • • • Pr(B(p i 01,d (s t )) = 1|s t i = 0)Pr(s t i = 0) = x t i (1 -δp i 00,d (s t )) + (1 -x t i )p i 01,d (s t ) = x t i (1 -δ) + (1 -(1 -δ)x t i )p i 01,d (s t )<label>(13)</label></formula><p>Note the expression for x t+1 i still depends stochastically on the state s t . To obtain a mean-field approximation of x t+1 i , we simply replace the state s t with x t (the n-vector with components x t i ) in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>. Thus, by redefining x t+1 i to obey this approximation and extending the domain of</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">µ i (•), a i (•) and p i 01,d (•) from {0, 1} n to [0, 1</formula><p>] n , we have the following approximate dynamics</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">x t+1 i = x t i (1 -δ) + (1 -(1 -δ)x t i )p i 01,d (x t )<label>(14)</label></formula><p>on the time evolution of node i's probability of being infected.</p><p>Stacking the dynamics for each node into a vector, we obtain a mapping φ :</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">[0, 1] n → [0, 1] n where φ i (x) = x i (1 -δ) + (1 -(1 -δ)x i )p i 01,d (x) and x t+1 = φ(x t</formula><p>). This MFA of the distancing chain is in contrast to the MFA of the benchmark chain,</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">x t+1 i = x t i (1 -δ) + (1 -(1 -δ)x t i )p i 01 (x t )<label>(15)</label></formula><p>which is studied thoroughly in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. It is derived in the same manner, and is described by the mapping ψ :</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">[0, 1] n → [0, 1] n with ψ i (x) = x i (1 -δ) + (1 -(1 -δ)x i )p i 01 (x) and x t+1 = ψ(x t ).</formula><p>We make a few remarks on the basic structure of these two mappings. They are nonlinear, continuous mappings satisfying</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">φ(x) ≺ ψ(x) whenever x ∈ [0, 1] n \0 n and α ∈ [0, 1). Also, φ(0 n ) = ψ(0 n ) = 0 n .</formula><p>Linearization of φ and ψ about the origin yields the same Jacobian matrix, βA C + (1δ)I, and hence the same linearized dynamics x t+1 = (βA C + (1δ)I)x t . The linear dynamics serve as an upper bound to both <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>. Therefore, if λ max (βA C + (1δ)I) &lt; 1, the origin is a globally stable fixed point and it is an unstable fixed point if λ max (βA C + (1δ)I) &gt; 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Existence of a Non-trivial Fixed Point</head><p>We now provide a sufficient condition for the existence of a non-trivial fixed point ( 0 n , the n-vector of zeros) of φ.</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">Theorem 1. If λ max (βA C + (1 -δ)I n ) &gt; 1,</formula><p>there exists a nontrivial fixed point for φ.</p><p>The existence of such a fixed point suggests the epidemic has an endemic state, where the disease spreads fast enough to sustain an epidemic in the network. Our condition coincides with the condition for existence, uniqueness, and global asymptotic stability of the non-trivial fixed point q * of ψ, which is λ max (βA C + (1δ)I) &gt; 1, i.e. when the origin in the linearized dynamics is unstable (Theorem 5.1, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>). This condition incorporates the factors that contribute to the rate of spreading -δ, β, and the contact network A C . The proof makes use of the following lemmas. Lemma 1 (Lemma 3.1, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>). There exists a vector ν</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">0 n such that (βA C -δI n )ν 0 n if and only if λ max (βA C + (1 - δ)I n ) &gt; 1.</formula><p>The connectedness assumption for G C is necessary for the above Lemma because the proof applies the Perron-Frobenius theorem for nonnegative irreducible matrices. The next result is an equivalent formulation of Brouwer's fixed point theorem. Lemma 2. (Theorem 4.2.3, <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>): Suppose f i : D n → R, i = 1, . . . , n are continuous mappings, where</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">D n = {x ∈ R n : x i ∈ [ i , u i ], ∀i}</formula><p>for real numbers i , u i . We also define the set</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">D -i = {x -i ∈ R n-1 : x j ∈ [ j , u j ] ∀j = i}</formula><p>If for every i and for all x -i ∈ D -i ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">f i (x 1 , . . . , i , . . . , x n ) = f i (x -i , i ) ≥ 0 (16) f i (x 1 , . . . , u i , . . . , x n ) = f i (x -i , u i ) ≤ 0,<label>(17)</label></formula><p>then there exists a point x * ∈ D n such that f i (x * ) = 0, for all i = 1, . . . , n.</p><p>The final lemma needed is a technical result for the meanfield mappings φ i . Lemma 3. For each i ∈ N , define the maps</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">f i : [0, 1] n → R f i (x) φ i (x) -x i = -δx i + (1 -(1 -δ)x i )p i 01,d (x)<label>(18)</label></formula><p>Then for any i ∈ N and</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">x -i ∈ [0, 1] n-1 , the function f i (x -i , •) has a unique root c * i (x -i ) ∈ [0, 1) which depends continuously on x -i . Furthermore, one can find a sequence x k -i → 0 n-1 s.t. c * i (x k -i</formula><p>) is monotonically decreasing to 0.</p><p>Proof. For any i ∈ N and</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">x -i ∈ [0, 1] n-1 , f i (x -i , 0) = p i 01,d (x -i , 0) ≥ 0. (<label>19</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_31">)</formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">f i (x -i , 1) = δ(p i 01,d (x -i , 1) -1) &lt; 0. (<label>20</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_33">)</formula><p>The function</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">f i (x -i , •) is strictly decreasing: for a, b ∈ [0, 1] s.t. a &lt; b, f i (x -i , a) -f i (x -i , b) is given by (b -a)(δ + (1 -δ)p i 01,d (x -i , b)) + • • • + (1 -a(1 -δ))(p i 01,d (x -i , a) -p i 01,d (x -i , b)) &gt; 0.</formula><p>This follows because p i 01,d (x -i , x i ) is decreasing in x i (x i contributes to global awareness). Hence for every x -i . To see this, observe that</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">x -i ∈ [0, 1] n-1 , there is a unique c * i (x -i ) ∈ [0, 1) s.t. f i (x -i , c * i (x -i )) = 0, and c * i (x -i ) depends continuously on D n φ + Ri(εν) εν 0 1 u u1 n-1 x i x -i φ + i ν c * i (x -i ) 1 n-1 c * i (εν -i ) p *</formula><formula xml:id="formula_36">c * i (x -i ) ∈ [0, 1) is a root of the equation (1 -(1 -δ)x i )   1 - j∈N C i (1 -a i (x -i , x i )βx j )   -δx i = 0,<label>(21)</label></formula><p>which is a polynomial in x i . The coefficients of the polynomial depend continuously on x -i ∈ [0, 1] n-1 , and the roots of any polynomial are continuous with respect to its coefficients. Consequently, for any sequence</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">x k -i → 0 n-1 , c * i (x k -i ) → c * i (0 n-1 )</formula><p>= 0 by continuity. This allows us to select a subsequence of x k -i such that c * i is monotonically decreasing along the subsequence.</p><p>We are now ready to prove the main result of this section.</p><p>Proof of Theorem 1:. Let the mappings f i , i ∈ N be as in Lemma 3. We need to verify ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_27">17</ref>) hold for all i and for choices of i , u i satisfying 0 &lt; i &lt; u i . This ensures the awareness dynamic φ has a fixed point other than the origin. Choose u i = u where u satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">max i∈N max x-i∈[0,1] n-1 c * i (x -i ) &lt; u &lt; 1.<label>(22)</label></formula><p>Then for all</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">x -i ∈ [0, u] n-1 , f i (x -i , u) &lt; 0 (23) since u &gt; c * i (x -i ).</formula><p>Thus, (17) holds, regardless of the choice of i . However, it remains to find the i &gt; 0 s.t. ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) is satisfied. Let f (x) [f 1 (x), . . . , f n (x)] T and define the sets</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">φ + i {x ∈ [0, 1] n : f i (x) ≥ 0}, φ + n j=1 φ + j (24)</formula><p>The Jacobian of f about the origin is (βA C -δI n ). By Lemma 1, there exists a vector ν 0 n such that (βA C -δI n )ν 0 n . Consequently for sufficiently small ε &gt; 0,</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">f (εν) 0 n ,<label>(25)</label></formula><p>or εν ∈ φ + . We also define the set</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">R i (x -i ) {y ∈ R n : y i ∈ [0, c * i (x -i )], y j ∈ [x j , u], j = i} (26) If εν i ≤ c * i (εν -i ) and R i (εν) ⊂ φ + i , then (16) is satisfied, i.e. f i (x -i , εν i ) ≥ 0 on D -i = {εν -i</formula><p>x -i u1 n-1 } for ε sufficiently small. We already have</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">εν i ≤ c * i (εν -i ) because εν ∈ φ + ⊂ φ + i . To show R i (εν) ⊂ φ + i , by Lemma 3 we can find a sequence ε k ν ∈ φ + with ε k → 0 s.t. c * i (ε k ν -i</formula><p>) is monotonically decreasing to 0. By stopping at a large enough k, we can take a ε small enough such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">c * i (εν -i ) = min x-i∈D-i c * i (x -i )<label>(27)</label></formula><p>Consequently, R i (εν) ⊂ φ + i . Choosing ε small enough to satisfy <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> for all i ∈ N verifies ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) by using <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> for an illustration of the proof. By Lemma 2, φ has a fixed point contained in D n .</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">D n = {x ∈ R n : x j ∈ [εν j , u]}. See Figure</formula><p>The condition of Theorem 1 is independent of the awareness parameter α and the structure of the information network G I . Hence, social distancing alone cannot restore stability of the disease-free equilibrium point. However, social distancing lowers the overall metastable state of an epidemic. Corollary 1. If q * 0 n is the unique nontrivial fixed point of ψ, then any nontrivial fixed point p * of φ satisfies p * ≺ q * whenever α ∈ [0, 1).</p><p>Proof. Define the sets ψ + i and ψ + similarly as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref>. It was shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> that q * is the unique maximal element of ψ + , i.e q * q, ∀q ∈ ψ + , q = q * . Observe φ(x) ≺ ψ(x) for any x ∈ [0, 1] n \0 n . Let x ∈ φ + , x = 0 n . Then x φ(x) ≺ ψ(x), so x ∈ ψ + . Therefore, φ + ⊂ ψ + , and since p * ∈ φ + for any nontrivial fixed point of φ, p * ≺ q * . The mean-field analysis of this section reveals the qualitative dynamics not addressed by an absorbing Markov chain analysis. Since the all-susceptible state is the unique absorbing state and accessible from every other state, the disease eradicates in finite time with probability one. This answers what happens in the long-run, whereas the MFA analysis answers what happens before this eventuality. The MFA analysis concurs with what is observed in simulations of the Markov chain dynamics -fast convergence to an endemic "metastable" state that persists for a very long time before eradication. Numerical simulations suggest stability of one particular nontrivial fixed point p * of φ. A characterization of these fixed points for different random graph families is given in Section V.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. STOCHASTIC COMPARISON BETWEEN AWARENESS</head><p>AND BENCHMARK MODEL In this section, we use the properties of monotone couplings to prove that adding awareness reduces the expectation of any increasing random variable quantifying an epidemic metric (e.g. absorption time, total infections), and that the benchmark chain dominates the distancing chain in terms of a partial ordering on sample paths. These results serve as a probabilistic analogue to the conclusions made in Section III about the strict ordering of the nontrivial fixed points in the corresponding mean-field approximations. Here, we have a closed form expression for the reduction whereas in Corollary 1, only an inequality relation is established. First, we provide relevant definitions and basic preliminary results of monotone couplings. For a full reference on monotone coupling, see Ch 4 of <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Monotone couplings</head><p>Consider a general countable space X. Recall a partially ordered set (X, X ) is the set X together with a relation X among its elements which satisfies for all x, y, and z ∈ X,</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">• x X x • If x X y and y X z, then x X z • If x X</formula><p>y and y X x, then x = y. Definition 1. Let p 1 , p 2 be probability measures on a measurable space (X, F) and suppose (X, X ) is a partially ordered set. A monotone coupling of p 1 , p 2 is a probability measure p on (X 2 , F 2 ) such that for all x , y ∈ X, x X y p(x, y ) = p 2 (y ) and y X x p(x , y) = p 1 (x ). (28) Thus, for any x, y ∈ X s.t x X y, p(x, y) = 0, and the marginals of p are p 1 , p 2 .</p><p>Example 1. For an illustrative example of monotone coupling, consider two biased coins where the biases q A , q B &lt; 1 for landing heads satisfy q A &lt; q B . The coupling is a joint distribution assigned to the pair of coin flips to ensure the q A coin can never land heads with the q B coin landing tails, while the marginal coin flip probabilities remain the same. Specifically, define p X (0) = 1q X , p X (1) = q X for X ∈ {A, B}. Also, define p AB : {0, 1} 2 → [0, 1] by</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">         p AB (0, 0) = 1 -q B p AB (0, 1) = q B -q A p AB (1, 0) = 0 p AB (1, 1) = q A (29)</formula><p>Checking <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref>, the marginals are such that b≥1 p AB (1, b) = q A , a≤1 p AB (a, 1) = q B and b≥0 p AB (0, b) = 1q A , a≤0 p AB (a, 0) = 1-q B . Thus, p AB is a monotone coupling of p A , p B .</p><p>We say a function Z : X → R is increasing in X if whenever x X y, Z(x) ≤ Z(y). The next result characterizes the difference in expectations of increasing random variables between the marginals of a monotone coupling. Proposition 1. Keeping the notation of Definition 1, suppose p is a monotone coupling of p 1 , p 2 . If a random variable Z :</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">X → Z + is increasing in X, then E p2 (Z) -E p1 (Z) = ∞ τ =0 p(Z c τ , Z τ )<label>(30)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">Z τ = {x : Z(x) &gt; τ }.</formula><p>Proof. Consider the following quantities:</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">p(Z τ , Z τ ) = x∈Zτ y∈Zτ p(x, y) = x∈Zτ y X x p(x, y) = p 1 (Z τ ) (31) p(X, Z τ ) = p 2 (Z τ )<label>(32)</label></formula><p>The second sum over {y ∈ Z τ } can be replaced with {y X x} in (31) because 1) for any x ∈ Z τ , we have {y : y X x} ⊂ Z τ ; and 2) since p is a monotone coupling, for any y ∈ Z τ s.t. y X x, p(x, y) = 0. The last equality of <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31)</ref> follows from <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref>. Since (X, Z τ ) ⊃ (Z τ , Z τ ) we can write</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">p 2 (Z τ ) -p 1 (Z τ ) = p(X, Z τ ) -p(Z τ , Z τ ) = p((X, Z τ )\(Z τ , Z τ )) = p(Z c τ , Z τ )</formula><p>Equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_48">30</ref>) immediately follows.</p><p>Example 2. Consider the biased coins of Example 1. One can extend this example to sequences of m ≥ 2 flips, {0, 1} m with the partial order x y if</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">x i ≤ y i , i = 1, . . . , m, for x, y ∈ {0, 1} m . Define p X (x) = m k=1 p X (x k ), X ∈ {A, B}<label>(33)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_53">p AB (x, y) = m k=1 p AB (x k , y k ).<label>(34)</label></formula><p>Then p AB is a monotone coupling of p A , p B . For x ∈ {0, 1} m , let Z(x) = m i=1 x i be the random variable of the number of heads for any given toss sequence. Then Z is increasing in {0, 1} m . By Proposition 1,</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">E p B (Z) -E p A (Z) = m τ =0 p AB (Z c τ , Z τ ).<label>(35)</label></formula><p>Of course, one could trivially compute the above as m(q Bq A ) since the distribution of Z is Bernoulli. However, Proposition 1 generalizes the difference for any increasing Z + -valued random variable over a partially ordered set.</p><p>The notion of stochastic domination is also relevant in our comparison analysis. Definition 2. An upper set I is a non-empty subset of (X, X ) that satisfies the following property: if x ∈ I and y X x, then y ∈ I. Let p 1 , p 2 be two probability measures on (X, F). Then p 2 stochastically dominates p 1 , written as p 2 p 1 , if for any upper set I ⊂ X, p 1 (I) ≤ p 2 (I).</p><p>Our comparison between benchmark and distancing chains falls into the framework of the above analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Sample path comparison analysis</head><p>Our main result provides a construction of a monotone coupling between the benchmark and distancing probability distributions on sample paths. Definition 3. A sample path is a sequence g = {g t } t∈Z+ such that g t ∈ Ω and K(g t , g t+1 ) &gt; 0 for all t ≥ 0, and there is a</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">t |s t | T (h) T (g) h g</formula><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>: A pair of sample paths (h, g) drawn from Φπ.</p><p>T &lt; ∞ such that g T = o. The set of sample paths is denoted by Γ.</p><p>The absorption time T : Γ → Z + of a sample path g is given by T (g) min{t :</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">g t = o}. (<label>36</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_57">)</formula><p>Thus for all g ∈ Γ, T (g) &lt; ∞. Also, g t = o and K(g t , g t+1 ) = 1 for all t ≥ T (g). Note that Γ is countable since it is the countable union of the finite sets {g : T (g) = t} for t = 0, 1, 2, . . .. The distribution µ π : P(Γ) → [0, 1] on sample paths under the benchmark SIS chain with starting distribution π ∈ ∆(Ω) is given, for any A ∈ P(Γ), by</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">µ π (A) g∈A π(g 0 ) T (g)-1 t=0 K(g t , g t+1 )<label>(37)</label></formula><p>and similarly under the distancing chain by</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">ν π (A) g∈A π(g 0 ) T (g)-1 t=0 K d (g t , g t+1 ).<label>(38)</label></formula><p>Also, note that Γ is defined to exclude the set of sample paths that are never absorbed, {g :</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">g t = o, ∀t ∈ Z + }.</formula><p>These are infinite sequences that never terminate, and therefore are uncountable. The probabilities µ π , ν π , however are welldefined on Γ without such sample paths:</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">g∈Γ µ π (g) = ∞ t=0 µ π ({g : T (g) = t}) (39) = s∈Ω π(s) ∞ t=0 r s (Q t ) -r s (Q t+1 ) (40) = 1 (41)</formula><p>Here, Q is the 2 n -1×2 n -1 sub-stochastic matrix of transition probabilities between non-absorbing states, and r s (Q) is the s th row-sum of Q. Hence, r s (Q t )-r s (Q t+1 ) is the probability a sample path starting from state s is absorbed at time t. The elements of Q t approach zero as t → ∞.</p><p>Remark 2. (Ω, Ω ) is a partially ordered set. For s, s ∈ Ω,</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">s Ω s if s i ≤ s i for all i ∈ N . Remark 3. (Γ, Γ ) is a partially ordered set. For h, g ∈ Γ, h Γ g if h t Ω g t for all t ∈ Z + .</formula><p>Next, we present the main result of this section, which constructs a monotone coupling distribution of ν π , µ π by exploiting the differences in node-level transition probabilities. Theorem 2. Suppose x, y ∈ Ω with x Ω y. For each i ∈ N , define ϕ x,y i : {0, 1} 2 → [0, 1] according to</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">x i = y i = 1,          ϕ x,y i (0, 0) = δ(1 -p i 01 (y)) ϕ x,y i (0, 1) = δ(p i 01 (y) -p i 01,d (x)) ϕ x,y i (1, 0) = 0 ϕ x,y i (1, 1) = 1 -δ(1 -p i 01,d (x))<label>(42)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_64">x i = y i = 0,          ϕ x,y i (0, 0) = 1 -p i 01 (y) ϕ x,y i (0, 1) = p i 01 (y) -p i 01,d (x) ϕ x,y i (1, 0) = 0 ϕ x,y i (1, 1) = p i 01,d (x)<label>(43)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_65">x i = 0, y i = 1,          ϕ x,y i (0, 0) = δ(1 -p i 01 (y)) ϕ x,y i (0, 1) = 1 -p i 01,d (x) -δ(1 -p i 01 (y)) ϕ x,y i (1, 0) = 0 ϕ x,y i (1, 1) = p i 01,d (x)<label>(44)</label></formula><p>Also, define ϕ x,y : Ω 2 → [0, 1] for x Ω y by</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">ϕ x,y (ω, ω ) n i=1 ϕ x,y i (ω i , ω i ) ∀ω, ω ∈ Ω.<label>(45)</label></formula><p>Lastly, define</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">Φ π : Γ 2 → [0, 1] for any π ∈ ∆(Ω) by Φ π (h, g) χ(h 0 = g 0 )π(h 0 ) T (g)-1 t=0 ϕ h t ,g t (h t+1 , g t+1 ).</formula><p>(46) Then Φ π is a monotone coupling of ν π , µ π .</p><p>Proof. See Appendix.</p><p>The couplings between node-level transition probabilities ϕ x,y i given in (42)-(44) are used to establish a coupling between benchmark and distancing probability distributions on sample paths in (46). The form of the ϕ x,y i is identical to the method in which two biased coins are coupled in <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref>. When the coupling rule is applied to each node's probability of infection, it ensures no node can be infected in the distancing chain while being susceptible in the benchmark chain. Consequently, the monotone coupling Φ π is a distribution on pairs of sample paths (h, g) satisfying h 0 = g 0 , h Γ g (see Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>) and marginally, h ∼ ν π , g ∼ µ π . The next result characterizes the difference between µ π and ν π -expectations of any non-negative increasing function on the sample paths Γ with respect to the coupling distribution Φ π .</p><p>Corollary 2. For any increasing Z + -valued random variable Z in Γ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">E µπ (Z) -E νπ (Z) = ∞ τ =0 Φ π (Z c τ , Z τ ).<label>(47)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">Z τ = {x ∈ Γ : Z(x) &gt; τ }.</formula><p>Proof. Immediate from Theorem 2 and Proposition 1.</p><p>One can think of an increasing Z : Γ → Z + as an epidemic cost metric. Here, Φ π (Z c τ , Z τ ) is simply the probability a benchmark sample path g incurs a cost greater than τ , while the corresponding distancing sample path h costs less than τ , where (h, g) ∼ Φ π . The difference (47) encodes many complex dependencies on the epidemic parameters δ and β, the awareness weight α, and the graphs G C and G I .</p><p>The following result establishes stochastic domination of the distancing chain by the benchmark chain. Corollary 3. The benchmark chain stochastically dominates the distancing chain on sample paths, i.e. µ π ν π .</p><p>Proof. For any upper set I ⊂ Γ, χ I (•) is increasing in Γ. By (47),</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">µ π (I) -ν π (I) = E µπ (χ I ) -E νπ (χ I ) = Φ π (I c , I) ≥ 0<label>(48)</label></formula><p>The difference in probability (48) confirms the intuition gained from Corollary 1 that sample paths with consistently high numbers of infected individuals are more probable under the benchmark chain. The closed-form differences (47) and (48) provide a stochastic analogue to Corollary 1, which only establishes inequality between the mean-field metastable states of benchmark and distancing models. Some examples of increasing Z + -valued random variables in Γ are</p><p>• The absorption time T : Γ → Z + , defined by (36).</p><p>• The social cost up to time m, defined by g → m t=0 |g t |, where |s| i∈N s i for s ∈ Ω. • The "epidemic spread", or how many unique nodes that contract the disease in a given amount of time m. This is given by g → i∈N χ Ei (g), where E i = {g : m t=0 g t i &gt; 0}. This metric is investigated on different network structures in the next section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. SIMULATIONS ON RANDOM NETWORKS</head><p>In this section, we illustrate through numerical simulations how the structure of the contact network G C affects the course of an epidemic in the presence of awareness and social distancing. Extensive analytical and simulation studies have been conducted without awareness ([1], <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>). Here, we look at three random graph families -geometric, Erdős-Renyi, and scale-free. These networks are relevant in studying epidemic spreading because they exhibit a variety of qualitative features that reflect real-world networks. Geometric networks portray people connected by geographic distance. Erdős-Renyi random networks display a small-world effect common in many real world networks -e.g neural and social influence networks. Online social networks and the World Wide Web are examples of scale-free networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</p><p>In our model, the social network G I is generated directly from G C via a parameter p ∈ (0, 1) through the following procedure: 1) Select a fraction p of existing edges in E C at random and remove them from the edge set; 2) For each of the selected edges, select one of the two end nodes randomly (e.g with probability 1/2) as the root node; 3) For each of the  </p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>: Epidemic spreading as a function of time (same networks as Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4</ref>). Local contact information (α near 1, p near 0) slows spread most effectively for (a),(c), and the early stages of (b), whereas global information (α near 0 or α = 1, p near 1) is least effective. Note the inversion of awareness effectiveness in (b). In these simulations, δ = β = 0.2.</p><p>selected root nodes i, select j = i uniformly at random and add the edge (i, j). For p close to one, the resulting graph G I = (N , E I ) exhibits the small-world effect (small average shortest path length and small clustering) <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>. When p = 0,</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">G I = G C .</formula><p>For the contact networks, geometric random graphs are generated by placing n points uniformly at random on the unit torus (unit square with periodic boundary conditions). An edge exists between any two points if they are less than a specified distance r ∈ (0, 1) away. Erdős-Renyi random graphs are constructed by forming an edge between any two nodes independently with a fixed probability p ER ∈ (0, 1). Scale-free networks are generated by the preferential attachment algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>: starting with an initial connected graph of m 0 ≥ m nodes, nm 0 additional nodes are added sequentially with each incoming node establishing links to m existing nodes in the network. The probability a node receives an incoming link is proportional to its degree. We performed simulation analysis on one network from each random graph family. The networks all have 1000 nodes with an average degree of 10, and hence the same number of edges.</p><p>In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4</ref>, the normalized non-trivial fixed points are characterized for the three random networks in the interval of epidemic persistence. The norms of these points indicate the size of the endemic states and they slightly overestimate the actual long-run infected fraction observed in stochastic simulations of the Markov chains.</p><p>In Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>, we quantify the "epidemic spread" by the number of unique nodes that contract an infection as time progresses when one uniformly random node is initially infected. This metric is an example of an increasing random variable over sample paths (Section IV) and is helpful in revealing not only how fast an epidemic initially spreads in the network, but also how far-reaching it is. A key observation is that contact awareness (p = 0, α = 1) slows epidemic spreading better than any other awareness configuration at the beginning of an epidemic. This is intuitively clear since contact awareness provides nodes with the most vital information if they are in danger of getting infected. As p increases, G I deviates more from G C and the information nodes receive become less vital.</p><p>Erdős-Renyi and scale-free (with m = 5) networks admit disease spread throughout the entire network in a short amount of time, even with social distancing (Figure <ref type="figure">5a,</ref><ref type="figure">5c</ref>). This is attributed to small average shortest path lengths (Ch. <ref type="bibr">8 &amp; 12, [4]</ref>), allowing the epidemic to quickly spread to other parts of the network. Random geometric networks are characterized by high clustering and large diameter. Clustering slows the spread of an epidemic (Figure <ref type="figure">5b</ref>), but also contributes to increasing the final epidemic size <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The virus stays localized and spreads slowly. This explains the inversion of awareness parameters in Figure <ref type="figure">5b</ref>. By the time the epidemic first reaches its endemic level around t = 20, many nodes have not yet been exposed because at this point their local communities are untouched. Thus, having global or long-range social awareness (low α or high p) is more beneficial over contact awareness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. CONCLUSIONS</head><p>We modified the benchmark networked SIS epidemic process to include agent awareness, where prevalence-based information comes from social contacts and a global broadcast of the overall infected fraction. Agents take social distancing actions based on the level of information received, which reduces their probabilities of getting infected. We showed that awareness does not change the epidemic threshold for persistence by proving existence of a nontrivial fixed point in the mean-field approximation. Any nontrivial fixed point of the distancing model is strictly component-wise less than the unique nontrivial fixed point of the benchmark model.</p><p>We provided a full stochastic comparison analysis between the benchmark and distancing chains in terms of their respective probability distributions on sample paths by constructing a monotone coupling. The construction relies on exploiting the differences in node transition probabilities between the two chains. Consequently, adding awareness reduces the expectation of any increasing random variable on sample paths and we obtain a closed form expression for the reduction. This implies the benchmark distribution on sample paths stochastically dominates the distancing distribution.</p><p>In simulations, we showed epidemic spreading heavily depends on the network structure. In particular, qualitative features such as small-world effects, clustering, and diameter explain the results seen in simulations. We also concluded local contact awareness is the most effective at slowing epidemic spread, and global awareness is the least effective.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX</head><p>Proof of Theorem 2. When x Ω y, the ϕ x,y i are well-defined probabilities since p i 01 (y)p i 01,d (x) ≥ 0 and 1p i 01,d (x)δ(1p i 01 (y)) &gt; 0. One can see by inspection that ϕ x,y i is a monotone coupling of P d i (x, •) and P i (y, •) defined in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_12">9</ref>), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">10</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">3</ref>), (4) respectively.</p><p>Observe from (45), ϕ x,y (ω, ω ) &gt; 0 implies x Ω y and ω Ω ω . Consequently, ϕ x,y is a monotone coupling of </p><p>By a completely analogous computation, we obtain ω Ω ω ϕ x,y (ω , ω) = K(y, ω). Also, notice from (46) that Φ π (h, g) &gt; 0 implies h 0 = g 0 and h Γ g. Consequently, Φ π is a monotone coupling of ν π , µ π :</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">g Γ h Φ π (h, g) = g Γh g 0 =h 0 π(h 0 ) T (g)-1 t=0 ϕ h t ,g t (h t+1 , g t+1 ) (52) = π(h 0 ) T (h) t=1 g t Ω h t ϕ h t-1 ,g t-1 (h t , g t ) (53) = π(h 0 ) T (h) t=1 K d (h t-1 , h t ) (54) = ν π (h)<label>(55)</label></formula><p>The equality (53) is the combinatorial form of writing (52), and the product terminates at T (h) because 1) g Γ h implies T (g) ≥ T (h), 2) h t = o for all t ≥ T (h) and 3) for any t &gt; T (h), g t Ω h t ϕ h t-1 ,g t-1 (h t , g t ) =</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">g t ∈Ω ϕ o,g t-1 (o, g t ) = K d (o, o) = 1</formula><p>By an analogous computation, h Γg Φ π (h, g) = µ π (g).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1: (a) Node-level state transition diagram. (b) System-level diagram</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2: Diagram of the proof of Theorem 1. Here, p * denotes a nontrivial fixed point of φ.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4: Norms of the nontrivial fixed points (solid lines) and long-run fraction of infected in stochastic simulations (diamonds) in the range of epidemic persistence, δ/β ∈ [0, λmax(AC )], for n = 1000 node networks. The fixed points are computed by iterating the MFA dynamics (14) and (15) with an arbitrary initial condition until convergence. The stochastic long-run infected fractions are computed by averaging the levels of epidemic states in the latter half of a sample run of length 200. Vertical dashed lines indicate λmax(AC ). (a) Erdős-Renyi random network with pER = .01, λmax(AC ) = 11.1. Here, pER &gt; log n/n, the regime where the network is connected with high probability. (b) Geometric random graph with r = .0564, λmax(AC ) = 16.52. (c) Scale-free generated from the PA algorithm with m = 5, λmax(AC ) = 19.9. The parameters are chosen such that all networks have the same average degree d ≈ 10.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>K=</head><label></label><figDesc>d (x, •), K(y, •): ω Ω ω ϕ x,y (ω, ω ) = K d (x, ω)</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>This work is supported by <rs type="funder">ARO</rs> grant #<rs type="grantNumber">W911NF-14-1-0402</rs>, and supported in part by <rs type="funder">KAUST</rs>. The authors thank <rs type="person">J. Walker Gussler</rs> (<rs type="affiliation">Georgia Inst. Tech.</rs>) for his contribution in the simulations.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_qVHXqSW">
					<idno type="grant-number">W911NF-14-1-0402</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epidemic spreading in real networks: an eigenvalue viewpoint</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chakrabarti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Faloutsos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings. 22nd International Symposium on</title>
		<meeting>22nd International Symposium on</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-10">2003. Oct 2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="34" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Reliable Distributed Systems</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of network topology on the spread of epidemics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ganesh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Massoulie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Towsley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">INFOCOM 2005. 24th Annual Joint Conference of the IEEE Computer and Communications Societies</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-03">March 2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1455" to="1466" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epidemic threshold in structured scalefree networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Eguíluz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Klemm</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">108701</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002-08">Aug 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Networks: An Introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Newman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press, Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, NY, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virus spread in networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Van Mieghem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Omic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kooij</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Networking, IEEE/ACM Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-02">Feb 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global dynamics of epidemic spread over complex networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hassibi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Decision and Control (CDC), 2013 IEEE 52nd Annual Conference on</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-12">Dec 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4579" to="4585" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of heterogeneous and clustered contact patterns on infectious disease dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Volz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Galvani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">Ancel</forename><surname>Meyers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimizing the social cost of an epidemic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bodine-Baron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hassibi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wierman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Game Theory for Networks, ser. Lecture Notes of the Institute for Computer Sciences, Social Informatics and Telecommunications Engineering</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kannan</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="594" to="607" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An efficient curing policy for epidemics on graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Drakopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ozdaglar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tsitsiklis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Decision and Control (CDC), 2014 IEEE 53rd Annual Conference on</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-12">Dec 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4447" to="4454" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal resource allocation for network protection against spreading processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Preciado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zargham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Enyioha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jadbabaie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pappas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="108" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-03">March 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Control of Network Systems</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protecting against network infections: A game theoretic perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Omic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Orda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Van Mieghem</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">INFOCOM 2009, IEEE</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-04">April 2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1485" to="1493" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decentralized protection strategies against sis epidemics in networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Trajanovski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hayel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Altman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Van Mieghem</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Control of Network Systems, IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-12">Dec 2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="406" to="419" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of imitation on vaccination behavior in social contact networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ndeffo Mbah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bauch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Tekel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Medlock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Meyers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Galvani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Game theory of pre-emptive vaccination before bioterrorism or accidental release of smallpox</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Molina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J D</forename><surname>Earn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of The Royal Society Interface</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">107</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vaccination and the theory of games</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bauch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J D</forename><surname>Earn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="391" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The public&apos;s response to the 2009 h1n1 influenza pandemic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Steelfisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Blendon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bekheit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lubell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>pMID: 20484390</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">New England Journal of Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">362</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e65</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strategies for containing ebola in west africa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pandey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Atkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Medlock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Wenzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Townsend</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Childs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Nyenswah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ndeffo-Mbah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Galvani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">346</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6212</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="991" to="995" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social factors in epidemiology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bauch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Galvani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">342</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6154</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coupled diseasebehavior dynamics on complex networks: A review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-X</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bauch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics of Life Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The spread of awareness and its impact on epidemic outbreaks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Funk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gilad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Watkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A A</forename><surname>Jansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of The National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6872" to="6877" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Game theory of social distancing in response to an epidemic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Reluga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a characterization of behavior-disease models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Perra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Balcan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gonalves</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vespignani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamical interplay between awareness and epidemic spreading in multiplex networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Granell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gómez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Arenas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevLett.111.128701</idno>
		<ptr target="http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.111.128701" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">128701</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013-09">Sep 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Competing spreading processes on multiplex networks: Awareness and epidemics</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevE.90.012808</idno>
		<ptr target="http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevE.90.012808" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. E</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12808</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014-07">Jul 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cost-optimal switching protection strategy in adaptive networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ogura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Preciado</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2015 54th IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-12">Dec 2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3574" to="3579" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Suppression of epidemic spreading in complex networks by local information based behavioral responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-R</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-C</forename><surname>Lai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chaos</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of awareness on epidemic spreading in networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Small</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-J</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chaos</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epidemic spread over networks with agent awareness and social distancing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Paarporn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Eksin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Weitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Shamma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2015 53rd Annual Allerton Conference on Communication, Control, and Computing (Allerton)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-09">Sept 2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="57" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of awareness on networked sis epidemics</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Decision and Control (CDC), 2016 IEEE 55th Annual Conference on (submitted)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-12">Dec 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the mixing time of the sis markov chain model for epidemic spread</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hassibi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Decision and Control (CDC), 2014 IEEE 53rd Annual Conference on</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-12">Dec 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6221" to="6227" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Istratescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Fixed Point Theory, An Introduction. Holland: D.Reidel</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Lectures on the Coupling Method, ser</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lindvall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<publisher>Dover Publications, Incorporated</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epidemic spreading in scale-free networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pastor-Satorras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vespignani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3200" to="3203" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-04">Apr 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collective dynamics of&apos;smallworld&apos;networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Watts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Strogatz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">393</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6684</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="409" to="410" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emergence of scaling in random networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A.-L</forename><surname>Barabási</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Albert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">286</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5439</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="509" to="512" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
