<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Delay-aware BS Discontinuous Transmission Control and User Scheduling for Energy Harvesting Downlink Coordinated MIMO Systems</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Huawei Technologies Co</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-11-01">November 1, 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>MIEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Ying</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
							<email>cuiying@ust.hk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">ECE Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hong Kong University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="HK">Hong Kong</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>FIEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Vincent</forename><forename type="middle">K N</forename><surname>Lau</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">ECE Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hong Kong University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="HK">Hong Kong</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>StMIEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Yueping</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">ECE Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hong Kong University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="HK">Hong Kong</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Delay-aware BS Discontinuous Transmission Control and User Scheduling for Energy Harvesting Downlink Coordinated MIMO Systems</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-11-01">November 1, 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1204.0199v1[cs.SY]</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T21:25+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>delay-aware</term>
					<term>base station discontinuous transmission control (BS-DTX)</term>
					<term>interference network</term>
					<term>renewable energy</term>
					<term>energy harvesting system</term>
					<term>distributed stochastic learning</term>
					<term>queueing theory</term>
					<term>stochastic geometry</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In this paper, we propose a two-timescale delay-optimal base station Discontinuous Transmission (BS-DTX) control and user scheduling for downlink coordinated MIMO systems with energy harvesting capability. To reduce the complexity and signaling overhead in practical systems, the BS-DTX control is adaptive to both the energy state information (ESI) and the data queue state information (QSI) over a longer timescale. The user scheduling is adaptive to the ESI, the QSI and the channel state information (CSI) over a shorter timescale. We show that the two-timescale delay-optimal control problem can be modeled as an infinite horizon average cost Partially Observed Markov Decision Problem (POMDP), which is well-known to be a difficult problem in general. By using sample-path analysis and exploiting specific problem structure, we first obtain some structural results on the optimal control policy and derive an equivalent Bellman equation with reduced state space. To reduce the complexity and facilitate distributed implementation, we obtain a delay-aware distributed solution with the BS-DTX control at the BS controller (BSC) and the user scheduling at each cluster manager (CM) using approximate dynamic programming and distributed stochastic learning. We show that the proposed distributed two-timescale algorithm converges almost surely. Furthermore, using queueing theory, stochastic geometry and optimization techniques, we derive sufficient conditions for the data queues to be stable in the coordinated MIMO network and discuss various design insights. Finally, we compare the proposed algorithm with various baseline schemes and show that significant delay performance gain can be achieved.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Inter-cell interference is a critical performance bottleneck in cellular networks. The interference mitigation techniques can be roughly classified into two types, namely coordinated MIMO techniques and cooperative MIMO techniques, according to the required backhaul consumption <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. For coordinated MIMO techniques, only the channel state information (CSI) is shared among MIMO base stations (BSs) through backhaul for the coordinated beamforming design at each BS to combat interference <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. On the other hand, for cooperative MIMO techniques, both the CSI and the payload data are shared among MIMO BSs through backhaul for joint precoder designs at all the BSs to combat interference <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Since CSI sharing is performed for each transmission frame, while data sharing is operated for each data symbol, coordinated MIMO consumes much less backhaul capacity than cooperative MIMO at the expense of performance (e.g., degrees of freedom).</p><p>Due to the limited degrees of freedom and the limited backhaul capacity at each BS, global cooperation or coordination of all the BSs in the network is not possible and the BSs are organized into disjoint clusters <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The BSs within each cluster cooperatively serve the users associated with them, which lowers the system complexity and completely eliminates intra-cluster interference.</p><p>For example, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, multi-antenna BSs in each fixed cluster adopt coordinated beamforming to serve the single-antenna users in their own cells and avoid the interference to the users served by other BSs in the same cluster. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, the authors propose a BS cooperation strategy for fixed clusters, including full intra-cluster cooperation to eliminate intra-cluster interference and limited inter-cluster coordination to reduce the interference for the cluster edge users based on the per-cluster CSI and the CSI of the edge users in the neighboring clusters. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, the authors consider different types of static cluster-based cooperation schemes in a multi-cell system with multiple sectors per cell. However, all these works focus on physical layer performance (such as sum throughput, transport capacity) in cellular networks. They ignore the bursty data arrivals and assume infinite backlogs of packets at the transmitter. In other words, the information flows are assumed to be delay insensitive.</p><p>The resulting control policy is adaptive to the CSI only and it cannot guarantee good delay performance for delay-sensitive applications <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. In practice, a lot of applications have bursty arrivals and they are delay-sensitive. It is very important to take into account the delay performance in designing the cross-layer interference control algorithms for the coordinated MIMO systems. The control policy for delay-sensitive applications should be adaptive to both the CSI and the queue state information 1   (QSI). The motivation can be illustrated by the following example, as illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref> (a). Under cluster-based cooperative or coordinated MIMO, MSs only suffer from inter-cluster interference, as 1 The CSI gives the knowledge about good opportunity to transmit whereas the QSI gives the knowledge about the urgency of the data flow.</p><p>November 1, 2018 DRAFT intra-cluster interference is eliminated. Therefore, cluster edge MSs suffer much more interference than cluster center MSs. In this work, we are interested to investigating delay-aware BS-discontinuous transmission (BS-DTX) control and user scheduling to reduce inter-cluster interference and save energy of the whole network. To maximize the sum throughput, the CSI-based BS-DTX control and user scheduling always favors cluster center MSs while starves cluster edge MSs. This may lead to infinite delay of cluster edge MSs and hence, infinite average delay of all the MSs. However, the QSI and CSI based design will dynamically favor different types of MSs to capture the urgency of data flows and the good opportunity of channels. Therefore, it can guarantee good delay performance.</p><p>However, the design framework taking into account the queueing delay and the physical layer performance is far from trivial as it involves both queuing theory (to model the queuing dynamics)</p><p>and information theory (to model the physical layer dynamics).</p><p>In addition, recent initiatives towards green communications have driven the design of wireless infrastructure to be more energy-efficient. One energy-efficient design is to exploit renewable energy at BSs. There are many recent works on power management in energy harvesting networks. For example, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, the authors extend the Lyapunov optimization framework to derive an efficient energy management algorithm for energy harvesting networks. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, the authors consider dynamic node activation in energy harvesting sensor networks and propose a simple threshold-based node activation policy to achieve near-optimal system throughput. Similarly, all these papers have focused on physical layer throughput performance and the nodes are powered by renewable energy source only with infinite energy storage size.</p><p>In this paper, we consider delay-optimal BS-DTX control and user scheduling algorithm in downlink energy harvesting coordinated MIMO systems with limited renewable energy storage. Each BS is powered by both conventional grid and renewable power sources. There are various first-order technical challenges involved in solving the problem.</p><p>• Renewable and Grid Power Control: The transmit power of a BS comes from both renewable and grid power sources, which have very different properties. For instance, the grid power has stable power supply but there is cost associated with it. On the other hand, the renewable power is virtually free but it has random supply and hence, an energy storage is needed for efficient utilization of the renewable energy. In practice, the energy storage has limited capacity and hence, the BS power control and user scheduling algorithm should be adaptive to the renewable energy state information (ESI) and the data QSI as well as the CSI. It is highly nontrivial to strike a balance between these factors in the control algorithm design.</p><p>• Delay-aware Low Complexity Distributed Algorithm: While the delay-optimal control problem can be casted into an Markov Decision Process (MDP), brute force solutions such as value iteration and policy iteration will suffer from the curse of dimensionality <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. For example, a very large state space (exponential to the number of users in the network) will be involved. In addition to the complexity issue, the solution obtained will be centralized and it requires knowledge of global system state information (ESI, QSI, CSI). However, these system state information is usually distributed locally at various BSs and huge signaling overhead will be involved in collecting these information.</p><p>Therefore, it is highly desirable to obtain a delay-aware low complexity and distributed algorithm with guaranteed delay performance.</p><p>• Performance Analysis: Besides algorithm development, it is important to analyze the system performance to understand how it is affected by the renewable energy storage size and the interference coupling in cellular networks. One challenge on the system performance analysis is the statistical characterization of interference. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, the authors study the coverage and rate of cellular networks without BS coordination using stochastic geometry <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. The locations of the BSs are modeled as a homogeneous Poisson point process (PPP) and the locations of the mobile stations (MSs) are modeled as some independent (of the point process of BSs) point process. The analysis for coordinated MIMO network is more challenging due to the asymmetric topology induced by clustering. In addition, the analysis becomes more involved when queueing dynamics of data queues and renewable energy queues are considered.</p><p>In this paper, considering the limited backhaul capacity and the latency in information exchange through backhaul in practical cellular systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, we adopt cluster-based coordinated 2 MIMO to eliminate intra-cluster interference. We propose a two-timescale delay-aware BS-DTX control and user scheduling for energy harvesting downlink coordinated MIMO systems as illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref> (a). The BS-DTX control is adaptive to both the ESI and the QSI over a longer timescale. The user scheduling is adaptive to the ESI, the QSI and the CSI over a shorter timescale. We show that the two-timescale delay-optimal control problem can be modeled as an infinite horizon average cost Partially Observed Markov Decision Process (POMDP), which is well-known to be a difficult problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. By using sample-path analysis and exploiting the specific problem structure, we first obtain some structural results on the optimal control policy and derive an equivalent Bellman equation with reduced state space. To derive a distributed control policy, we approximate the Q-factor and potential function associated with the equivalent Bellman equation by the per-flow functions. The per-flow functions are estimated online using distributed stochastic learning at each BS. We prove the almost-sure convergence of the proposed distributed algorithm. Furthermore, using queueing theory, stochastic geometry and optimization techniques, we characterize the sufficient conditions for data queues in the coordinated MIMO networks to be stable. Based on the analysis, we discuss the impacts of the 2 The design framework proposed in this paper does not rely on specific physical layer transmission schemes and can be easily extended to cluster-based cooperative MIMO.</p><p>November 1, 2018 DRAFT interference coupling and the size of renewable energy storage on network performance. Finally, we compare the proposed algorithm with various baseline schemes and show that significant delay performance gain can be achieved.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. SYSTEM MODELS</head><p>In this section, we shall elaborate on the system architecture, the physical layer model as well as the bursty source model for the coordinated MIMO networks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Architecture of Downlink Distributed MIMO Systems</head><p>We consider a downlink coordinated MIMO system consisting of B multi-antenna BSs and K single-antenna MSs as illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>  , where B n denotes the set of B n BSs in cluster n. Each coordination cluster contains N t neighboring BSs and is managed by a cluster manager (CM) and all the N CMs are managed by a BS controller (BSC). The BSs in the same cluster share the CSI and perform coordinated beamforming <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> to combat intra-cluster interference. Besides conventional grid power source, each BS is able to harvest energy from the environment, e.g., using solar panels <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. At each BS, there is a renewable energy queue (battery) with limited capacity for storing the harvested energy. In addition, at each BS, there are multiple data queues for buffering the packets to all the MSs associated with the BS (one queue for each MS) as illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">1 (a)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Physical Layer Model</head><p>Let h k,b ∈ H and L k,b denote the N t × 1 complex small-scale fading vector and the long-term path gain between the b-th BS and the k-th MS, where H ⊂ C Nt×1 denotes the finite discrete complex CSI state space. Let</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">H n = {h k,b : k ∈ K b , b ∈ B n } ∈ H n H b∈Bn Kb and H = ∪ N n=1 H n ∈ H H K denote</formula><p>the intra-cluster CSI at n-th CM and the aggregation of the CSI over N clusters, respectively. In this paper, the time dimension is partitioned into scheduling slots indexed by t with slot duration τ (second). 3 For simplicity, we assume B is a multiple of Nt.</p><p>We assume all the BSs in the system share a common spectrum. Let p b ∈ P {0, 1} denote the binary BS-DTX control action of the b-th BS, where p b = 1 indicates the b-th BS is active and p b = 0 otherwise. Between the coordination clusters, the inter-cluster interference is managed by a binary BS-DTX control action p = {p b : p b ∈ P, b ∈ B} ∈ P, where P ⊆ P B is the aggregate BS-DTX control action space and specifies the BS-DTX patterns <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. Since each BS has renewable and grid power sources, we have p b = p E b + p G b , where p E b ∈ P and p G b ∈ P denote the power contribution from the renewable power and grid power sources of the b-th BS, respectively. Let s k ∈ S {0, 1} denote the user scheduling action of the k-th MS, where s k = 1 indicates the k-th MS is selected to receive packets and s k = 0 otherwise. Thus, users are selected according to a user scheduling action s = {s k : s k ∈ S, k ∈ K} ∈ S, where S ⊆ S K is the aggregate user scheduling action space. The BS-DTX control and user scheduling are performed according to a control policy to be defined in Definition 1.</p><p>In each slot, each active BS selects one MS to serve. Within each coordination cluster, the active BSs combat the intra-cluster interference using coordinated beamforming <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Let P b and x k denote the instantaneous transmit power of the b-th BS and the information symbols for the k-th MS, respectively. The received signal at the k-th MS of the b-th cell in the n-th cluster is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">y k = p b P b L k,b h T k,b w k,b s k x k desired signal + b ′ ∈Bn,b ′ =b p b ′ P b ′ L k,b ′ h T k,b ′   k ′ ∈K b ′ w k ′ ,b ′ s k ′ x k ′   intra-cluster interference + n ′ =n b ′ ∈B n ′ p b ′ P b ′ L k,b ′ h T k,b ′   k ′ ∈K b ′ w k ′ ,b ′ s k ′ x k ′   inter-cluster interference + z k noise , k ∈ K b , b ∈ B n</formula><p>where z k ∼ CN (0, N 0 ) is the AWGN noise and w k,b ∈ C Nt×1 is the zero-forcing beamforming weight for the k-th MS at the b-th BS. Specifically, {w k,b } is given by the solution <ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">4</ref> of the zero-</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">forcing problem: k∈Kb ||w k,b || 2 s k = p b and s k h T k,b ′ k ′ ∈K b ′ w k ′ ,b ′ s k ′ = 0 (∀b ′ ∈ B n , b ′ = b).</formula><p>The receive SINR at the k-th MS of the b-th cell in the n-th cluster is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">ρ k (H, p, s) = P rx k N 0 + I k , k ∈ K b , b ∈ B n<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where the receive power P rx k and the inter-cluster interference power I k are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">P rx k = p b P b L k,b ||h T k,b w k,b || 2 s k<label>(2)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">I k = n ′ =n b ′ ∈B n ′ p b ′ P b ′ L k,b ′ ||h T k,b ′ k ′ ∈K b ′ w k ′ ,b ′ s k ′ || 2<label>(3)</label></formula><p>We have the following assumption regarding packet transmission.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Assumption 2 (Packet Transmission Model):</head><p>One data packet with certain fixed packet size can be successfully received by the k-th MS if the receive SINR ρ k exceeds a certain threshold<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">foot_2</ref> δ k , i.e., ρ k ≥ δ k . There exists a state-action pair (H, p, s)</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">∈ H × P × S, such that Pr[ρ k (H, p, s) ≥ δ k ] &gt; 0.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Bursty Source Model and Queue Dynamics</head><formula xml:id="formula_7">Let A Q (t) = {A Q k (t) : k ∈ K} and A E (t) = {A E b (t) : b ∈ B}</formula><p>be the number of packets arriving to the K MSs and the number of renewable energy units <ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">6</ref> arriving to the B BSs at the end of the t-th scheduling slot, respectively. We have the following assumptions <ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">7</ref> regarding the bursty data and renewable energy arrival processes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Assumption 3 (Bursty Data Source Model):</head><p>The arrival process A Q k (t) is i.i.d. over scheduling slots and independent w.r.t. k according to a general distribution </p><formula xml:id="formula_8">P A Q k (•) with average arrival rate E[A Q k (t)] = λ Q k &lt; 1. The statistics of A Q k (t)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_9">P A E b (•) with average arrival rate E[A E b (t)] = λ E b &lt; 1. The statistics of A E b (t) is unknown to the controller.</formula><p>Remark 1 (Interpretation of Assumption 4): Assumption 4 implies that the renewable power source is stationary. Although the renewable energy source is not stationary over a very long time horizon in practice, it is stationary over a typical communication session, which lasts for less than 30 mins.</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">Let Q n (t) = {Q k (t) : k ∈ K n } ∈ Q n Q b∈Bn Kb be the n-th cluster QSI and Q(t) = ∪ N n=1 Q n (t) ∈ Q Q K be</formula><p>the aggregation of the QSI over N clusters at the beginning of the t-th slot, where </p><formula xml:id="formula_11">Q k (t) ∈ Q {0, 1, • • • , N Q } denotes</formula><formula xml:id="formula_12">Q k (t + 1) = min Q k (t) -I[ρ k (t) ≥ δ k ] + + A Q k (t), N Q , k ∈ K<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where ρ k (t) (H(t), p(t), s(t)) and x + max{x, 0}. </p><formula xml:id="formula_13">Similarly, let E n (t) = {E b (t) : b ∈ B n } ∈ E n E Bn be the n-th cluster ESI and E(t) = ∪ N n=1 E n (t) ∈ E E B be</formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">E b (t + 1) = min E b (t) -p E b (t) + + A E k (t), N E , b ∈ B<label>(5)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. BS-DTX Control and User Scheduling Policy</head><p>For notation convenience, we denote</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">χ(t) = E(t), Q(t), H(t) ∈ X = E × Q × H as the global</formula><p>system state at the t-th slot. We first define the centralized control policy. Specifically, at the beginning of each slot, the controller determines the renewable power DTX control action</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">p E = {p E b : p E b ∈ P, b ∈ B} ∈ P, grid power DTX control action p G = {p G b : p G b ∈ P, b</formula><p>∈ B} ∈ P as well as the user scheduling action s = {s k : s k ∈ S, k ∈ K} ∈ S based on the global system state χ(t) according to the control policy defined below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definition 1 (BS-DTX Control and User Scheduling Policy): A BS-DTX control and user scheduling policy consists of a sequence of mappings</head><formula xml:id="formula_17">π = {Ω 1 , Ω 2 , • • • }.</formula><p>The mapping for the t-th slot</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">Ω t = (Ω E,t p , Ω G,t p , Ω t s</formula><p>) is a mapping from the system state χ(t) ∈ X to the renewable power DTX control action Ω E,t p (E(t), Q(t)) = p E (t) ∈ P, the grid power DTX control action Ω G,t p (E(t), Q(t)) = p G (t) ∈ P and the user scheduling action Ω t s (χ(t)) = s(t) ∈ S. A policy π is called feasible if for all t, the following constraints are satisfied:</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">1) p E b (t) = 0 if E b (t) = 0 for all b ∈ B (no renewable energy available for transmission). 2) p b (t) = p E b (t) + p G b (t) ∈ P for all b ∈ B (binary BS-DTX control). 3) k∈Kb s k (t) = p b (t)</formula><p>for all b ∈ B (each active BS selects one MS in its cell).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Remark 2 (Motivation of Two-Timescale Control Policy):</head><p>The two-timescale control is a constraint we impose due to the following practical reasons. The QSI and ESI are changing on a longer timescale (e.g., several slots) while the CSI is changing on a shorter timescale (e.g., per-slot). The BS-DTX control is usually implemented at the BSC for interference reduction and energy saving of the whole network. As a result, the BS-DTX control cannot afford to be running on a per-slot basis, due to the high complexity and signaling overhead in collecting the local CSI from all the BSs. Therefore, it is desirable to make it a function of the ESI and QSI only. On the other hand, the low complexity distributed user scheduling is implemented locally at each CM (similar to HSDPA in current 3G networks) and they can afford to run on a per-slot basis and adapt to the ESI, QSI and CSI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. PROBLEM FORMULATION AND OPTIMAL SOLUTION</head><p>In this section, we shall first elaborate on the dynamics of the system state under a control policy π. Based on that, we shall formulate the delay-optimal control problem and derive some structural properties for the optimal solution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Delay-Optimal Problem Formulation</head><p>Under Assumptions 1, 3 and 4, the induced random process {χ(t)} for a given feasible control </p><formula xml:id="formula_20">policy π = {Ω 1 , Ω 2 , • • • } is a</formula><p>As a result, given a feasible control policy π, the average delay cost per stage of the k-th MS starting from a given initial state χ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">1</ref>) is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">D π,k χ(1) = lim sup T →∞ 1 T E π T t=1 f Q k (t) , ∀k ∈ K<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where the expectation is taken w.r.t. the measure induced by the policy π and f <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> can be used to measure the average delay and the average queue outage probability of the k-th MS under policy π. Similarly, given a feasible control policy π, the average grid power cost per stage of the b-th BS starting from a given initial state χ(1) is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">(Q k ) is a monotonic increasing utility function of Q k . For example, with f (Q k ) = Qk λk and f (Q k ) = 1[Q k ≥ Q o k ] (Q o k ∈ {0, • • • , N Q }),</formula><formula xml:id="formula_24">p G π,b χ(1) = lim sup T →∞ 1 T E π T t=1 p G b (t) , ∀b ∈ B<label>(8)</label></formula><p>We are interested in minimizing the average delay cost of each MS k ∈ K in (7) and the average grid power cost of each BS b ∈ B in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>. A Pareto optimal tradeoff on the average delay and average grid power consumption can be obtained by solving the following problem.</p><p>Problem 1 (Two-Timescale Delay-Optimal Control): For some positive constants β = {β k &gt; 0 :</p><p>k ∈ K} and γ = {γ b &gt; 0 : b ∈ B}, the delay-optimal problem is formulated as</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">min π J (β,γ) π χ(1) = k∈K β k D π,k χ(1) + b∈B γ b p G π,b χ(1) = lim T →∞ 1 T E π T t=1 g χ(t), Ω t (χ(t))<label>(9)</label></formula><p>where g χ(t),</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">Ω t (χ(t)) = k∈K β k f Q k (t) + b∈B γ b p G b (t)</formula><p>and the control policy π satisfies the two-timescale requirement in Definition 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Remark 3 (Two-Timescale Control and POMDP):</head><p>By two-timescale requirement, the BS-DTX control policy is defined on the partial system state (E, Q), while the user scheduling policy is defined on the complete system state χ = (E, Q, H). Due to the two-timescale control constraint as in Definition 1, Problem 1 is a POMDP <ref type="foot" target="#foot_5">8</ref> .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Policy and State Space Reduction</head><p>Problem 1 belongs to POMDP, which is well-known to be a challenging problem in general. Yet, we shall exploit some special structures in our problems to reduce the policy and state spaces. Based on that, we can simplify the POMDP. We first have the following lemma on the structural property of the BS-DTX control, which helps to reduce the policy space.</p><p>Lemma 1 (Structure of Optimal BS-DTX Control): Let the BS-DTX control for the t-th slot be denoted by Ω t p : E × Q → P, which is a mapping from the partial system state</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">(E, Q) ∈ E × Q to the BS-DTX control action Ω t p (E(t), Q(t)) = p(t) ∈ P. Conditioned on any Ω t p,b , the optimal Ω E,t p,b and Ω G,t p,b satisfy Ω E,t p,b (E(t), Q(t)) = Ω t p,b (E(t), Q(t))I[E b (t) &gt; 0] and Ω G,t p,b (E(t), Q(t)) = Ω t p,b (E(t), Q(t))I[E b (t) = 0]</formula><p>for all b ∈ B and all t.</p><p>Proof: Please refer to Appendix A.</p><p>Remark 4 (Interpretation of Lemma 1): Lemma 1 indicates that we are inclined to consume renewable power first. This is because renewable power is free while grid power has cost. In addition, due to the limited energy storage size, we may suffer from renewable energy loss when the energy queue size is large. Therefore, it is preferable to keep the size of the energy queue small.</p><p>Based on Lemma 1, without loss of optimality, we can first solve Problem 1 over a reduced policy</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">π = {Ω 1 , Ω 2 , • • • },</formula><p>where Ω t = (Ω t p , Ω t s ) and then obtain the optimal Ω E,t p and Ω G,t p from the optimal Ω t p using Lemma 1. Next, we exploit the i.i.d. property of the CSI to reduce the state space. We first define partitioned actions below:</p><p>Definition 2 (Partitioned Actions): Given Ω t = (Ω t p , Ω t s ), we define</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">Ω t (E, Q) = {(p, s) = Ω t p (E, Q), Ω t s (E, Q, H) : H ∈ H}, Ω t s (E, Q) = {s = Ω t s (E, Q, H) : H ∈ H}</formula><p>as the collection of actions (p, s) and s for all possible CSI H conditioned on a given ESI and QSI pair (E, Q). Ω t and Ω t s are therefore equal to the union of all partitioned actions. i.e.</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">Ω = (E,Q) Ω(E, Q) and Ω s = (E,Q) Ω s (E, Q).</formula><p>Based on Lemma 1 and Definition 2, the optimal control policy in Problem 1 can be obtained by solving an equivalent Bellman equation over a reduced state space, which is summarized in the lemma below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lemma 2 (Equivalent Bellman Equation for POMDP):</head><p>The optimal control policy for Problem 1 can be obtained by solving the following equivalent Bellman equation w.r.t. θ, {V (E, Q)} :</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">θ + V (E, Q) = min Ω(E,Q) g (E, Q), Ω(E, Q) + (E ′ ,Q ′ ) Pr[(E ′ , Q ′ )|(E, Q), Ω(E, Q)]V (E ′ , Q ′ ) ∀(E, Q) ∈ E × Q (10)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">g (E, Q), Ω(E, Q) = k∈K β k f (Q k ) + b∈B γ b Ω p (E, Q)I[E b = 0] is the per-stage cost function, Pr[(E ′ , Q ′ )|(E, Q), Ω(E, Q)] = E Pr[(E ′ , Q ′ )|χ, Ω(χ)] (E, Q) is the transition kernel.</formula><p>θ is the optimal value for all χ, i.e., θ = min π J</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">(β,γ) π χ ∀χ ∈ X and {V (E, Q)} is called the potential function. Furthermore, if Ω * (E, Q) = Ω * p (E, Q), Ω * s (E, Q) attains the minimum of the R.H.S. of (10) for all (E, Q) ∈ E × Q, the stationary policy Ω * = (Ω * p , Ω * s ) is optimal (i.e., π * = {Ω * , Ω * , • • • }).</formula><p>Proof: Please refer to the Appendix B.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Remark 5 (Interpretation of Equivalent Bellman Equation):</head><p>The equivalent Bellman equation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> is defined on the reduced space of the ESI and QSI (E, Q) only. Nevertheless, by solving <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, we can obtain a stationary BS-DTX policy Ω * p , which is a function of (ESI, QSI), and a stationary user scheduling policy Ω * s , which is a function of (ESI, QSI, CSI).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Centralized Optimal BS-DTX Control and User Scheduling</head><p>To facilitate the BS-DTX control, which is only adaptive to the ESI and the QSI, we introduce the BS-DTX control Q-factor Q(E, Q, p) w.r.t. the BS-DTX control action p. Based on Lemma 2, we summarize the optimal BS-DTX control in the following corollary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Corollary 1 (Optimal BS-DTX Control):</head><p>The optimal BS-DTX control is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">Ω * p (E, Q) = arg min p∈P Q(E, Q, p), ∀(E, Q) ∈ E × Q<label>(11)</label></formula><p>where Q(E, Q, p) is the BS-DTX control Q-factor given by the following Bellman equation w.r.t.</p><p>θ, {Q(E, Q, p)} :</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">θ + Q(E, Q, p) ∀(E, Q) ∈ E × Q, p ∈ P<label>(12)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>= min</head><p>Ωs(E,Q)</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">g (E, Q), p, Ω s (E, Q) + (E ′ ,Q ′ ) Pr[(E ′ , Q ′ )|(E, Q), p, Ω s (E, Q)] min p ′ ∈P Q(E ′ , Q ′ , p ′ ) Proof: Please refer to Appendix B.</formula><p>As the distributions of the energy and data arrival processes are unknown to the controllers, we introduce the post-decision state potential function U ( E, Q) to determine the user selection <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. The post-decision state ( E, Q) is defined to be the virtual partial system state immediately after making an action before the new renewable energy and data arrive 9 . Based on Lemma 2, we summarize the optimal user scheduling in the following corollary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Corollary 2 (Optimal User Scheduling):</head><p>The optimal user scheduling is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">Ω * s (χ) = arg min s∈S(p * ) d∈D k∈K 1 -d k -(-1) dk Pr[ρ k (H, p * , s) ≥ δ k ] U [E -p * ] + , [Q -d] + ∀χ ∈ X<label>(13)</label></formula><p>where p * = Ω * p (E, Q) is the optimal BS-DTX control action given by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_34">11</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_38">θ + U ( E, Q) ∀( E, Q) ∈ E × Q (14) = A E ,A Q Pr[A E ] Pr[A Q ] min Ω(E,Q) g (E, Q), Ω(E, Q) + ( E ′ , Q ′ ) Pr[( E ′ , Q ′ )|(E, Q), Ω(E, Q)]U ( E ′ , Q ′ )</formula><p>where </p><formula xml:id="formula_39">E = min{ E + A E , N E } and Q = min{ Q + A Q , N Q }.</formula><formula xml:id="formula_40">O (N E + 1) B (N Q + 1) K .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. LOW COMPLEXITY DELAY-AWARE DISTRIBUTED SOLUTION</head><p>Obtaining the optimal control in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_34">11</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_37">13</ref>) has exponential complexity and requires centralized implementation at the BSC and knowledge of the aggregation of the ESI, QSI and CSI, which leads to huge signaling overhead. In this section, we shall first introduce a randomized base policy.</p><p>Based on that, we shall propose a low complexity distributed deterministic policy using approximate dynamic programming <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. We shall show that the proposed solution has better performance than the randomized base policy. 9 For example, χ = (E, Q, H) is the state at the beginning of some slot (also called the pre-decision state) and making an action (p, s) = Ω(χ) leads to ρ = {ρ k : k ∈ K} with ρ k given by (1). Then, the post-decision state immediately after the action is χ</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">= ( E, Q, H), where E = [E -p] + and Q = Q -I[ρ δ] + , where δ = {δ k : k ∈ K}. If new arrivals</formula><p>A E and A Q occur in the post-decision state, and the CSI changes to H ′ , then the system reaches the next actual state, i.e., pre-decision state χ ′ = (min{</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">E + A E , NE}, min{ Q + A Q , NQ}, H ′ ).</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Randomized Base Policy</head><p>We first introduce a randomized base policy and discuss an important structural property of the equivalent Bellman equations in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_35">12</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>)) under this base policy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definition 3 (Randomized Base Policy):</head><p>A randomized base policy is denoted as Ω = ( Ωp , Ωs ).</p><p>The randomized base policy for BS-DTX control Ωp is given by a distribution on the action space of p, i.e., P. The randomized base policy for user scheduling Ωs is given by a mapping from the CSI H to a probability distribution Ωs (H) on the action space of s, i.e., S.</p><p>Under a randomized base policy, the corresponding Q-factor and post-decision potential function have the following decomposition structure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lemma 3 (Decomposition under Randomized Base Policy):</head><p>Given any randomized base policy Ω, the Q-factor Q(E, Q, p) and the potential function Û ( E, Q) associated with the equivalent Bellman equations in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_35">12</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>) can be expressed as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">Q(E, Q, p) = b∈B k∈Kb Qk (E b , Q k , p) and Û ( E, Q) = b∈B k∈Kb Ûk ( E b , Q k ), where θk + Qk (E b , Q k , p) ∀E b ∈ E, Q k ∈ Q, p ∈ P (15) =ĝ k (E b , Q k , p b ) + (E ′ b ,Q ′ k ) Pr[(E ′ b , Q ′ k )|(E b , Q k ), p]E Ωp [Q k (E ′ b , Q ′ k , p ′ )] θk + Ûk ( E b , Q k ) ∀ E b ∈ E, Q k ∈ Q (16) = (A E b ,A Q k ) Pr[A E b ] Pr[A Q k ]   E Ωp [ĝ k (E b , Q k , p b )] + ( E ′ b , Q ′ k ) E Ωp Pr[( E ′ b , Q ′ k )|(E b , Q k ), p] V k ( E ′ n , Q ′ k )   with ĝk (E b , Q k , p b ) = β k f (Q k ) + γ b p b I[E b = 0]E Pr[s k = 1|H] and Pr [(E ′ b , Q ′ k )|(E b , Q k ), p] = E E Ωs Pr[(E ′ b , Q ′ k )|(E b , Q k , H), p b , s k ] H . Proof: Please refer to Appendix C.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Low Complexity Delay-aware Distributed Solution</head><p>Based on the randomized base policy Ω, we shall obtain a low complexity distributed deterministic policy Ω * by Q-factor and potential function approximation. The solution is elaborated below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1) BS-DTX Control Policy Over a Longer Timescale:</head><p>To reduce the complexity and to facilitate distributed implementation, we approximate the BS-DTX control Q-factor Q(E, Q, p) in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> by</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">Q(E, Q, p), i.e., Q(E, Q, p) ≈ Q(E, Q, p) = b∈B k∈Kb Qk (E b , Q k , p)<label>(17)</label></formula><p>November 1, 2018 DRAFT</p><p>where Qk (E b , Q k ) is given by the per-flow fixed point equation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>. The BSC determines the BS-DTX control based on the aggregation of the ESI and QSI according to</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">p * (E, Q) = arg min p∈P b∈B k∈Kb Qk (E b , Q k , p)<label>(18)</label></formula><p>Remark 7 (Complexity of the BS-DTX Control): Under the linear Q-factor approximation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>, the complexity of obtaining the BS-DTX control is reduced from</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">O (N E + 1) B (N Q + 1) K 2 B to O (N E + 1)(N Q + 1)2 B K .</formula><p>To further reduce the complexity w.r.t. B, we can partition the BSs into macro-groups with size N B . The BS-DTX control in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_45">18</ref>) can be done for each of the B NB macrogroups separately <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. In practice, N B ≪ B and hence, the complexity becomes O((</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">N E + 1)(N Q + 1)2 NB B NB K), which is linear w.r.t. B.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2) Distributed User Scheduling Policy at the CM Over a Shorter Timescale:</head><p>To reduce the complexity and to facilitate distributed implementation of the user scheduling, we approximate the postdecision state potential function U ( E, Q) in ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>) by Û ( E, Q), i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">U ( E, Q) ≈ Û ( E, Q) = b∈B k∈Kb Ûk (E b , Q k )<label>(19)</label></formula><p>where Ûk ( E b , Q k ) is given by the per-flow fixed point equation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>. Substituting the approximation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref> into the optimal user scheduling in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>, the user scheduling solution under the approximation is summarized below.</p><p>Lemma 4 (Distributed User Scheduling): Under the linear potential function approximation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>, the distributed user scheduling action ŝ * n of the n-th cluster based on the per-cluster ESI, QSI and CSI under p * (E, Q) obtained by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_45">18</ref>) is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">ŝ * n (E n , Q n , H n ), ∀E n ∈ E n , Q n ∈ Q n , H n ∈ H n , ∀n<label>(20)</label></formula><p>= arg max</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">sn∈Sn(p * n ) k∈Kn s k Pr[ρ k (H n , p * , s n ) ≥ δ k ] Ûk ([E b -p * b ] + , Q k ) -Ûk ([E b -p * b ] + , [Q k -1] + )</formula><p>where S n (p n ) {s n ∈ S b∈Bn Kb : k∈Kb s k = p b , b ∈ B n } denotes the feasible user scheduling action space of cluster n under the BS-DTX control action p n .</p><p>Proof: Please refer to Appendix D.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Remark 8 (Complexity of the User Scheduling):</head><p>The user scheduling action in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_49">20</ref>) is a function of the per-cluster ESI, QSI and CSI, and is computed locally at the n-th CM. Under the linear potential function approximation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>, the complexity of user scheduling is reduced from</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">O (N E +1) B (N Q + 1) K to O (N E + 1)(N Q + 1)K .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Performance of Low Complexity Delay-aware Distributed Solution</head><p>The key motivation of the linear approximatios of the Q-function and potential function in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_48">19</ref>) is to facilitate distributed control. The following theorem shows that the proposed distributed policy always achieves better performance than the randomized base policy.</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">Theorem 1 (Performance Improvement): If Pr[(E ′ , Q ′ )|(E, Q), (p, s)] = Pr[(E ′ , Q ′ )|(E, Q), (p ′ , s ′ )] for any (p, s) = (p ′ , s ′ ) and (E, Q) ∈ E × Q, then we have θ * (E, Q) &lt; θ for all (E, Q) ∈ E × Q,</formula><p>where θ * (E, Q) is the average cost under the proposed solution starting from state (E, Q) and θ is the average cost under any randomized base policy, respectively.</p><p>Proof: Please refer to Appendix E.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. DISTRIBUTED ONLINE LEARNING VIA STOCHASTIC APPROXIMATION</head><p>Observe that the BS-DTX control and the user scheduling in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_45">18</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_49">20</ref>) require the knowledge</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">of { Qk (E b , Q k , p)} and { Ûk ( E b , Q k )}</formula><p>, respectively, which are defined in the fixed point equations in ( <ref type="formula">15</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>), respectively. However, solving these fixed point equations is also quite challenging.</p><p>In this section, we shall propose an online distributed stochastic learning <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> algorithm to estimate { Qk (E b , Q k , p)} and { Ûk ( E b , Q k )} using the per-cluster system state information only. We shall prove that the proposed distributed algorithm converges almost surely to the fixed point solutions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Distributed Online Learning for</head><formula xml:id="formula_54">{ Qk (E b , Q k , p)} and { Ûk ( E b , Q k )}</formula><p>Since the statistics of A Q (t) and A E (t) are unknown to the controller, instead of computing </p><formula xml:id="formula_55">{ Qk (E b , Q k , p)} and { Ûk ( E b , Q k )} of</formula><formula xml:id="formula_56">(t) = p * b (t)I[E b (t) &gt; 0] and pG * b (t) = p * b (t)I[E b (t) = 0]</formula><p>, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Step 3 [User Scheduling at the CMs]:</head><formula xml:id="formula_57">Each BS b reports Û t k (E b (t), Q k (t)) : k ∈ K b to its CM. Each CM n determines user selection ŝ * n (t) ŝ * n (E n (t), Q n (t), H n (t)</formula><p>) according to (20) under given BS-DTX control p * (t).  <ref type="formula">21</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>) for all k ∈ K b .</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">Qt+1 k (E b , Q k , p) ∀E b ∈ E, Q k ∈ Q, p ∈ P (21) = Qt k (E b , Q k , p) + ǫ t F k ( Qt k , E b , Q k , p) -F k ( Qt k , E I b , Q I k , p I ) -Q t k (E b , Q k , p) Û t+1 k ( E b , Q k ) ∀ E b ∈ E, Q k ∈ Q (22) = Û t k ( E b , Q k ) + ǫ t T k ( Ût k , E b , Q k ) -T k ( Ût k , E I b , Q I k ) -Û t k ( E b , Q k )</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">F k ( Qt k , E b , Q k , p) =ĝ k (E b , Q k , p b ) + (E ′ b ,Q ′ k ) Pr[(E ′ b , Q ′ k )|(E b , Q k ), p] × E Ωp Q t k (min{E ′ b + A E b (t), N E }, min{Q ′ k + A Q k (t), N Q }, p ′ ) (<label>23</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_60">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_61">T t k ( Ût k , E b , Q k ) = E Ωp ĝk min{ E b + A E b (t), N E }, min{ Q k + A Q k (t), N Q }, p b + ( E ′ b , Q ′ k ) E Ωp Pr ( E ′ b , Q ′ k )| min{ E b + A E b (t), N E }, min{ Q k + A Q k (t), N Q } , p Û t k ( E ′ b , Q ′ k )<label>(24)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_62">E ′ b = [E b -p b ] + , Q ′ k = [Q k -I[ρ k (H n , p, s n ) ≥ δ k ]] + , E ′ b = min{ E b + A E b (t), N E } -p b + , Q ′ k = min{ Q k + A Q k (t), N Q } -I[ρ k (H n , p, s n ) ≥ δ k ] + . p I is the reference BS-DTX control</formula><p>action and E I b , Q I k , E I b , Q I k are the reference states 10 for the Q-factor update in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> and the potential function update in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref>, respectively. {ǫ t } are diminishing positive step size sequences satisfying the following conditions:</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">ǫ t ≥ 0, t ǫ t = ∞, t ǫ 2 t &lt; ∞.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Performance of the Distributed Learning Algorithm</head><p>The convergence of Algorithm 1 is summarized below.  <ref type="formula">15</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>), respectively.</p><p>Proof: Please refer to Appendix F.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Remark 9 (Signaling Requirement of Distributed Two-Timescale Algorithm 1):</head><p>• Signaling requirement over a short timescale (per slot): Each BS needs to collect the local CSI over the radio interface. The BSs within a cluster also need to report the local CSI to its CM. 10 The reference action and states are used to bootstrap the online learning algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> for <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> and ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>) respectively.</p><p>Without loss of generality, we set</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">E I b = 0, Q I k = 0, p I = {p I b = 1 : b ∈ B}, E I b = 0 and Q I k = 0.</formula><p>Yet, the signaling loading and the latency requirement for this part is in fact similar to the existing HSDPA and LTE systems.</p><p>• Signaling requirement through the backhaul over a long timescale (in convergent stage):</p><p>Each BS needs to report the Q-factors of the (updated) local QSI to the BSC (for the BS-DTX control)</p><p>as well as the potential functions of the (updated) local QSI to the CM (for the user scheduling within a cluster). These signaling exchanges are over the high-speed backhaul and over a longer timescale (not on a slot by slot basis). The latency of signaling over backhaul (typically less than 10ms) is negligible.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. STABILITY ANALYSIS</head><p>In this section, we shall analyze the stability conditions for the data queues in the coordinated MIMO networks with infinite data buffer size (N Q = ∞) and finite energy storage size (N E &lt; ∞), and discuss various design insights. We have the following assumption on the BS and MS distributions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Assumption 5 (BS and MS Distributions):</head><p>The location of the BSs follows a homogeneous Poisson Point Process (PPP) Φ of density λ and the location of the MSs follows independent stationary point process in the Euclidean plane <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. Each MS is associated with the closest BS, i.e., the MSs in the Voronoi cell of a BS are associated with it.</p><p>To simplify the analysis, we consider a homogeneous network with K b = 1, P b = P ∀b ∈ B and δ k = δ ∀k ∈ K. In addition, we assume the CSI follows complex Gaussian fading and the longterm path gain follows standard power law L k,b = r -α k,b , where r k,b is the distance between BS b and MS k and α &gt; 2 is the path loss exponent. Furthermore, the renewable energy and bursty data arrivals under Assumptions 3 and 4 are specialized to Bernoulli processes, i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">A Q k (t), A E b (t) ∈ {0, 1}, E[A Q k (t)] = λ Q &lt; 1 and E[A E b (t)] = λ E &lt; 1 for all k ∈ K and b ∈ B.</formula><p>We consider the following randomized BS-DTX policy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definition 4 (Randomized BS-DTX control Policy</head><formula xml:id="formula_66">): At each slot t, each BS b ∈ B is active with probability p tx &gt; 0, i.e., Pr[p b (t) = 1] = p tx , if k∈Kb Q k (t) &gt; 0; p b (t) = 0 otherwise.</formula><p>In the following, we shall analyze the sufficient conditions for the queue stability (i.e., Q k (t) having a steady state limiting distribution for t → ∞ <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>) under the randomized policy in Definition 4 of a randomly chosen user.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Stability Analysis for Systems without BS Coordination (N t = 1)</head><p>In this case, we consider no cooperation among BSs (N t = 1). Using stochastic geometry <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> and the technique of parallel dominant queues <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, the following lemma summarizes the sufficient condition for the queue stability of a randomly chosen MS at a distance r 1 from its BS 11 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lemma 6 (Sufficient Condition for Queue Stability without BS Coordination):</head><p>The data queue of a randomly chosen MS is stable if</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">λ Q &lt; p tx exp -C 1 p tx λ - N 0 P δr α 1 λ Q max (p tx , N t )<label>(25)</label></formula><p>In addition, λ Q max (p tx , N t ) corresponds to the maximum average grid power cost per</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">p G max (p tx , N E ) = 1 -f (p tx , N E ) p tx . N t = 1, C 1 = 2 α-2 πr 2 1 δ and f (p tx , N E ) =      (λ E /ptx) 1-(λ E /ptx) N E 1-(λ E /ptx) N E +1 , λ E = p tx NE NE+1 , λ E = p tx<label>(26)</label></formula><p>Proof: Please refer to Appendix G.</p><p>Remark 10 (Interpretation of Lemma 6): f (p tx , N E ) can be interpreted as the probability that a energy queue is non-empty in a parallel dominant network <ref type="foot" target="#foot_6">12</ref> , i.e., f</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">(p tx , N E ) = Pr[E b &gt; 0]. It can be easily verified from (26) that f (p tx , N E ) increases as N E increases and lim NE→∞ f (p tx , N E ) = min{ λ E ptx , 1} f (p tx , ∞)</formula><p>, which corresponds to the case with infinite energy storage size. In addition,</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">p G max (p tx , N E ) = Pr[p G b = 1].</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Stability Analysis for Systems with BS Coordination (N t &gt; 1)</head><p>In this part, we extend the analysis to the case with BS coordination (N t &gt; 1). For a randomly chosen MS, the interference comes from the active BSs outside its cluster. Hence, we need to consider the distribution of the coordination clusters and the associated analysis is more challenging compared with the case without BS coordination (N t = 1) <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</p><p>Lemma 7 (Sufficient Condition for Queue Stability with BS Coordination): For N t &gt; α 2 , <ref type="foot" target="#foot_7">13</ref> the data queue of a randomly chosen MS in the coordinated MIMO network can be stabilized if</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">λ Q &lt; p tx exp -C Nt p tx λ - N 0 P δr α 1 λ Q max (p tx , N t )<label>(27)</label></formula><p>In addition, λ Q max (p tx , N t ) corresponds to the maximum average grid power cost per BS</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">p G max (p tx , N E ) = 1 -f (p tx , N E ) p tx . C Nt = 2 α-2 πr 2 1 δ min{1, r α-2 1 (λπ) -1+ α 2 Γ(Nt-α 2 ) Γ(Nt-1) } = O(N 1-α 2 t ) as N t → ∞.</formula><p>Proof: Please refer to Appendix H. 11 When NE → ∞ and ptx = 1, the result in <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref> reduces to the coverage probability for cellular networks without BS coordination obtained in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Optimization of Randomized Policy</head><p>We are interested in maximizing λ Q max (p tx , N t ) under grid power constraint P G w.r.t. the parameter p tx in the randomized control policy for any given N E &gt; 0 and N t ≥ 1. Specifically, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">p * tx (N E , N t ) = arg max ptx∈[0,1] λ Q max (p tx , N t )<label>(28)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_74">s.t. p G max (p tx , N E ) ≤ P G Let λ Q * max (N , N t ) = λ Q max (p * tx , N t )</formula><p>denote the optimal value of the optimization problem in (28). Let x * (N E ) denote the solution to p G max (x, N E ) = P G for any given N E &gt; 0. The following theorem summarizes the optimal solution.</p><p>Theorem 2 (Optimization Solution for Queue Stability):</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">p * tx (N E , N t ) = min{x * (N E ), 1, 1 CN t λ }. For any given N t ≥ 1, λ Q * max (N E , N t ) is strictly increasing in N E if x * (N E ) &lt; min{1, 1 CN t λ } and is a constant for all N E if x * (N E ) ≥ min{1, 1 CN t λ }. For any given N E &gt; 0, λ Q * max (N E , N t ) is strictly increasing in N t .</formula><p>Proof: Please refer to Appendix I.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. RESULTS AND DISCUSSIONS</head><p>In this section, we shall discuss the design insights from the analytical results in Section VI. We also compare the delay performance gain of the proposed delay-aware low complexity distributed scheme in Section IV and Section V with the following two baseline schemes using simulation.</p><p>• </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Effect of BS Coordination</head><p>From Theorem 2, we can see that for any given N E &gt; 0, the loading supported by the energy harvesting system λ Q * max (N E , N t ) increases as N t increases. Intuitively, the gain comes from BS coordination. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">2</ref> illustrates the average delay versus the average transmit power cost for different number of transmit antennas N t . It can be observed that the average delay of Baseline 2 and the proposed scheme decreases as N t increases. This demonstrates that BS coordination improves the delay performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Effect of Energy Buffer Size</head><p>From Theorem 2, we can see that for any given N t ≥ 1, the loading supported by the energy</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">harvesting system λ Q * max (N E , N t ) increases in N E . Specifically, when x * (N E ) &lt; min{1, 1 CN t λ }, λ Q * max (N E , N t ) increases as N E increases.</formula><p>The intuition is that the above condition corresponds to the power-limited region. By increasing N E , more renewable energy can be accumulated due to less renewable energy loss when the energy storage is full, and hence more traffic loading can be supported.</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">However, when x * (N E ) ≥ min{1, 1 CN t λ }, λ Q * max (N E , N t ) is constant for all N E &gt; 0.</formula><p>The intuition is that the above condition corresponds to the interference-limited region, in which the traffic loading supported cannot be increased by accumulating more renewable energy through increasing N E . Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">3</ref> illustrates the average delay versus the energy storage size N E at average transmit grid power 15 dBm. It can be observed that the average delay decreases as the energy storage size increases for all the schemes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Performance of the Proposed Scheme</head><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">4</ref> illustrates the average delay versus per-flow loading (average arrival rate λ k ). The average delay of all the schemes increases as the loading increases. The proposed scheme also achieves significant gain over the baselines across a wide range of input loading. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">5</ref> illustrates the convergence property of the proposed distributed online learning algorithm for estimating the per-flow potential function and the per-flow Q-factor. It can be observed that the proposed distributed learning algorithm converges quite fast. Furthermore, the average delay at the the 500-th scheduling slot is 4.1853 pcks, which is much smaller than the other baselines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VIII. SUMMARY</head><p>In this paper, we propose a two-timescale delay-optimal BS-DTX control and user scheduling for energy harvesting downlink coordinated MIMO networks. We show that the two-timescale delayoptimal control problem can be modeled as a POMDP and derive the optimal centralized control. To reduce the complexity and facilitate the distributed implementation, we obtain a distributed solution November 1, 2018 DRAFT</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">A E b (t) + ∆p G b (t) -p E b ′ (t), N E + ∆p G b (t + 1)} ≥ E ′ b (t + 1). (3) When E b (t) = 0 and E ′ b (t) = 0, we have p E b (t) = p E b ′ (t) = 0 and p G b (t) = p G b ′ (t) = p b (t). Thus, we have E b (t + 1) = min{0 + A E b (t), N E }, E ′ b (t + 1) = min{0 + A E b (t), N E } and ∆p G b (t + 1) = ∆p G b (t) + 0 ≥ 0, and hence, E b (t + 1) + ∆p G b (t + 1) = E ′ b (t + 1) + ∆p G b (t + 1) ≥ E ′ b (t + 1)</formula><p>. Therefore, by induction, we can show ∆p G b (ω, t) ≥ 0 for all t. Since the average delay costs per stage are the same, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">1 T T t=1 k β k f (Q k (ω, t)) + b γ b p G b (ω, t) ≤ 1 T T t=1 k β k f (Q k (ω, t)) + b γ b p G b ′ (ω, t)</formula><p>for any given {p(t)} and {s(t)} and T . By taking expectations over all sample paths, lim sup and optimizations over BS-DTX control and user selection policy space, we have min π J</p><formula xml:id="formula_80">(β,γ) π χ(1) ≤ min π ′ J (β,γ) π ′ χ(1)</formula><p>, where π = {Ω 1 , Ω  </p><formula xml:id="formula_81">(E ′ , Q ′ )|(E, Q), Ω(E, Q)], per-stage cost function g (E, Q), Ω(E, Q) .</formula><p>Since the Weak Accessibility (WA) condition holds under our problem setup, by Proposition 4.2.3. in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, the optimal average cost of the transformed MDP is the same for all initial states. In addition, by Proposition 4.1.3. and Proposition 4.1.4. in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, we know that the solution θ, {V (E, Q)} to the Bellman equation in (10) exists. By Proposition 4.2.1. in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, we can complete the proof.</p><formula xml:id="formula_82">Corollary 1: Define Q(E, Q, p) min Ωs(E,Q) g (E, Q), p, Ω s (E, Q) + (E ′ ,Q ′ ) Pr[(E ′ , Q ′ )|(E, Q), p, Ω s (E θ. Thus, we have V (E, Q) = min p∈P Q(E, Q, p).</formula><p>Based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, we can obtain <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>, which is in terms of BS-DTX control Q-factor {Q(E, Q, p)}. From Lemma 2, we have the optimal BS-DTX control action given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>.</p><p>Corollary 2: Based on (10), we can obtain ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. For any (E, Q) ∈ E ×Q, as p * = Ω * p (E, Q) can by obtained by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>, we can obtain Ω * s (E, Q, H) by solving the R.H.S. of ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>) under p * for any A E and A Q as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_83">min Ωs(E,Q) g (E, Q), p * , Ω s (E, Q) + ( E ′ , Q ′ ) Pr[( E ′ , Q ′ )|(E, Q), p * , Ω s (E, Q) ]U ( E ′ , Q ′ ) (a) = min Ωs(E,Q) ( E ′ , Q ′ ) E Pr[( E ′ , Q ′ )|χ, p * , Ω s (χ) ] (E, Q) U ( E ′ , Q ′ ) , ∀(E, Q) ∈ E × Q (b) ⇔ min Ωs(χ) ( E ′ , Q ′ ) Pr[( E ′ , Q ′ )|χ, p * , Ω s (χ) ] (E, Q) U ( E ′ , Q ′ ) , ∀χ ∈ X (c) = min s∈S(p * ) d∈D k∈K 1 -d k -(-1) dk Pr[ρ k (H, p * , s) ≥ δ k ] U ([E -p * ] + , [Q -d] + ) (<label>29</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_84">) (a) ≤ (λπ) Nt-1 (N t -2)! ∞ 0 u 1-α 2 exp (-λπu) u Nt-2 du = (-λπ) α 2 -1 Γ(N t -α 2 ) Γ(N t -1) , N t &gt; α 2<label>(33)</label></formula><p>where (a) is due to α &gt; 2 and the change of variables u = r 2 Ntr 2 1 . (a) is tight for small r 1 . In addition</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">, E[R 2-α Nt |R 1 = r1] ≤ r 2-α 1 .</formula><p>Next, we shall calculate p s (r 1 , λ, λ ′ , N t ). Note that the interference to MS k 0 comes from the active BSs in Φ ′ -B 0 Φ ′ . In addition, the signal power G 1 and interference power G b (from the active BS b ∈ Φ ′ -B 0 Φ ′ ) due to small scale fading are exponentially distributed with mean 1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>. Let Let s = -1 P δr α 1 and R b denote the distance between BS b ∈ Φ ′ -B 0 Φ ′ and MS k 0 , we have        </p><formula xml:id="formula_86">I RN t denote</formula><formula xml:id="formula_87">E IR N t exp -sI RN t = E Φ ′ ,{Gb}   exp   -s b∈Φ ′ -B0 Φ ′ P G b R -α b     =E Φ ′ ,{Gb}   b∈Φ ′ -B0 Φ ′ exp -sP G b R -α b   =E Φ ′   b∈Φ ′ -B0 Φ ′ E {Gb} exp -sP G b R -α b   = E Φ ′   b∈Φ ′ -B0 Φ ′ 1 1 + sP G b R -α b   = exp -2λ ′ π RN t 1 - 1 1 + sP G b R -α b vdv (a) = exp -2λ ′ π r1 R N t r 1 1 1 + ( v r1δ 1/α ) -α vdv (b) = exp -λ ′ πr 2 1 δ 2 α δ -2 α ( R N t r 1 ) 2 1 1 + u α 2 vdv = exp -λ ′ πr 2 1 δ 2 α η δ( r 1 R Nt ) α , α ⇒E RN t E IR N t exp - 1 P δr α 1 I RN t (c) ≥ exp -λ ′ πr 2 1 δ 2 α E RN t η(δ( r 1 R Nt ) α , α) (d) ≥ exp -λ ′ πr 2 1 δ 2 α E RN t η δ( r 1 R Nt ) α , α = exp -λ ′ 2 α -2 πr 2 1 δr α-2 1 E RN t (R Nt</formula></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a). Each BS has N t transmit antennas. Let K b denote the set of K b MS indices associated with the b-th BS and K denote the set of K = b K b MS indices in the network. The set of BSs B = {1, • • • , B} are partitioned into N = B/N t coordination clusters 3 , i.e., B = ∪ N n=1 B n and B n ∩ B n ′ = ∅ ∀n = n ′</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Assumption 1 (</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Quasi-static Fading): h k,b (t) is quasi-static in each scheduling slot for all (k, b) ∈ K × B. Furthermore, each element of vector h k,b (t) follows a general distribution with mean 0 and vairiance 1. The distribution of each element of vector h k,b (t) is i.i.d. over scheduling slots and independent w.r.t. {k, b}. The long-term path gain L k,b remains constant for the duration of the communication session.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the number of data packets at the data queue for the k-th MS and N Q denotes the data buffer size. At slot t, there is I[ρ k (t) ≥ δ k ] ∈ {0, 1} packet successfully received at the k-th MS, where I[•] denotes the indicator function. Hence, the data queue dynamics of the k-th MS is given by</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the aggregation of the ESI over N clusters at the beginning of the t-th slot, where E b (t) ∈ E {0, 1, • • • , N E } denotes the number of renewable energy units in the energy queue for the b-th BS and N E denotes the energy storage size. At slot t, p E b (t) ∈ P unit of renewable energy is consumed from the b-th energy queue for packet transmission. Hence, the energy queue dynamics of the b-th BS is given by</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>), S(p) {s ∈ S : k∈Kb s k = p b , b ∈ B} denotes the feasible user scheduling action space under the BS-DTX control action p, d k ∈ D {0, 1}, and d = {d k ∈ D k : k ∈ K} ∈ D D K . U ( E, Q) is the post-decision potential function given by the following Bellman equation w.r.t. θ, {U ( E, Q)} [17]:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Proof:Remark 6 (</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Please refer to Appendix B. Complexity of Centralized Delay-Optimal Solution): The complexity of obtaining the original Q-factor and the associated BS-DTX control is O (N E + 1) B (N Q + 1) K 2 B . The complexity of obtaining the original post-decision state potential function and the associated user scheduling is</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>• Step 1 [</head><label>1</label><figDesc>a chosen Ω offline, we shall estimate them distributively at each BS based on the instantaneous observations. Algorithm 1: (Online Per-User Q-factor and Potential Function Learning Algorithm) Initialization at the BSs]:Set t = 0. Each BS b initializes { Q0 k (E b , Q k , p)} and { Û 0 k ( E b , Q k )} for all k ∈ K b .• Step 2 [BS-DTX Control at the BSC]: At the beginning of the t-th slot, each BS b reports k∈Kb Qt k (E b (t), Q k (t), p) : p ∈ P to the BSC. The BSC determines BS-DTX control p * (t) p * (E(t), Q(t)) according to (18) and broadcasts p * (t) to all the CMs. Each CM n informs p * b (t) to each BS b ∈ B n . Each BS b determines its renewable and grid power allocations, i.e., pE * b</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>• Step 4 [</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Per-flow Q-factor and Potential Function Update at the BSs]: Based on the current observations A E b (t) and A Q k (t) (k ∈ K b ), each BS b updates the per-flow Q-factor and potential function for the MSs in its cell according to (</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Lemma 5 (</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Convergence of Algorithm 1): iterative updates of the per-flow Q-factor and the per-flow potential function in (21) and (22) converge almost surely, i.e., lim t→∞ Q t k = Q∞ k a.s. and lim t→∞ Ût k = Û∞ k a.s. (∀k ∈ K), where Q∞ k and Û∞ k are the solutions of the fixed point equations in (</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Baseline 1 [</head><label>1</label><figDesc>CSI-based Single Cell Scheme]: Baseline 1 refers to the randomized BS-DTX control and CSI-based user scheduling without BS coordination. Each multi-antenna BS uses maximal ratio combining (MRC) and selects one MS with the maximum successful packet transmission probability based on the observed local CSI. • Baseline 2 [CSI-based Clustered Coordinated MIMO Scheme]: Baseline 2 refers to the randomized BS-DTX control and CSI-based clustered coordinated MIMO with the same coordinated beamforming as the proposed scheme. Each CM determines the user scheduling to maximize the sum successful packet transmission probability of each cluster based on the observed per-cluster CSI. In the simulation, we consider a cellular system with 19 BSs, each has a coverage of 500m and 2 mobiles per cell, which distribute uniformly in the cell-edge with range [400m, 500m] from the BS. We apply the Urban Macrocell Model in 3GPP [23] with path loss model given by P L = 34.5 + 35 log 10 (r), where r (in m) is the distance from the transmitter to the receiver. Each element of h k,b is CN (0, 1). The total bandwidth is 1MHz. The BS transmit power is P b = 35 dBm for all b ∈ B, the threshold is δ k = 0.5, and β k = 1 for all k ∈ K. γ b is the same for all b ∈ B. We consider Bernoulli arrival processes for the renewable energy and busty data arrivals. The maximum buffer size N Q = 15 pcks.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>2 α u -α 2 du = 2x 1- 2 α α- 2 η 1 .</head><label>2221</label><figDesc>) 2-α |R 1 = r 1 (e) ≥ exp -C Nt λ ′ (35)where (a) is due to plugging in s = -1 P δr α 1 , (b) is due to the change of variables u = ( v r1δ 1/α ) -α , (c) is due to the convexity of the exponential function, (d) is due to η(x, α) (x, α), (e) is due to inequality (33) andE[R 2-α Nt |R 1 = r1] ≤ r 2-αSubstituting (35) into (34), we have p s (r 1 , λ, λ ′ , N t ) ≥ exp -C Nt λ ′ -N0 P δr α 1 . Since λ ′ = p tx λ, we can prove (27).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. System model and control architecture of the downlink coordinated MIMO systems. The dotted lines and solid lines on Fig 1. (b) denote the control path and data path, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Average delay versus average transmit grid power (dBm) at Nt = 2 and Nt = 4. The average data arrival rate is λ Q k = 0.4 pck/slot, the average renewable energy arrival rate is λ E b = 0.5 unit/slot, and the energy storage size NE = 4 units for all k ∈ K and b ∈ B.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Average delay versus energy storage size at average transmit grid power 15 dBm. The average data arrival rate is λ Q k = 0.4 pck/slot and the average renewable energy arrival rate is λ E b = 0.6 unit/slot for all k ∈ K and b ∈ B.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Average delay versus average data arrival rate at average transmit grid power 25 dBm. The average renewable energy arrival rate is λ E b = 0.5 unit/slot and the energy storage size NE = 4 for all b ∈ B.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Markov chain with the following transition probability</figDesc><table><row><cell>Pr[χ(t + 1)|χ(t), Ω t (χ(t))]</cell></row><row><cell>= Pr[H(t + 1)|χ(t), Ω t (χ(t))] Pr[E(t + 1)|χ(t), Ω t (χ(t))] Pr[Q(t + 1)|χ(t), Ω t (χ(t))]</cell></row></table><note><p>= Pr[H(t + 1)] Pr[E(t + 1)|χ(t), Ω t (χ(t))] Pr[Q(t + 1)|χ(t), Ω t (χ(t))]</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>2 </figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, • • • } with Ω t satisfying the structure in Lemma 1.</figDesc><table /><note><p>APPENDIX B: PROOF OF LEMMA 2, COROLLARY AND COROLLARY Lemma 2: Based on Definition 2, we can transform the POMDP into the MDP with a tuple of the following four objects: state space E × Q, action space P × S with partitioned architecture {Ω t (E, Q)} according to Definition 2, transition kernel Pr[</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the interference, which is a function of random variable R B . Therefore, we havep s (r 1 , λ, λ ′ , N t ) = Pr[SIN R ≥ δ|R 1 = r 1 ] = Pr[ P G 1 r -α 1 N 0 + I RN t ≥ δ] =E RN t E IR N t Pr[G 1 ≥ 1 P δr α 1 (N 0 + I RN t )|I RN t ] = E RN t E IR N t</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>exp -</cell><cell>1 P</cell><cell>δr α 1 (N 0 + I RN t )</cell></row><row><cell>= exp -</cell><cell>N 0 P</cell><cell>δr α 1</cell><cell>E RN t E IR N t</cell><cell>exp -</cell><cell>1 P</cell><cell>δr α 1 I RN t</cell><cell></cell><cell>(34)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>-C Nt λp tx λ) exp -C Nt p tx λ -f (p tx , N E )) &gt; 0, ∀N E &gt; 0where the last inequality is due to ∂f (ptx,NE)∂ptx &lt; 0 and f (p tx , N E ) ≤ 1. In addition, p tx ∈ [0, 1].Therefore, we can easily obtain p * tx (N E , N t ). Next, we shall prove the property ofλ Q * max (N E , N t ) w.r.t. N E . It is obvious that x * (N E ) increases with N E . If x * (N E ) &lt; min{1, 1 CN t λ } , p * tx (N E ) = x * (N E ) and dλ Q max dptx ptx=p * tx (NE ,Nt) &gt; 0. Thus, λ Q * max (N E , N t ) is increasing in N E . If x * (N E ) ≥ min{1, 1 CN t λ }, p * tx (N E ) = min{1, 1 CN t λ }. λ Q * max (N E , N t )is a constant for all N E . Finally, we shall show the property of λ Q * max (N E , N t ) w.r.t. N t for any given N E &gt; 0. It can be easily verified that C Nt is decreasing in N t . Thus, when p * tx(N E , N t ) = x * (N E ) or 1, we have that λ Q * max (N E , N t ) = p * tx (N E ) exp -C Nt p * tx (N E )λ -N0 P δr α 1 is increasing in N t . When p * tx (N E , N t ) = 1 CN t λ , we have that λ Q * max (N E , N t ) = C Nt λ exp -1 -N0 P δr α 1 is increasing in N t .</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">APPENDIX I: PROOF OF THEOREM 2</cell></row><row><cell>dλ Q max dp tx</cell><cell cols="4">= (1 N 0 P</cell><cell>δr α 1</cell><cell>   ≤ 0, p tx ≥ 1 CN t λ   &gt; 0, p tx &lt; 1 CN t λ</cell><cell>(36)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">∂p G max (p tx , N E ) ∂p tx</cell><cell>= 1 -</cell><cell>∂f (p tx , N E ) ∂p tx</cell><cell>+ (1</cell></row><row><cell>November 1, 2018</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>DRAFT</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>November 1, 2018 DRAFT</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_1"><p>If there are more than one solutions, we choose the one maximizes ||h T k,b w k,b || 2 .</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_2"><p>In general, we allow different MSs with different packet sizes, and hence the threshold is indexed by k and may be different for different MSs.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_3"><p>One unit of energy for the b-th BS corresponds to the amount of energy consumed in downlink transmission at each slot for the b-th BS, i.e. P b τ Joule. Note that the instantaneous transmit power from the renewable power source is finite (i.e., P b ). The notion "unit of energy" can be easily extended from binary (on-off) power control to handle (multi-level) power control.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="7" xml:id="foot_4"><p>Note that under Assumption 3 and Assumption 4, we have Pr[A Q k (t) = 0] &gt; 0 and Pr[A E b (t) = 0] &gt; 0 for all k ∈ K and b ∈ B, respectively.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="8" xml:id="foot_5"><p>POMDP is an extension of MDP when the control agent does not have direct observation of the entire system state.November 1, 2018 DRAFT</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="12" xml:id="foot_6"><p>In the parallel dominant network, dummy packets are transmitted if a data queue is empty. Thus, the BS-sDTX controls are decoupled from the data queues, i.e., independent of the QSI, and hence, the renewable and grid power consumptions are symmetric across all the BSs.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="13" xml:id="foot_7"><p>Note that Nt &gt; α 2 implies Nt &gt; 1 for most of the cases we are interested in, as wu usually have 2 &lt; α &lt; 4 in practical systems.November 1, 2018 DRAFT</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div><p>This work was supported by <rs type="funder">Huawei Technologies Co</rs>. Ltd.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>with the BS-DTX control at the BSC based on the aggregation of the ESI and QSI and the user scheduling at each CM based on the per-cluster ESI, QSI and CSI with guaranteed delay performance. We prove the almost-sure convergence of the proposed distributed two-timescale algorithm. Furthermore, we analyze the stability conditions for the data queues in coordinated MIMO networks and discuss various design insights.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX APPENDIX A: PROOF OF LEMMA 1</head><p>We shall prove Lemma 1 using sample path arguments. Let {A E (ω, t)}, {A Q (ω, t)} and {H(ω, t)} be a given sample path (i.e., ω) of energy arrivals, packet arrivals and CSI states. Let {p(t)} and {s(t)} be any given sequences of feasible BS-DTX control actions and user scheduling actions.</p><p>Note that for given {p(t)} and {s(t)}, the trajectory of QSI {Q(ω, t)} is uniquely determined.</p><p>Let {p E (ω, t)} and {p G (ω, t)} be the sequences of the renewable power DTX control actions and grid power DTX control actions satisfying the structure in Lemma 1 for the given {p(t)}, i.e.,</p><p>), where {E(ω, t)} is the trajectory of ESI associated with {p E (ω, t)}. Let {p E ′ (ω, t)} and {p G′ (ω, t)} be any other sequences of feasible renewable power DTX control actions and grid power DTX control actions conditioned</p><p>, and {E ′ (ω, t)} be the trajectory of ESI associated with {p E ′ (ω, t)}.</p><p>In the following, for each b ∈ B, we shall show that for E ′ (ω, 1) = E(ω, 1), we have</p><p>and ∆p G b (ω, t) ≥ 0 for all t ≥ 1 by induction. (In the following proof, we omit ω for notation simplicity.)</p><p>We shall show the conclusions hold for t + 1 by considering the following three cases. (1) When E b (t) &gt; 0, we have p E b (t) = p b (t) and p G b (t) = 0. Thus, we have  </p><p>APPENDIX C: PROOF OF LEMMA 3</p><p>We shall prove the additive property w.r.t. the potential function. Following the proofs of Corollary 1 and Corollary 2, the additive property can be easily extended to the Q-factor and the post-decision potential function. Let θ and V (E, Q) be the average cost and the potential function under Ω. Then, we have the following Bellman equation in terms of ( θ, { V (E, Q)}):</p><p>where</p><p>Let θk and Vk (E, Q) be the per-flow average cost and potential function under Ω. Then, we have the following per-flow fixed point equation in terms of ( θk</p><p>Under Ω, the induced Markov chain has a single recurrent class. Therefore, the solutions to (30) and</p><p>(31) exist, respectively. First, we have</p><p>Second, by the relationship between the joint distribution and the marginal distribution, we have</p><p>. Therefore, substitute θ = k∈K θk and V (E, Q) = b∈B k∈Kb Vk (E b , Q k ) into (30), we can see that the equality holds. Therefore, we complete the proof.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX D: PROOF OF LEMMA 4</head><p>Using the approximation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref> and (29), we have</p><p>Under the assumptions 3 and 4 as well as Ω in Definition 3, Markov chain {(E(t), Q(t))} has a single recurrent class (and possibly some transient states). Thus, Ω is a unchain policy. In addition, it is obvious that Ω * = Ω. Therefore, the conditions of Proposition 4.4.2 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> are satisfied expect for the assumption that Ω * is a unchain policy. We shall modify the proof of Proposition 4.4.2 to incorporate a general Ω * as follows. We adopt the same notations as Proposition 4.4.2. (µ can be treated as Ω and μ can be treated as Ω * ). Let ( λ, h μ) be the gain-bias pair of a general μ. Thus, by Proposition 4.1.9, ( λ, h μ) satisfies λ = P λ and λ+h μ = T μh μ. However, let (λ, h µ ) be the gain-bias pair of a unchain µ, which satisfies λe</p><p>there is strict performance improvement under Ω * over Ω. Thus, we have a stronger result than (4.97),</p><p>i.e. δ(i) &gt; 0 ∀i. To incorporate a general μ, we have δ = (λe -λ) + (I -P)∆ instead of (4.98).</p><p>Since λ = P λ, we have N -1 k=0</p><p>Pk δ = N (λe -λ) + (I -PN )∆ in stead of (4.99), which implies P * δ = λe -λ instead of (4.100). Since δ(i) &gt; 0 ∀i, we have λ &gt; λ(i) ∀i. In other words, we can</p><p>APPENDIX F: PROOF OF LEMMA 5</p><p>Note that the update equations in ( <ref type="formula">21</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>) can be treated as the synchronous stochastic versions of the synchronous relative value iterations (RVI) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> for the Markov chains</p><p>)with the policy space containing only one policy Ω <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. Under Ω defined in Definition 3, the two Markov chains have a single recurrent class (and possibly some transient states).</p><p>Therefore, the condition of Lemma 2 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> holds, according to the explanation for the conditions of Proposition 4.3.2 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. Following the proof of Lemma 2 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, which is a modified version of the proof for Proposition 4.3.2 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, we can prove Lemma 5. We omit the details here due to page limit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX G: PROOF OF LEMMA 6</head><p>From the conditional coverage probability (conditioned on the nearest BS being at a distance r 1 from the randomly chosen MS) for cellular networks without BS coordination obtained in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, we have the conditional successful packets transmission probability of the randomly chosen MS given by</p><p>, where λ ′ is the density of the homogeneous PPP Φ ′ used to model the locations of active BSs and the inequality is due to η</p><p>Next, we shall show sufficiency by proving that <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref> guarantees stability in a parallel dominant network, in which dummy packets are transmitted when a data queue is empty. Sending dummy packets is only aimed to cause interference to the other MSs and not counted as an actual packet transmission. The dominant system stochastically dominates the original system in the sense that the queue sizes and grid power costs in that system are necessarily not smaller (bigger) than those in the original system. Therefore, the stability conditions obtained for the dominant systems are sufficient for the stability of the original system. In the dominant system, since Pr[p b = 1] = p tx , we have λ ′ = p tx λ. Therefore, the service rate of the randomly chosen MS is µ(p tx , λ) = p tx p s (r 1 , λ ′ ).</p><p>By Loynes' Theorem, the queue of the randomly chosen MS is stable if λ Q &lt; µ(p tx , λ). Thus, we complete the proof for <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref>. Note that E b is decoupled from Q k and forms a discrete-time M/M/1/N E system with arrival rate λ E and departure rate p tx . By queueing theory, we have <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. Thus, we can prove the average grid power cost in the dominant system is</p><p>APPENDIX H: PROOF OF LEMMA 7</p><p>In the following proof, we shall focus on the derivation of the conditional successful packet transmission probability p s (r 1 , λ, λ ′ , N t ). The remaining proof is similar to that in the proof of   </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-cell MIMO cooperative networks: A new look at interference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gesbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hanly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shamai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Shitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Simeone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Select. Areas Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1380" to="1408" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-12">Dec. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coordinated beamforming for the multicell multi-antenna wireless system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Dahrouj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">17481759</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010-05">May 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Networked MIMO with clustered linear precoding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ghosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Heath</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1910" to="1921" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-04">Apr. 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterizing multi-cell cooperation via the outage-probability exponent</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE Int. Conf. on Commun. (ICC)</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE Int. Conf. on Commun. (ICC)<address><addrLine>Ottawa, Canada</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-06">Jun 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coordinated multi-cell MIMO systems with cellular block diagonalization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Heath</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of Asilomar Conference on Signals, Systems and Computers (ACSSC)</title>
		<meeting>of Asilomar Conference on Signals, Systems and Computers (ACSSC)<address><addrLine>Pacific Grove, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007-11">Nov. 2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1669" to="1673" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Limited downlink network coordination in cellular networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Boccardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE International Symposium on Personal, Indoor and Mobile Radio Communications (PIMRC)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Athens, Greece</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007-09">Sept. 2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Centralized scheduling for joint transmission coordinated multipoint in LTE-advanced</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brueck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Giese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Amin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of International ITG Workshop on Smart Antennas (WSA)</title>
		<meeting>of International ITG Workshop on Smart Antennas (WSA)<address><addrLine>Bremen</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010-02">Feb. 2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="184" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Utility optimal scheduling in energy harvesting networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Neely</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of Mobihoc</title>
		<meeting>of Mobihoc<address><addrLine>Paris, France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-05">May 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">control of wireless networks with rechargeable batteries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gatzianas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Georgiadis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tassiulas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="581" to="593" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic node activation in networks of rechargeable sensors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Krishnamurthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Jaggi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Trans. Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-02">Feb. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Dynamic Programming and Optimal Control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Bertsekas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>Athena Scientific</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Massachusetts</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>rd ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A tractable approach to coverage and rate in cellular networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Baccelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ganti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Commun</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>under revision</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interference in Large Wireless Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Haenggi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ganti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.nd.edu/∼mhaenggi/pubs/now.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Foundations and Trends in Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Solving POMDPs by searching the space of finite policies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Meuleau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kaelbling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cassandra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the Fifteenth Conf. on Uncertainty in AI</title>
		<meeting>of the Fifteenth Conf. on Uncertainty in AI</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="426" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Green radio technologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gozalvez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Vehicular Technology Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-03">Mar. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Binary power control for multi-cell capacity maximization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gjendemsj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gesbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE 8th Workshop on Signal Processing Advances in Wireless Communications (SPAWC)</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE 8th Workshop on Signal essing Advances in Wireless Communications (SPAWC)<address><addrLine>Helsinki, Finland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Online Algorithms for Delay Constrained Scheduling over a Fading Channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Salodkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-05">May 2008</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Indian Institute of Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning algorithms for Markov decision processes with average cost</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B J</forename><surname>Abounadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Borkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Control Optim</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="681" to="698" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stochastic approximation with two time scales</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Borkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Systems and Control Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="294" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stability conditions for some distributed systems: Buffered random access systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Szpankowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Buffered Random Access Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="498" to="515" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The stability region of random multiple access under stochastic energy harvesting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jeon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ephremides</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)<address><addrLine>Saint-Petersburg, Russia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-08">Aug. 2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1796" to="1800" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the stability of interacting queues in a multiple-access system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ephremides</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="918" to="930" />
			<date type="published" when="1988-09">Sept. 1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://www.3gpp.org/technologies" />
		<title level="m">TR 25.996 v8.0.0, Spatial channel model for Multiple Input Multiple Output (MIMO) simulations</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributive stochastic learning for delay-optimal OFDMA power and subband allocation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">K N</forename><surname>Lau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4848" to="4858" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-09">Sept. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On distance in uniformly random networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Haenggi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3584" to="3586" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-10">Oct. 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-antenna communication in ad hoc networks: Achieving MIMO gains with SIMO transmission</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Jindal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="540" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-02">Feb. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
