<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Relationship between Principal Transformational Leadership and Teacher Professionalism through Discipline and Work Climate of State Elementary School Teachers in Tanjung District</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Rikhe</forename><surname>Adriani</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master in Educational Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ahmad</forename><forename type="middle">Muhyani</forename><surname>Rizalie</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master in Educational Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Relationship between Principal Transformational Leadership and Teacher Professionalism through Discipline and Work Climate of State Elementary School Teachers in Tanjung District</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-41</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T21:35+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>transformational leadership</term>
					<term>teacher professionalism</term>
					<term>discipline</term>
					<term>work climate</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This study aims to analyze the direct and indirect relationship between the principal's transformational leadership, teacher professionalism, discipline, and teacher work climate. This study uses the regression method with path analysis. The study population was 314 teachers, and a sample of 176 respondents was taken using a simple proportionate random sampling technique. Data collection uses an instrument using a scale Likert. The questionnaire consists of a principal transformational leadership questionnaire (35 items), teacher professionalism (30 items), discipline (32 items), and work climate (35 items). The instrument was tested for validity and reliability and analyzed using path analysis. The study results found a direct relationship between the principal's transformational leadership, discipline, and work climate with teacher professionalism; there was an indirect relationship between the principal's leadership through field and work climate with teacher professionalism.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>RI Law Number 14 of 2015 concerning Teachers and Lecturers in article 1 paragraph (1) states that teachers are professional educators with the main task of educating, teaching, guiding, directing, training, assessing, and evaluating students in early childhood education through the education pathway. Formal education, primary education, and secondary education <ref type="bibr">(Depdiknas, 2005)</ref>. Rusman (2016: 55) states that professional teachers are a determining factor in a quality education process, the current low quality of education is an indication of the need for professional teachers, for those teachers are expected not only to carry out their profession, but teachers must have a strong desire to carry out their duties. Their duties are in line with the rules of teacher professionalism required. In Tanjung District, 33 SD Countries have different accreditation values. Differences in accreditation status are caused by the diversity of quality and quantity of teachers, administrative staff, financial capabilities, facilities, infrastructure, etc. Based on data in the field, information on academic data is obtained from ASN and non-ASN teachers. They teach at State Elementary Schools in Tanjung Subdistrict all have D4/S1 certificates. Many teachers teach subjects that do not match the major or diploma of expertise; many teachers do not recognize the characteristics of students well. They tend to teach conventionally, and many teachers do not use information technology as a learning tool/media. The fact above shows the low professionalism of teachers in Tanjung Subdistrict, caused by various factors. Internal factors include the discipline of teachers and the work they carry out, while external factors include leadership behavior and work climate. Leadership is a process in which an individual influences a group of individuals to achieve a goal. To be an effective leader, a school principal must influence the entire school community he leads in positive ways to achieve educational goals at school. Permendikbud Number 6 of 2018 Article 1 paragraph (3) states that the competence of school principals is the competence of knowledge, attitudes, and skills inherent in the dimensions of personality, managerial, entrepreneurial, supervisory, and social competencies (Depdiknas, 2016). Principal leadership is an important component in the school management system, directing the input, process, and output of education in schools. The principal is responsible for and is responsible for the success of education by carrying out school administration with all its substance. In addition, the principal is responsible for the quality of existing resources to carry out their respective duties and functions <ref type="bibr">(Juliantoro, 2017: 22)</ref>. According to Hariyanti ( 2016: 18), the transformational leadership style is appropriate to be applied within the shaping of school culture. Therefore, principals must use the characteristics and qualities of transformational leadership when making decisions in implementing school culture reform. Yukl (2015:134) adds that transformational leadership can negatively affect followers and organizations. If leaders influence organizational members with different visions, increased role ambiguity and role conflict will be increased. In addition, competition among sub-units can result in a decrease in organizational effectiveness. Teacher professionalism is also determined by high discipline. Thus, the school in the teaching-learning process grows discipline and will function as a shaper of teachers' individual values and norms, self-control, attitudes, and responsibilities. Prijodarminto (2014: 28) explains that discipline is a person's awareness and willingness to obey the rules that exist in the organization and the prevailing social norms. From this opinion, when it is associated with teacher work, teacher work discipline is the teacher's willingness to obey the rules and norms at school, in the community, and the state. <ref type="bibr">Winardi (2019: 43)</ref> states that work discipline is a management action to encourage awareness and willingness of its members to obey all regulations that have been determined by the organization or company and social norms that apply voluntarily. If it is associated with teacher work discipline, management actions encourage teachers' awareness and willingness to obey the school and the state's rules. Another factor that influences the professionalism of teachers in schools is the work climate. According to Robbin (2013: 46), this climate is manifested in the context of communication between people who are working. Thus the questions that need to be asked are: (1) what is the level of support for people who are working with each other; (2) what is the collegial level (friendship) of the people who are working; and (3) how intimate (intimacy) the people who are working because behavior can be observed, measured, and has a high value of openness compared to other dimensions. Good and bad work climates in schools can cause changes in teacher behavior to be negative or positive. A positive influence can lead to changes towards improvement, in this case, an increase in teacher professionalism, which can achieve organizational goals. The climate in the school organization is a work atmosphere that leads to an atmosphere of relationships within the school. Climate is seen as something that distinguishes one school from another. By creating a conducive school climate, teachers will feel comfortable working and motivated to work better. This condition reflects that a conducive school atmosphere strongly supports the improvement of the teacher's work climate. The school climate needs to be created by the school leader (principal) to create a conducive school atmosphere and a teacher's work environment. So teachers can carry out their duties with pleasure, enthusiasm, and passion for working well. There needs to be good communication between fellow school members, close relationships between individuals, openness, teacher involvement in decision making, appreciation for achievements achieved, respect and respect for fellow school members, etc. Based on the description above, many factors influence the professionalism of teachers in Tanjung Subdistrict, namely the principal's transformational leadership in building school activity plans, high work discipline to comply with existing regulations in the organization, and applicable social norms and management of a conducive work climate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHOD</head><p>This study aims to describe and analyze direct and indirect relationships between principal transformational leadership, teacher professionalism, discipline, and teacher work climate. The population in this study amounted to 314 people with a total sample of 176 people. The sampling technique in this study is simple proportionate random sampling, and the researchers determine the number of samples based on the Cronbach Alpha formula. Data were collected through a questionnaire using a Likert scale measurement scale that had been tested for validity and reliability by choosing one of 4 alternative answers, namely Strongly Agree (SS), Agree (S), Disagree (KS), Disagree (TS), and Strongly Disagree (STS). Descriptive and inferential statistics then analyzed the answers through SPSS 26. The research instrument is designed in The questionnaires are the principal's transformational leadership ( idealized influence, inspirational motivation, intellectual stimulation, individualized consideration), discipline ( official duties, time, work atmosphere, community service, behavior), teacher work climate (conformity, responsibility, standards, rewards), and teacher profession ( high level of commitment, high level of abstract ). The questionnaire was prepared using a Likert scale, analyzed by correlation using path analysis to see direct and indirect relationships between variables, by first using the prerequisite analysis test. The conceptual relationship model between variables are seen in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1. Conceptual Relationship Model Between Variables</head><p>Analysis using the path according to the conceptual model, there are seven research hypotheses, namely: H 1: there is a direct relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and teacher professionalism; H 2: there is a direct relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and teacher discipline; H 3: there is a direct relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and the teacher's work climate; H4: _ there is a direct relationship between teacher discipline and teacher professionalism; H 5: there is a direct relationship between work climate and teacher professionalism; H 6: there is an indirect relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and teacher professionalism through teacher discipline; H 7: there is an indirect relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and teacher professionalism through the teacher's work climate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head><p>Based on the results of SPSS-assisted data processing, the researchers found coefficients that show direct and indirect relationships between variables as described in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> This relationship is evidenced by the regression path coefficient of the transformational leadership variable on teacher professionalism (Pxy) of 0.247. This result indicates that the principal's transformational leadership will increase teacher professionalism. The principal's transformational leadership relationship is very important to make efforts to encourage and empower teachers to be more professional. A leader needs to motivate his subordinates to carry out more responsibilities than expected. In addition, it must be able to define, communicate and articulate the organization's vision, and subordinates must accept and recognize its leader. The results of this study support previous research, namely Fernandes, Cedwyn, and Awamleh ( 2018), Lasmi (2018), Baskoro (2020), Rahmah (2019), and Harahap (2019). Humphreys <ref type="bibr">(Winardi, 2019: 96)</ref> states that leaders who apply transformational leadership will cause constant change towards improvement for the organization. With these positive changes, the teacher is ready to accept the tasks given by the leader without a burden, happy and satisfied in doing the work and improving the teacher's performance.</p><p>The impact applied by transformational leadership is that the leader can influence the performance of his subordinates; subordinates will feel confident, amazed, proud, loyal, and respectful to superiors and motivated to do work with results that exceed the targets that have been set together.</p><p> There is a Direct Relationship Between a Principal's Transformational Leadership and Teacher Discipline Based on the path analysis test results, there is a relationship between transformational leadership and teacher discipline. This relationship is evidenced by the regression coefficient value, which is 0.338. This value indicates that the principal's transformational leadership will improve teacher discipline.Principal leadership affects teacher work discipline; this shows that effective leadership can result in higher levels of teacher work discipline. In general, a teacher can achieve expectations at work if there is good selfdiscipline. Good discipline reflects a person's sense of responsibility for the tasks assigned to him. Therefore, every principal always tries so that the teachers have the good discipline for the success of printing their students. The principal's transformational leadership is said to be effective if the teachers under his responsibility have good discipline. The results of this study support the opinion of Sedarmayanti (2013:37). Transformational leaders behave in a way that can motivate and inspire those around them by giving meaning and challenges to the work done by their followers so that team motivation will increase and the emergence of enthusiasm and optimism. Bass Avolio (Duhou, 2013141) states that the core of this motivation lies in the leader's ability to awaken the depth of followers' willingness to believe in the future and commit to goals to achieve the vision. Other studies that are in line regarding the influence of leadership on discipline are Kusnandi (2018), Rahmah (2019), Aslamiah &amp; Normianti ( 2019 ), and Putriningsih (2021 ), which state that there is a direct influence of the principal's transformational leadership on teacher discipline.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> There is Connection Direct Between Principal Transformational Leadership and Teacher Work Climate</head><p>Based on the calculation of the regression analysis with the t-test of the principal's transformational leadership variable with the work climate variable, it was obtained a significance value of 0.000 &lt;0.05 and seen from the T-value of 20.092 &gt; 1.654 (Ttable), meaning that there was a significant relationship between the principal's transformational leadership variable ( X) with the work climate variable (Z2), so the higher the transformational leadership of the principal, the higher the teacher's work climate.</p><p>Transformational leadership is a leadership style that can transform the organization in the face of change and dare to take risks so that it becomes an ideal leader for the context of organizational effectiveness. At the same time, the work climate is the atmosphere or working atmosphere in an organization. The work climate is one of the important aspects that support the success of the teacher's learning process. A conducive work climate supports the smoothness and continuity of the learning process.</p><p>Transformational leadership based on conceptual wealth through charisma, individual consideration, intellectual stimulation, and inspiring professionalism can produce thoughts that reach out to the future. The principal's transformational leadership that creates positive relationships in the work climate will create a conducive atmosphere to support useful actions.</p><p>The results of this study support previous research conducted by Sudiyanto (2019), Aminuddin (2019), <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Wirawan (2018)</ref>, and Harahap (2019), all of these researchers produced the same finding that there is a relationship between transformational leadership and work climate.</p><p> There is a Direct Relationship Between Teacher Discipline and Teacher Professionalism The significant value of the relationship between teacher discipline and teacher professionalism is 0.002 &lt; 0.05. The T count value of 3.182 &gt; 1.974 (Ttable) means that there is a direct relationship between discipline and teacher professionalism. Teacher work discipline is the act of a person complying with the rules that have been mutually agreed upon. This action, if done correctly and continuously, will become a habit that is embedded in the teacher's behavior and will help achieve the work goals that have been determined. High discipline will be able to build professional performance because with good discipline; the teacher can observe the rules and strategic steps in carrying out teaching and learning activities.</p><p>The study in line with this research is Kartini (2020), whose research results have a significant relationship between teacher discipline and teacher work professionalism with a beta value of 0.369, a t-count value of 2.826, and a significance value of 0.007. Laeli's  There is an Indirect Relationship Between Transformational Leadership Principals and Teacher Professionalism through Discipline Based on the study results obtained by 0.247, there is an increase in the value of teacher professionalism directly in every 1-point increase in the value of the work climate variable. This result means that the work climate will increase the professionalism of teachers. Some of the things that lead to teacher work discipline include the principal's transformational leadership, work climate, and co-workers. The principal acts as a supervisor who provides an example so that teachers will set an example in being disciplined at work. If this work discipline is embedded in a teacher, the teacher's desire will arise to take any action or good performance. So work discipline has a role in creating an atmosphere of enthusiasm, forging oneself to become a better educator. Thus, if an organization wants to have discipline, With a high level of leadership, leadership is needed that can move subordinates to feel excited to do work with a high level of discipline. The results of this study support the findings of Aslamiah &amp; Normianti (2019), Rahmah (2019), Taufiqurrahman (2019), and Wahyudi (2020); all of these researchers produced the same findings that there is a relationship between transformational leadership, teacher professionalism, and discipline,  There is an Indirect Relationship Between Principal Transformational Leadership and Teacher Professionalism Through Work Climate The indirect relationship of the principal's transformational leadership variable to teacher professionalism through the work climate variable has a regression coefficient value of 0.367, supported by the results of the Sobel test, which shows that t count (5.421) &gt; t table (1.654). This shows that the work climate as a mediation (intervening) can bring a positive relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and teacher professionalism. It can be concluded that there is an indirect relationship between transformational leadership through the work climate and teacher professionalism. The work climate in a school is very influential on the behavior of teachers. Therefore, the work climate must get the attention of the principal. The work climate has a positive effect on the continuity and profitability of the school. A school will only develop well if it is supported by a conducive work climate. With transformational leadership, the principal is responsible for the creation of a harmonious work climate. Transformational leadership with the ability to individualize influence can influence teachers in building a work climate by creating an environment of openness so that teachers do not hesitate to express their desires and needs to be needed at work. The principal always supports any activities aimed at improving education or school progress. The results of this study support the findings of Normianti </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Based on this study's analysis results and discussion, the researchers concluded that v variables of transformational leadership of principals are in the high category. Then, the teacher discipline is in the very high category, work climate is in the high category, and teacher professionalism is in the very high category. Moreover, there is a direct relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and teacher professionalism. The principal's transformational leadership also relates directly to teacher discipline. Further, there is a direct relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and the teacher's work climate. The teacher's</p><p>The Relationship Between Principal Transformational Leadership and Teacher Professionalism through Discipline and Work Climate of State Elementary School Teachers in Tanjung District</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(2019). The Influence of Principal Transformational Leadership, Teacher Work Climate, Teacher Discipline with Professional Work of State Elementary School Teachers in South Labuan Amas District. Other similar studies, such as Harahap (2019), Aslamiah &amp; Normianti (2019), Djatmiko (2018), and Kusnandi (2018), in their conclusions, both mention the existence of a transformational leadership relationship through work climate with teacher professionalism.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 . Summary of path analysis results</head><label>1</label><figDesc>.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Model</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Unstandardized Coefficients</cell><cell>Standardized Coefficients</cell><cell>t</cell><cell>Sig.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>B</cell><cell cols="2">Std. Error Beta</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(Constant)</cell><cell>28,490</cell><cell>7,623</cell><cell></cell><cell>3,737</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>Transformational leadership</cell><cell>,233</cell><cell>,088</cell><cell>,247</cell><cell>2,654</cell><cell>,009</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Discipline</cell><cell>,167</cell><cell>0.052</cell><cell>,176</cell><cell>3.182</cell><cell>,002</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Working Climate ,364</cell><cell>,077</cell><cell>,439</cell><cell>4,717</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">a. Dependent Variable: Teacher Professionalism</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">b. R Square : 0,559</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Structure 2 transformational leadership, discipline</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Unstandardized</cell><cell cols="2">Standardized</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Coefficients</cell><cell>Coefficients</cell><cell>t</cell><cell>Sig.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>B</cell><cell cols="2">Std. Error Beta</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>(Constant)</cell><cell>78,687</cell><cell>9,380</cell><cell></cell><cell>8,389</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Transformational</cell><cell>,388</cell><cell>0.070</cell><cell>,388</cell><cell>5.557</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>leadership</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">a. Dependent Variable: Discipline</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">b. R Square : 0.151</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>Structure 1 principal transformational leadership, discipline, work climate, professionalism teacher.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Wo rk climate The Relationship between Principal Transformational Leadership and Teacher Professionalism through Discipline and Work Climate of State Elementary School Teachers in Tanjung District</head><label></label><figDesc>Based on table 1 and figure 2 above, the rejection and acceptance of the hypothesis in this study can be seen in table 2 below.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">Structure 3 transformational leadership and work climate</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Unstandardized</cell><cell>Standardized</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Coefficients</cell><cell></cell><cell>Coefficients</cell></row><row><cell>Model</cell><cell></cell><cell>B</cell><cell cols="2">Std. Error Beta</cell><cell>t</cell><cell>Sig.</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>(Constant)</cell><cell>1,819</cell><cell>6,361</cell><cell></cell><cell>,286</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>,775</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Transformational</cell><cell>,950</cell><cell>0.047</cell><cell>,836</cell><cell>20.092</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>leadership</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">a. Dependent Variable: Work Climate</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">b. R Square : 0.699</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="4">Figure 2. Path Analysis Results</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 . Summary of Path Analysis Regression Analysis Test Results</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Hypothesis</cell></row></table><note><p>Based on the results of the analysis in table 1 and figure 2 above, this study, it was successfully found the relationship between variables that can be explained as follows:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>367) The Relationship Between Principal Transformational Leadership and Teacher Professionalism through Discipline and Work Climate of State Elementary School Teachers in Tanjung District  There is a Direct Relationship between Transformational Leadership and Teacher Professionalism</head><label></label><figDesc>Based on the research hypothesis test results, there is a relationship between transformational leadership and teacher professionalism.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>The Relationship Between Principal Transformational Leadership and Teacher Professionalism through Discipline and Work Climate of State Elementary School Teachers in Tanjung District (</head><label></label><figDesc>2020) research results found that work discipline had a significant effect on teacher professionalism. Rahmah (2019) the result is that there is a significant influence of teacher discipline on the professionalism of teachers at the Tabalong City Junior High School.  There</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>is a Direct Relationship Between Work Climate and Teacher Professionalism</head><label></label><figDesc>The professional factor of teachers in improving their professional skills is strongly influenced by the support of the work climate, which includes flexibility in participating in training, development, equipment, technology, performance standards, management, and colleagues. This organizational climate support is defined as a work climate. The work climate needs attention because these factors affect the behavior of teachers, employees, and students. Thus, schools should develop dynamically, leading to a better continuity and progress of education. One way to build school organizations is to achieve a conducive work climate. This variable contributes to explaining teacher performance because an excellent working atmosphere will provide a high achievement boost for teachers. A conducive school work climate will have an impact, especially on the professionalism of teachers to further improve their skills in actualizing ideas, creativity, innovation, cooperation, and healthy competition in seeking to achieve the school's vision, mission, and goals that have been set. The results of this study strengthen the opinion of Harahap (2019) in his research stating that there is an influence between work climate and work professionalism.<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Taufiqurrachman (2019)</ref> stated that there is a relationship between the work climate and professional teachers with a powerful category equal to 0.908. Aslamiah &amp; Normianti (2019) A conducive work climate can improve teacher professionalism. Wibowo Research (2017) put forward a significant relationship between work climate and teacher professionalism.</figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>discipline also directly relates to the teacher's professionalism. There is a direct relationship between the work climate and teacher professionalism. Furthermore, there is an indirect relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and teacher professionalism through teacher discipline. There is an indirect relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and teacher professionalism through the teacher's work climate. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>REFERENCES</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of School Climate, Teacher Motivation, and Discipline on the Professionalism of State Senior High School teachers, Pademawu District, Pamekasan Regency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mohammad</forename><surname>Taufiqurrachman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Social Studies Research and Education (JPPI)</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1858-4985</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of The Transformational Leadership and Work Climate and Discipline on Teachers Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wahyudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Scientific &amp; Technology Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship between Transformational Leadership, Work Discipline and Teacher&apos;s Work Climate on Teacher Profession in SD Negeri Kec. Kersana, Brebes Regency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wibowo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Science Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Winardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Organizational Behavior Management</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Jakarta</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kencana</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Organizational Culture and Climate: Application Theory and Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wirawan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Four Salemba</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">), which permits remixing, adapting and building upon the work for non-commercial use</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gary</forename><surname>Yukl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Leadership in the organization. Jakarta: PT. Gramedia Group Index. There is an Open Access article, distributed under the term of the Creative Commons Attribution -Non Commercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>provided the original work is properly cited</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
