<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wen</forename><forename type="middle">Wei</forename><surname>Loh</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Data Analysis</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ghent University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Gent</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Beatrijs</forename><surname>Moerkerke</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Data Analysis</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ghent University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Gent</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tom</forename><surname>Loeys</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Data Analysis</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ghent University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Gent</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Stijn</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Mathematics, Computer Science and Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ghent University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Gent</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medical Statistics</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1037/met0000314</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T21:45+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Direct and indirect effects</term>
					<term>Interventional effects</term>
					<term>Multiple mediation analysis</term>
					<term>Path analysis</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>When multiple mediators exist on the causal pathway from treatment to outcome, path analysis prevails for disentangling indirect effects along paths linking possibly several mediators. However, separately evaluating each indirect effect along different posited paths demands stringent assumptions, such as correctly specifying the mediators' causal structure, and no unobserved confounding among the mediators. These assumptions may be unfalsifiable in practice and, when they fail to hold, can result in misleading conclusions about the mediators. Nevertheless, these assumptions are avoidable when substantive interest is in inference about the indirect effects specific to each distinct mediator. In this article, we introduce a new definition of indirect effects called interventional indirect effects from the causal inference and epidemiology literature.</p><p>Interventional indirect effects can be unbiasedly estimated without the assumptions above while retaining scientifically meaningful interpretations. We show that under a typical class of linear and additive mean models, estimators of interventional indirect effects adopt the same analytical form as prevalent product-of-coefficient estimators assuming a parallel mediator model. Prevalent estimators are therefore unbiased when estimating interventional indirect effects -even when there are unknown causal effects among the mediators -but require a different causal interpretation. When other mediators moderate the effect of each mediator on the outcome, and the mediators' covariance is affected by treatment, such an indirect effect due to the mediators' mutual dependence (on one another) cannot be attributed to any mediator alone. We exploit the proposed definitions of interventional indirect effects to develop novel estimators under such settings.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Mediation analysis is widely used in the behavioral, psychological and social sciences to gain insight into the extent to which the causal effect of a treatment (A) on an outcome (Y ) is transmitted through intermediate variables on the causal pathway from A to Y . Consider the following social psychology example by <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Voelkel et al. (2019)</ref>, who investigated the causal effect of a political inclusion manipulation (A) on the level of prejudice toward a political outgroup (Y ). Perceived worldview dissimilarity of the political outgroup (M 1 ) is considered a mediator if the manipulation affects how strongly an individual regards the political outgroup as holding political or social beliefs different from her/his own, which in turn causes a change in prejudice toward that outgroup. Similarly, perceived fairness of the political outgroup (M 2 ) is also considered a mediator if the manipulation affects how strongly an individual regards the outgroup as being open to different opinions, which in turn causes a change in prejudice toward that outgroup. Many realistic mediation analyses involve multiple mediators, either because interventions are designed to affect outcome by changing multiple (repeated measures of) mediators, or because scientific interest is in trying to understand the various causal pathways through (simultaneous) competing candidate mediators. Path analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Wright, 1934;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Duncan, 1966)</ref> is therefore commonly used to disentangle the indirect or mediated effects of A on Y along the causal paths through the multiple mediators.</p><p>Building on our example, the causal diagram of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>(a) depicts the causal relations between the variables when worldview dissimilarity (M 1 ) and fairness (M 2 ) are assumed not to affect each other. In this article, a causal diagram is a causal directed acyclic graph (DAG) <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Hayduk et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Pearl, 2012)</ref> that, similar to path diagrams in the structural equation modeling (SEM) framework, represents (assumed) causal relations among a set of variables. Vertices represent variables, and a directed edge e.g., from M 1 to Y , represents the causal effect M 1 may exert on Y . The absence of a DISENTANGLING <ref type="bibr">INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 4</ref> directed edge between two variables, e.g., between M 1 and M 2 in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>(a), implies that neither variable causally affects the other, conditional on their common causes, e.g., treatment A and observed baseline covariate(s), such as political ideology, henceforth denoted by C. A summary of key concepts of causal DAGs can be found in e.g., <ref type="bibr">Moerkerke et al. (2015, Figure</ref>  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">2</ref>). Here and throughout, the causal effects between the treatment and each mediator, between each mediator and the outcome, and between the treatment and the outcome, are assumed to be based on well-established scientific theoretical knowledge or empirical laws that satisfy logical and causal-temporal constraints <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Fiedler et al., 2018)</ref>. Unlike path diagrams, causal DAGs do not rely on (parametric) assumptions about the nature of the relationship between the variables; hence path coefficients and error terms are not displayed on causal diagrams in this article.</p><p>Mediation using path analysis within the SEM framework extends the <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Baron &amp; Kenny (1986)</ref> approach for a single mediator by employing (multiple) linear regression models for the mediator(s) and the outcome; see e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">MacKinnon (2008)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Hayes (2018)</ref> for book-length presentations and the detailed references therein. A linear path analysis model (or set of linear regression models) is first fitted to the outcome and the mediator(s) using SEM (or ordinary least squares; OLS). The effect of treatment transmitted along a particular path, as encoded by the (partial) regression coefficients of the variables on the path, is then calculated using the product-of-coefficients method <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alwin &amp; Hauser, 1975;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">MacKinnon et al., 2002)</ref>. This method prevails (as opposed to the "difference" method) when there are multiple mediators <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(MacKinnon, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Preacher &amp; Hayes, 2008)</ref>. Continuing our example above in the causal diagram of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>(a), when M 1 and M 2 are assumed not to affect each other, the indirect effect via M 1 in the corresponding (linear) path model is defined to be the product of the coefficient of A in the regression of M 1 on A and C, and the coefficient of M 1 in the regression of Y on A, M 1 , M 2 and C. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS</head><formula xml:id="formula_0">5 A M 2 M 1 Y C (a) A M 2 M 1 Y C (b) A M 2 M 1 Y C U (c) A M 2 M 1 Y C (d)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Existing path analysis approaches for multiple causally linked mediators</head><p>When the assumed causal structure of the mediators allows for "compound" paths from treatment to outcome that traverse several (causally) linked mediators, each indirect effect along any path that passes through at least one of the mediators can be separately assessed <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Hayes, 2018</ref>). Using the motivating example, suppose that worldview dissimilarity (M 1 ) is assumed to causally affect fairness (M 2 ), as depicted in the causal diagram of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>(b). The "three-path" mediated effect passing through both mediators along the path A → M 1 → M 2 → Y <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Taylor et al., 2008</ref>) is defined to be the product of the coefficient of A in the regression of M 1 on A and C, the coefficient of M 1 in the regression of M 2 on A, M 1 and C, and the coefficient of M 2 in the regression of Y on A, M 1 , M 2 and C. However, there are three potential pitfalls when DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 6 estimating the separate indirect effects along each path. First, the indirect effects are well-defined exclusively when the assumed (directions of the) causal effects among the mediators are correct. For example, suppose that the true causal relation between the mediators was that fairness (M 2 ) affected worldview dissimilarity (M 1 ) as shown in the causal diagram of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1(d)</ref>. The estimated mediated effect along the assumed path A → M 1 → M 2 → Y will not (generally) be unbiased for the true effect along the (different) path A → M 2 → M 1 → Y . Second, even when the causal effects are correctly specified, estimates can be biased when there is hidden or unobserved confounding of the mediators. For example, suppose that worldview dissimilarity (M 1 ) and fairness (M 2 ) do not causally depend on each other, but instead share a hidden confounder U (such as prior adverse interactions with a political outgroup) as depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1(c)</ref>. Because neither mediator exerts a causal effect on the other, there is no causal effect along any path where one mediator affects the other. But incorrectly assuming that M 1 affects M 2 will result in biased (non-zero) estimates of the mediated effect along the path</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">A → M 1 → M 2 → Y .</formula><p>Specifically, the bias is due to biased estimates of the (partial) regression coefficient of M 1 (in the regression of M 2 on A, M 1 and C) because M 1 and M 2 are correlated only due to hidden U , and not because M 1 influences M 2 . Third, even when the causal effects are correctly specified, and there is no hidden confounding of the mediators, the causal effect transmitted along the path A → M 1 → M 2 → Y cannot be (non-parametrically) identified in general without (empirically untestable) assumptions about the mediators' joint distribution. We elaborate on this last point using the counterfactual-based mediation framework later in this article.</p><p>Notwithstanding the possibility of (unbiasedly) estimating separate indirect effects along different assumed paths, substantive interest may be in the indirect effects transmitted through each distinct mediator instead. We first consider settings where the causal structure among the mediators can be (correctly) assumed, and defer settings that do not require assuming any causal structure (among the mediators) to the next section. Separate indirect effects along a set of different paths may be combined based on a given definition of an indirect effect via a specific mediator <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Bollen, 1987)</ref>. For DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 7 example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Greene (1977)</ref> proposes a restrictive definition of the indirect effect via a mediator of interest to include only the path that intersects the particular mediator alone and no other mediators, whereas <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Brown (1997)</ref>, following <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Fox (1980)</ref>, proposes a less restrictive definition that includes all paths that intersect the particular mediator.</p><p>The former approach fails to account for mediated effects along compound paths traversing several linked mediators, whereas the latter approach can potentially yield indirect effects whose sum is greater than the total (treatment) effect. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alwin &amp; Hauser (1975)</ref> propose including all paths intersecting that mediator and any of its descendants, and excluding all paths via mediators that causally precede the mediator of interest. This approach ensures that the sum of the indirect effects via each mediator equals the joint indirect effect via all the mediators, but only when each indirect effect via a mediator is not moderated by any other mediator. Furthermore, we reiterate that it is necessary to correctly specify the (directions of the) causal effects among the mediators in the assumed path model for the above definitions of indirect effects via each distinct mediator to be valid.</p><p>In general when multiple mediators are correlated, there may be several plausible explanations of the associations, such as those depicted in the causal diagrams of Figures 1(b), 1(c), and 1(d) for M 1 and M 2 . Researchers seeking to learn about the causal effects among the mediators may consider fitting different models assuming different (possibly conflicting) causal structures, then ideally select the model that best fits the observed data. But different models can be statistically indistinguishable, e.g., when they are saturated with zero degrees of freedom, or have identical goodness-of-fit measures. Merely assuming causal effects among the mediators can result in severely misleading conclusions about the mediated effects. Even when the assumed causal effects among the mediators are correct, it may be unrealistic to assume that the mediators do not share hidden or unobserved confounders, such as when the mediators are manifestations of an unknown latent variable or process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 8</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A different definition of indirect effects via each mediator</head><p>In this article we propose a different definition of indirect effects when substantive interest is in the indirect effects that are specific to each mediator. The proposed definitions do not require (correctly) specifying how the mediators causally depend on one another. We first provide an intuitive motivation, and defer its formal derivation to the next section. Suppose that the outcome obeys the following linear and additive mean model:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">E(Y |A, M 1 , M 2 , C) = β 0 + β A A + β 1 M 1 + β 2 M 2 + β C C.</formula><p>(1)</p><p>The effect of each mediator M s on outcome is encoded by the (partial) regression coefficient β s , s = 1, 2 in (1). To avoid specifying any causal dependence among the mediators, consider the marginal mean model for each mediator M s , s = 1, 2, that depends only on treatment A and baseline covariate(s) C, and does not depend on the other mediator. In particular, suppose that the linear and additive (marginal) mean model for M s is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">E(M s |A, C) = δ 0s + δ s A + δ Cs C, s = 1, 2. (<label>2</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">)</formula><p>It is important to note that (2) does not imply assuming that there are no causal effects between M 1 and M 2 . Indeed, the intention is simply to leave the causal structure of the mediators unspecified, and to only consider the "overall" or "total" (i.e., marginal) effect of treatment A on each mediator M s , s = 1, 2 (conditional on C). The overall effect of A on M s captures all of the treatment effects that are transmitted through any intermediate variables on the causal pathway between A and M s . This overall or total effect is simply encapsulated by the (partial) regression coefficient δ s , s = 1, 2 in (2).</p><p>Using the product-of-coefficients method, the indirect effect via mediator M s is therefore encoded by β s δ s . Estimating this product requires no knowledge of the (possibly unknown) causal structure among the mediators from which the observed data is generated.</p><p>The mean models implied by ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">2</ref> where the mediators are a priori assumed not to causally affect each other. Such path models (without baseline covariates C) are termed "parallel" multiple mediator models <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Hayes, 2018)</ref>. In fact, a prevalent approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(MacKinnon, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Preacher &amp; Hayes, 2008)</ref>   <ref type="bibr">, 2000)</ref>, or freely estimated <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Preacher &amp; Hayes, 2008)</ref>.</p><p>The indirect effect estimates remain unchanged when the mediator residuals are permitted to covary only if either (i) there are no mediator-mediator interaction terms in the outcome mean model ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) or (ii) the covariances do not depend on treatment.</p><p>When other mediators moderate the effect of each mediator on the outcome, and the mediators' covariances are affected by treatment, existing indirect effect estimates assuming a parallel path model may be severely biased. Furthermore, there can be an indirect effect that cannot be attributed to any specific mediator due to the mediators' </p><formula xml:id="formula_5">mutual</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Interventional direct and indirect effects</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mediation analysis using a counterfactual-based framework</head><p>Notwithstanding the widespread use of parametric approaches to mediation analysis, a counterfactual-based framework for mediation analysis has been developed using model-free definitions of natural direct and indirect effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(Robins &amp; Greenland, 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Pearl, 2001)</ref>. This development enables extensions to non-additive and non-linear models, and formalizes the "ignorability" assumptions needed to identify the natural (in)direct effects, without relying on a specific statistical model; see e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Imai, Keele, &amp; Tingley (2010)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Pearl (2014)</ref> for the single mediator setting. Under these assumptions, the total effect can be decomposed into a direct and an indirect effect.</p><p>Using linear and additive (i.e., without interactions) mean models for the mediator and outcome in the mediation formula yields the same estimators as the path analysis approach using the product-of-coefficients method <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Imai, Keele, &amp; Yamamoto, 2010)</ref>.</p><p>When there are multiple mediators, identifying the natural indirect effects via each mediator is challenging because one mediator that is affected by treatment can concurrently be a confounder of the mediator-outcome association for another mediator, also known as post-treatment or treatment-induced confounding; see e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">VanderWeele et al. (2014)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Moerkerke et al. (2015)</ref>. Here and throughout we will consider all post-treatment confounders to be competing possible mediators. Continuing our example above, suppose that worldview dissimilarity (M 1 ) affects fairness (M 2 ), as <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Avin et al., 2005)</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">depicted in Figure 1(b), so that M 1 is a post-treatment confounder of the M 2 -Y relation. Then the natural indirect effect via M 2 cannot be (non-parametrically) identified because M 1 is a recanting witness that is set to different counterfactual values along the different paths A → M 1 → Y and A → M 1 → M 2 → Y (</formula><p>Strong (empirically untestable) parametric assumptions about the joint distribution of the (counterfactual) mediators are required to identify the natural effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Shpitser, 2013)</ref>. Recent proposals of counterfactual-based mediation analysis for multiple DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 12 (repeated measures of) mediators have thus relied on stringent ("sequential ignorability") assumptions to carefully identify natural indirect effects either along certain causal pathways <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Daniel et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Steen et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Albert et al., 2019)</ref>, or assuming no causal effects among the mediators <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Lange et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Taguri et al., 2018)</ref>. But (fine-grained) decompositions of indirect effects using these existing methods require correctly specifying the (absence of) causal effects among the mediators, and assuming that the mediators share no hidden confounders. In most realistic scenarios, the directions of the causal effects between the various mediators are unknown, thus either violating the assumptions needed to identify the indirect effects, or demanding additional assumptions about the correct specification of the causal structure.</p><p>In contrast, interventional (in)direct effects, first introduced by Didelez et al. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definition of potential outcomes</head><p>To facilitate the conceptual development of interventional (in)direct effects, we present definitions under a setting with two mediators M 1 and M 2 , and defer results for more than two mediators to the Online Supplemental Materials. In this article, uppercase letters denote (observed) random variables and (possibly unobserved) potential outcomes, and lowercase letters denote specific values, for each individual. For</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">s = 1, 2, let M s,a (s) denote the potential outcome for M s if, possibly counter to fact, treatment A is set to a (s) . Let Y am 1 m 2 denote the (individual) potential outcome for Y</formula><p>if, possibly counter to fact, A is set to a, and when each mediator M s is set to the value</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">m s , s = 1, 2.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definition of interventional indirect and direct effects</head><p>In this section, we formally define the interventional indirect and direct effects and describe the exact decomposition of the total effect for a binary treatment A. We provide interpretations of the interventional (in)direct effects in terms of the underlying causal path(s) in the causal diagrams of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</p><p>Define the interventional indirect effect of treatment on outcome via M 1 , henceforth denoted by IE 1 , as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">E m 1 ,m 2 E(Y 1m 1 m 2 |C) {Pr(M 1,1 = m 1 |C) -Pr(M 1,0 = m 1 |C)} Pr(M 2,0 = m 2 |C) . (3)</formula><p>The interventional indirect effect via mediator M 1 is the treatment effect of changing M 1 from its marginal (counterfactual) distribution under treatment level a (1) = 1 to its distribution under level a (1) = 0, while fixing the mediator M 2 at its distribution under Similarly, define the interventional indirect effect of treatment on outcome via M 2 , henceforth denoted by IE 2 , as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">E m 1 ,m 2 E(Y 1m 1 m 2 |C) Pr(M 1,1 = m 1 |C) {Pr(M 2,1 = m 2 |C) -Pr(M 2,0 = m 2 |C)} . (4)</formula><p>The interventional indirect effect via mediator M 2 can be analogously interpreted as the indirect effect via M 1 . In particular, when the underlying causal structure among the mediators is as depicted in the causal diagrams of Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1(a</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_11">→ M 2 → Y and A → M 1 → M 2 → Y .</formula><p>As before, the interventional indirect effect via M 2 is interpreted as the effect of treatment that is mediated by M 2 , and any other mediators causally preceding M 2 , in the underlying causal diagram. In general, when there are t &gt; 2 distinct mediators, the interventional indirect effect via each mediator M s , henceforth denoted by IE s , for s = 1, . . . , t, is defined in the Online Supplemental Materials.</p><p>In this article, subscripts in the notation for mediators are merely used to distinguish the different mediators, and not to indicate an a priori assumed causal ordering of the mediators; e.g., M 1 is not necessarily assumed to causally precede M 2 .</p><p>Nonetheless, the definitions of the indirect effects via each mediator will generally, but not necessarily, differ by changing the indices of the mediators, due to fixing the other mediator at its distribution under a different hypothetical treatment level. For example, had worldview dissimilarity been merely indexed as M 2 , the indirect effect via worldview dissimilarity would hold the distribution of perceived fairness (now M 1 ) fixed under the political inclusion condition instead. The hypothetical treatment levels are fixed at different values merely to ensure that the separate indirect effects via each mediator add up to the same quantity in (5) defined below, regardless of the (typically arbitrary)</p><p>indices used solely to label the mediators for statistical analysis. Notwithstanding such differences, we emphasize that the conceptual interpretation of the interventional indirect effect via each mediator -in terms of the causal pathways in the underlying causal structure -is invariant to the different mediator indices. In later sections, we describe the estimators when the effect of each mediator on the outcome is moderated by treatment, or the other mediator, or both, and describe a sensitivity analysis.</p><p>It follows that the sum of the separate interventional indirect effects via each mediator, i.e., IE 1 + IE 2 , is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">E m 1 ,m 2 E(Y 1m 1 m 2 |C) {Pr(M 1,1 = m 1 |C) Pr(M 2,1 = m 2 |C) -Pr(M 1,0 = m 1 |C) Pr(M 2,0 = m 2 |C)} . (<label>5</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">)</formula><p>This indirect effect describes the average difference in the outcome when both marginal DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 16</p><p>(counterfactual) distributions of the mediators M 1 and M 2 are simultaneously shifted from the treated group (a (1) = a (2) = 1) to the control group (a (1) = a (2) = 0). Because the product of the marginal distributions does not equal the joint distribution of the mediators in general, define the joint indirect effect via the mediators, henceforth denoted by IE jo , as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">E m 1 ,m 2 E(Y 1m 1 m 2 |C) {Pr(M 1,1 = m 1 , M 2,1 = m 2 |C) -Pr(M 1,0 = m 1 , M 2,0 = m 2 |C)} . (<label>6</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_15">)</formula><p>We emphasize that in (6) the joint (counterfactual) distribution of the mediators M 1 and M 2 is shifted, instead of the marginal distributions as defined in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_12">5</ref>). The difference between IE jo in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_14">6</ref>) and IE 1 + IE 2 in (5), henceforth denoted by IE mu , is therefore:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">E   m 1 ,m 2 E(Y 1m 1 m 2 |C)    Pr(M 1,1 = m 1 , M 2,1 = m 2 |C) - 2 s=1 Pr(M s,1 = m s |C) -Pr(M 1,0 = m 1 , M 2,0 = m 2 |C) + 2 s=1 Pr(M s,0 = m s |C)      . (7)</formula><p>We refer to (7) as the indirect effect due to the mediators' mutual dependence on each other <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Vansteelandt &amp; Daniel, 2017</ref>). We will demonstrate in the next section that under assumed linear models for the means of the mediators and the outcome, this indirect effect is non-zero only if (i) the effect of each mediator on the outcome is moderated by the other mediator, and (ii) the covariance of the mediators is affected by treatment. Because this effect cannot be attributed to any mediator alone, it should be considered separately from the indirect effects via each mediator.</p><p>The interventional direct effect of treatment on outcome that avoids both mediators, henceforth denoted by DE, is correspondingly defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">E m 1 ,m 2 {E(Y 1m 1 m 2 |C) -E(Y 0m 1 m 2 |C)} Pr(M 1,0 = m 1 , M 2,0 = m 2 |C) . (<label>8</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_18">)</formula><p>The direct effect (8) is the treatment effect when controlling the joint (counterfactual) distribution of the mediators M 1 and M 2 to be under control, i.e., a (1) = a  <ref type="formula" target="#formula_14">6</ref>) and the direct effect (8) to be the total effect of treatment on outcome, henceforth denoted by TE, as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">E   m 1 ,m 2 E(Y 1m 1 m 2 |C) Pr(M 1,1 = m 1 , M 2,1 = m 2 |C) -E(Y 0m 1 m 2 |C) Pr(M 1,0 = m 1 , M 2,0 = m 2 |C) . (<label>9</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_20">)</formula><p>In other words, TE = DE + IE jo = DE + IE 1 + IE 2 + IE mu . Definitions for settings with more than two distinct mediators are provided in the Online Supplemental Materials.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Identification of interventional effects</head><p>Identification of the interventional effects defined above requires the following assumptions <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Vansteelandt &amp; Daniel, 2017)</ref>: scenario under which assumption (A2) is violated, as illustrated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Mayer et al. (2014)</ref> in their opening example (for a single mediator), is when baseline measurements of a mediator and the outcome are correlated and unadjusted for, even in a randomized experiment. For this reason, baseline covariates were adjusted for in models ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">2</ref>).</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">(A1) The effect of treatment A on outcome Y is unconfounded conditional on C. (<label>A2</label></formula><p>Because M 1,a (1) and M 2,a (2) are unknown for each value of {a (1) , a (2) } except when a (1) = a (2) = A, assumption (A3) states that there are no unobserved confounders between A and any of (M 1 , M 2 ), or equivalently, that the observed covariate(s) C are sufficient to adjust for confounding of the effects of A on (M 1 , M 2 ). This assumption is implied in the causal diagrams of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> by the absence of any hidden common causes of A and any of (M 1 , M 2 ). Note that assumptions (A1) and (A3) are satisfied in randomized trials when A is randomly assigned. When treatment is not randomly assigned, observed (baseline) confounders of the treatment-mediator(s) and treatment-outcome should be included in C and adjusted for in the mediator and outcome models.</p><p>When the assumptions (A1)-(A3) hold, the interventional direct and indirect effects defined above can be inferred from the observed data. In particular, the average potential outcomes, and joint distribution of the counterfactual mediators, can be (non-)parametrically identified by the following observable quantities:</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">E m 1 ,m 2 E(Y a (0) m 1 m 2 |C) 2 s=1 Pr(M s,a (s) = m s |C) = E m 1 ,m 2 E(Y |A = a (0) , M 1 = m 1 , M 2 = m 2 , C) 2 s=1 Pr(M s = m s |A = a (s) , C) ; (10) E m 1 ,m 2 E(Y a (0) m 1 m 2 |C) Pr(M 1,a (1) = m 1 , M 2,a (1) = m 2 |C) = E m 1 ,m 2 E(Y |A = a (0) , M 1 = m 1 , M 2 = m 2 , C) Pr(M 1 = m 1 , M 2 = m 2 |A = a (1) , C) . (<label>11</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_23">)</formula><p>In practice, unbiased estimation of the interventional direct and indirect effects therefore depends on correctly modeling the outcome conditional on treatment, mediators, and covariates, e.g., </p><formula xml:id="formula_24">E(Y |A = a, M 1 = m 1 , M 2 = m 2 , C), that is unbiased for E(Y am 1 m 2 |C),</formula><formula xml:id="formula_25">= m 1 , M 2 = m 2 |A = a, C), that is unbiased for Pr(M 1,a = m 1 , M 2,a = m 2 |C).</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Estimators of interventional indirect and direct effects</head><p>In this section we describe estimators of the interventional (in)direct effects defined in the previous section. We first assume a parallel path model with no interaction terms in the outcome model, then relax this assumption to allow for treatment-mediator, mediator-mediator, and treatment-mediator-mediator interactions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outcome models without interaction terms</head><p>Suppose that the outcome obeys the linear and additive mean model in (1), i.e., The interventional indirect effect via each mediator M s , s = 1, 2, is identified upon plugging the assumed outcome model (1) and mediator models (2) into (10); i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">E(Y |A, M 1 , M 2 , C) = β 0 + β A A + β 1 M 1 + β 2 M 2 + β C C.</formula><formula xml:id="formula_27">IE s = β s {E(M s |A = 1) -E(M s |A = 0)} = β s δ s .</formula><p>The joint indirect effect (IE jo ) and direct effect (DE) are similarly identified under the assumed outcome model (1) and mediator models (2) using (11); i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">IE jo = 2 s=1 β s {E(M s |A = 1) -E(M s |A = 0)} = 2 s=1 β s δ s , DE = β A .</formula><p>Unbiased estimation of the interventional (in)direct effects thus requires correctly specifying the outcome mean model (1) and mediator (marginal) mean models (2)</p><p>under assumptions (A1)-(A3).</p><p>As previously noted in the introduction, the derivation of the interventional effects imply mean models (1) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">2</ref> OLS, then plugging in estimates of the (partial) regression coefficients for the respective effects using the product-of-coefficients method. Standard errors can be estimated using a nonparametric percentile bootstrap procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Efron &amp; Tibshirani, 1994</ref>) that randomly resamples observations with replacement. In general when there are t &gt; 2 distinct mediators, the estimators of the interventional indirect effects via each mediator M s , s = 1, . . . , t, are described in the Online Supplemental Materials.</p><p>Again we emphasize that δ s in (2) encodes the overall or total effect of A on M s and captures all of the underlying treatment effects that are transmitted from A to M s through any causal ancestors of M s . To see why fitting mean models (1) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">2</ref> path model where M 1 has a causal effect on M 2 , with the mediator and outcome models: </p><formula xml:id="formula_29">E(M 1 |A, C) = α * 01 + α * 1 A + α * C1 C, E(M 2 |A, M 1 , C) = α * 02 + α * 2 A + η * 12 M 1 + α * C2 C, E(Y |A, M 1 , M 2 , C) = β * 0 + β * A A + β * 1 M 1 + β * 2 M 2 + β * C C.</formula><formula xml:id="formula_30">E(M 2 |A, C) = m 1 E(M 2 |A, M 1 = m 1 , C) Pr(M 1 = m 1 |A, C) = α * 02 + α * 2 A + η * 12 E(M 1 |A, C) + α * C2 C = α * 02 + α * 2 A + η * 12 (α * 01 + α * 1 A + α * C1 C) + α * C2 C = (α * 02 + η * 12 α * 01 ) + (α * 2 + η * 12 α * 1 )A + (α * C2 + η * 12 α * C1 )C.</formula><p>The interventional indirect effect via M 2 in the true but unknown model is thus</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">identified by β * 2 (α * 2 + η * 12 α * 1 )</formula><p>. By fitting to the observed data a parallel path model with outcome mean model ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>), so that β 2 = β * 2 , and mediator mean model ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">2</ref>), so that</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">δ 2 = α * 2 + η * 12 α * 1</formula><p>, it follows that the interventional indirect effect can be unbiasedly estimated using the product-of-coefficients method because</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">β 2 δ 2 = β * 2 (α * 2 + η * 12 α * 1 )</formula><p>(assuming (A1)-(A3) hold). Hence the parallel path model is used merely to obtain estimators of the interventional indirect and direct effects using ubiquitous linear SEM or OLS estimation methods. Unbiased estimation does not require the mediators to be causally independent, as implied in the parallel path model; in fact, the (marginal) mean model ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">2</ref>) is used precisely so that the interventional indirect effects are agnostic to the underlying causal dependence among the mediators.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outcome models with treatment-mediator, mediator-mediator, and treatment-mediator-mediator interaction terms</head><p>Under the assumed outcome model (1), the joint indirect effect via both mediators (IE jo ) equalled the sum of both separate indirect effects via each mediator (IE 1 + IE 2 ).</p><p>As we will demonstrate next, this was a consequence of excluding mediator-mediator interaction terms from the outcome model, which precluded a non-zero estimate of the indirect effect due to the mediators' mutual dependence on each other (IE mu ). The effect of a mediator on the outcome is moderated by a third variable if the effect depends on, or is a function of, the third variable. In this section, we develop estimators for the interventional (in)direct effects when the effect of each mediator on the outcome is moderated by treatment, or the other mediator, or both. First, allow for the following DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 22 treatment-mediator, mediator-mediator, and treatment-mediator-mediator interaction terms in the assumed linear mean model (1); i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">E(Y |A, M 1 , M 2 , C) = β 0 + β A A + β 1 M 1 + β 2 M 2 + β A1 AM 1 + β A2 AM 2 + β 12 M 1 M 2 + β A12 AM 1 M 2 + β C C. (<label>12</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_35">)</formula><p>Next, allow the mediators' covariance to depend on treatment A, which we denote by cov(M 1 , M 2 |A) = Σ(A) for notational simplicity. Then under the outcome mean model ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_34">12</ref>) and mediator mean models (2), the indirect effect due to the mediators' mutual dependence ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>) is identified by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">E   m 1 ,m 2 E(Y |A = 1, m 1 , m 2 , C) × Pr(M 1 = m 1 , M 2 = m 2 |A = 1, C) -Pr(M 1 = m 1 |A = 1, C) Pr(M 2 = m 2 |A = 1, C) -Pr(M 1 = m 1 , M 2 = m 2 |A = 0, C) + Pr(M 1 = m 1 |A = 0, C) Pr(M 2 = m 2 |A = 0, C)   = (β 12 + β A12 ) E{cov(M 1 , M 2 |A = 1, C) -cov(M 1 , M 2 |A = 0, C)} = (β 12 + β A12 ){Σ(1) -Σ(0)}. (<label>13</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_37">)</formula><p>We make the perhaps obvious point that the indirect effect ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_36">13</ref>) is non-zero only if (i)</p><p>there is a non-zero (treatment-)mediator-mediator interaction in the outcome model ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_34">12</ref>), i.e., β 12 + β A12 = 0; and (ii) the covariance of the mediators is affected by treatment, i.e., Σ(1) -Σ(0) = 0. Continuing the motivating example from the introduction, perceived worldview dissimilarity (M 1 ) and perceived fairness (M 2 ) may become more weakly correlated among those who were politically included (A = 1) than those in the control condition (A = 0). The treatment group-specific covariances of the mediators can be straightforwardly estimated from the observed data using the empirical covariances within each observed treatment group.</p><p>The interventional indirect effect via mediator M 1 (3) under the outcome mean DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 23 model ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_34">12</ref>) is identified by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">E   m 1 ,m 2 E(Y |A = 1, m 1 , m 2 , C) × Pr(M 1 = m 1 |A = 1, C) -Pr(M 1 = m 1 |A = 0, C) Pr(M 2 = m 2 |A = 0, C)   = {(β 1 + β A1 ) + (β 12 + β A12 ) E(M 2 |A = 0)}δ 1 = {(β 1 + β A1 ) + (β 12 + β A12 )(δ 02 + δ C2 µ C )}δ 1 ,</formula><p>where we denote µ C = E(C) for simplicity. The interventional indirect effect via mediator M 2 (4) is similarly identified by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">{(β 2 +β A2 )+(β 12 +β A12 ) E(M 1 |A = 1)}δ 2 = {(β 2 +β A2 )+(β 12 +β A12 )(δ 01 +δ 1 +δ C1 µ C )}δ 2 .</formula><p>Estimators of the interventional indirect effects when there are more than two mediators are provided in the Online Supplemental Materials. We emphasize that unbiased estimation under the above (correctly-assumed) linear mean models for the mediators and outcome therefore requires no distributional assumptions on the random errors for the variables. We demonstrate this empirically using a simulation study in the next section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Simulation studies</head><p>Three simulation studies were conducted to illustrate estimating the proposed interventional indirect effects. In each study, all mediators were correlated due to an unobserved confounder (of the mediators). In Study 1, a setting with two mediators was used simply to demonstrate the estimators presented in the preceding section. In Studies 2 and 3, we considered more complex and realistic settings with four mediators.</p><p>To provide an overview, in Study 2, a posited path model that incorrectly assumed (the presence of) causal effects among merely correlated mediators was used to estimate separate mediated effects along different paths. For comparison, existing product-of-coefficient estimators under a parallel path model, that adopted the same analytical form as interventional (in)direct effect estimators assuming linear and additive models for the mediators and outcome, were calculated. In Study 3, the effect of each (true) mediator on the outcome was moderated by another mediator, and the mediators' covariance (possibly) depended on treatment. The interventional indirect effects, including the indirect effect due to the mediators' mutual dependence on one another, were estimated using an outcome model that included all mediator-mediator interaction terms. For comparison, indirect effects using a misspecified parallel path model (with only main effects for the mediators in the outcome model) were estimated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 25</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Simulation Study 1</head><p>Each observed dataset was generated with the following linear models corresponding to the causal diagram of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">2</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">A ∼ Bernoulli(0.5) C, U ∼ N (1, 1) M 1 = α 1 A + α C1 C + α U 1 U + 1 , 1 ∼ N (0, σ 2 1 ) M 2 = α 2 A + η 12 M 1 + α C2 C + α U 2 U + 2 , 2 ∼ N (0, σ 2 2 ) Y = β A A + β 1 M 1 + β 2 M 2 + β C C + Y , Y ∼ N (0, σ 2 Y ).</formula><p>Both mediators shared an unobserved (baseline) common cause U that precluded unbiased estimation of the separate (three-path) mediated effect along in (2). Under the assumed models, the interventional (in)direct effect estimators adopted the same analytical form as existing product-of-coefficient estimators under a parallel path model. We reiterate that the mediators need not be causally independent, as implied by the fitted parallel path model. The (marginal) mean models (2) are used solely to estimate the interventional indirect effects that are agnostic to the underlying causal structure among the mediators. 10000 observed datasets with sample size of either 50, 200, or 1000 were generated. Average estimates and empirical standard errors of the mediated effects from fitting the parallel path model to the generated data are displayed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">1</ref>. As expected, all the interventional (in)direct effects were unbiasedly estimated.</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">A → M 1 → M 2 → Y in</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Simulation Study 2</head><p>This simulation study was motivated by a substantive mediation analysis on climate change beliefs and attitudes from the psychology literature (van der <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Linden et al., 2015)</ref>. Each observed dataset was generated with the following linear and additive  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">3</ref>:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 27</head><formula xml:id="formula_42">A ∼ Bernoulli(0.5) C, U ∼ N (0, 1) M s = α s A + α Cs C + α U s U + s , s = 1, 2, 3, M 4 = α 04 + α C4 C + α U 4 U + 4 , s ∼ N (0, σ 2 s ), s = 1, 2, 3, 4, Y = β 2 M 2 + β 3 M 3 + β 4 M 4 + β C C + Y , Y ∼ N (0, σ 2 Y ).</formula><p>Under the (true) data-generating model, the unobserved variable U was a (baseline) confounder of all four mediators, and the observed variable C was a (baseline) confounder of all four mediators and the outcome. The variables A, C, U, and residuals </p><formula xml:id="formula_43">E(Y |M 1 , M 2 , M 3 , M 4 , C) = β 0 + β A A + β 1 M 1 + β 2 M 2 + β 3 M 3 + β 4 M 4 + β C C.</formula><p>Under the assumed models, the interventional (in)direct effect estimators adopted the same analytical form as existing product-of-coefficient estimators under a parallel path model. Average estimates and empirical standard errors of the mediated effects from fitting the posited path model in Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> to the generated data are displayed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>. As expected, all the estimated mediated effects for the separate paths were empirically biased due to unobserved confounding of the mediators. The estimates could be either positively or negatively biased, and remained biased even at large sample sizes. In contrast, all the interventional indirect effects were unbiasedly estimated. </p><formula xml:id="formula_44">A M 1 U M 2 M 3 M 4 Y C</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Simulation Study 3</head><p>This simulation study was used to demonstrate how to obtain estimators of the interventional indirect effects that allowed for mediator-mediator interaction terms in the outcome model. Each observed dataset was generated with the following linear models corresponding to the causal diagram of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">3</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">A ∼ Bernoulli(0.5) C, U ∼ N (0, 1) M s = α s A + α Cs C + α U s U + α U As (U × A) + s , s = 1, 2, 3, M 4 = α 04 + α C4 C + α U 4 U + α U A4 (U × A) + 4 , s ∼ N (0, σ 2 s ), s = 1, 2, 3, 4, Y = β 2 M 2 + β 3 M 3 + β 4 M 4 + β 23 M 2 M 3 + β C C + Y , Y ∼ N (0, σ 2 Y ).</formula><p>The (true) data-generating model in this study differed from the previous study in two respects. The effect of the unobserved confounder U on each mediator was moderated by treatment A due to the U -A interaction term in each mediator mean model. The effect of each (true) mediator on the outcome was moderated by the other (true)</p><p>mediator due to the M 2 -M 3 interaction term in the outcome mean model. The true value of the coefficient for this interaction was set to e.g., β 23 = -(β 2 + β 3 ), simply to amplify possible biases that may arise when omitting this term in the fitted outcome model. For simplicity, there were no other interaction effects in the outcome model, and the direct effect was zero. The variables A, C, U, and residuals 1 , 2 , 3 , 4 , Y were mutually independent of each other. The covariance between the mediators, induced by</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">the unobserved confounder U , was Σ sp (A) = (α U s + α U As A)(α U p + α U Ap A) for s = p,</formula><p>and therefore depended on treatment when α U As = 0 or α U Ap = 0. Following the Online Supplemental Materials, the indirect effect due to the mediators' mutual dependence was identified by</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">β 23 (α U 2 α U A3 + α U 3 α U A2 + α U A2 α U A3</formula><p>). The indirect effects via M 2 and via M 3 were respectively identified by {β 2 + β 23 E(M 3 |A = 0)}α 2 and</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">{β 3 + β 23 E(M 2 |A = 1)}α 3 .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 32</head><p>We generated data under each of two different scenarios in turn. (I) In the first setting, the coefficients for the confounder-treatment interactions in the mediator models were set to zero, i.e., α U As = 0, s = 1, . . . , 4, so that the mediators' covariance did not differ by treatment. The indirect effect due to the mutual dependence of the mediators was therefore zero. However, the indirect effect estimates assuming a parallel path model would be biased due to omitting the mediator-mediator interaction terms in the fitted outcome model. (II) In the second setting, set the coefficients α U As = 0.1, s = 1, . . . , 4, so that the indirect effect due to the mediators' mutual dependence was non-zero. The remaining coefficients and residual variances for both scenarios were set to the same values as in Simulation Study 1.</p><p>The interventional indirect effects were estimated by fitting to each generated data a (marginal) mean model for each mediator, where each mediator depended only on treatment A and observed (baseline) covariate C as shown in (2), and the following outcome model that included all mediator-mediator interaction terms:</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">E(Y |M 1 , M 2 , M 3 , M 4 , C) = β 0 + β A A + β 1 M 1 + β 2 M 2 + β 3 M 3 + β 4 M 4 + β C C + β 12 M 1 M 2 + β 13 M 1 M 3 + β 14 M 1 M 4 + β 23 M 2 M 3 + β 24 M 2 M 4 + β 34 M 3 M 4 .</formula><p>For simplicity, no treatment-mediator or treatment-mediator-mediator interaction terms were included. The indirect effect estimators, as shown in the Online Supplemental Materials, were respectively:</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">IE 1 = {β 1 + β 12 E(M 2 |A = 0) + β 13 E(M 3 |A = 0) + β 14 E(M 4 |A = 0)}δ 1 , IE 2 = {β 2 + β 12 E(M 1 |A = 1) + β 23 E(M 3 |A = 0) + β 24 E(M 4 |A = 0)}δ 2 , IE 3 = {β 3 + β 13 E(M 1 |A = 1) + β 23 E(M 2 |A = 1) + β 34 E(M 4 |A = 0)}δ 3 , IE 4 = {β 4 + β 14 E(M 1 |A = 1) + β 24 E(M 2 |A = 1) + β 34 E(M 3 |A = 1)}δ 4 , IE mu = 4 k,l=1, k&lt;l β kl {Σ kl (1) -Σ kl (0)}.</formula><p>Under the assumed outcome model, different indices for the mediators lead to different (definitions and) estimators of the indirect effects. In particular, swapping the labels for</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 33</head><p>M 2 and M 3 would lead to an estimator for the indirect effect via M 2 where M 3 is fixed at its mean value under treatment instead; i.e., Average estimates and empirical standard errors of the (in)direct effects are displayed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">3</ref>. As expected, the (in)direct effects assuming a parallel path model were empirically biased under both scenarios even in large samples. Furthermore, the indirect effect via a mediator may be of the opposite sign as the true effect. In contrast, estimates of the interventional indirect effects allowing for mediator-mediator interaction terms in the outcome model were empirically unbiased under both scenarios.</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">{β 2 + β 12 E(M 1 |A = 1) + β 23 E(M 3 |A = 1) + β 24 E(M 4 |A = 0)}δ 2 .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary of simulation studies</head><p>The results of Simulation Study 1 empirically demonstrated that the parallel path model can be used to unbiasedly estimate the interventional indirect and direct effects proposed in this article, even when the mediators can be causally ordered, and there is hidden confounding among the mediators. However, this is predicated on the outcome model being correctly specified in that there are no mediator-mediator interaction terms. Unbiased estimation does not require the mediators to be causally independent, as implied in the parallel path model; in fact, the (marginal) mean model ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">2</ref>) is used   <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Preacher &amp; Selig, 2012)</ref>, are thus deferred to future work.</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 34</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Application</head><p>The proposed estimation procedure was illustrated using a publicly-available data set from a randomized study assessing the effect of (non-)political inclusion on political prejudice that was possibly mediated by six different mediators <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Voelkel et al., 2019)</ref>.</p><p>The data set is available as part of a preregistered study via the Open Science control (A = 0). In the treatment group, participants' political inclusion experiences were manipulated using an online political discussion. In the control group, participants experienced a neutral scenario where no discussion (political or non-political) occurred, and they were only asked to fill in a questionnaire. The outcome Y (prejudice) was an average of three items: dislike of, social distance from, and perceived immorality of, the participant's political outgroup. Larger values indicated higher levels of prejudice.</p><p>To understand how political inclusion affected prejudice, the authors of the study considered six possible mediators of the causal relationship between political inclusion and prejudice: satisfaction of the need to belong (M 1 ), satisfaction of the need for self-esteem (M 2 ), satisfaction of the need for control (M 3 ), satisfaction of the need for meaningful existence (M 4 ), perceived worldview dissimilarity of the political outgroup (M 5 ), and perceived fairness of the political outgroup (M 6 ). In addition, we considered political ideology ("Ideology"), age in years ("Age"), and gender ("Gender") as (baseline) confounders of the mediator-outcome relation for all the mediators.</p><p>Summaries of the variables for each treatment group are provided in Table <ref type="table">4</ref>. We adjusted for the baseline covariates toward satisfying the assumptions (A1)-(A3) needed to identify the interventional direct and indirect effects.</p><p>The total effect of treatment was estimated by regressing prejudice on treatment, political ideology, gender and age (without any mediators). The estimated total effect of the political inclusion manipulation (versus control) was an average change in prejudice by -0.076 (95% confidence interval (CI) = (-0.135, -0.017)). All standard errors and 95% (percentile) confidence intervals were constructed using 1000 (non-parametric) bootstrap samples. To estimate the interventional (in)direct effects, the following mediator and outcome models were fitted to the observed data: (counterfactual) distribution of fairness from the political inclusion manipulation to that under control resulted in lower prejudice on average, while holding treatment and the distributions of all other mediators fixed. The estimated indirect effects via the remaining mediators were not statistically significant at 5%. For example, the indirect effect of changing the (counterfactual) distribution of the need to belong from the politically included group to the control group (holding treatment and distributions of all other mediators fixed) was an increase in prejudice by 0.016 on average, but the 95% CI of (-0.016, 0.053) included zero. The indirect effect due to the mediators' mutual dependence on one another was 0.009 (95% CI = (-0.048, 0.051)), suggesting a positive (but not statistically significant) average effect on prejudice when changing the mediators' covariance from the political inclusion manipulation to that under control.</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">E(M s |A, C) = δ 0s + δ s A + δ</formula><p>The mediator indices were arbitrarily labelled and used merely to distinguish the mediators for statistical analysis when considering simultaneous mediators, and did not  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recommendations for multiple mediation analysis</head><p>When there are multiple or competing mediators on the causal pathway from treatment to outcome, path analysis is commonly used to disentangle the indirect effects transmitted along causal path(s) through each mediator. But indirect or mediated effects along separate paths traversing several linked mediators are valid only when (i) the causal dependence among the mediators is correctly specified, and (ii)</p><p>there is no unobserved confounding of the mediators. When these assumptions are violated, estimates of mediated effects along separate paths can be severely biased; the biases were demonstrated empirically using a simulation study in this article.</p><p>When scientific interest is in inferring indirect effects transmitted through each distinct mediator, the aforementioned assumptions are avoidable by using the interventional indirect effects proposed in this article. Intuitively, the causal dependence DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 41 among the mediators is left unspecified, by focusing on only the marginal mean model for each mediator that captures the overall treatment effect (on that mediator). The interventional indirect effect via a mediator of interest is interpreted as the combined effect along all (unknown) causal pathways from treatment to outcome that intersect that mediator and any others that causally precede the mediator in question.</p><p>Interventional indirect effects are therefore agnostic to the (unknown) causal structure of the mediators. Estimators assuming linear and additive mean models for the mediators and the outcome, such as (1) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">2</ref>), imply the same analytical form as prevailing indirect effects using parallel path models. But when treatment affects the mediators' covariance, and the effect of each mediator on the outcome is moderated by the other mediator(s), such an indirect effect that is due to the mediators' mutual dependence on one another cannot be attributed to any mediator alone. We proposed new estimators of interventional indirect effects under such settings that exploit the mediators' covariance under the assumed linear mean models, thus simplifying closed form solutions when there are more than two mediators. Unbiased estimators of the interventional effects can be straightforwardly obtained using conventional OLS estimation methods, and are robust against an incorrectly specified causal structure of the mediators, and unobserved confounding among the mediators.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Practical considerations for applied researchers</head><p>It is important to note that we are not advocating researchers avoid multiple mediation analyses using "serial" mediation models <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Hayes, 2018)</ref> whose causal structure among the mediators represent theoretical models. On the contrary, we encourage mediation analysis using causal structures that are grounded in established scientific knowledge or prior thoughtful experimentation; see e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Pek &amp; Hoyle (2016)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Fiedler et al. (2018)</ref> for the single mediator setting. For example, in the single mediator setting, experimentally manipulating the mediator to examine its effect on the outcome can lend empirical support for the posited causal effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Spencer et al., 2005)</ref>.</p><p>In principle, such methods may be extended to multiple mediator settings toward DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 42 establishing the mediators' causal structure, by experimentally manipulating each mediator in turn to examine its causal effect(s) on other mediator(s). Valid inference of causal effects using causal diagrams that carefully represent theoretical models is invaluable toward understanding and reasoning of underlying causal mechanisms <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Grosz et al., 2020)</ref>. But often in practice the plausibility of an assumed (path) model is evaluated based solely on statistical associations or observed goodness-of-fit criteria.</p><p>Practitioners of multiple mediation analysis should therefore be cognizant of the implied causal assumptions when inferring causal effects linking different mediators and the implications when the assumptions are violated.</p><p>Applied researchers across different areas in psychology (often) seek to explore attributing the total effect of a treatment on an outcome to each of multiple possible that simply cannot be attributable to any mediator alone.</p><p>One of the assumptions (A2) required to identify the interventional (in)direct effects presented in this paper is that there be no hidden common causes of the mediators and outcome. Future research could include extending sensitivity analyses to unobserved confounding of the mediator-outcome relations for a single mediator <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Cox et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Fritz et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hong et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Liu &amp; Wang, 2020)</ref> to the multiple mediator setting. The path analysis approach can be extended to accommodate latent mediators or outcome, or both, by including latent variable models; see e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Loeys et al. (2014)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Loh, Moerkerke, Loeys, Poppe, et al. (2020)</ref>. VanderWeele &amp; Tchetgen Tchetgen (2017) proposed interventional indirect effects for mediation analysis with longitudinal data under a formal causal framework, and described estimators using sets of linear structural equation models under the so-called "Autoregressive Model III"</p><p>of <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">MacKinnon (2008)</ref>. The interventional indirect effects defined in this paper have focused on a binary treatment, continuous mediators, and a continuous outcome.</p><p>Continuous treatments may be accommodated by extending the interventional effect models proposal <ref type="bibr">(Loh, Moerkerke, Loeys, &amp; Vansteelandt, 2020a)</ref> to parameterize a linear treatment effect in future work. When there are non-continuous mediators, or outcome, or both, the product-of-coefficients method may not result in a valid decomposition of the direct and indirect effects, due to misspecification of non-linear (e.g., logistic regression) models for the mediators or outcome; see MacKinnon et al.</p><p>(2020) for the single mediator setting. Assuming non-linear models for the means of the mediators, or the outcome, or both, will generally lead to different estimators of the interventional indirect effects defined in this paper. For example, when the outcome is binary and rare, and a logistic outcome model is assumed, the indirect effect due to the mediators' mutual dependence ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>) is non-zero only if (i) the main effect of each mediator on the outcome is non-zero, and (ii) the covariance of the (continuous) mediators is affected by treatment <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Loh, Moerkerke, Loeys, &amp; Vansteelandt, 2020b)</ref>.</p><p>Unlike the linear setting assumed in this paper, estimating this indirect effect may not require a mediator-mediator interaction term in the (non-linear) outcome model. More </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1 . Causal diagrams with two mediators where either (a) M 1 and M 2 are independent conditional on A and C, or (b) M 1 causally precedes M 2 , or (c) M 1 and M 2 do not affect each other but share an unobserved common cause U , or (d) M 2 causally precedes M 1 . Rectangular nodes denote observed variables, while round nodes denote unobserved variables. For visual clarity, edges emanating from C are drawn in gray.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>) therefore adopt the same functional form as a (linear) path model corresponding to the causal diagrams of Figures1(a) and 1(c), DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 9</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>is to fit a parallel multiple mediator model (henceforth termed a parallel path model for simplicity) to the observed data. Recent examples across different areas in psychology implementing this prevailing approach for multiple mediation analysis are provided in the Discussion section. In a fitted parallel path model, the formulae for the indirect effect is β s δ s , because there is only one path from A to Y that intersects each mediator M s . Hence, existing indirect effects using parallel path models possess the same interpretation as the proposed indirect effects when considering only the marginal effect of treatment on each mediator, regardless of the unknown causal structure among the mediators. Furthermore, the indirect effect estimates are robust against unobserved confounding of the mediators, such as by U in Figure 1(c), that induces correlation among the mediators unexplained by the mediators' dependence on treatment A and baseline covariates C. This is because the (point) estimates of the path coefficients β s and δ s in a fitted parallel path model remain the same regardless of whether the mediator residuals covariances are constrained to zero (MacKinnon</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>2006) and<ref type="bibr" target="#b60">VanderWeele et al. (2014)</ref> for a single mediator, then generalized by<ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Vansteelandt &amp; Daniel (2017)</ref> to the multiple mediator setting, can be identified under much weaker conditions than natural effects, and still achieve an exact decomposition of the total effect. Unlike natural effects that are defined in terms of individual-level (deterministic) interventions on the mediator, interventional effects consider population-level (stochastic) interventions that set the value of the mediator to a random draw from its counterfactual distribution. Continuing with the motivating example above, the natural indirect effect via worldview dissimilarity (M 1 ) is the average change in prejudice (Y ) when each individual's (counterfactual) value of worldview dissimilarity is manipulated from being political included (A = 1) to that under control (A = 0). In contrast, the interventional indirect effect is the average change in prejudice when the (counterfactual) distribution of worldview dissimilarity under the political inclusion manipulation is shifted to that under control.Interventional effects can therefore be scientifically meaningful even when the treatment cannot be realistically manipulated at the individual level. For example,<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Jackson &amp; VanderWeele (2018)</ref> describe interventional (in)direct effects using race as the treatment and socioeconomic status as the mediator, without having to define nested potential outcomes (for each individual) where race is set to one group but socioeconomic status DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 13 is simultaneously set to its potential value under a different group, depending on the treatment effect of race. Quynh<ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Nguyen et al. (2019)</ref> compare different definitions of direct and indirect effects used in causal mediation analysis that may be motivated by different research questions. We refer interested readers to<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Lin &amp; VanderWeele (2017)</ref>,<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Moreno-Betancur &amp;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Carlin (2018), and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Lok (2019)</ref> among many others for discussions of interventional effects in the causal inference and epidemiology literature.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 1(d), the indirect effect combines the effects along the paths A → M 1 → Y and A → M 2 → M 1 → Y . The interventional indirect effect via M 1 thus captures all of the treatment effect that is mediated by M 1 , and any other mediators causally preceding M 1 , in the underlying causal diagram.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>), 1(c), and 1(d), the interventional indirect effect via M 2 (4) corresponds to the causal effect transmitted along the path A → M 2 → Y ; in the causal diagram of Figure 1(b), the indirect effect DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 15 combines the effects along the paths A</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(2) = 0. The direct effect (8) corresponds to the causal effect along the path A → Y that avoids all the mediators in the causal diagrams of Figure 1. Define the sum of the joint indirect DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 17 effect (</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>) The effect of both mediators M 1 , M 2 on outcome Y is unconfounded conditional on A and C. (A3) The effect of treatment A on both mediators is unconfounded conditional on C. Assumption (A1) states that there are no unobserved confounders between A and Y , or equivalently, that the observed covariate(s) C are sufficient to adjust for confounding of the effect of A on Y . This assumption is implied in the causal diagrams of Figure 1 by the absence of any hidden common causes of A and Y .Because the potential outcome Y am 1 m 2 is unknown for each value of (a, m 1 , m 2 ) except for the observed realization (A, M 1 , M 2 ), assumption (A2) states that there is available sufficient covariate information observed in C so that the association between any of (M 1 , M 2 ) and Y is unconfounded within levels of the covariate(s) C. This assumption requires that there is no confounder of any mediator-outcome association that is affected by treatment; such potential post-treatment confounders can merely be included in the set of possible mediators under the multiple mediator setting considered in this article. This assumption is implied in the causal diagrams of Figure1by the absence of any hidden common causes of any of (M 1 , M 2 ) and Y . Hence one possible DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 18</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Further suppose that the marginal treatment effect on each mediator, given baseline covariate(s) C, is parametrized by the (partial) regression coefficient of treatment A in the linear and additive (marginal) mean models in (2), i.e., E(M s |A, C) = δ 0s + δ s A + δ Cs C, s = 1, 2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>) that adopt the same form for the expected values of the outcome Y and mediators M s , s = 1, 2, as a parallel path model where the mediators are assumed not to causally affect each other. The interventional indirect effect via each DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 20 mediator M s thus equals the indirect effect using the product-of-coefficients method β s δ s for the path A → M s → Y in the parallel path model. Similarly, the interventional direct effect equals β A for the path A → Y that avoids both mediators in the parallel path model. Estimators of the interventional effects can therefore be straightforwardly obtained by fitting the parallel path model to the observed data using linear SEM or</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 1(b). Suppose that the observed data is generated from a true (but unknown)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>Asterisks denote parameters in the true but unknown data-generating model.) Note that the α s parameter encodes the conditional association between treatment A and mediator M s , s = 1, 2, possibly given other mediators such as M 1 in the model for M 2 , and will therefore differ from δ s in general. The mean of the implied marginal DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 21 distribution of M 2 , obtained by averaging over the distribution of M 1 , is then:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>When a mean outcome model without interactions, such as (1), is assumed, the resulting indirect effect estimators are invariant to the mediator indices. In other words, merely switching the indices, e.g., by denoting worldview dissimilarity and fairness by M 2 and M 1 respectively, yields the same estimators. In contrast, under the assumed outcome model (12), the estimator of the indirect effect via one mediator is a (linear) function of the mean value of the other mediator under a given treatment level. Hence different indices lead to different estimators of the interventional indirect effects. For example, the indirect effect via M 1 would be {(β1 + β A1 ) + (β 12 + β A12 ) E(M 2 |A = 1)}δ 1instead, where M 2 is now fixed at its mean value under treatment; similarly, the indirect effect via M 2 would be {(β 2 + β A2 ) + (β 12 + β A12 ) E(M 1 |A = 0)}δ 2 instead,with M 1 fixed at its mean value under control. Because the choice of mediator indices can lead to different estimators, we describe in the applied example how to carry out a sensitivity analysis where the mediator indices are permuted, and the indirect effects estimated under each permutation. When the (true) effect of each mediator on the outcome is DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 24 moderated by treatment, or the other mediator, or both, (incorrectly) assuming no interactions in the outcome model can lead to biased estimates of the indirect effects.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2 . Causal diagram used to generate each simulated dataset with two possible mediators in simulation study 1. Rectangular nodes denote observed variables, while round nodes denote unobserved variables. For visual clarity, edges emanating from the baseline covariate C are drawn in gray, while edges emanating from the hidden confounder U are drawn as broken lines.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>1 , 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>, 3 , 4 , Y were mutually independent of each other. Following the path coefficient estimates in Figure 2 of van der Linden et al. (2015), the values of the (partial) regression coefficients in the data-generating model were set as α 1 = 12.80, α 2 = 1.50, α 3 = 1.92, β 2 = β 3 = 0.08, β 4 = 0.19. The values of the remaining coefficients and residual variances were set to one for simplicity. There were no indirect effects via M 1 or via M 4 because M 1 did not affect Y , and M 4 did not depend on any of the other mediators or treatment and hence unaffected by treatment. The DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 28 interventional indirect effects via M 2 and M 3 corresponded to the causal effects along the paths for A → M 2 → Y and A → M 3 → Y respectively, and were identified by β 2 α 2 and β 3 α 3 . For simplicity, the direct effect was zero. The interventional (in)direct effects were estimated by fitting to each generated observed data: a (marginal) linear and additive mean model for each mediator, where each mediator depended only on treatment A and observed (baseline) covariate C as shown in (2), and the following (linear and additive) outcome mean model:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Figure 3 .Figure 4 .</head><label>34</label><figDesc>Figure 3 . Causal diagram used to generate each simulated dataset with four possible mediators. Rectangular nodes denote observed variables, while round nodes denote unobserved variables. For visual clarity, edges emanating from the baseline covariate C are drawn in gray, while edges emanating from the hidden confounder U are drawn as broken lines.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Similarly, the estimator for the indirect effect via M 3 would fix M 2 at its mean value under control instead; i.e., {β 3 + β 13 E(M 1 |A = 1) + β 23 E(M 2 |A = 0) + β 34 E(M 4 |A = 0)}δ 3 . A sensitivity analysis where the mediator indices are permuted, and the indirect effects estimated under each permutation, is carried out and discussed in the applied example, and hence not considered here. 10000 observed datasets with sample size of either 50, 200, or 1000 were generated, and estimators of the indirect effects from a fitted outcome model that either included all mediator-mediator interactions, or excluded such interactions in a parallel path model, were obtained. The model syntax in R describing the fitted models and the indirect effect estimators are provided online as part of the R scripts for this article 2 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>dependence among the mediators. The results of Simulation Study 2 showed that the estimated mediated effects along separate paths were empirically biased when the DISENTANGLINGINDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 35    statistical associations between the mediators were (incorrectly) assumed to be causal effects. In contrast, the existing product-of-coefficient indirect effect estimates under a parallel path model were unbiased. When the (true) mediators moderated each other's effects on the outcome in Simulation Study 3, the indirect effect estimates under a fitted parallel path model were empirically biased even in large samples. The biases were due to omitting mediator-mediator interaction terms in the (misspecified) outcome model fitted to the data. Hence allowing for (all) mediator-mediator interaction terms in the (fitted) outcome model yielded unbiased estimates of the interventional indirect effects.We have focused on unbiased estimation of the proposed interventional indirect effects in the simulation studies. Inference using a non-parametric bootstrap as suggested in this paper is straightforward and builds on established bootstrap theory and procedures. For this reason, we have chosen not to evaluate the statistical efficiency of the resulting confidence intervals or hypothesis tests. Comparisons of the (non-parametric) bootstrap with other (parametric) methods, such as the Monte Carlo method (MacKinnon</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Framework 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>The goal of the study was to assess the causal effect of either political inclusion or non-political inclusion versus control on momentary prejudice toward the political outgroup. The sample consisted of college freshmen from a large university in the Netherlands who received course credit in a psychology course for their participation. Participants were randomly assigned to one of three conditions: political inclusion, non-political inclusion, or control. For the purposes of illustration, we DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 36 considered only the 183 participants assigned to either political inclusion (A = 1) or</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 39represent or imply any causal ordering of the mediators. Under the assumed outcome model where the effect of each mediator on the outcome was moderated by treatment, or another mediator, or both, a different permutation of the (arbitrary) mediator labels corresponded to a different decomposition of the joint indirect effect, whereby the indirect effects via each mediator held the (counterfactual) mediator distributions fixed at different hypothetical treatment levels. We carried out a sensitivity analysis, by considering each of the 6! = 720 possible permutations of the six mediators in turn, and calculated the indirect effects (and the 95% CIs) under each permutation. Each permutation of the indices thus implies a different decomposition of the joint indirect effect, and subsequently, may result in different estimates of the separate indirect effects. Details on enumerating all possible permutations, especially with a large number of mediators, when implementing the sensitivity analysis are provided online as part of the R scripts for this article 4 . The minimum and maximum estimates (and bounds of the 95% CIs) across all the permutations are shown in Table6. Inference for the indirect effects was unchanged across the different decompositions resulting from different permutations of the mediator indices. We again emphasize that the conceptual interpretations of the interventional indirect effects via each mediator using the causal paths in the underlying causal structure remain the same regardless of the chosen decomposition. For example, the estimated indirect effect via fairness was significantly different from zero (statistically at the 5% level) regardless of the chosen decomposition.Conversely, the 95% CIs for the indirect effect via the need to belong always included zero. In general, when changing the mediators' labels leads to conflicting inferences about the indirect effects, theoretical knowledge may be used to determine the most scientifically relevant decomposition (of the joint indirect effect) and the implied definitions of the indirect effects. These results suggested that the total diminishing effect of political inclusion on prejudice was primarily explained by the mediating effect through perceived fairness of the political outgroup.DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 40</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>mediators, without having to specify (arbitrary) causal effects among the mediators. Recent examples include Bergfeld &amp; Chiu (2017), Brooks et al. (2019), Irwin et al. (2019), Schroeder et al. (2019), and Ren et al. (2020), among many others. Possible reasons may be that the mediators were contemporaneously measured, or there was simply insufficient theoretical or experimental justification to warrant positing a causal structure among the mediators. The framework proposed in this article is particularly well-suited for such (common) research settings, because interventional indirect effects have the benefit of being well-defined and possessing the same interpretation, regardless of the mediators' underlying causal structure. Existing indirect effects using prevailing parallel path models are unbiased estimators of the interventional indirect effectswithout necessarily requiring the absence of causal effects among the mediators as implied by the fitted model -under certain assumptions. When these assumptions fail to hold, such as when the (true) effect of each mediator on the outcome is moderated by another mediator, incorrectly fitting a parallel path model can lead to biased estimates of the interventional indirect effects. We therefore recommend applied researchers conducting multiple mediation analysis to consider outcome models with mediator-mediator interactions terms when feasible, and investigate the indirect effect due to the mediators' mutual dependence, which may reveal part of the treatment effect DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 43</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 44general estimation strategies for non-continuous mediators, or outcome, or both, are described in<ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Vansteelandt &amp; Daniel (2017)</ref> andLoh, Moerkerke, Loeys, &amp; Vansteelandt   (2020a). Estimation requires (correctly) specifying a model for the joint distribution of the mediators and a (mean) model for the outcome, and proceeds via Monte Carlo integration.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Average estimates ("Est.") and empirical standard errors ("Ese.") of the mediated effects in simulation study 1. The sample size (n) was either 50, 200, or 1000. All results were rounded to two decimal places.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>n = 50</cell><cell>n = 200</cell><cell>n = 1000</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Effect True value Est. Ese. Est. Ese. Est. Ese.</cell></row><row><cell>IE 1</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell cols="2">0.00 0.09 -0.00 0.02 0.00 0.01</cell></row><row><cell>IE 2</cell><cell>0.06</cell><cell cols="2">0.06 0.48 0.06 0.23 0.06 0.10</cell></row><row><cell>DE</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell cols="2">-0.00 0.30 0.00 0.14 -0.00 0.06</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">models corresponding to the causal diagram of Figure</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Average</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>n = 50</cell><cell>n = 200</cell><cell>n = 1000</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Effect True value Est. Ese. Est. Ese. Est. Ese.</cell></row><row><cell>PE 12</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell cols="2">0.14 0.22 0.14 0.10 0.14 0.05</cell></row><row><cell>PE 13</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell cols="2">0.17 0.25 0.17 0.12 0.17 0.05</cell></row><row><cell>PE 14</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell cols="2">-0.19 0.16 -0.19 0.07 -0.19 0.03</cell></row><row><cell>PE 124</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell cols="2">0.11 0.10 0.11 0.04 0.11 0.02</cell></row><row><cell>PE 134</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell cols="2">0.13 0.11 0.13 0.05 0.13 0.02</cell></row><row><cell>IE 1</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell cols="2">0.03 1.79 0.02 0.82 -0.00 0.37</cell></row><row><cell>IE 2</cell><cell>0.12</cell><cell cols="2">0.12 0.22 0.12 0.10 0.12 0.04</cell></row><row><cell>IE 3</cell><cell>0.15</cell><cell cols="2">0.15 0.27 0.15 0.13 0.15 0.05</cell></row><row><cell>IE 4</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell cols="2">-0.00 0.10 0.00 0.04 -0.00 0.02</cell></row><row><cell>DE</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell cols="2">-0.03 1.71 -0.01 0.79 0.00 0.35</cell></row></table><note><p>estimates ("Est.") and empirical standard errors ("Ese.") of the mediated effects under the posited "gateway belief" path model in the simulation study. The sample size (n) was either 50, 200, or 1000. All results were rounded to two decimal places.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Average estimates("Est.") and empirical standard errors ("Ese.") of the interventional indirect and direct effects under each fitted model in the simulation study. An -A int. True value Est. Ese. Est. Ese. Est. Ese.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="6">interaction between the mediators' unmeasured confounder U and the treatment A was</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">either absent ("U -A int."=False) or present ("U -A int."=True) when generating the</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">data. The assumed outcome model either included all mediator-mediator interactions</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">("M -M int."), or main effects only ("Parallel"). The sample size was either 50, 200,</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">or 1000. All results were rounded to two decimal places.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>n = 50</cell><cell>n = 200</cell><cell>n = 1000</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">IE 1 IE 2 IE 3 Fitted model Effect U M -M int. IE 4</cell><cell>False True False True False True False True</cell><cell>0.00 0.00 0.12 0.12 -0.31 -0.31 0.00 0.00</cell><cell cols="2">-0.01 1.93 0.01 0.86 -0.00 0.37 0.00 1.94 -0.01 0.85 0.00 0.36 0.13 0.48 0.12 0.19 0.12 0.08 0.13 0.46 0.12 0.18 0.12 0.08 -0.32 0.44 -0.31 0.19 -0.31 0.08 -0.34 0.47 -0.31 0.20 -0.31 0.09 0.00 0.12 0.00 0.04 0.00 0.02 -0.00 0.15 0.00 0.06 -0.00 0.02</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>IE mu</cell><cell>False True</cell><cell>0.00 -0.48</cell><cell cols="2">0.00 0.19 -0.00 0.09 -0.00 0.04 -0.48 0.31 -0.48 0.15 -0.48 0.06</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>DE</cell><cell>False True</cell><cell>0.00 0.00</cell><cell cols="2">0.01 1.79 -0.01 0.81 0.00 0.35 -0.01 1.80 0.01 0.79 -0.00 0.34</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>IE 1</cell><cell>False True</cell><cell>0.00 0.00</cell><cell cols="2">0.01 2.14 0.02 1.02 -0.01 0.45 -0.45 2.52 -0.48 1.20 -0.48 0.53</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>IE 2</cell><cell>False True</cell><cell>0.12 0.12</cell><cell cols="2">-0.11 0.28 -0.11 0.13 -0.11 0.06 -0.18 0.35 -0.17 0.16 -0.17 0.07</cell></row><row><cell>Parallel</cell><cell>IE 3 IE 4</cell><cell>False True False True</cell><cell>-0.31 -0.31 0.00 0.00</cell><cell cols="2">-0.08 0.36 -0.08 0.17 -0.08 0.07 -0.16 0.43 -0.15 0.20 -0.15 0.09 0.00 0.10 0.00 0.04 0.00 0.02 -0.01 0.13 0.00 0.05 -0.00 0.02</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>DE</cell><cell>False True</cell><cell>0.00 0.00</cell><cell cols="2">-0.01 2.04 -0.02 0.98 0.00 0.43 0.12 2.40 0.14 1.15 0.13 0.51</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">precisely so that the interventional indirect effects are agnostic to the underlying causal</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>C1s Ideology + δ C2s Age + δ C3s Gender, s = 1, . . . , 6; E(Y |A, M 1 , . . . , M 6 , C) = β 0 + β A A + C1 Ideology + β C2 Age + β C3 Gender.Sample means and standard deviations (in brackets) for the baseline confounders,mediators and outcome for each treatment group in the applied example.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="5">DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 37 DISENTANGLING INDIRECT EFFECTS THROUGH MULTIPLE MEDIATORS 38</cell></row><row><cell>Table 4 Table 5</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Interventional (in)direct effect estimates, bootstrap standard errors ("SE") and 95%</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">bootstrap (percentile) confidence intervals ("CI") for the applied example. All results</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">were rounded to three decimal places.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Treatment group</cell><cell></cell><cell>A = 0</cell><cell>A = 1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Number of participants Interventional effect</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">95 Estimate Bootstrap SE 88</cell><cell>95% CI</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Ideology Indirect effect via M 1 (belong)</cell><cell cols="3">-0.51 (0.9) -0.43 (0.7) 0.016 0.017</cell><cell>(-0.016, 0.053)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Gender Indirect effect via M 2 (self-esteem)</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.73 (0.4) 0.76 (0.4) 0.000 0.007</cell><cell>(-0.015, 0.015)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Age Indirect effect via M 3 (control)</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">20.0 (2.3) 20.1 (2.5) -0.002 0.012</cell><cell>(-0.029, 0.020)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">M 1 (belong) Indirect effect via M 4 (meaningful existence)</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.81 (0.2) 0.69 (0.2) -0.003 0.008</cell><cell>(-0.024, 0.008)</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">M 2 (self-esteem) Indirect effect via M 5 (worldview dissimilarity)</cell><cell cols="2">0.50 (0.2) 0.50 (0.2) -0.006 0.011</cell><cell>(-0.029, 0.015)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">M 3 (control) Indirect effect via M 6 (fairness)</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.37 (0.2) 0.30 (0.2) -0.077 0.030</cell><cell>(-0.139, -0.021)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">M 4 (meaningful existence) Indirect effect due to mutual dependence</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.83 (0.2) 0.81 (0.2) 0.009 0.025</cell><cell>(-0.048, 0.051)</cell></row><row><cell>Direct effect</cell><cell cols="4">M 5 (worldview dissimilarity) 0.65 (0.2) 0.56 (0.2) -0.013 0.044</cell><cell>(-0.088, 0.085)</cell></row><row><cell>Total effect</cell><cell>M 6 (fairness)</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.48 (0.2) 0.62 (0.2) -0.076 0.031</cell><cell>(-0.135, -0.017)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Y</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.46 (0.2) 0.38 (0.2)</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Each mediator depended only on treatment, political ideology, age, and gender. The</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">outcome model included all treatment-mediator, mediator-mediator, and</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">treatment-mediator-mediator interaction terms. Closed form expressions for the</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">interventional direct and indirect effect estimators as functions of the outcome and</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">mediator model parameters are provided in the Online Supplemental Materials. The</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">estimated effects using the observed data are shown in Table 5.</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">The estimated interventional direct effect was -0.013 (95% CI = (-0.088, 0.085)),</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">suggesting that politically included individuals had lower prejudice (than if assigned to</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">the control condition), when holding the (counterfactual) distributions of all mediators</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>6</cell><cell></cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">(β s + β As A)M s +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>s=1</cell><cell></cell><cell>k,l=1,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>k&lt;l</cell></row></table><note><p><p>(β kl + β Akl A)M k M l + β</p>(given ideology, age, and gender) fixed under those of the control condition. There was only one mediator with a statistically significant indirect effect. The estimated indirect effect via fairness was -0.077 (95% CI = (-0.139, -0.021)), so that shifting the</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="4">Interventional (in)direct effect estimates and 95% bootstrap (percentile) confidence</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">intervals ("CI") for the applied example. The minimum ("min.") and maximum</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">("max.") estimates, and 95% CI lower and upper bounds, across all 6! = 720 possible</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">permutations of the mediator indices are presented. All results were rounded to three</cell></row><row><cell>decimal places.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Estimate</cell><cell>95% CI</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Interventional indirect effect</cell><cell cols="3">Min. Max. Min. (lower) Max. (upper)</cell></row><row><cell>Belong</cell><cell>0.011 0.025</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.073</cell></row><row><cell>Self-esteem</cell><cell>0.000 0.000</cell><cell>-0.019</cell><cell>0.021</cell></row><row><cell>Control</cell><cell>-0.012 0.012</cell><cell>-0.044</cell><cell>0.053</cell></row><row><cell>Meaningful existence</cell><cell>-0.004 -0.001</cell><cell>-0.034</cell><cell>0.014</cell></row><row><cell>Worldview dissimilarity</cell><cell>-0.014 0.006</cell><cell>-0.049</cell><cell>0.039</cell></row><row><cell>Fairness</cell><cell>-0.094 -0.074</cell><cell>-0.156</cell><cell>-0.013</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>https://github.com/wwloh/disentangle-multiple-mediators</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>https://github.com/wwloh/disentangle-multiple-mediators</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_2"><p>https://github.com/wwloh/disentangle-multiple-mediators</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalized causal mediation and path analysis: Extensions and practical considerations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Albert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0962280218776483</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistical Methods in Medical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1793" to="1807" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The decomposition of effects in path analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Alwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2094445</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Sociological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifiability of path-specific effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Avin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Shpitser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 19th international joint conference on artificial intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the 19th international joint conference on artificial intelligence<address><addrLine>San Francisco, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann Publishers Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005-07">2005, July</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="357" to="363" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The moderator-mediator variable distinction in social psychological research: Conceptual, strategic, and statistical considerations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Baron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kenny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0022-3514.51.6.1173</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1173</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mediators in the relationship between minority stress and depression among young same-sex attracted women</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bergfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/pro0000155</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Professional Psychology: Research and Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="294" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Total, direct, and indirect effects in structural equation models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bollen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/271028</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Methodology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Brooks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Graham-Kevan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/tra0000372</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Trauma characteristics and posttraumatic growth: The mediating role of avoidance coping, intrusive thoughts, and social support</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="238" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing specific mediational effects in complex theoretical models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10705519709540067</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="156" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sensitivity plots for confounder bias in the single mediator model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kisbu-Sakarya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Miočević</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mackinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0193841X14524576</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eval Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="405" to="431" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-10">2013. Oct</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causal mediation analysis with multiple mediators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Daniel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>De Stavola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Cousens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/biom.12248</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct and indirect effects of sequential treatments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Didelez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dawid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Geneletti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 22nd conference on uncertainty in artificial intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the 22nd conference on uncertainty in artificial intelligence<address><addrLine>Arlington, VA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>AUAI Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="138" to="146" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Path analysis: Sociological examples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Duncan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1086/224256</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Sociology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An introduction to the bootstrap</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Efron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tibshirani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-1-4899-4541-9</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<publisher>Chapman and Hall/CRC</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unwarranted inferences from statistical mediation tests-an analysis of articles published in 2015</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fiedler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jesp.2017.11.008</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="102" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect analysis in structural equation models: Extensions and simplified methods of computation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/004912418000900101</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Methods &amp; Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The combined effects of measurement error and omitting confounders in the single-mediator model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Fritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kenny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mackinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/00273171.2016.1224154</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Multivariate Behavioral Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="681" to="697" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An algorithm for total and indirect causal effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Greene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/25791510" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Methodology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="381" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The taboo against explicit causal inference in nonexperimental psychology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Grosz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rohrer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Thoemmes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1745691620921521</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">32727292</idno>
		<idno>10.1177/1745691620921521</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1745691620921521" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perspectives on Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1243" to="1255" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pearl&apos;s D-separation: One more step into causal thinking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hayduk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cummings</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Stratkotter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nimmo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Grygoryev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dosman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">.</forename><surname>Boadu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1207/s15328007sem1002_8</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="311" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to mediation, moderation, and conditional process analysis: a regression-based approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Guilford press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, NY, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conditional process analysis: Concepts, computation, and advances in the modeling of the contingencies of mechanisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rockwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Behavioral Scientist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="54" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Weighting-based sensitivity analysis in causal mediation studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Qin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3102/1076998617749561</idno>
		<idno>doi: 10.3102/1076998617749561</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3102/1076998617749561" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational and Behavioral Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A general approach to causal mediation analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Imai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Keele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tingley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0020761</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">309</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification, inference and sensitivity analysis for causal mediation effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Imai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Keele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/41058997</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistical Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of shame in chronic peer victimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Irwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Craig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hollenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/spq0000280</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">School Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="178" to="186" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decomposition analysis to identify intervention targets for reducing disparities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vanderweele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/EDE.0000000000000901</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="825" to="835" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing natural direct and indirect effects through multiple pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rasmussen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Thygesen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/aje/kwt270</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">179</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="513" to="518" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interventional approach for path-specific effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-H</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Vanderweele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1515/jci-2015-0027</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Causal Inference</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of measurement error and omitting confounders on statistical inference of mediation effects and tools for sensitivity analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/met0000345</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-07">2020. Jul</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation of controlled direct effects in the presence of exposure-induced confounding and latent variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Loeys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Moerkerke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Raes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Rosseel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10705511.2014.915372</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="396" to="407" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation of controlled direct effects in longitudinal mediation analyses with latent variables in randomised studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Loh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Moerkerke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Loeys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Poppe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Crombez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/00273171.2019.1681251</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Multivariate Behavioral Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="763" to="785" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Heterogeneous indirect effects for multiple mediators using interventional effect models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Loh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Moerkerke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Loeys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1907.08415</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>arXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Non-linear mediation analysis with high-dimensional mediators whose causal structure is unknown</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Loh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Moerkerke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Loeys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2001.07147</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020b</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lok</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1903.04697</idno>
		<title level="m">Causal organic direct and indirect effects: closer to Baron and Kenny</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019-03">2019, Mar</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Contrasts in multiple mediator models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mackinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Multivariate applications in substance use research: New methods for new questions</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chassin</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Presson</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sherman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Mahwah, NJ, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates Publishers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="160" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mackinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4324/9780203809556</idno>
		<title level="m">Introduction to statistical mediation analysis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>st ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison of methods to test mediation and other intervening variable effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mackinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lockwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Sheets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/1082-989X.7.1.83</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Confidence limits for the indirect effect: Distribution of the product and resampling methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mackinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lockwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Multivariate Behavioral Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The correspondence between causal and traditional mediation analysis: the link is the mediator by treatment interaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mackinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Valente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Gonzalez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11121-019-01076-4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prevention Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theory and analysis of total, direct, and indirect causal effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Thoemmes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Steyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/00273171.2014.931797</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Multivariate Behavioral Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="425" to="442" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural equation modeling versus marginal structural modeling for assessing mediation in the presence of posttreatment confounding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Moerkerke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Loeys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0036368</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">204</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding interventional effects: A more natural approach to mediation analysis?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moreno-Betancur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Carlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/EDE.0000000000000866</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="614" to="617" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct and indirect effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 17th conference on uncertainty in artificial intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the 17th conference on uncertainty in artificial intelligence<address><addrLine>San Francisco, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann Publishers Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="420" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The causal foundations of structural equation modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.21236/ADA557445</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of structural equation modeling</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hoyle</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Guilford Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="68" to="91" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interpretation and identification of causal mediation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0036434</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">459</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the (in) validity of tests of simple mediation: Threats and solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hoyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/spc3.12237</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social and personality psychology compass</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="163" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymptotic and resampling strategies for assessing and comparing indirect effects in multiple mediator models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Preacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3758/BRM.40.3.879</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behavior Research Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="879" to="891" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advantages of Monte Carlo confidence intervals for indirect effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Preacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Selig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communication Methods and Measures</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Clarifying causal mediation analysis for the applied researcher: Defining effects based on what we want to learn</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Quynh Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Schmid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stuart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1904.08515</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019-04">2019, Apr</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">R: A language and environment for statistical computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Team</forename><surname>Core</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Computer software manual</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Seeking solitude after being ostracized: A replication and beyond. Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wesselmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Van Beest</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0146167220928238</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">32515281</idno>
		<idno>10.1177/0146167220928238</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0146167220928238" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifiability and exchangeability for direct and indirect effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Greenland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/00001648-199203000-00013</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Handshaking promotes deal-making by signaling cooperative intent</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Risen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Norton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/pspi0000157</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="743" to="768" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Counterfactual graphical models for longitudinal mediation analysis with unobserved confounding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Shpitser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/cogs.12058</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cognitive Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1011" to="1035" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Establishing a causal chain: Why experiments are often more effective than mediational analyses in examining psychological processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Spencer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Zanna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Fong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0022-3514.89.6.845</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="845" to="851" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flexible mediation analysis with multiple mediators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Steen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Loeys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Moerkerke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/aje/kwx051</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">186</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causal mediation analysis with multiple causally non-ordered mediators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Taguri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Featherstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0962280215615899</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistical Methods in Medical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tests of the three-path mediated effect</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mackinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-Y</forename><surname>Tein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1094428107300344</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organizational Research Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="269" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The scientific consensus on climate change as a gateway belief: Experimental evidence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Van Der Linden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Leiserowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Feinberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Maibach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0118489</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLOS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-02">2015, 02</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mediation analysis with time varying exposures and mediators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vanderweele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tchetgen Tchetgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/rssb.12194</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B (Statistical Methodology)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="917" to="938" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect decomposition in the presence of an exposure-induced mediator-outcome confounder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vanderweele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/EDE.0000000000000034</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">300</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interventional effects for mediation analysis with multiple mediators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Daniel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/EDE.0000000000000596</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="258" to="265" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Political inclusion reduces political prejudice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Voelkel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.31234/osf.io/dxwpu</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PsyArXiv</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The method of path coefficients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1214/aoms/1177732676</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Annals of Mathematical Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="1934">1934</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
