<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Qualitative Possibilistic In°uence Diagrams</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wided</forename><surname>Guezguez</surname></persName>
							<email>widedguezguez@gmail.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institut Sup ¶ erieur de Gestion de Tunis</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">LARODEC</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>41 Avenue de la Libert ¶ e</addrLine>
									<postCode>2000</postCode>
									<settlement>Le Bardo</settlement>
									<country key="TN">Tunisie</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nahla</forename><forename type="middle">Ben</forename><surname>Amor</surname></persName>
							<email>nahla.benamor@gmx.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institut Sup ¶ erieur de Gestion de Tunis</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">LARODEC</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>41 Avenue de la Libert ¶ e</addrLine>
									<postCode>2000</postCode>
									<settlement>Le Bardo</settlement>
									<country key="TN">Tunisie</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Qualitative Possibilistic In°uence Diagrams</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T18:58+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>decision making</term>
					<term>in°uence diagrams</term>
					<term>qualitative utility</term>
					<term>possibility theory</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In°uence diagrams (IDs) are one of the most commonly used graphical decision models for reasoning under uncertainty. The quanti¯cation of IDs which consists in de¯ning conditional probabilities for chance nodes and utility functions for value nodes is not always obvious. In fact, decision makers cannot always provide exact numerical values and in some cases, it is more easier for them to specify qualitative preference orders. This work proposes an adaptation of standard IDs to the qualitative framework based on possibility theory.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. Introduction</head><p>In°uence diagrams introduced by Howard and Matheson in 1981 <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> provide an e±cient tool for decision making in intelligent systems, they allow to model and evaluate complex decision problems via a compact graphical representation.</p><p>In°uence diagrams are quanti¯ed by conditional probabilities relative to uncertain variables and utility functions evaluating decision maker's satisfaction. Nevertheless, the speci¯cation of this numerical component is not always obvious. In fact, experts may be enable to provide exact conditional probabilities. Moreover, it is generally more easier for them to provide a preferential relation between di®erent consequences that expresses utilities rather than numerical values.</p><p>To overcome these limitations, this paper proposes a new approach extending standard IDs to a qualitative framework based on the possibility theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. In fact, this theory can be interpreted in two ways: qualitatively, if the handled values re°ect only an ordering between di®erent states of the world or quantitatively, if the handled values make sense in the ranking scale.</p><p>Our idea is to use the qualitative aspect of this theory in order to specify qualitative relations between chance nodes.</p><p>Concerning utilities, in the literature we can distinguish two kinds of utility: cardinal utility <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> when the decision maker is able to express his satisfaction by exact numerical values and ordinal utility <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> otherwise.</p><p>Di®erent combinations of the quanti¯cation between chance and utility nodes o®er several kinds of possibilistic in°uence diagrams. In this paper, we are interested in qualitative ones.</p><p>Our new approach named, qualitative possibilistic in°uence diagrams, bene¯ts from the simplicity and e±cacity of standard in°uence diagrams and from the suitability of the possibility theory for modeling qualitative uncertainty.</p><p>We also propose an evaluation method to generate optimal decisions maximizing the expected utility. The proposed method is based on the transformation of qualitative possibilistic in°uence diagrams into qualitative possibilistic causal networks recently proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> and on making inference in this secondary structure.</p><p>This paper is organized as follows: Section 2 provides a brief description of the basics of in°uence diagrams. The necessary background on possibility theory is recalled in Section 3. Ordinal utility theory is brie°y presented in section 4. Then in Section 5, we will de¯ne qualitative possibilistic in°uence diagrams. Finally, section 6 presents an evaluation method relative to these graphical decision models.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. In°uence Diagrams</head><p>An in°uence diagram is a directed acyclic graph (DAG) denoted by G=(N, A) where A is the set of arcs and N = fC; D; V g such that: </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">i (resp. D i , V i ).</formula><p>Di®erent links existing between chance nodes are quanti¯ed by conditional probability tables representing dependencies between them. Namely, each chance node C i will be attached to its probability in the context of its parents, denoted by P a(C i ) (pa(C i ) denoted any instance of P a(C i )). Whereas, each value node V i is characterized by a utility function U in the context of its parents. In fact, the set of combinations of di®erent parents of value nodes represent the set of consequences relative to the decision problem represented by the in°uence diagram.</p><p>Decision nodes act di®erently from remaining nodes, since they are not quanti¯ed.</p><p>Once the ID constructed, it can be used to identify better decisions via evaluation algorithms which allow to generate the optimal strategy yielding to the highest expected utility.</p><p>IDs can be evaluated through direct methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> which operate directly on the original structure or indirect methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>[16] <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> which transform them into Bayesian networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> [10] <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> and reduce the ID evaluation problem into a Bayesian networks inference one. Direct evaluation requires a lot of probabilistic calculations which justify the great development of indirect methods initiated by Cooper <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> for the particular case of in°uence diagrams with a unique value node.</p><p>The key idea of indirect methods is to transform decision and value nodes into chance nodes. Indeed, each decision node D i is converted into a chance node with an equi-probability distribution. The value node V is transformed into a binary chance node with two values False (F) and True (T) and its utility function is converted into a probability distribution by rescaling it in the unit interval [0, 1].</p><p>Finally, the maximal expected utility is computed begining by the last decision D m to the ¯rst one D 1 , by considering for each node a set of evidence E updated in the light of the previous step.</p><p>More formally, for each decision node D i , the maximal expected utility is computed as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">MEU(D i ; E) = K 1 :max dij [P (v = T j d ij ; E)] ¡ K 2</formula><p>(1) where 8pa(V ) 2 P a(V ):</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">K 1 = max pa(V ) (U (pa(V ))) ¡ min pa(V ) (U (pa(V )))</formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">K 2 = ¡min pa(V ) U (pa(V )).</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. Possibility theory</head><p>This section brie°y recalls basic elements of possibility theory, for more details see <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</p><p>The basic buildings block in the possibility theory is the notion of possibility distribution denoted by ¼, it is a mapping from the universe of discourse denoted by -to the unit interval [0,1]. This scale has two interpretations, a quantitative one when the handled values have a real sense and a qualitative one when the handled values re°ect only an ordering between the di®erent states of the world. In the ¯rst case, the product operator can be applied and in the second one, the min operator is used.</p><p>A possibility degree is the value from the interval [0,1] associated to each element ! of -. The possibility measure of any subset Ã μ -is de¯ned as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">¦(Ã) = max !2Ã ¼(!)<label>( 2 )</label></formula><p>A possibility distribution is said to be normalized, if</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">max !2Ã ¼(!) = 1.</formula><p>In the possibilistic framework, extreme forms of partial knowledge can be represented as follows:</p><p>² Complete knowledge:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">9! i 2 -; s:t ¼(! i ) = 1 and ! j 6 = ! i ; ¼(! j ) = 0 (3)</formula><p>² Total ignorance:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">8! i 2 -; ¼(! i ) = 1<label>(4)</label></formula><p>The two interpretations of the possibilistic scale induce two de¯nitions of the conditioning <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>:</p><p>² min-based conditioning relative to the ordinal setting:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">¼(!j m Ã) = 8 &lt; : 1 if ¼(!) = ¦(Ã) and ! 2 Ã ¼(!) if ¼(!) &lt; ¦(Ã) and ! 2 Ã 0 otherwise:<label>(5)</label></formula><p>² product-based conditioning relative to the numerical setting: The problem with cardinal utility comes from the di±culty in expressing the utilities by numerical values, and in ¯nding the appropriate measurement index (metric). This is not the case in the context of ordinal utility, when we suppose that the decision maker can only provide a total preference relation on the di®erent states of the world. Let A, B and C be three states and º be the relative preference relation: </p><formula xml:id="formula_9">¼(!j p Ã) = ( ¼(!) ¦(!) if ! 2 Ã 0 otherwise:<label>(6)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">² A º B means that A is more preferred than B, ² A ¹ B means that A is less preferred than B, ² A » B</formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">A º B iff U(A) ¸U (B)<label>( 7 )</label></formula><p>and Numerical component evaluating di®erent links in the graph concerning chance nodes and utilities for value nodes in the following way:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">A » B iff U(A) = U (B)<label>( 8 )</label></formula><p>For each chance node C i , experts should provide conditional possibility degrees ¦(c ij j pa(C i )) of each instance c ij of C i and each instance pa(C i ) of P a(C i ) of its parents. In order to satisfy the normalization constraint, these conditional distributions should satisfy:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">max cij ¦(c ij j pa(C i )) = 1; 8pa(C i )<label>(9)</label></formula><p>Note that for root chance nodes (i.e (P a(C i ) = ;), this will correspond to an a prior possibility distribution ¦(c ij ) satisfying max cij ¦(c ij ) = 1.</p><p>For the value node V, we assume that ordinal utilities are used for the quanti¯cation. Namely, the decision maker can express a preferential relation º between di®erent consequences.</p><p>To develop possibilistic chain rule, utility nodes and links into decision nodes in possibilistic in°uence diagrams must be ignored, as in standard in°uence diagrams <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</p><p>As mentioned before, decision nodes act di®erently from chance nodes, thus it is meaningless to specify prior possibility distribution on them. Moreover, it has no meaning to attach a possibility distribution to children nodes of a decision node D i unless a decision</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">d ij has been taken.</formula><p>Therefore what is meaningful is ¦(c ij j do(d ij )), where do(d ij ) is the particular operator de¯ned by Pearl <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, and not ¦(c ij ; d ij ). When iterating this reasoning we can bunch the whole decision nodes together and express the joint possiblity distribution of di®erent chance nodes conditioned by decision nodes. This means that if we ¯x a particular con¯guration of decision nodes, say d, we get a min-based possibilistic causal network <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> representing ¦(C j do(d)) i.e the joint possibility relative to C, in the context of the decision d.</p><p>In other words, the joint distribution relative to C remains the same when varying d. Thus, using the possibilistic chain rule relative to min-based causal network <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, we can infer the following chain rule relative to qualitative possibilistic IDs:</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">¼(C j m D) = min Ci2C ¦(C i j m P a(C i ))<label>(10)</label></formula><p>Example 1: Let ¦ID O min be a qualitative in°uence diagram with three chance nodes (A, B and C), one decision node (D) and one value node (V)(see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref>). The a priori and conditional possibility distributions for A, B and C are presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">1</ref>.</p><p>The preference order between di®erent combinations of parents of the value node V (i.e A and D) is  </p><formula xml:id="formula_16">A ¦(A) A B ¦(BjA) B C ¦(CjB) T 1 T T 0.9 T T 1 F 0.6 F T 0.2 F T 0.3 T F 1 T F 0.2 F F 1 F F 1</formula><p>expressed by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">(D = Act2 ^A = F ) º (D = Act1 ^A = T ) º (D = Act1 ^A = F ) º (D = Act2 ^A = T ):</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. Evaluation of qualitative in°uence diagrams</head><p>To evaluate qualitative possibilistic in°uence diagrams, we propose to de¯ne the possibilistic counterpart of the indirect Cooper's method <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. This choice allows us to avoid heavy computations of direct methods. In addition, we will use the possibilistic counterpart of Bayesian networks, recently proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. The principal steps of our evaluation's method are detailed in what follows.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Decision nodes transformation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Each decision node D i in ¦ID O</head><p>min is transformed into a chance node which will be quanti¯ed by the following conditional possibility distribution in the context of its parents:</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">¦(d ij j pa(D i )) = 1; 8d ij ; 8pa(D i )<label>(11)</label></formula><p>This distribution expresses the state of total ignorance with respect to the new chance node D i . Note that this quanti¯cation is more appropriate than the one used in standard in°uence diagram, since equiprobability represents randomness rather than total ignorance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Value node transformation</head><p>The value node V is converted into a new binary chance node having two values: False (F) and True (T). The new chance node is characterized by a possibility distribution deduced from the original preference relation.</p><p>The following proposition gives a transformation function of the preference relation between di®erent consequences which satis¯es VNM axioms into numerical utilities.</p><p>Proposition 1: Let º be a preference relation between di®erent consequences. Then, the order induced by º can be transformed into a numerical scale as follows: <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> where card(Pa(V)) is a function that determines the number of combinations of pa(V ) 2 P a(V ). rank(pa(V)) is the rank of pa(V) in the preference order.</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">U (pa(V )) = card(P a(V )) ¡ rank(pa(V )) + 1</formula><p>Proof 1: Let pa 1 (V ) and pa 2 (V ) be two consequences such that pa 1 (V ) º pa 2 (V ), we have:</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">rank(pa 1 (V )) • rank(pa 2 (V )) ) ¡rank(pa 1 (V )) + 1 ¸¡rank(pa 2 (V )) + 1 ) card(P a(V )) ¡ rank(pa 1 (V )) + 1 çard(P a(V )) ¡ rank(pa 2 (V )) + 1 ) U (pa 1 (V )) ¸U (pa 2 (V )).</formula><p>The set of utilities assigned to the di®erent consequences according to the preference relation will be transformed into a possibility distribution. Namely, we are interested in computing ¦(v = T j P a(V )) and ¦(v = F j P a(V )) which can be obtained as follows:</p><p>¦(v = T j P a(V )) = U (P a(V ))¡U min Umax¡Umin <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> ¦(v = F j P a(V )) = U (P a(V ))¡Umax U min ¡U max <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> Where U max and U min are the maximal utility level and the minimal utility level, respectively.</p><p>The obtained qualitative possibilistic distribution ¦(V j P a(V )) is sub-normalized. Then, to satisfy the normalization constraint, the qualitative possibilistic distribution should be transformed as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">8pa(V ) 2 P a(V ) and v 2 fT; F g, ¦(vj m pa(V )) = ½ 1 if max(¦(vjmpa(V )); ¦(:vjmpa(V ))) = ¦(vjmpa(V )) ¦(vj m pa(V )) otherwise:<label>(15)</label></formula><p>After the transformation phase, we should determine for each decision node D i the Maximal Expected Utility with respect to the set of evidences E in order to generate the optimal decision strategy. This computation is based on the max and min operators instead of standard addition and multiplication ones as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">MEU(D i ; E) = max dij [max pa 0 (V ) min(¦(v = T j pa(V )); ¦(pa 0 (V ) j d ij ; E))]<label>(16)</label></formula><p>where Pa'(V) denotes the set of chance nodes in Pa(V) and pa'(V) is an instance of Pa'(V).</p><p>Note that ¦(v = T j pa(V )) is a transformation of U(Pa(V)) into the unit interval [0,1] using <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> in order to let U (P a(V )) and ¦(pa 0 (V ) j d ij ; E) commensurable.</p><p>To compute ¦(pa 0 (V ) j d ij ; E) and ¦(v = T j pa(V )), a min-based propagation algorithm for qualitative possibilistic networks can be applied. Indeed, two min-based propagation algorithms have been de¯ned according to the nature of the DAG in the possibilistic causal network <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Namely, the qualitative possibilistic adaptation of the centralized version of Pearl's algorithm is used when the DAG is singly connected, and the qualitative possibilistic adaptation of junction trees propagation are appropriate for multiply connected DAGs. In the case that these two algorithms are blocked, the anytime algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> can be used.</p><p>Example 2: Let us continue with Example 1, after the transformation of the in°uence diagram presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref>, we will have the possibilistic network represented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref>.   </p><formula xml:id="formula_23">D ¦(D j C) T Act1 1 F Act2 1 T Act2 1 F Act1 1</formula><p>The preference relation will be transformed into numerical utilities using <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> as presented in Table <ref type="table">3</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">TABLE III Ordinal utilities A D U(A,D) T Act1 3 F Act2 4 T Act2 1 F Act1 2</formula><p>To compute possibility degrees for the value node presented in Table <ref type="table">4</ref>, ( <ref type="formula">13</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>) are used.  Suppose that we receive a certain information saying that the variable C takes the value T, then ¦(pa 0 (V ) j d ij ; E)) is computed using a min-based propagation algorithm in Junction Trees. We have: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. Conclusion</head><p>In this paper we have developed a new approach for decision making under uncertainty, namely qualitative in°uence diagrams. This new approach allows to experts to quantify the dependencies between chance nodes qualitatively by means of possibility distributions. Moreover, utility nodes are supposed to be quanti¯ed by qualitative utilities. An indirect evaluation's method was proposed allowing the determination of the optimal strategy which o®ers the maximal expected utility. As a future work, we will investigate to optimize indirect evaluation's method to deal with IDs with more than one value node. Alternative methods to quantify value nodes are under study, namely, binary qualitative utility <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>means that A and B are equally preferred.Von Neumann and Morgenstern<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> have de¯ned the following axiom's system for any preference relation:² Axiom 1. Completeness (Orderability): It is always possible to state either that A º B or that B º A or A » B. ² Axiom 2. Re°exivility: any consequence A is always at least as preferred as itself: A º A. ² Axiom 3. Transitivity: If A º B and B º C then A º C. If a preference relation º veri¯es these axioms then there exists a utility function U such that:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>V.</head><label></label><figDesc>Qualitative possibilistic in°uence diagrams A qualitative possibilistic in°uence diagram, denoted by ¦ID O min , is de¯ned by two components: Graphical component represented by a DAG G = (N; A) having the same structure than stantard in°uence diagrams (c.f section 2).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>WorldFig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Example of an in°uence diagram</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Obtained possibilistic network</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>min(¦(v = T j A = T; D = Act1); ¦(A = T j D = Act1; C = T )) = min(0:666; 0:666), min(¦(v = T j A = F; D = Act1); ¦(A = F j D = Act1; C = T )) = min(0:6; 0:3), min(¦(v = T j A = T; D = Act2); ¦(A = T j D = Act2; C = T )) = min(0; 0:9), min(¦(v = T j A = F; D = Act2); ¦(A = F j D = Act2; C = T )) =min(0:333; 0:3), Thus, MEU(D; C = T ) = 0:666 and D ¤ = Act 1 . World Academy of Science, Engineering and Technology International Journal of Mathematical and Computational Sciences Vol:2, No:9, 2008</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>International Science Index, Mathematical and Computational Sciences Vol:2, No:9, 2008 waset.org/Publication/1815 ² C = fC 1 ; ::; C n g is the set of chance nodes represented by circles. ² D = fD 1 ; ::; D m g is the set of decision nodes represented by rectangles. ² V = fV 1 ; ::; V k g is the set of value nodes represented by lozenges. In what follows c ij (resp. d ij , v ij ) denotes an instance of the variable C</figDesc><table><row><cell>World Academy of Science, Engineering and Technology</cell></row><row><cell>International Journal of Mathematical and Computational Sciences</cell></row><row><cell>Vol:2, No:9, 2008</cell></row></table><note><p>671 International Scholarly and Scientific Research &amp; Innovation 2(9) 2008 scholar.waset.org/1307-6892/1815</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Mathematical and Computational Sciences Vol:2, No:9, 2008 waset.org/Publication/1815IV. Ordinal utility theoryAs mentioned above, each value node in the in°uence diagram is quanti¯ed by a utility function in the context of its parents. Both cardinal and ordinal utility can be used for this quanti¯cation.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">World Academy of Science, Engineering and Technology</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">International Journal of Mathematical and Computational Sciences</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Vol:2, No:9, 2008</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>International Science Index,</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>International Scholarly and Scientific Research &amp; Innovation 2(9) 2008</cell><cell>672</cell><cell>scholar.waset.org/1307-6892/1815</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>presents the a priori and conditional</cell></row><row><cell>possibility distributions for A, B and C.</cell></row><row><cell>The decision node D is transformed into a chance</cell></row><row><cell>node using (11) and conditional possibility degrees</cell></row><row><cell>¦(D j C) are presented in</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>International Scholarly and Scientific Research &amp; Innovation 2(9) 2008 scholar.waset.org/1307-6892/1815 International Science Index, Mathematical and Computational Sciences Vol:2, No:9, 2008 waset.org/Publication/1815</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">microeconomie du consommateur et du producteur</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Akari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">95</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Anytime propagation algorithm for min-based possibilistic graphs, Soft Computing a fusion of foundations methodologies and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ben Amor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Benferhat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mellouli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<publisher>Springer Verlag</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">161</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Qualitative Possibilistic Graphical Models: From Independence to Propagation Algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ben</forename><surname>Amor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">A method for using belief networks as in°uence diagrams, Fourth workshop on uncertainty in arti¯cial intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Possibility theory, an approach to computerized processing of uncertainty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<publisher>Plenum Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An introductory survey of possibility theory and its recent developments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois And .H Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Didier</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Henri</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Smets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">New semantics for quantitative possibility theory, 2nd International Symposium on imprecise probabilities and their applications</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ithaca, new York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Matheson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">In°uence diagrams. In the principles and applications of decision analysis</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Matheson</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Menlo Park, Calif</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">II</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Strategic decisions group</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to Bayesian networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<publisher>UCL Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Bayesian networks and decision graphs. Springer, statistics for engineering and information science</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Convince, A conversational inference consolidation engine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trains. on Systems, Man and Cybernetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">132</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Causality Models, Reasoning and Inference</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison of graphical techniques for decision analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Shenoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Operational Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two axiomatic approaches to decision making using possibility theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Giang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Shenoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European journal of operational research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">162</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">467</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating in°uence diagrams</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Shachter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Operation Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">882</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decision making using probabilistic inference methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Shachter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Poet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 8th Conference on Uncertainty in Arti¯cial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>8th Conference on Uncertainty in Arti¯cial Intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">276</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">283</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Von</forename><surname>Neumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Morgenstern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1948">1948</date>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabilistic inference in in°uence diagrams</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 14th Conference on Uncertainty in Arti¯cial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>14th Conference on Uncertainty in Arti¯cial Intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="514" to="522" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Academy of Science, Engineering and Technology International Journal of Mathematical and Computational Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno>waset.org/1307-6892/1815</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">676 International Scholarly and Scientific Research &amp; Innovation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2008</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno>waset.org/Publication/1815</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Science Index, Mathematical and Computational Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
