<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Valuing portfolios of interdependent real options using influence diagrams and simulation-and-regression: A multi-stage stochastic integer programming approach $</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">International Symposium for Next Generation Infrastructure</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">INFORMS</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">European Institute of Innovation &amp; Technology&apos;s Climate-KIC</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_gnsZWQh">
					<orgName type="full">Annual International Conference on Operations Research</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-02-19">February 19, 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sebastian</forename><surname>Maier</surname></persName>
							<email>sebastian.maier@imperial.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Grantham Institute -Climate Change and the Environment</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Polak</surname></persName>
							<email>j.polak@imperial.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Centre for Transport Studies and Urban Systems Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gann</surname></persName>
							<email>d.gann@imperial.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Imperial College Business School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Valuing portfolios of interdependent real options using influence diagrams and simulation-and-regression: A multi-stage stochastic integer programming approach $</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-02-19">February 19, 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Preprint submitted to Computers &amp; Operations Research</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T19:05+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Real options portfolio</term>
					<term>Influence diagram</term>
					<term>Simulation-and-regression</term>
					<term>Approximate Dynamic Programming</term>
					<term>Natural resource investment</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Although real options generally occur within portfolios, most valuation approaches based on either option pricing or decision analysis alone focus on single well-defined options. In this paper we present a new approach for modelling and approximating the value of portfolios of interdependent real options using both influence diagrams and simulation-and-regression. The key feature of this approach is that it translates the interdependencies between real options into a set of constraints and then directly models the dynamics of all underlying uncertainties using (Markovian) stochastic processes.</p><p>These are then integrated in a portfolio optimisation problem which is formulated as a multi-stage stochastic integer program. Applying a simulation and regression approach to approximate the value of this optimisation problem, we present a transparent valuation algorithm that explicitly takes into account vector-valued exercise decisions and the state variable's multidimensional resource component. The approach is therefore applicable to a wide range of complex investment projects with both inherent interdependent flexibilities and many underlying uncertainties. The approach is illustrated by evaluating a complex natural resource investment that features both a large portfolio of interdependent real options and four stochastic factors. We analyse the way in which the approximated value of the portfolio and its individual options are affected by the initial copper price as well as by the degrees of production cost and copper price uncertainty.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Making sound investment decisions in the context of uncertainty and irreversibility is a challenging problem for decision makers in both the public and private sectors. The value of an investment project and its exposure to risks are generally affected directly by both a sequence of decisions, which may be strategic, operational or tactical <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Chevalier-Roignant et al., 2011)</ref>, and their interactions (e.g. between financing and investment decisions <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Myers, 1974)</ref>). In addition, decisions makers often have to make such sequential decisions simultaneously with respect to several interacting projects, thus have to manage portfolios of investment projects, rather than individual ones.</p><p>While there exist a range of capital budgeting techniques, valuation methods based on simple temporal discounting are still widely used in practice <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Ryan and Ryan, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bennouna et al., 2010)</ref>. Given their prevalence, discounting cash flow (DCF) methods such as net present value (NPV) have been extended considerably in order to allow for more accurate investment analyses. Popular extensions include the Weighted Average Cost of Capital, or WACC; the Capital Asset Pricing Model, or CAPM; Monte Carlo simulation; and sensitivity analysis. Despite all these extensions, however, the inherent limitation of DCF methods remains: since they assume that investment decisions are "now or never" propositions they do not correctly take into account the value of managerial flexibility, thereby undervalue uncertain investment projects.</p><p>To address this limitation, real options analysis (ROA), or real options valuation, has received increasing attention and a wide range of different ROA approaches and techniques have been developed <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(De Reyck et al., 2008)</ref>. In particular, ROA has extended to accommodate portfolios of interdependent real options <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Trigeorgis, 1995)</ref>, potentially significantly enhancing the applicability of ROA to many practical situations. However, recent surveys indicate that the practical application of ROA is still limited, and largely confined to companies and industries with more sophisticated analytical cultures <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Block, 2007)</ref> or those exposed to high levels of financial uncertainty <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">(Verbeeten, 2006)</ref>. Lander and Pinches (1998) highlighted a number of institutional factors impeding the practical application of ROA techniques and <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Zapata and Reklaitis (2010)</ref> noted a number of theoretical limitations in ROA when used in a portfolio context. A key limitation is that when ROA is extended to the context of portfolios of options, traditional option valuation techniques (e.g. binomial/lattice and finite difference) become impractical <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Longstaff and Schwartz, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Gamba, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Trigeorgis, 2005)</ref>.</p><p>In this paper we present a new approach to model and approximate the value of portfolios of interdependent real options using influence diagrams and simulation-andregression. Although it is rarely used by real options analysts, the influence diagram (ID) is a promising alternative to the traditionally-applied decision tree and has many advantages as a framework for identifying, defining, and modelling interdependent flexibilities in investment projects. For example, IDs are intuitive and can be readily applied by decision makers to identify flexibilities <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Lander and Shenoy, 1999)</ref>, thereby focusing on the decisions the manager can make, rather than the risk modelling <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Sick and Gamba, 2010)</ref>. From a modelling perspective, IDs allow a more compact representation than lattice/tree techniques <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Charnes and Shenoy, 2004)</ref>, particularly in situations where there are multiple uncertainties and a sequence of decisions, or path dependency <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Demirer et al., 2003)</ref>. This is because IDs do not scale with the number of uncertainties and grow linearly rather than combinatorially in the number of decision variables considered <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Lander and Pinches, 1998)</ref>. Finally, ID representations are simple, intuitive, transparent and flexible. In our approach, we use IDs to graphically model the flexibilities contained in a portfolio of interdependent real options. The interdependencies between options are then translated into a set of constraints and integrated into the portfolio optimisation problem, which is formulated as a multi-stage stochastic integer program.</p><p>In order to approximate the value of portfolios of interdependent real options we apply simulation combined with parametric regression. It is widely acknowledged that simulation techniques, despite their computational complexity, have significant advantages over traditional option pricing techniques such as analytical and lattice-based methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Pringles et al., 2015)</ref>. Several authors have proposed numerical methods for the valuation of single American options using simulation and regression <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Denault and Simonato, 2017)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Stentoft (2014)</ref> recently compared the approaches of <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Carriere (1996)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Tsitsiklis and Van Roy (2001)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Longstaff and Schwartz (2001)</ref> and recommends the least squares Monte Carlo (LSM) approach of <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Longstaff and Schwartz (2001)</ref> for computational reasons. While the portfolio optimisation problem is formulated here as a multi-stage stochastic program (rather than an optimal stopping problem for American option pricing), we also apply "continuation function approximation" 1 by using both a parametric model and a least-squares method 2 like Tsitsiklis and Van Roy (2001);</p><p>1 It is important to note that functional approximations have been used at least since <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bellman and Dreyfus (1959)</ref> to increase the computational efficiency of dynamic programming.</p><p>2 By contrast, <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Tsitsiklis and Van Roy (1999)</ref> use a stochastic approximation algorithm to fit the model. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Longstaff and Schwartz (2001)</ref>. In this way, we are able to approximate the complex (hard or impossible to determine) continuation functions that describe the expected future contributions associated with transitions in the ID. These approximations are then used in the simulation-and-regression-based valuation algorithm to determine pathwise optimal decisions -by solving integer programs -for all available transitions at each possible resource state, subject to the constraints that describe interdependencies. We refer to this method as the influence diagram simulation-and-regression (IDSR) approach.</p><p>The main contributions of this work are: (i) introduction of an approach for the valuation of portfolios of interdependent real options using IDs and simulation-andregression, where IDs are used to graphically model the interdependencies between real options, which are then translated into a set of constraints; (ii) modelling of the portfolio optimisation problem as a sequential (stochastic) decision problem with vector-valued exercise decisions and formulation as a multi-stage stochastic integer program; (iii) development of a simulation-and-regression-based valuation algorithm that consists of a forward and backward induction procedure and that contains several important features specific to option portfolios such as the explicit consideration of the state variable's multidimensional resource component; and (iv) a demonstration of the ability of the proposed approach to evaluate a complex natural resource investment that features both a large options portfolio and four underlying uncertainties, including an investigation of the way in which the value of the portfolio and its individual real options are effected by both the underlying copper price level and the degrees of different uncertainties as well as an analysis of the effect of different parametric models on the value of the portfolio. These four areas of innovation are important as they highlight the potential of our approach to enhance the applicability of ROA to a wide range of complex yet practical and important investment problems and to lay the basis for further theoretical developments.</p><p>The remainder of this paper is organized as follows: Section 2 reviews the relevant literature on portfolios of real options. Section 3 describes both the approach that a decision maker can apply to model inherent flexibilities and formulates the corresponding portfolio optimisation problem. A valuation algorithm is presented in Section 4 that approximates the optimal value of portfolios of interdependent real options (Subsection 3.2). The approach is then applied to the example of evaluating a complex natural resource investment in Section 5. Section 6 presents and discusses the results. Finally, Section 7 provides some concluding remarks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Literature review</head><p>Early studies on portfolios of real options explored the concept rather qualitatively and in the context of corporate strategy and planning <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Myers, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Trigeorgis and Kasanen, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Bowman and Hurry, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Luehrman, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Smit and Trigeorgis, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Anand et al., 2007)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Trigeorgis (1993)</ref> investigated the nature of interactions between a firm's real options and found that options' individual values are generally non-additive. More recently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Trigeorgis (2005)</ref> argued that decision problems represented by a portfolio of interdependent real options can be decomposed into a few basic-building blocks (i.e. individual options) and then combined by one of four commonly encountered basic decision operators, which are "or" (max), "and", "average" and "multi-stage" (compound).</p><p>Various scholars have presented approaches to value portfolios of real options in the context of specific practical applications. One of the first publications to do so was Rose (1998), who valued two interacting options embedded in a toll-road project and found that ignoring the options' interactions results in significantly underestimated project values. Other relevant articles presented approaches in the context of R&amp;D projects <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(Vassolo et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">McGrath and Nerkar, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">van Bekkum et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Zapata and Reklaitis, 2010)</ref>, maritime investments <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Bendall and Stent, 2007)</ref>, IT investments <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Pendharkar, 2010)</ref>, and transmission network expansion <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Loureiro et al., 2015)</ref>. While these approaches have applied ROA in a portfolio context, they have developed rather inflexible and restricted quantitative approaches tailored to specific applications and limited to problems instances with specific features in terms of both options portfolio and uncertainties; by contrast, this paper takes a fundamentally different approach by proposing a valuation approach for portfolios of interdependent options applicable to a wide range of complex and risky investment problems in many practical situations.</p><p>A number of publications aimed at presenting more general quantitative frameworks for the problem of valuing portfolios of real options<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">foot_0</ref> . In an important early theoretical contribution, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Childs et al. (1998)</ref> provided closed-form (analytic) solutions for the value of two investment project that can be developed either in parallel or in sequence. <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Smith and Thompson (2008)</ref> provided analytic solutions whilst considering the problem of valuing a portfolio of sequencing options that represent projects. Considering one underlying source of uncertainty, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Meier et al. (2001)</ref> proposed two models: the first combines contingent claims analysis (replicating portfolios) with the well-known Knapsack problem to select projects, whereas the second is essentially an "Asset Liability Model" solved by stochastic programming whilst combining simulation with a binomial tree for scenario generation. Despite presenting more general portfolio-based real options approaches, neither addresses the problem in such a general way as we do because their focus is rather on portfolios of interrelated projects than on interdependent real options.</p><p>Furthermore, these approaches are simply impractical in most real-life situations.</p><p>Several recent studies have explored more holistic approaches including <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Gamba (2003)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Wang and de Neufville (2004)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Brosch (2008)</ref>. Most recently, the work of <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Brosch (2008)</ref> addressed portfolios of real options by proposing a forward-backward looking algorithm based on stochastic mixed-integer programming and lattice/tree modelling, where the forward looking element captures the budget constraint by making sure only feasible paths can be chosen from. The framework presented by <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Wang and de Neufville (2004)</ref> consists of an options identification stage which contains a screening and simulation model, plus an options analysis stage which applies a stochastic mixed-integer programming model and a binomial technique for scenario generation. Interestingly, both authors discussed computational issues with respect to the optimality of solutions, but only <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Brosch (2008)</ref> also discussed simulation, yet dismissed it as an alternative technique in his model. While these studies constitute important contributions, for example the global, dynamic budget constraints in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Brosch (2008)</ref> as well as the identification and definition of real options in physical systems by <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Wang and de Neufville (2004)</ref>, the combined complexity of applying both binomial techniques for scenario generation and stochastic mixed-integer programming for optimal options timing as well as the resulting adverse computational issues make both of them impractical in most real-life situations.</p><p>In contrast, the framework presented by <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Gamba (2003)</ref> overcomes the computational limitations of the binomial techniques used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Wang and de Neufville (2004)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Brosch (2008)</ref> by applying simulation and linear regression. In fact, Gamba considered a portfolio of interdependent real options that can be decomposed into a set of simple real options, which can be independent, mutually exclusive, compound, or of the switching type, and presented decision rules for each of the four cases. These rules were then used within a valuation procedure that applies the LSM algorithm to analyse the four sub-problems individually. Although Gamba has proposed an interesting extension of the LSM algorithm, his paper neither addresses the modelling of portfolios of interdependent real options, nor presents a single framework (it considers four sub-problems individually). Our work differs in a number of ways when compared with <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Gamba, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Wang and de Neufville, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Brosch, 2008)</ref>. For example, we use IDs to model portfolios of interdependent real options and translate the interdependencies into constraints.</p><p>Furthermore, we integrate both the constraints and the directly modelled dynamics of all underlying uncertainties into a multi-stage stochastic integer program in which the continuation function is approximated by parametric regression. In order to illustrate the IDSR approach, we apply it to the evaluation of a complex natural resource investment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Problem formulation</head><p>In this section, we present our approach to both the modelling of portfolios of interdependent real options and the formulation of the related portfolio optimisation problem as a multi-stage stochastic integer program.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Modelling flexibilities with influence diagrams</head><p>We consider the valuation of an investment project that is represented by a portfolio of interdependent real options. The flexibilities contained in this portfolio of interdependent real options are then modelled through an ID, which is composed of both a graphical and a numerical part. The former consists of two elements: a set of (decision and terminal) nodes N = {1, 2, . . . , N }, which may represent stages of development or operating modes, as well as a set of directed edges H = {1, 2, . . . , H}, which represents the transitions linking the nodes in the ID, or in other words the flexibilities available to the decision maker. Unlike most modelling approaches for IDs in the context of real options (e.g. see <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Lander and Pinches (1998)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Lander and Shenoy (1999)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Charnes and Shenoy (2004)</ref>, we allow for cycles in the ID, which is then represented through a directed cyclic graph (N , H) instead of an acyclic one. Although we only consider decision nodes, so apply the deterministic use case of IDs as noted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Howard and Matheson (2005)</ref>, our specification can be easily extended to the probabilistic case by including chance nodes in the ID, as shown by <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Charnes and Shenoy (2004)</ref>. Appendix A contains an example of an American option to illustrate the graphical part of the modelling approach.</p><p>The numerical part of the ID is specified by information associated with both nodes and transitions. Let the state of the system at time t, S t , be composed of a resource and an information component denoted by R t ∈ R t and I t ∈ I t , respectively, thus having  <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Nadarajah et al., 2017)</ref> or continuous <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Denault et al., 2013)</ref> scalar for R t . Here, in order to deal with complexities of portfolios of real options, including path-dependencies and interdependencies between options, we explicitly consider R t to be a vector made up of multiple resource state variables characterising the valuation problem<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">foot_1</ref> .</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">S t = (R t , I t ),</formula><p>In order to simplify the valuation algorithm presented in the next section, we assume that N contains exactly one beginning node (no incoming transition(s)), but may have several terminal nodes, which are characterised through not having outgoing transitions.</p><p>The value of a terminal node at t is given by its terminal value</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">G T t (S t ), for all S t ∈ S t ∈ S t : b D (N t ) = ∅ , where b D (N t ) represents the set of outgoing transitions of node N t .</formula><p>The set of decision times, which is often referred to as decision epochs in the Markov Decision Process (MDP) literature, is denoted by T .</p><p>With regard to the information associated with transitions, there are three elements to any transition h ∈ H:</p><p>1. The feasible region A St , which is composed of one or more constraints that describe the interdependencies between flexibilities, defines the transition(s) one can make given state S t . Let the decision to make any transition h ∈ b D (N t ) at node N t be represented by a binary decision variable a th ∈ {0, 1}, where a th = 1 means transition h is made at time t and vice versa, as well as let the duration of transition h be ∆ h . Then, the vector a t = (a th ) h∈b D (Nt) has to satisfy all constraints defined in A St , in other words a t ∈ A St .</p><p>2. The transition function, which is generically written as S M (S t , a t , W t+∆ h ), describes the evolution of the state S t from time t to t + ∆ h when making transition h and given new exogenous information W t+∆ h that is learned between t and t+∆ h .</p><p>In terms of the state's two components, S M (•) can be interpreted as a composition of both a resource transition function S R (•) and an information transition function S I (•) which describe individually the evolution of R t and I t to R t+∆ h and I t+∆ h , respectively, when making transition h at time t.</p><p>3. The immediate payoff Π t S t , a t is obtained at time t when making decision a t = (a th ) h∈b D (Nt) given state S t . Note that Π t (•) depends only on variables whose value is known at time t, so is deterministic, and is being received at the beginning of the period t to t + ∆ h .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Portfolio optimisation problem</head><p>The problem of determining the optimal value of the portfolio of interdependent real options is formulated as a multi-stage stochastic integer program. Unlike the approach of <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Gamba (2003)</ref>, who decomposed a portfolio of interacting real options into a set of independent, compound, mutually exclusive and switching options and then valued these sub-problems individually by enumeration, this paper proposes a single framework to value a portfolio of interdependent real options whilst using both a set of constraints and a vector of binary variables to model strategic interdependencies and exercise decisions, respectively. Let the optimal value of the portfolio of real options at time t given state S t be denoted by G t (S t ). The value of the portfolio of interdependent real options, G 0 (S 0 ), is given by the optimal solution of the stochastic optimisation problem:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">G 0 (S 0 ) = max (at) t∈T E t∈T e -kt Π t (S t , a t ) S 0 ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where S 0 is the state at time 0,</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">a t = (a th ) h∈b D (Nt) , a t ∈ A St , a th ∈ {0, 1}, k is the risk-free rate, and S t+∆ h = S M (S t , a t , W t+∆ h ).</formula><p>Applying Bellman's "principle of optimality", the above optimisation problem with objective (1) can be solved recursively by using the following value function for each</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">state S t ∈ S t ∈ S t : b D (N t ) = ∅ at time t: G t (S t ) = max at Π t (S t , a t ) + E e -k∆ h G t+∆ h (S t+∆ h ) S t , a t (2) s.t. a t ∈ A St ,<label>(3)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">a th ∈ {0, 1}, ∀h ∈ b D (N t ),<label>(4)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_6">S t+∆ h = S M (S t , a t , W t+∆ h ), ∀h ∈ b D (N t ),<label>(5)</label></formula><p>with the terminal condition</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">G t (S t ) = G T t (S t ), for all S t ∈ S t ∈ S t : b D (N t ) = ∅ , t ∈ T .</formula><p>Ultimately, the aim of solving the stochastic dynamic programming (SDP) recursion</p><p>(2)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">5</ref>) is to determine a decision vector a * t = a * t (S t ) St∈St for all t ∈ T , i.e. an optimal policy, that maximises the value of the portfolio of interdependent real options given the state S 0 at time 0, G 0 (S 0 ). It is important to note that, unlike traditional solution approaches for MDPs, the terminal condition used in (2)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">5</ref>) is not directly dependent on time t, but on whether the current node N t in the ID is a terminal node, which may or may not has to be reached at a certain t ∈ T . In the context of real option portfolios, for instance, one may decide to irreversibly abandon a project at any point in time t ∈ T , thereby reaching the corresponding terminal node perhaps well before max T .</p><p>At this point, it is important to note that while many approaches for real options valuation resort to an algorithmic strategy based on a dynamic programming representation, their original optimisation problems are often distinctly different. For example, valuing an American-style option entails solving an optimal stopping problem, which requires finding the stopping time that maximises the option's value. The corresponding SDP recursion 5 then characterises an optimal exercise policy, that is the stopping rule which solves the optimal stopping problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Glasserman, 2003)</ref>. While switching options can be valued by simply extending this SDP formulation (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Gamba (2003)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Cortazar et al. (2008)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Tsekrekos et al. (2012)</ref>), solving the embedded optimal switching problem means determining the optimal switching policy rather than just the stopping policy. The valuation of options with early and multiple exercise features such as swing and storage options can be formulated as a discrete MDP and then be solved, in theory, using SDP to obtain an optimal exercise policy, as described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Nadarajah et al. (2017)</ref>.</p><p>In contrast to these stochastic optimisation problems, we formulate the options portfolio problem as a multi-stage stochastic integer program to account for the complexities involved in valuing portfolios of interdependent real options. These complexities include path-dependencies, interdependencies between options, as well as higher dimensional decision vectors and resource state variables. Unlike the standard MDP formulation mentioned above, which assumes the decision and resource state variable are scalars, in our formulation the decision variable a t and the resource state variable R t are vectorvalued and multidimensional, respectively. Also, our feasible region A St is defined by a set of constraints, rather than just a discrete action space as in the optimisation problems described above, where A St represents either a binary choice or a fairly small set of discrete choices. Importantly, it can be shown that the multi-stage stochastic integer program (1) and solving the SDP recursion (2)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">5</ref>) are equivalent, e.g. see <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Powell (2011)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Curses of dimensionality</head><p>In general, solving the backward recursion in (2)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">5</ref>) can be computationally expensive, even intractable due to at least three curses of dimensionality: (i) the high dimensionality of the resource state space R t and information state space I t ; (ii) the 5 Interestingly, unlike <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Tsitsiklis and Van Roy (2001)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Longstaff and Schwartz (2001)</ref> neither presented the optimal stopping problem nor formulated the SDP recursion despite obviously addressing these.</p><p>inability to (exactly) compute the conditional expectation in (2); and (iii) the highdimensionality of the decision vector a t and the feasible region A St . Of these, the curses related to both I t and (ii) are being addressed through the simulation and parametric regression approach 6 described in Section 4. Also, in simple real option problems the action and resource state spaces are, in general, relatively small so the dimensionality of R t and (iii) can be neglected. For example, in the case of swing and storage options considered by <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Nadarajah et al. (2017)</ref>, where both a t and R t are scalar discrete, the number of actions and R t are relatively small. They can therefore assume that the intractability of their MDP (more precisely, of their SDP formulations) is solely due to the curses related to both I t and (ii), and implicitly ignore the ones related to R t and (iii).</p><p>In the context of real option portfolios, however, the action space or the resource state space or both will generally be larger, potentially making the related curse(s) difficult to ignore. In some practical option portfolio problems a t will still be a rather low-dimensional vector of binary variables and A St will be small in size, so (iii) can be neglected. Also, although R t is generally a vector of discrete variables, as demonstrated by the problem considered in Section 5, in which R t has 4 dimensions, in general by appropriately modelling the problem at hand and carefully choosing relevant parameters a large resource state space R t is prevented and a computationally manageable valuation process is ensured. However, there are a range of practical problems that involve higher dimensional decision vectors and resource state variables as well as a larger number of constraints 7 . Nevertheless, it should be relatively straightforward to extend our approach to account for higher dimensional problems by simply adapting the (already vector-valued) decision variable 8 a t and the (already multidimensional) resource state variable R t appropriately. Given the capabilities of modern integer programming packages, standard commercial solvers can then be used, again, to solve the embedded integer program within (2)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">5</ref>), and the dimensionality of R t can be addressed by suitable approximate dynamic programming approaches, e.g. see <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Denault et al. (2013)</ref>. 6 While such an approach is, in theory, not entirely free of the curse of dimensionality related to It because the number of basis functions needed (e.g. multivariate polynomials) and the computational cost of estimating the parametric model's coefficients are not linear in the dimension of It <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">(Tsekrekos et al., 2012)</ref>, the parametric model's size often remains very manageable in practice, e.g. see Judd (1998).</p><p>7 For example, resource allocation problems -e.g. in facility location and power transmission planning -are naturally multidimensional and feature (very) large action and resource state spaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Powell, 2011)</ref>.</p><p>8 It should be noted that our formulation lends itself to integer variables as binary variables can be used to represent general integers through binary expansion, and the feasible region can be adapted using standard modelling techniques associated with integer programming <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">(Wolsey, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Williams, 2013)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">The valuation algorithm</head><p>This section contains the approach to approximate the value of portfolios of interdependent real options as well as the corresponding simulation-based valuation algorithm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Approximating the continuation function by parametric regression</head><p>The strategy chosen in this paper is to approximate the value of the conditional expectation in (2), which represents the continuation value, using a parametric regression model. Using such an approximation of the continuation value is a commonly used strategy in the Approximate Dynamic Programming literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Tsitsiklis and Van Roy, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Longstaff and Schwartz, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Glasserman, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Powell, 2011)</ref> and directly tackles the curse of dimensionality related to I t and the outcome space. In particular, conditional upon being in state S t = (R t , I t ) at time t and making decision a t ∈ A St , we approximate E • |S t , a t of (2) by the following finite-dimensional, continuous function:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">ΦL t (S t , a t ) = L l=0 αl (S R (R t , a t ))φ l (I t ), (<label>6</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_9">)</formula><p>where L is the model's dimension, the functions {φ l } L l=0 are called basis functions (or features), and the optimal values of the coefficients (or weights), (α l (S R (R t , a t ))) L l=0 , are estimated using least-squares regression as described in the following subsection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">The simulation-and-regression-based valuation algorithm</head><p>To approximate the value of the multi-stage stochastic integer program, we apply a simulation-based algorithm that consists of both a forward and a backward induction procedure. The forward induction procedure initialises (and discretises) the state space S t for all t ∈ T . More specifically, using the numerical part of the ID and starting at t = 0, the state space of the resource state variable, R t , is being initialised for all t ∈ T through simple "exploration" to find all feasible resource states subject to A St , and by using the resource transition function S R (•) to step forward in time. On the other hand, the state space of the information state variable, I t , is generated by simulation (Monte Carlo sampling) while applying the information transition function S I (•), resulting in a set of |Ω| independent sample realisations {I t (ω) : ω ∈ Ω} for all t ∈ T . While the latter part of the above procedure is standard in the literature (e.g. see <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Glasserman (2003)</ref>), the former is a direct necessity of our portfolio approach yet uncommon in the real options literature, in which resource states are either not modelled explicitly or scalar.</p><p>Using the initialisations of R t and I t for all t ∈ T from the forward pass, the backward induction (or pass) determines an approximate value of the problem (2)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">5</ref>). Starting at max T and moving backwards to min{T \ 0}, for each resource state R t ∈ R t ∈ R t : b D (N t ) = ∅ the following three steps are performed: (i) applying least-squares regression, determine the optimal values of the coefficients α l (S R (R t , a t ))</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">L l=0 for all a t ∈ A St 9 : αl (R t+∆ h ) L l=0 = arg min (α l (•)) L l=0 ω∈Ω e -k∆ h Ḡt+∆ h (S t+∆ h (ω)) - L l=0 α l (R t+∆ h )φ l (I t (ω)) 2 ,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where R t+∆ h = S R (R t , a t ) and S t+∆ h (ω) = (R t+∆ h , I t+∆ h (ω)); (ii) using the result of (i) with ΦL t (S t , a t ) as in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">6</ref>), compute the pathwise optimisers ât (ω) of the pathwise approximation of the problem (2)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">5</ref>) for all ω ∈ Ω:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">ât (ω) = arg max at(ω) Π t S t (ω), a t (ω) + max Φt R t , a t (ω) , ΦL t S t (ω), a t (ω) (8) s.t. a t (ω) ∈ A St(ω) ,<label>(9)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_12">a th (ω) ∈ {0, 1}, ∀h ∈ b D (N t ),<label>(10)</label></formula><p>where Φt R t , a t (ω) is a lower bound on the continuation value, given R t and a t (ω); (iii) using the result of (ii), approximate the optimal portfolio value G t (S t ) given S t at time t along each path ω ∈ Ω by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">Ḡt (S t (ω)) = Π t S t (ω), ât (ω) + e -k∆ h Ḡt+∆ h S R (R t , ât (ω)), I t+∆ h (ω)<label>(11)</label></formula><p>At time 0, however, these three steps cannot by applied as S 0 = S 0 (ω), for all ω ∈ Ω, but now the conditional expectation in (2) can be computed directly by taking the average over all |Ω| pathwise continuation values Ḡ∆ h S R (R 0 , a 0 ), I ∆ h (ω) , so the approximate value of the portfolio of interdependent real options is then:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">Ḡ0 (S 0 ) = max a 0 ∈A S 0 Π 0 (S 0 , a 0 ) + 1 |Ω| ω∈Ω e -k∆ h Ḡ∆ h S R (R 0 , a 0 ), I ∆ h (ω) ,<label>(12)</label></formula><p>where a 0,h ∈ {0, 1}, for all h ∈ b D (N 0 ).</p><p>In the first and third step above as well as in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_14">12</ref>), the pathwise (approximated) continuation values Ḡt+∆ h (•) and Ḡ∆ h (•) are already known at times t and 0, respectively, since these are defined recursively. Importantly, unlike <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Tsitsiklis and Van Roy (2001)</ref>, we use ΦL t (•) only for the sake of computing the pathwise optimal decisions in step (ii), but the actually realised, pathwise continuation values, Ḡt+∆ h (•), to approximate G t (•) by Ḡt (•) in step (iii), which is in accordance with the approach of <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Longstaff and Schwartz (2001)</ref> and results in a comparatively smaller absolute bias as well as less and much slower accumulating approximation errors, as recently demonstrated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Stentoft (2014)</ref>. In addition, assuming a deterministic lower bound exists, we correct obviously erroneous approximations of the continuation value by replacing ΦL t (•) in ( <ref type="formula">8</ref>) with max{ Φt (•), ΦL t (•)}; e.g., Φt = 0 for an American option, as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Glasserman (2003)</ref>. A summary of the backward induction procedure is shown by Algorithm 1.</p><p>Algorithm 1: Approximation of optimal value of problem ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">5</ref>)</p><p>Data: From forward induction procedure and problem specific inputs Result: Ḡ0 (S 0 )</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">1 for t = max{T \ 0} do 2 forall R t ∈ R t ∈ R t : b D (N t ) = ∅ do 3 forall a t ∈ A St do 4</formula><p>Use both Φt R t , a t and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">6</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">7</ref>) to determine: Approximate optimal portfolio value along each path ω:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">F t (S t (ω), a t ) ← max Φt R t ,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_17">Ḡt (S t (ω)) ← Π t (S t (ω), ât (ω)) + e -k∆ h Ḡt+∆ h S R S t (ω), ât (ω) , I t+∆ h (ω) 9 end 10 end 11 T ← T \ t 12 end 13 At t = 0, determine: Ḡ0 (S 0 ) ← max a 0 ∈A S 0 Π 0 (S 0 , a 0 ) + 1 |Ω| ω∈Ω e -k∆ h Ḡ∆ h S R S 0 , a 0 , I ∆ h (ω)</formula><p>Although backward induction procedures are widely applied, the one described above contains several important features that allow us to approximate the value of a portfolio of interdependent real options. Firstly, the backward induction has to be applied for each resource state R t ∈ R t that does not correspond with a terminal node (no decision needed there), which is a direct consequence of our portfolio approach. By contrast, this is generally not needed for the regression-based pricing of single options with early-exercise features, where R t is commonly not modelled explicitly. Indeed, the pricing algorithms of <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Tsitsiklis and Van Roy (2001)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Longstaff and Schwartz (2001)</ref> for American-style options, for example, solely loop over all exercise times t ∈ T -i.e. there is no inner loop over R t -, whilst assuming that the option has not been exercised prior to t. Secondly, two of the procedure's three nested loops perform particular portfolio-related tasks.</p><p>In step (i), the optimal coefficients αl (S R (R t , a t ))</p><p>L l=0 are determined for every feasible decision a t , given R t , which consequently satisfy the set of constraints describing the interdependencies between real options in the portfolio. But this is generally not necessary for the pricing of single, well-defined options, which often feature trivial decision spaces; for instance, consider the simple "hold vs. exercise" decision underlying an American-type option shown in Figure A.3. Also, unlike the approach of <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Longstaff and Schwartz (2001)</ref>, we include in the regression (7) all |Ω| paths thereby improving approximation accuracy <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Areal et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Stentoft, 2014)</ref>. It is important to note that doing so is in fact necessary here as the exercise decision is required for all paths (and not just for in-the-money-paths as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Longstaff and Schwartz (2001)</ref>) given that the pathwise values of Π t (•) generally differ for compound real options within the portfolio.</p><p>In step (ii), the optimal decision ât (ω) along path ω is computed by optimally solving the integer program (8)-(10) for each path ω ∈ Ω, giving |Ω| pathwise optimisers ât (ω).</p><p>These represent the decision vectors that maximise the pathwise approximated portfolio value given S t at time t whilst satisfying the constraints in A St(ω) . In contrast, the decision-making process underlying most existing regression-based pricing algorithms boils down to simply comparing Π t (•) with ΦL t (•), e.g. by max{Π t (•), ΦL t (•)}, under total (or complete) enumeration of all mutually exclusive alternatives; e.g., two in the case of Bermudan <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Glasserman, 2003)</ref> and purchase swing options <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Nadarajah et al., 2017)</ref>, several in the case of switching <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">(Tsekrekos et al., 2012)</ref> and storage options <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Nadarajah et al., 2017)</ref>. Hence, these algorithms are limited to problems where the number of possible actions is small enough to enumerate because total enumeration tends to become impractical when the decision is a vector and when there are no appropriate constraints such as "mutual exclusivity". Rather than relying on such a brute force strategy, in our algorithm an integer programming formulation is used to optimise pathwise decisions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Computational efficiency and numerical accuracy</head><p>Since the IDSR approach uses a continuation function approximation, it shares a number of desirable properties with the LSM approach. For example, convergence results have been provided by <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Longstaff and Schwartz (2001)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Clément et al. (2002);</ref><ref type="bibr">Stentoft (2004b)</ref>. The robustness of the approach to different choices of basis functions has been shown by <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Moreno and Navas (2003)</ref> and more recently by <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Tsekrekos et al. (2012)</ref>, as well as with an emphasis on the tade-off between computational time and precision by <ref type="bibr">Stentoft (2004a)</ref>. More recently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Areal et al. (2008)</ref> have demonstrated various ways to improve the accuracy of the valuation approach by investigating the influence of different regression algorithms, several variance reduction techniques, various polynomial families, as well as varying numbers of both model dimensions (L) and paths (|Ω|). Furthermore, <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Longstaff and Schwartz (2001)</ref> recommend appropriate scaling before performing the least-squares regression in order to avoid numerical errors and computational underflows.</p><p>By its nature, the proposed algorithm applies the same strategy regarding mutually exclusive options as the one of <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Areal et al. (2008)</ref>, who has shown that this strategy provides faster and more accurate results than the algorithm presented by <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Gamba (2003)</ref>.</p><p>Despite providing a lower bound on the true value of the portfolio of interdependent real options, the IDSR approach can be extended by applying duality theory (e.g. see <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Haugh and Kogan, 2007)</ref>) to allow for the estimation of accurate upper (dual) bounds similar to <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Nadarajah et al. (2017)</ref>. Furthermore, the integer programming problem ( <ref type="formula">8</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_12">10</ref>) can be solved efficiently by standard solvers applying such algorithms as branch and bound <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Ahmed et al., 2003)</ref>. Lastly, while more advanced regression methods such as nonparametric models (e.g. kernel regression, local averaging, smoothing splines, and neural networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Carriere, 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Judd, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Powell, 2011)</ref>) can lead to more accurate results with lower computational efforts (e.g. see <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kohler (2010)</ref>), they are generally not readily applicable in high-dimensional settings and even low-dimensional problems can be comparatively complex <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Pizzi and Pellizzari, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kohler, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Powell, 2011)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Evaluating complex natural resource investments</head><p>In this section we demonstrate how the IDSR approach can be used to evaluate a complex natural resource investment by first presenting the problem setting, then detailing the modelling of the problem, and lastly approximating the value of the investment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Problem setting</head><p>The problem considered in this Section is a complex yet important and realistic extension <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Savolainen, 2016)</ref> of the example of valuing a copper mine, which was proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Brennan and Schwartz (1985)</ref> and solved by the authors using a finite difference method, and which has been used by <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Sabour and Poulin (2006)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Cortazar et al. (2008)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Tsekrekos et al. (2012)</ref> as a benchmark to assess the LSM approach. The original copper mine example of Brennan and Schwartz has only considered a limited set of options (option to temporarily close the mine and possibly reopen as well as early abandonment option) and only treated the price of copper to be uncertain. Here we substantially extend their example in two respects.</p><p>First, in terms of portfolio of real options considered, we integrate the option to defer (or delay) the development of the copper mine as proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Gamba (2003)</ref> and valued by the author using the LSM approach; however, <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Sabour and Poulin (2006)</ref> discussed the findings of Gamba and showed that there are some inconsistencies related to both numerical results (mine value cyclic in copper price) and switching decisions obtained. In addition to the option to defer, our example takes into account the option to irreversibly expand production capacity of the operating mine, which was proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Cortazar and Casassus (1998)</ref> and solved by the authors using partial differential equations; however, the authors did not consider the option to abandon the project.</p><p>The second extension is in terms of uncertainties considered. We replace the onefactor setting considered in Brennan and Schwartz (stochastic copper price) by applying the three-factor model (copper price, convenience yield and interest rate) of <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Schwartz (1997)</ref>, which has been analysed in the context of the original copper mine example by <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Tsekrekos et al. (2012)</ref> using the LSM approach. In addition to these three stochastic factors, we introduce a forth factor by treating the extraction (production) costs of copper to be uncertain, as argued for by <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Slade (2001)</ref>. It is important to note that traditional valuation methods (e.g. lattice and finite difference) are impractical for the problem considered here given its large size in terms of portfolio of options and uncertainties.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">Modelling</head><p>The flexibilities inherent in the mine project are represented by the ID in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>. It contains 5 decision nodes and 3 terminal nodes, as well as 18 transitions that link these nodes, resulting in N = {1, 2, . . . , 8} and H = {1, 2, . . . , 18}. The duration of transition h ∈ H is ∆ h years. When the mine is Undeveloped, the decision maker may decide either to Defer (1) development or Develop (2) the mine, both of which can be done for up to T max 1 years, after which the right to develop the mine expires. Once developed and in mode Opened-I, the decision maker has to decide whether to Operate (4) for the duration of ∆ 4 while extracting an amount q I ∆ 4 of copper, irreversibly Expand (5) the mine operation by increasing extraction rate from q I to q II , temporarily Close ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">6</ref>  <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">4</ref>) Idle ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">9</ref>)</p><p>Operate ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">11</ref>) Idle ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_20">15</ref>) Develop ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>)</p><p>Close ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">6</ref>)</p><p>Open ( <ref type="formula">8</ref>)</p><p>Close ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_14">12</ref>)</p><p>Open ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_19">14</ref>)</p><p>Expand ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">5</ref>) Abandon ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">7</ref>) Abandon ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_12">10</ref>) Expire ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">3</ref>) Abandon ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_18">13</ref>) Abandon ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">16</ref>)</p><p>Closure ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_22">17</ref>)</p><p>Closure ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_23">18</ref>) irreversibly Abandon (7) the project. On the other hand, if the mine is Closed-I (or Closed-II), the available transitions are to keep the mine Idle (9 or 15), Open (8 or 14) it again, or irreversibly Abandon (10 or 16) the project. In either operating mode, however, the mine closures if the commodity inventory with initial inventory Q 0 is fully depleted.</p><p>Also, the project has to be Abandoned when reaching its lifetime of T max 2 years.</p><p>Let the decision node, the inventory of the mine, and the remaining time to develop the mine/lifetime of the mine at time t be denoted by N t , Q t , and T t , respectively, as well as let the spot price of copper, the instantaneous convenience yield, the instantaneous risk-free interest rate, and the (per-unit) production cost at time t be denoted by X t , δ t , r t , and A t , respectively. Thus, the resource and information state component are given by R t = (t, N t , Q t , T t ) and I t = (X t , δ t , r t , A t ), respectively, hence S t = (R t , I t ).</p><p>The binary decision variables related to the transitions available at decision node N t , a t = (a th ) h∈b D (Nt) , have to satisfy the feasible region A St , which is defined by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">                                             h∈b D (Nt) a th = 1, ∀N t ∈ N \ {2, 4, 6},<label>(13)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_19">a t1 T max 1 &lt; T max 1 + T t ,<label>(14)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_20">a t3 T t = 0,<label>(15)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">a th q I ∆ h ≤ Q t , ∀h ∈ {4, 8},<label>(16)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">a th q II ∆ h ≤ Q t , ∀h ∈ {11, 14},<label>(17)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_23">a th 1 + a th 2 + T t &gt; 0, ∀(h 1 , h 2 ) ∈ {(7, 17), (13, 18)},<label>(18)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_24">a th + T t &gt; 0, ∀h ∈ {10, 16},<label>(19)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_25">a th + Q t &gt; 0, ∀h ∈ {17, 18},<label>(20)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_26">a th Q t = 0, ∀h ∈ {17, 18},<label>(21)</label></formula><p>where a th ∈ {0, 1}, ∀h ∈ H, and the set of outgoing transitions of node N t is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">b D (N t ) =                            {1, 2, 3}, if N t = 1, {4, 5, 6, 7, 17}, if N t = 3, {8, 9, 10}, if N t = 5, {11, 12, 13, 18}, if N t = 7, {14, 15, 16}, if N t = 8, {}, otherwise.<label>(22)</label></formula><p>These constraints accomplish the following: constraints (13) make sure that exactly one transition is made at a decision node; constraints ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_19">14</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_20">15</ref>) ensure the development can only be delayed if T t &gt; 0 and the right to develop can only expire at T t = 0, respectively; constraints ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">16</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_22">17</ref>) make sure the inventory does not become negative; constraints (18), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_25">20</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_26">21</ref>) require the opened mine to closure if and only if Q t = 0, and to be abandoned if both T t = 0 and Q t &gt; 0; and, finally, constraints (19) make sure the mine is abandoned if closed at T t = 0. It is important to note that constraints ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_19">14</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_23">18</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_25">20</ref>) can be easily transformed into (weak) inequality constraints if needed.</p><p>Subsequently, the resource state R t evolves deterministically to R t+∆ h , with the transition of t being rather trivial as it simply evolves from t to t + ∆ h after having made transition h. The evolution of N t is implicitly described by the adjacency matrix of the digraph (N , H), which is not shown here for brevity. The evolution of Q t and T t are specified by the following transition equations for all h ∈ H:</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">Q t+∆ h = Q t -q I ∆ h (a t4 + a t8 ) -q II ∆ h (a t11 + a t14 ),<label>(23)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_29">T t+∆ h =    T max 2 -(T max 1 -T t ) -∆ 2 , if a t2 = 1, max(T t -∆ h , 0), otherwise,<label>(24)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">T 0 = T max 1 .</formula><p>On the other hand, the information state I t evolves stochastically to I t+∆ h under the risk-neutral measure according to the following discrete diffusion processes. As reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Tsekrekos et al. (2012)</ref>, the discretised version of the joint stochastic process for the three factors of <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Schwartz (1997)</ref> is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">X t+∆ h = X t exp r t -δ t - σ 2 x 2 ∆ h + σ x ∆ h x t+∆ h ,<label>(25)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_32">δ t+∆ h = 1 -e -κ δ ∆ h θ δ + e -κ δ ∆ h δ t + σ δ 1 -e -2κ δ ∆ h 2κ δ δ t+∆ h ,<label>(26)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_33">r t+∆ h = 1 -e -κr∆ h θ r + e -κr∆ h r t + σ r 1 -e -2κr∆ h 2κ r r t+∆ h ,<label>(27)</label></formula><p>where σ x , σ δ and σ r are the standard deviations of changes in X t , δ t and r t , respectively; κ δ and κ r are positive mean reversion (speed of adjustment) coefficients; θ δ and θ r are the long run mean of convenience yield and interest rate, respectively; and x t+∆ h , δ t+∆ h and r t+∆ h are correlated standard normal random variables (mean 0, variance 1) with correlation coefficients ρ x,δ , ρ x,r and ρ δ,r (the correlation matrix equals the covariance matrix Σ here, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Glasserman (2003)</ref>). For the evolution of A t , as suggested by <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Slade (2001)</ref>, we consider a mean-reverting process, in particular we use the following approximation of the geometric mean reversion described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Metcalf and Hassett (1995)</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">A t+∆ h = A 0 e πt -A t κ a A t ∆ h + e π∆ h A t + σ a A t ∆ h a t+∆ h , (<label>28</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_35">)</formula><p>where π is the cost inflation rate, κ a is a positive mean reversion coefficient, σ a is the standard deviation of the production cost, and a t+∆ h is a standard normal random variable (mean 0, variance 1), which is assumed to be uncorrelated with the ones above and whose increments are independently and identically distributed.</p><p>The deterministic payoff obtained at time t when making transition h given I t is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">Π t I t , a t = -I d t a t2 + q I (X t -A t ) -f I (X t , A t ) ∆ h (a t4 + a t8 ) -K c,I t a t6 -K o,I t a t8 -M I t ∆ h (a t6 + a t9 ) -I e t a t5 + q II (X t -A t ) -f II (X t , A t ) ∆ h (a t11 + a t14 ) -K c,II t a t12 -K o,II t a t14 -M II t ∆ h (a t12 + a t15 ),<label>(29)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">I d t = I d 0 e πt is the development cost at time t, f I (X t , A t ) = τ 1 q I X t +max{τ 2 q I (X t (1- τ 1 ) -A t ), 0}</formula><p>is the sum of royalties and income tax paid at time t with τ 1 the royalty rate and τ 2 the income tax rate; M I t = M I 0 e πt is the maintenance cost at time t; K c,I t = K c,I 0 e πt and K o,I t = K o,I 0 e πt are the costs to switch to the Closed-I and Opened-I node at time t, respectively; and I e t = I e 0 e πt is the expansion cost at time t. For costs/revenues related to the Closed-II and Opened-II nodes simply replace "I" with "II" in the above definitions. For the sake of simplicity, if Q t &lt; q II then the payoff associated with transitions 11 and 14 equals the one of transitions 4 and 8, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.">Valuation</head><p>For valuation, we used the parameter values of <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Brennan and Schwartz (1985)</ref> for the copper mine and of <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Tsekrekos et al. (2012)</ref> for the three-factor model. The initial development cost and the initial expansion cost are estimated at US$ 8 millions (I d 0 ) and US$ 4 millions (I e 0 ), respectively. In addition, we consider the following: the possibility to defer development for up to two years (i.e. T max 1 =2); a lifetime of 45 years (T max 2 ); no values associated with terminal nodes i.e. G T t (S t ) = 0, for all S t ∈ S t ∈ S t : b D (N t ) = ∅ ; and 5 decisions to be made per year (i.e. ∆ h = 1/5, for h ∈ H \ {3, 7, 10, 13, 16, 17, 18}, and 0 otherwise). Also, we considered 100,000 (|Ω|) sample paths (half of which antithetic for variance reduction) and complete sets of the first five (i.e. L = 4) Legendre/Hermite polynomials, as well as applied a singular value decomposition (SVD) algorithm with properly scaled basis functions to avoid numerical problems when solving the leastsquares regression in <ref type="bibr">(7)</ref>. For an analysis of the effects of different parametric models see Appendix C. The chosen input data for this example are summarised in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</p><p>The forward induction procedure for this problem consists of the following steps:</p><p>1. Determine the set of decision times, T n , for all decisions nodes n ∈ {1, 3, 5, 7, 8}, Table <ref type="table">1</ref>: Input data for hypothetical copper mine adapted from <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Brennan and Schwartz (1985)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Tsekrekos et al. (2012)</ref> and own estimates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Description</head><p>Parameter Value Unit</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mine</head><p>Output rate q I (q II ) 10 ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_25">20</ref> forming subsets of T :</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">T n =                i∆ 1 : i ∈ Z ≥0 , 0 ≤ i∆ 1 ≤ T max 1 , if n = 1, i∆ 1 : i ∈ Z ≥0 , τ 1 ∈ T 1 , τ 1 + ∆ 1 ≤ i∆ 1 ≤ T max 2 , if n = 3, i∆ 1 : i ∈ Z ≥0 , τ 1 ∈ T 1 , τ 1 + 2∆ 1 ≤ i∆ 1 ≤ T max 2 , if n ∈ {5, 7} i∆ 1 : i ∈ Z ≥0 , τ 1 ∈ T 1 , τ 1 + 3∆ 1 ≤ i∆ 1 ≤ T max 2 , if n = 8,<label>(30)</label></formula><p>2. Use ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_33">27</ref>), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_32">26</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_31">25</ref>) to sample |Ω| paths of r t , δ t and X t , respectively, giving X t (ω), δ t (ω), r t (ω) ω∈Ω , ∀t ∈ T 3. Use (28) to sample |Ω| paths of A t , giving A t (ω) ω∈Ω , ∀t ∈ T 4. Generate the possible resource state space R t for each decision node and time<ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">foot_3</ref> :</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">R t =                                                                  t, 1, Q 0 , T max 1 -t , if t ∈ T 1 , t, 3, i∆ 1 q I , T max 2 -t : τ 1 ∈ T 1 , i ∈ Z ≥0 , τ 1 ≤ t -∆ 1 , Q 0 -min (t -τ 1 -∆ 1 )q I , Q 0 ≤ i∆ 1 q I , i∆ 1 q I ≤ Q 0 -q I min ∆ 1 , max(t -T max 1 -∆ 1 , 0) , if t ∈ T 3 , t, 5, i∆ 1 q I , T max 2 -t : τ 1 ∈ T 1 , i ∈ Z ≥0 , τ 1 ≤ t -2∆ 1 , Q 0 - min (t -τ 1 -2∆ 1 )q I , Q 0 -∆ 1 q I min(1, t/∆ 1 -2) ≤ i∆ 1 q I ≤ Q 0 , if t ∈ T 5 , t, 7, i∆ 1 q I , T max 2 -t : τ 1 ∈ T 1 , i ∈ Z ≥0 , τ 1 ≤ t -2∆ 1 , Q 0 -min (t -τ 1 -2∆ 1 )q II , Q 0 ≤ i∆ 1 q I , i∆ 1 q I ≤ Q 0 -q I min ∆ 1 , max(t -T max 1 -2∆ 1 , 0) , if t ∈ T 7 , t, 8, i∆ 1 q I , T max 2 -t : τ 1 ∈ T 1 , i ∈ Z ≥0 , τ 1 ≤ t -3∆ 1 , Q 0 - min (t -τ 1 -3∆ 1 )q II , Q 0 -∆ 1 q I min(1, t/∆ 1 -3) ≤ i∆ 1 q I ≤ Q 0 , if t ∈ T 8 ,<label>(31)</label></formula><p>The valuation algorithm was implemented in MATLAB.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Results and discussion</head><p>This section begins with an analysis of the way in which the mine value with different configurations of option portfolios is affected by the initial copper price, X 0 . Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref> summarises the results when X 0 is in the range from $ 0.30 to 1.00 per pound. Columns ( †) and ( ‡) give the expected values of the mine under "now-or-never strategies", which assume it must be either (developed and in case ( ‡) expanded immediately and then) operated at the rate of 10 and 20 Mlbs/year, respectively, until the inventory is fully exhausted, or left undeveloped. As can be seen, the value of the mine with fixed-outputrate q I (q II ) is positive for copper prices of $ 0.70 (0.80) per pound and above, making development of the mine viable, but only for X 0 = 1.00 is it optimal to have an expanded mine with fixed-output-rate q II . While these price levels are not the critical prices (i.e.    <ref type="bibr">16} in (d); and H in (a,b,c,d)</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">I q II Mothball Abandon Switch Mothball Abandon Switch X 0 ( †) ( ‡) (a) (b-i) (b-ii) (b) (c) (d-i) (d-ii)<label>(d)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_41">-) (-) (-) (-) (-) (-) (-)<label>(</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_43">† = {2, 3, 4, 17} in ( †); H ‡ = {2, 3, 5, 11, 18} in ( ‡); H † ∪ {1} in (a); H † ∪ {6, 8, 9} in (b-i); H † ∪ {7, 10} in (b-ii); H † ∪ {6, . . . , 10} in (b); H † ∪ {5, 11, 18} in (c); H ‡ ∪ {12, 14, 15} in (d-i); H ‡ ∪ {13, 16} in (d-ii); H ‡ ∪ {12, . . . ,</formula><p>the point at which it becomes optimal to invest, which largely depends on the input data of Table <ref type="table">1</ref>), these can be estimated simply and accurately through numerical simulation.</p><p>As can be seen from Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>, the flexibility provided by individual real options can add considerable value. Column (a) displays the value added to the mine with fixedoutput-rate q I when development can be deferred for up to 2 years. Determined by the difference between the value of the fixed-output-rate mine with the option to defer (not shown here) and column ( †), the value of the option to defer is positive for all copper prices listed. This means it adds value in every situation. Its adds sufficient value even when X 0 ≤ 0.60, enabling the mine to become economically viable by allowing the mine's development to be deferred. For X 0 ≤ 0.60, the value of this option would be much higher if we had used the actual NPV (which is highly negative in these situations)</p><p>as a benchmark instead of the non-negative value of the fixed-output-rate mine. As expected, the value of this option decreases as X 0 increases because the ability to defer development is economically less attractive when prices are high.</p><p>Considering a developed but not expanded mine, columns (b-i), (b-ii) an (b) report the value of the option to temporarily mothball the operation, to abandon the project during operation and to switch, respectively. These values were determined such that the mine values with these individual options were measured against the value of the mine with fixed-output-rate q I as the benchmark. Having either of these individual options is valuable for copper prices of $ 0.60/lbs and above, showing the mine to be viable in situations where the fixed-output-rate mine does not. At the same time, abandoning the project was found to be more valuable than mothballing, and switching more valuable than abandoning. In fact, representing the portfolio of the option to mothball and to abandon, the option to switch will always be at least as valuable as its constituent options. Although the values of these three options decline as the price increases, their levels remain comparatively high and they decline less strongly than the value of the option to defer. This indicates that operational flexibility is more beneficial than the flexibility associated with investment timing when price levels are high. that mothballing, abandoning and switching during operation of the developed but not expanded mine is more valuable. This implies that operational flexibility to deviate from the extraction of copper is less beneficial if the mine is expanded.</p><p>The value of the mine with the portfolio of interdependent real options is shown in column <ref type="bibr">(a,b,c,d)</ref>. As seen in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref> in most cases its value is considerably larger than the value of the mine without options or with only an individual real option. This highlights the substantial added value achieved by considering such a complex portfolio. While the value of the mine with the portfolio increases in X 0 , the absolute difference between this value and the value of the best-performing fixed-output-rate mine decreases as X 0 increases. This is because flexibility to deviate from the static now-or-never strategy becomes less valuable. However, the relative difference is still over 28% for the highest copper price considered. Comparing the values of the individual options of columns (a)</p><p>to <ref type="bibr">(d)</ref> shows that the option to expand is the only option whose value increases in the copper price, all other options diminish in value. These results, which are in line with the real options literature, demonstrate the ability of the option to expand to exploit upside potential, and the ability of the other options (i.e. to defer, to mothball, to abandon, and to switch) to limit downside risk when operating margins are lower.</p><p>To illustrate the effects of the degrees of different uncertainties on the value of the copper mine, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref> shows for X 0 = 0.70 the way in which the standard deviations of the production cost, σ a , and the copper price, σ x , effect the investment value. As we would expect, the value of the mine without options, which applies the best-performing static now-or-never strategy (always with fixed-output-rate q I here) and hence does not consider any flexibility, decreases as price uncertainty increases and eventually reaches zero at σ x = 0.30 (σ x = 0.35 for 0.09 ≤ σ a ≤ 0.24, σ x = 0.40 for σ a ≥ 0.27). On the other hand, the (expected) value of the mine without options, if positive, slightly increases in σ a because, although production cost uncertainty increases, average production cost slightly decreases due to the characteristics/parameters of the stochastic process in (28).</p><p>Taking into account the portfolio of real options and thus allowing the decision-maker to exploit flexibilities adds substantial value for all degrees of uncertainties considered, especially for high degrees of uncertainties<ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">foot_4</ref> . Increasing σ a from 0 to 0.30 generally results in appreciably higher values of the mine with the portfolio and this effect tends to be stronger for lower σ x . In contrast, there is an unexpected twofold effect of the degree of price uncertainty on the value of the mine with options portfolio: values actually decrease in σ x for low σ x -values, but, beginning at a σ x of 0.15 (0.20 for σ a ≥ 0.24), increase in σ x ; this decrease (increase) tends to be steeper for higher (lower) σ a -values. The reasons for this somewhat intriguing twofold effect are believed to be the overall volatility in the three-factor model, which depends non-linearly on σ x and features a similar pattern to the one shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref>, as well as portfolio effects which, as mentioned earlier and indicated by the filled circles<ref type="foot" target="#foot_5">foot_5</ref> in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref>, means that the portfolio's individual options are affected differently (beneficially or adversely) by changes of the underlying conditions resulting in positively or negatively affected portfolio values.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Conclusions</head><p>This paper presents a new approach for modelling and approximating the value of portfolios of interdependent real options using both influence diagrams and simulationand-regression. Our modelling technique is intuitive and compact; strategic interdependencies between real options are translated into a set of constraints and the risk-neutral dynamics of all underlying uncertainties are directly modelled using (Markovian) stochastic processes. These are then easily implemented in the multi-stage stochastic integer program. To approximate the value of this optimisation problem, we apply simulation and parametric regression and have presented a transparent valuation algorithm. In contrast to existing regression-based valuation algorithms, ours explicitly takes into account vector-valued exercise decisions and the state variable's multidimensional resource component that generally occur in real option portfolios. We demonstrate the ability of this approach to evaluate complex and risky investment projects by evaluating a complex yet realistic natural resource investment that features both a large portfolio of interdependent real options and four stochastic factors. Using this example, we show how our approach can be used to investigate the way in which the value of the portfolio and its individual options are effected by the underlying operating margin and the degrees of different uncertainties. Future work will investigate ways to integrate other types of uncertainties into the modelling framework presented here as well as explore possibilities to improve the efficiency of the simulation-and-regression-based valuation algorithm.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Influence diagram for the mine development project.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Column (c) reports the value of the option to expand, which enables the mine to double its fixed-output-rate to 20 Mlbs/year at any point during operation. Its value is given by the difference between the value of the mine with the option to expand and the maximum of the values shown in columns ( †) and ( ‡). Considering a developed and immediately expanded mine, columns (d-i), (d-ii) an (d) give the value of the option to temporarily mothball the operation, the value of the option to abandon the project during operation and the value of the option to switch, respectively. These values were determined in a similar way to those shown in columns (b-i), (b-ii) an (b), but now measured against the value of the mine with fixed-output-rate q II . Comparing the values of columns (d-i), (d-ii) an (d) with the ones of columns (b-i), (b-ii) an (b) shows</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure2: Value of investment project, Ḡ0(S0) (in $ millions), with portfolio of real options and without options as well as portfolio's most valuable individual option (filled circles), as a function of degrees of production cost (σa) and copper price (σx) uncertainty.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>where R t and I t are the corresponding resource and information state spaces. In general, R t is an endogenous component (evolves deterministically), whereas I</figDesc><table /><note><p>t is an exogenous component (evolves stochastically). The former is modelled to contain at least information about the current decision node N t ∈ N , but, generally, will contain further problem-dependent resource state variables. On the other hand, I t contains one or several stochastic factors (or random variables) describing the value of the problem's uncertain parameters at t. Most existing real options valuation approaches consider I t to represent the "state" and do not explicitly model R t . The few exceptions usually only consider either a discrete</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The values of the correlation coefficients are: ρx,r = 0.15, ρ x,δ = 0.40, and ρ δ,r = 0.10. b The value of the discount rate at time t, kt, is rt + λ1.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>)</cell><cell>Mlbs/year</cell></row><row><cell>Initial inventory</cell><cell>Q 0</cell><cell>150</cell><cell>Mlbs</cell></row><row><cell>Initial cost of opening Initial cost of closing Initial maintenance cost Cost inflation rate</cell><cell cols="3">K o,I 0 (K o,II 0 K c,I 0 (K c,II 0 ) 0.20 (0.40) $m ) 0.20 (0.40) $m M I 0 (M II 0.50 (1.00) $m/year 0 ) π 8% year -1</cell></row><row><cell>Initial development cost Initial expansion cost Expiration of development right Lifetime of copper mine project</cell><cell>I d 0 I e 0 T max 1 T max 2</cell><cell>8 4 2 45</cell><cell>$m $m year year</cell></row><row><cell>Production cost</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Initial average production cost</cell><cell>A 0</cell><cell>0.50</cell><cell>$/lbs</cell></row><row><cell>Speed of mean reversion in production cost</cell><cell>κ a</cell><cell>0.20</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Standard deviation of production cost</cell><cell>σ a</cell><cell>15%</cell><cell>year -1</cell></row><row><cell>Copper a</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Price variance Initial convenience yield</cell><cell>σ 2 x δ 0</cell><cell>8% 1%</cell><cell>year -1 year -1</cell></row><row><cell>Speed of mean reversion in convenience yield</cell><cell>κ δ</cell><cell>0.30</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Long-run mean convenience yield level</cell><cell>θ δ</cell><cell>1%</cell><cell>year -1</cell></row><row><cell>Standard deviation of convenience yield</cell><cell>σ δ</cell><cell>5%</cell><cell>year -1</cell></row><row><cell>Initial short-term interest rate</cell><cell>r 0</cell><cell>10%</cell><cell>year -1</cell></row><row><cell>Speed of mean reversion in interest rate</cell><cell>κ r</cell><cell>0.50</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Long-run mean interest rate level</cell><cell>θ r</cell><cell>10%</cell><cell>year -1</cell></row><row><cell>Standard deviation of interest rate</cell><cell>σ r</cell><cell>1.5%</cell><cell>year -1</cell></row><row><cell>Taxes</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Royalty</cell><cell>τ 1</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Income</cell><cell>τ 2</cell><cell>50%</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Property b , Opened/Closed</cell><cell>λ 1</cell><cell>2%</cell><cell>year -1</cell></row><row><cell>Property, Abandoned</cell><cell>λ 3</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>year -1</cell></row></table><note><p>a</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Value of copper mine (in $ millions) for different levels of initial copper prices.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Value with</cell><cell>Portfolio of</cell><cell>Options</cell></row><row><cell>During operation -mode II</cell><cell>Value of Option to</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Value of</cell><cell>Option to</cell><cell>Expand</cell></row><row><cell>During operation -mode I</cell><cell>Value of Option to</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Value of</cell><cell>Option to</cell><cell>Defer</cell></row><row><cell>Value of Fixed-</cell><cell>Output-Rate Mine</cell><cell>q</cell></row><row><cell>Copper</cell><cell>Price</cell><cell>($/lbs)</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Another related article is<ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Zhang and Babovic (2011)</ref>, which integrates evolutionary algorithms into a real options framework to value and select portfolios of real options.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_1"><p>For example, in the transmission network expansion planning problem considered by<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Loureiro et al. (2015)</ref> Rt would contain the current network configuration, whereas in the pharmaceutical R&amp;D portfolio valuation problem studied by<ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Zapata and Reklaitis (2010)</ref> Rt would include the number of resources allocated to drugs within different portfolio configurations and their stages of development at time t.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="9" xml:id="foot_2"><p>To simplify the presentation of the algorithm, the special case of transitions leading to terminal nodes with deterministic values (no approximation needed) is not treated separately here.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="10" xml:id="foot_3"><p>For simplicity, we assume Qt mod (q I ∆1) = 0.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="11" xml:id="foot_4"><p>Note that at σx = 0, Xt still evolves stochastically due to its dependence on the stochastic factors δt and rt in the three-factor model, with the value added by the options portfolio at σa = σx = 0 amounting to almost 46% of the value of the project without options.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="12" xml:id="foot_5"><p>The portfolio's least valuable options (not shown here) are the option to abandon (b-ii) for very high degrees of uncertainties of (σa, σx) ∈ {(0.27, 0.50), (0.30, 0.45), (0.30, 0.50)}, and either the option to mothball (d-i) or to abandon (d-ii) for the remainder of degrees of uncertainties.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head n="8.">Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors are grateful to the three anonymous reviewers for their valuable comments and suggestions. The authors would like to thank participants at the 19th &amp; 20th Annual International Real Options Conference, the <rs type="funder">Annual International Conference on Operations Research</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">OR2015</rs>), the <rs type="funder">International Symposium for Next Generation Infrastructure</rs>, and the <rs type="funder">INFORMS</rs> Annual Meeting 2014 &amp; 2015. This work was supported by the <rs type="institution">Grantham Institute at Imperial College London</rs> and the <rs type="funder">European Institute of Innovation &amp; Technology's Climate-KIC</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_gnsZWQh">
					<idno type="grant-number">OR2015</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix A. Modelling example of an American option</head><p>The managerial flexibility provided by a standard American-type (Bermudan in (3), as well as three transitions termed Hold (1), Exercise (2) and Expire (3). Consequently, the sets of nodes and transitions are given by N = {1, 2, 3} and H = {1, 2, 3}, respectively. When Holding at time t, the option holder has to decide whether to exercise the option immediately, or to hold the option until t + ∆ 1 . At the expiration date T max , however, this option automatically expires if not exercised.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix B. Nomenclature</head><p>This appendix contains a summary of most of the notation used in this work. Panel A: Power series Spec.  <ref type="bibr">, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6, results in 5, 15, 35, 70, 126, and 210</ref>, respectively, basis functions (or regressors) in the respective parametric model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sets and indices</head><p>It is evident from the results that in general the approximated value of the mine investment project (which is a lower bound on its true value) improved as the parametric model's dimension, L, increased, regardless of the family of polynomials used. This is in line with the multidimensional convergence results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Moreno and Navas (2003)</ref>; <ref type="bibr">Stentoft (2004b)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Areal et al. (2008)</ref>. As can be seen, the results for specifications 41 and 81 are essentially the same across polynomial families, suggesting that any polynomial family with sufficient degree L can be used in these two cases. In the case of specification 1, however, our analysis revealed considerable value differences amongst different polynomials for high model dimensions, with differences between the highest and lowest project values at around $32k and $83k for L = 5 and L = 6, respectively. This suggests that the approximation can be improved considerably by choosing an appropriate polynomial family. Note that while standard errors in specification 1 are higher than in the other two specifications, project values are proportionally even higher.</p><p>Compared with values obtained for specifications 41 and 81, which eventually levelled off at high L, the trends corresponding with specification 1 seem to indicate that values have not converged yet. This suggests that an increase in L would further improve the lower bound. Although the Power series was found to perform surprisingly well and reduced computational time by about 40-45% (which is similar to the reduction found by <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Areal et al. (2008)</ref>), the number of basis functions used in the regression grows exponentially in L. This substantially increased both the complexity of the parametric model and computational cost; e.g., plus 84 basis functions and 50% more time when L is increased from 5 to 6. In Section 5, complete sets of Legendre and Hermite polynomials with L = 4 are used for Table <ref type="table">2</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, respectively. Although different parametric model choices may result in better approximations, our choice, which presents the best trade-off between accuracy and computational time amongst all models tested, is sufficient for the purposes of demonstration. Future work might therefore investigate the convergence properties and the computational efficiency of different parametric models in situations with both complex and large portfolios of interdependent real options.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Mathematical Functions: With Formulas, Graphs, and Mathematical Tables</title>
		<title level="s">Applied Mathematics Series</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Abramowitz</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stegun</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, D.C., USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>National Bureau of Standards</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1972-12">December 1972</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>th Printing</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A multi-stage stochastic integer programming approach for capacity expansion under uncertainty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ahmed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Parija</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Global Optimization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Managing a portfolio of real options</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Anand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Oriani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vassolo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Real Options Theory: Advances in Strategic Management</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Reuer</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tong</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier Ltd</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="303" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On improving the least squares Monte Carlo option valuation method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Areal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rodrigues</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Armada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Derivatives Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="151" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional approximations and dynamic programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bellman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dreyfus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mathematical Tables and Other Aids to Computation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="247" to="251" />
			<date type="published" when="1959">1959</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maritime investment strategies with a portfolio of real options</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bendall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stent</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Maritime Policy &amp; Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="441" to="452" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved capital budgeting decision making: evidence from Canada</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bennouna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Meredith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Marchant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Decision</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="247" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Are &quot;real options&quot; actually used in the real world?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Block</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Engineering Economist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="267" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strategy through the option lens: An integrated view of resource investments and the incremental-choice process</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Bowman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hurry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Academy of Management Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="760" to="782" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating natural resource investments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brennan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Business</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Portfolios of Real Options</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Brosch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Lecture Notes in Economics and Mathematical Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">611</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin Heidelberg</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Valuation of the early-exercise price for options using simulations and nonparametric regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Carriere</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Insurance: Mathematics and Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multistage Monte Carlo method for solving influence diagrams using local computation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Charnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Shenoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="405" to="418" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strategic investment under uncertainty: A synthesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chevalier-Roignant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Flath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Huchzermeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Trigeorgis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Operational Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">215</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="639" to="650" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capital budgeting for interrelated projects: A real options approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Childs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Triantis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Financial and Quantitative Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="334" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An analysis of a least squares regression method for American option pricing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Clément</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lamberton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Protter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Finance and Stochastics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="471" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal timing of a mine expansion: Implementing a real options model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cortazar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Casassus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Quarterly Review of Economics and Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="755" to="769" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The valuation of multidimensional american real options using the (LSM) simulation method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cortazar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gravet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Urzua</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers &amp; Operations Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Project options valuation with net present value and decision tree analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>De Reyck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Degraeve</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Vandenborre</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Operational Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">184</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="355" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Influence diagrams for real options valuation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Demirer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Charnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kellogg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.siue.edu/business/economicsandfinance/pdf/demirer-agouron.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-05">May 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic portfolio choices by simulation-andregression: Revisiting the issue of value function vs portfolio weight recursions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Denault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-G</forename><surname>Simonato</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers &amp; Operations Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="174" to="189" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simulation-and-regression approach for stochastic dynamic programs with endogenous state variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Denault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-G</forename><surname>Simonato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Stentoft</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers &amp; Operations Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2760" to="2769" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Real options valuation: A Monte Carlo approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gamba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">December 2003. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Faculty of Management, University of Calgary</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Working Paper</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Monte Carlo Methods in Financial Engineering, 1st Edition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Glasserman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>of Applications of mathematics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Duality theory and approximate dynamic programming for pricing american options and portfolio optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Haugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kogan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Handbooks in Operations Research and Management Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="925" to="948" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Matheson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Influence diagrams. Decision Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Numerical Methods in Economics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Judd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<publisher>The MIT Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A review on regression-based monte carlo methods for pricing american options</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kohler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Recent Developments in Applied Probability and Statistics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Devroye</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Karasözen</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kohler</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Korn</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Physica-Verlag HD</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="58" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Challenges to the practical implementation of modeling and valuing real options</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Pinches</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Quarterly Review of Economics and Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="537" to="567" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Modeling and valuing real options using influence diagrams</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Shenoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://pshenoy.faculty.ku.edu/Papers/WP283.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>School of Business, University of Kansas</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Working Paper 283</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Valuing American options by simulation: a simple least-squares approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Longstaff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Financial Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capacity expansion in transmission networks using portfolios of real options</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Loureiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Claro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pereira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Electrical Power &amp; Energy Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="439" to="446" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strategy as a portfolio of real options</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Luehrman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Harvard business review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real options reasoning and a new look at the R&amp;D investment strategies of pharmaceutical firms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mcgrath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nerkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Strategic Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capital budgeting under uncertaintyan integrated approach using contingent claims analysis and integer programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Meier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Christofides</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Salkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Operations Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="196" to="206" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investment under alternative return assumptions comparing random walks and mean reversion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Metcalf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hassett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Dynamics and Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1471" to="1488" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the robustness of least-squares Monte Carlo (LSM) for pricing american derivatives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moreno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Navas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Derivatives Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactions of corporate financing and investment decisionsimplications for capital budgeting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Myers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Myers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Finance theory and financial strategy. Interfaces</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="126" to="137" />
			<date type="published" when="1984-02">January-February 1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of least squares monte carlo methods with applications to energy real options</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nadarajah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Margot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Secomandi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Operational Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">256</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="196" to="204" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Valuing interdependent multi-stage IT investments: A real options approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Pendharkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Operational Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">201</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="847" to="859" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Monte carlo pricing of american options using nonparametric regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Pizzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pellizzari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rendiconti per gli Studi Economici Quantitativi</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="91" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Approximate Dynamic Programming: Solving the Curses of Dimensionality, 2nd Edition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Powell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real option valuation of power transmission investments by stochastic simulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pringles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Olsina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Garcs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">0</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Valuation of interacting real options in a tollroad infrastructure project</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Quarterly Review of Economics and Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="711" to="723" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capital budgeting practices of the Fortune 1000: How have things changed?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business and Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="355" to="364" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Valuing real capital investments using the leastsquares Monte Carlo method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A A</forename><surname>Sabour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Poulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Engineering Economist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="160" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real options in metal mining project valuation: Review of literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Savolainen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Resources Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The stochastic behavior of commodity prices: Implications for valuation and hedging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="923" to="973" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some important issues involving real options: an overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gamba</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Multinational Finance Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1/2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Valuing managerial flexibility: An application of real-option theory to mining investments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Slade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Economics and Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="193" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strategic planning: valuing and managing portfolios of real options</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T J</forename><surname>Smit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Trigeorgis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">R&amp;D Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="419" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Managing a portfolio of real options: Sequential exploration of dependent prospects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Energy Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing the least squares Monte-Carlo approach to American option valuation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Stentoft</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Derivatives Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="168" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Convergence of the least squares Monte Carlo approach to American option valuation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Stentoft</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1193" to="1203" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Value function approximation or stopping time approximation: A comparison of two recent numerical methods for American option pricing using simulation and regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Stentoft</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computational Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The nature of option interactions and the valuation of investments with multiple real options</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Trigeorgis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Financial and Quantitative Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real options: An overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Trigeorgis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Real Options in Capital Investment: Models, Strategies, and Applications</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Trigeorgis</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="28" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Making use of real options simple: An overview and applications in flexible/modular decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Trigeorgis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Engineering Economist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="53" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrated options-based strategic planning and control model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Trigeorgis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kasanen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Managerial Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2/3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating natural resource investments under different model dynamics: Managerial insights</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Tsekrekos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Shackleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wojakowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Financial Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="543" to="575" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regression methods for pricing complex Americanstyle options</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tsitsiklis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Van Roy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="694" to="703" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-07">Jul 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal stopping of markov processes: Hilbert space theory, approximation algorithms, and an application to pricing high-dimensional financial derivatives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Tsitsiklis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Van Roy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1840" to="1851" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A real options perspective on R&amp;D portfolio diversification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Bekkum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pennings</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T J</forename><surname>Smit</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1150" to="1158" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-additivity in portfolios of exploration activities: a real options-based analysis of equity alliances in biotechnology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vassolo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Anand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Folta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Strategic Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1045" to="1061" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do organizations adopt sophisticated capital budgeting practices to deal with uncertainty in the investment decision?: A research note</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Verbeeten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Accounting Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building real options into physical systems with stochastic mixed-integer programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>De Neufville</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 8th Annual International Real Options Conference</title>
		<meeting>the 8th Annual International Real Options Conference<address><addrLine>Montréal, Canada</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-06">June 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Model Building in Mathematical Programming, 5th Edition</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integer programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wolsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Wiley-Interscience Series in Discrete Mathematics and Optimization</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Valuation of project portfolios: An endogenously discounted method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Zapata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Reklaitis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Operational Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">206</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="653" to="666" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An evolutionary real options framework for the design and management of projects and systems with complex real options and exercising conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Babovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Decision Support Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
