<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">TRIZ-ISHIKAWA diagram, a new tool for detecting influencing factors: a case study in HVAC business</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Soumaya</forename><surname>Elyoussoufi</surname></persName>
							<email>soumaya.elyoussoufi@ensem.ac.ma</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mohamed</forename><surname>Mazouzi</surname></persName>
							<email>m.mazouzi@ensem.ac.ma</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anass</forename><surname>Cherrafi</surname></persName>
							<email>a.cherrafi@ensam.umi.ac.ma</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">El</forename><surname>Mehdi Tamasna</surname></persName>
							<email>el-mehdi.tamasna@ensem.ac.ma</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">2D2I National school of Electricity and Mechanics (ENSEM)</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory LM2I</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hassan II University Casablanca</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="MA">Morocco</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">2D2I National school of Electricity and Mechanics (ENSEM)</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory LM2I</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hassan II University Casablanca</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="MA">Morocco</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">2D2I National school of Electricity and Mechanics (ENSEM)</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory LM2I</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">ENSAM School Moulay Ismail University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Hassan II University Casablanca</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="MA">Morocco</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">TRIZ-ISHIKAWA diagram, a new tool for detecting influencing factors: a case study in HVAC business</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T19:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Ishikawa diagram</term>
					<term>TRIZ</term>
					<term>Resources</term>
					<term>HVAC</term>
					<term>Problem solving</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Eliminating an undesirable effect or reducing the gap between the desired situation and the actual situation, becomes a necessity for a performing organization. The Ishikawa diagram is one of the important tools that organizations use to find factors generating an effect. However, authors are still searching for the most convenient form of the diagram and still looking for generic cornerstones. This paper aims to integrate TRIZ into the Ishikawa diagram to overcome the diagram's actual limitations. The case study demonstrates the effectiveness of TRIZ-Ishikawa diagram. The new diagram will enable users to overcome psychological inertia and systematically identify influencing factors.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Organizations need to overcome daily problems to sustain their performance and competitiveness. Eliminating the problem or the effect is related to finding the root cause. Ishikawa diagram is one of the most relevant tools for analyzing problems and finding the main reason for a problem's existence. Many authors used the diagram to prevent or solve manufacturing and service effects <ref type="bibr">(Suárez-Barraza and Rodriguez 2019)</ref>. Others use the diagram to solve supply chain problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Elleuch &amp; al. 2016)</ref>. While some research focus on medical issues <ref type="bibr">(Ma &amp; al. 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Kudla &amp;</ref> Proceedings of the International Conference on Industrial <ref type="bibr">Engineering and</ref><ref type="bibr">Operations Management Istanbul, Turkey, March 7-10, 2022 Brook 2018)</ref>. The diagram has proven to be used in many fields. However, Ishikawa diagram have some limitations. In fact, finding the root cause and associating cornerstones is still difficult. Furthermore, at the end of the brainstorming, there may be no cornerstone to express the potential cause. Some research tried to standardize cornerstones as 6M or 4P <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Koripadu &amp; Subbaiah 2014)</ref>. In addition, <ref type="bibr">Suárez-Barraza &amp; Rodriguez (2019)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Wong &amp; al. (2016)</ref> were rare authors that critics the method and attempt to develop it. Based on their studies, the literature review, and the authors' experience, this paper tries to remove Ishikawa's barriers. First, we present the correlation between the 5M and TRIZ resources. Then, using resources strength, we propose an improved diagram that we test to reduce accumulated inventory in the HVAC business. Finally, we discuss the result and present the research limitations and future opportunities for the TRIZ-Ishikawa diagram.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Literature Review</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Ishikawa diagram</head><p>Ishikawa Diagram Known also as cause-and-effect diagram (CE), or fishbone diagram is one of the seven basic quality control tools (Suárez-Barraza and Rodriguez 2019). Professor Ishikawa and his team used the diagram during the 1952-53 periods to structure factors in their research work <ref type="bibr">(Suárez-Barraza and Rodriguez 2019)</ref>.The classical definition of the diagram relates the Ishikawa diagram to the identification of variation factors as a cause of an effect. Whenever a problem is detected, it is essential to detail all the potential causes of the variation (Suárez-Barraza and Rodriguez 2019). <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Ma &amp; al. (2020)</ref> defines Ishikawa as a tool that helps users to visualize and illustrate the complexity of the problem and shows how multiple factors can contribute to the effect. <ref type="bibr">Hola &amp; al. (2017)</ref> acknowledges that a specific effect depends on many factors that can be divided into groups. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Kudla and Brook (2018)</ref> adds that the diagram recognize and inspect contributing factors to an undesirable event or inefficient process. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Dobrusskin (2015)</ref> defines the Ishikawa diagram as a standardized way to conduct efficient investigations. We conclude using those definitions that the Ishikawa diagram is a standardized tool that helps users to extract and identify contributing factors to a specific effect. The identified factors are divided into categories or cornerstones. We need to highlight that, in the original version; the cornerstone was defined according to the problem or effect context. Then, next to each cornerstone, we define factors that may influence the effect. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Kudla and Brook (2018)</ref> chooses Pathology, process, policies and practice, Equipment, environment, and people as cornerstones for near-miss interpretive errors. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Ma &amp; al. (2020)</ref> defines organization, equipment, providers, and people as cornerstones for communication issues. Moreover, Simanova and Gejdos (2015), choose four groups which are: input material, working conditions, service equipment and employee to reduce disagreements.</p><p>Nowadays, the new version includes the 5M acronym of Machinery, Manpower, Material, measurement, and method (Suárez-Barraza and Rodriguez 2019). Other authors add Management <ref type="bibr">(Dobrusskin 2015) Method, and</ref><ref type="bibr">environment (Hola &amp;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">al. 2017)</ref>.Moreover, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Koripadu and Subbaiah (2014)</ref> categorizes the 6M (Machine, Method, Material, measurement, Mother Nature, and manpower) for manufacturing industries and 4Ps acronym of policies, procedure, people and plant as the diagram branches for service industries.</p><p>Another aspect of the diagram is asking "why" for each cause-and-effect relation. The objective is to put the "why" question for each cause at the primary level. Then, the "Why" question is repeated for each level until reaching the root cause. At the end, we choose the appropriate causes that have a direct impact on the studied problem.</p><p>The Ishikawa diagram proved its efficiency in many fields; industry, Medicine, Services, supply chain, and education (Suárez-Barraza and Rodriguez 2019). It may be used to correct or to prevent an effect, it offers benefits for users such as:</p><p>• Systemizes the analysis step (Suárez-Barraza and Rodriguez 2019; <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Wong &amp; al. 2016</ref>).</p><p>• 5M or 4P facilitates the use of cornerstones as guidelines for gathering information. (Koripadu and Subbaiah 2014)</p><p>• Present a variety of potential causes, and diversify ideas <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Wong &amp; al. 2016)</ref> • Visual classification that can be used for further investigation <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Wong &amp; al. 2016)</ref> Unfortunately, this approach can present many barriers such as:</p><p>• Difficulty to relate some causes to a particular category.</p><p>• Potential bias (Culture, motivation, personality, and the team) may affect the result.</p><p>• The Manpower factor is usually misunderstood. The fear of being personally attacked or accused by the problem presents a natural barrier.</p><p>Proceedings of the International Conference on Industrial Engineering and Operations Management Istanbul, Turkey, March 7-10, 2022</p><p>• The Time and the system evolution is missing in the diagram • The need for more factors to adapt the diagram to the effect.</p><p>• There may no cornerstone proposed to explain the cause of an effect.</p><p>Questions that arise are: How can we improve the diagram limitations and lead users to find the root cause easily? Knowing that resources are cause of problems, how can we use them to create a new diagram?</p><p>2.2 5M factors and TRIZ resources assessment <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Mann (2002)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Mueller (2005)</ref> formulate resources as anything, in or around, the studied system. They have direct effects on the problem. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Mueller (2005)</ref> presented an elementary level to define resources as presented in table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. Besides, we present the correlation between the 5M and resources. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Mueller (2005)</ref> synthesize TRIZ preliminary resources in six categories, which are Substances, Field, functional, informational, time and spatial. In TRIZ definition, substances may refer to the studied system elements or the system's environment. It submits Materiel, Manpower, and Machines. Moreover, Fields present the interaction between systems. It describes the energy and the interaction in the system or between the system and substances. In addition, functional resources show the methodology of how substances are used according to basic needs. The informational resource helps to understand the non-detection causes. It also shows inherent proprieties of the system and substances, including data, knowledge, behaviors, and communication systems. Additionally, space refers to space between elements, space occupied by substances, or external factors like temperatures, pressure, or light. Eventually, Time expresses any kind of time, including time intervals, duration, and the system within substances evolution. It describes the Time before the problem starts and during the problem. It also may illustrate time organization, habits, or temporary actions.</p><p>TRIZ resources support solvers in explaining predominantly technical or managerial problems. The main advantage is when we extract substances around the studied problem. For example, if we want to study signature variation cause for the same person, substances are the hand, the pen, the paper, and the paper support. Variation causes are related to those substances. The energy of a substance or between substances may have an impact on the problem. For or example energy to maintain the pen by the person or stabilization of the paper support may have an impact on the signature variation. In addition, functionalities of the substance, as the hand speed, the pen functionality, or the paper proprieties may influence the signature. In time resource, substance description during time can reveal some variation causes.</p><p>We conclude, as presented in table 1 that there is an implication between 5M and resources. Moreover, Time is not well explored in 5M. We detect also that resources can describe a detailed and large spectrum around the studied system. It will have better and structured guidelines for solvers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">The methodology and case study</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">TRIZ-Ishikawa diagram</head><p>Using this correlation, we propose, in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, the TRIZ-ISHIKAWA diagram as an improved analyze tool to detect influencing factors. To complete the diagram first, we need to place on the right side of the diagram the studied effect. Then, the team lists substances concerning the studied subject. The objective here is to have a global vision of the system and its context. Then, in the Time factor, the team describes substance during Time. By enumerating substance evolution, solvers may detect immediately potential cause. Finally, Space, field, Functional, and Informational resources are discussed to extract other influencing factors.</p><p>Proceedings of the International Conference on Industrial Engineering and Operations Management Istanbul, Turkey, March 7-10, 2022 The classic Ishikawa diagram is based on hazardous method to collect potential causes (wong2016). However, enumerating substance around the studied system, helps users to focus on a small spectrum of potential causes. The root cause is for sure one of the listed factors. In addition, the diagram conception eliminates the need for other cornerstones to complete the diagram.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">The case study:</head><p>In an HVAC Company, the accumulation of inventory is a serious issue. First, it occupies an important storage space because of the material volume, and it blocks capitals. The generation of inventory can be caused by many factors.</p><p>The studied HVAC Company works in air conditioning projects. They are called to study and propose the aeraulic system and to install piping and air conditioning systems according to the customer requirements, and control specifications. At the end of projects, the company observes the raw material accumulation. To detect factors influencing raw material accumulation we use the TRIZ-Ishikawa diagram as presented in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>.</p><p>Proceedings of the International Conference on Industrial Engineering and Operations Management Istanbul, Turkey, March 7-10, 2022 The accumulation of inventory is due to many factors. Any person in the study process, procurement chain, or operations may influence the inventory. In addition, supplier conditions, customer requirements, and even the storage place may influence the inventory value. Furthermore, engineers use a new procedure to list component for procurement and import them directly from sources. As well, behaviors, the company's culture, communication between actors and storage space will influence the inventory.</p><p>In this case, we observe that the accumulation of inventory does not depend only on the purchaser or worker but depend on the chain, from defining the project specification by the customer, to the project closing. To detect the root cause, we need to complement the study with investigations. We may have one or more influencing factors depending on the context.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Result and discussion</head><p>According to the review, Ishikawa diagram present limitations to have accurate data. In fact, users still have difficulties to relate some cause to a particular category, they need more factors to adapt the diagram to the effect and there may no cornerstone proposed to explain the cause of an effect. Some authors add other factors to adapt the diagram to the studied situation. As resource and evolution systems are used to analyze issues in TRIZ philosophy, we integrate them into the Ishikawa diagram.</p><p>The TRIZ-Ishikawa is the improved version of the Ishikawa diagram. It allows detecting all substances that may influence the problem. The evolution system can help to detect some changes that happen in the system or around the system. Then substance functionalities, the energy between substance and the studied problem, information, and the space are guidelines factors to detect others influencing factors. The TRIZ-Ishikawa can open psychological inertia and eliminate resistance because we are not just inventorying the cause factors directly, but we are inventorying substance around the studied system that may have an influencing impact on the studied effect.</p><p>Proceedings of the International Conference on Industrial Engineering and Operations Management Istanbul, Turkey, March 7-10, 2022</p><p>The case study shows that the diagram can be used in supply chain issues, and it presents an exhaustive potential causes list. However, in further research, we need to test the diagram in other filed to prove its efficiency.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p>The TRIZ-Ishikawa diagram is an improved version to detect contributing factors to a specific effect. It presents guidelines for users in the brainstorming process and surmounts the classical Ishikawa diagram barriers. Substance inventory helps users to overcome psychological inertia and the time pillar integrates the evolution system concept in the diagram. Using TRIZ resources as cornerstones avoids the need to add more cornerstones.</p><p>In addition, we are aware that a unique case study does not allow diagram generalization. Therefore, it is necessary, in future research, to explore the diagram in a different field with different issues.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. TRIZ-ISHIKAWA Diagram</figDesc><graphic coords="5,72.75,72.75,453.60,314.30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. TRIZ-Ishikawa diagram applied to the accumulation of inventory</figDesc><graphic coords="6,73.50,73.50,453.58,318.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Resources description according to Sandra Mueller and the correlation with 5M.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Resources in Management TRIZ</cell><cell>Machinery</cell><cell>Manpower</cell><cell>Material</cell><cell>Measurement</cell><cell>method</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(technology)</cell><cell>(physical</cell><cell>(raw</cell><cell>/inspection /</cell><cell>(process)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>work)</cell><cell>material)</cell><cell>environment</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Substances</cell><cell>• Studied system elements. Machines, products and humans) • System's environment (Material,</cell><cell>X</cell><cell>X</cell><cell>X</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• Between system elements and/or</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Fields (Interactions)</cell><cell>within a system (e.g., communication; energy) • From a system's environment • Between systems (e.g., network) • Reserves (utilization of substance full potential.(e.g., enthusiasm) (e.g., competition, electricity, transition system)</cell><cell>X</cell><cell>X</cell><cell>X</cell><cell></cell><cell>X</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• defeat (e.g., anger, Power)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Functional</cell><cell>• Gaps in a function • Application of harmful factors • provided functions • Additional useful functions • Exploit casual</cell><cell>X</cell><cell>X</cell><cell>X</cell><cell>X</cell><cell>X</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• Emitted/transmitted information</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>from the system and its elements</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Informational</cell><cell>• Intrinsic properties of the system and its elements. explicit and implicit availability, transparency, shape) • Temporary information (e.g. date) knowledge (e.g., behavior or inherent information such as efficiency,</cell><cell>X</cell><cell>X</cell><cell>X</cell><cell></cell><cell>X</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• Information flow.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• information change</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Proceedings of the International Conference on IndustrialEngineering and Operations Management  Istanbul, Turkey, March 7-10, 2022   </p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>proceedings, and has been a Guest Editor for special issues of various international journals. His research interests include Industry 4.0, green manufacturing, Lean Six Sigma, integrated management systems and supply chain management.</p><p>El Mehdi TAMASNA, Ph.D. student Eng. Is an international innovation expert in the field of Shop floor measurement solutions, active since 2012 in various fields from Product Development to R&amp;D project management. He has been involved in several innovation projects internationally: defense, automotive, aerospace and he is now a project manager in the sector of measurement solutions for the wind-power branches.</p><p>Proceedings of the International Conference on Industrial <ref type="bibr">Engineering and Operations Management Istanbul, Turkey, March 7-10, 2022</ref> </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cornerstone root causes through the analysis of the Ishikawa diagram, is it possible to find them?: A first research approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Suárez-Barraza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Rodríguez-González</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Quality and Service Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="302" to="316" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quality and Efficiency improvement tools for Every Radiologist</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kudla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Brook</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academic Radiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="757" to="766" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of factors affecting the accident rate in the construction industry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hoła</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nowobilski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Szer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Szer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Procedia Engineering 2nd International Joint Conference on Innovative Solutions in Construction Engineering and Management</title>
		<meeting>edia Engineering 2nd International Joint Conference on Innovative Solutions in Construction Engineering and Management</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="42" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the identification of contradictions using Cause Effect Chain Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dobrusskin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Procedia CIRP TRIZ FUTURE</title>
		<meeting>edia CIRP TRIZ FUTURE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="224" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manufacturing technology evolution trends, Integrated Manufacturing Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="90" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Quality Function Deployment approach for Production Resilience improvement in Supply Chain: Case of Agrifood Industry, IFAC-papersonline</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Elleuch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Dafaoui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>El Mhamedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chabchou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="130" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vision to improve: qualityimprovement in ophthalmology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Micieli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Calafati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Low</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>El-Defrawy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hatch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Canadian Ophthalmological Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Problem Solving Management Using Six Sigma Tools &amp; Techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Koripadu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Subbaiah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International journal of scientific &amp; technology research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The TRIZ Resource Analysis Tool for Solving Management Tasks: Previous Classifications and their Modification, Blackwell, Creativity and innovation management</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Simanová</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gejdos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Use of Statistical Quality Control Tools to Quality Improving in the Furniture Business, Procedia Economics and Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="276" to="283" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ishikawa diagram, Quality improvement in behavior health</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Woo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Woo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="132" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">She worked in automotive, aeronautic, industrial and BTP companies were she could make radical changes and improve performances. She holds an undergraduate degree in electro-mechanics Engineering department of ENSAM School, and she is a Ph.D. student In ENSEM school in Industrial innovation and Durable development department</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Soumaya</forename><surname>El Youssoufi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ph</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Eng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>She is a strategy and operational improvement manager at HVAC Company. She has more than twelve years as Improvement manager and Technical manager. Her researches interests include Lean Six Sigma, operations, strategies and TRIZ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Holding a Ph.D. in genetic algorithms and eco-innovation, he has ten years teaching experience. Moreover, he has more than thirty years in national and international experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mohamed</forename><surname>Mazouzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ph</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Eng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">articles in international journals and conferences. His research interests include TRIZ in technical and non-technical fields</title>
		<imprint/>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>ENSEM Casablanca, Hassan II University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>He is the founder and the CEO of many automotive and industrial companies. In addition, he is the president of several associations. innovation, creative thinking and sustainable development</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Holding a Ph.D. in Industrial Engineering, he has nine years of industry and teaching experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anass</forename><surname>Cherrafi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>Morocco</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Industrial Engineering, ENSAM-Meknes, Moulay Ismail University UMI</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Ph.D. is an Assistant</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
