<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Factors Related to Choking under Pressure in Sports and the Relationships among Them*</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-02-24">February 24, 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Takayuki</forename><surname>Murayama</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Sport Education</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Health Service Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kanazawa University Kakuma-machi</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>920-1192</postCode>
									<settlement>Kanazawa</settlement>
									<region>Ishikawa</region>
									<country key="JP">JAPAN</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hiroshi</forename><surname>Sekiya</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Graduate School of Integrated Arts and Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hiroshima University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1-7-1 Kagamiyama</addrLine>
									<postCode>739-8521</postCode>
									<settlement>Higashihiroshima</settlement>
									<region>Hiroshima</region>
									<country key="JP">JAPAN</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Factors Related to Choking under Pressure in Sports and the Relationships among Them*</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-02-24">February 24, 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received October 29, 2014; Accepted February 10, 2015;</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T19:28+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>pressure</term>
					<term>performance</term>
					<term>attention</term>
					<term>safety-oriented strategy</term>
					<term>changes in motor control</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Factors related to choking under pressure during sports were investigated through a questionnaire survey and the relationship among the factors was examined. A questionnaire survey of choking was conducted among university students in sports-oriented school clubs (n＝535). Exploratory factor analysis extracted 11 factors: changes in motor control and vicious circles, abnormal physical sensations, perceptual and cognitive confusion, introversion, self-consciousness, feelings of physical heaviness and weakness, conscious processing (attention to movements), passivity, feelings of physical fatigue, safety-oriented strategies, and heat sensations. An analytical model with nine factors, (excluding feelings of physical fatigue and heat sensations) as latent variables was constructed, and covariance structure analysis was performed. The results indicated the validity of the mechanistic model of choking, consisting of nine latent variables. According to the model, when self-consciousness, or abnormal physical sensations, had a high proˆle, conscious processing increased. Furthermore, it was conˆrmed that conscious processing aŠected changes in motor control and vicious circles, which led directly to a decline in motor performance. It was also indicated that abnormal physical sensations determined perceptual and cognitive confusion, or feelings of physical heaviness and weakness. On the other hand, when perceptual and cognitive confusion and feelings of physical heaviness and weakness had a high proˆle, passivity increased. High passivity caused changes in motor control and vicious circles. Moreover, increased passivity led to the adoption of a safety-oriented strategy that often caused changes in motor control and vicious circles. While previous studies have tried to explain choking only from the perspective of changes in attention, the above results suggest the following mechanistic model of choking, indicative of another perspective: Changes in psychological, physiological, and behavioral variables cause a decline in performance. Especially interactions between emotions and cognitions and the adoption of a strategy with a low risk of failure determine changes in motor control.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>For many athletes, it is not easy to perform to the best of one's ability during competition. During competition, an athlete may not be able to perform as he/she normally could because of anxiety from spectators or the pressure to perform well. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Baumeister (1984)</ref> deˆnes ``pressure'' as a factor or combination of factors that increase the importance of performing well under certain situations. He refers to ``choking under pressure'' * 1 as the phe-nomenon in which an athlete's performance declines under pressure. Typical sources of pressure include spectators, evaluation, reward, and time constraints. These types of pressure are common for many competitions. Therefore, the ability to remain unnerved under pressure situations to perform to the best of one's ability can have a great impact on the outcome of a match. Recently, a considerable number of athletes consult specialists for sport mental training or psychological support to control ``choking under pressure.'' When dealing with ``choking under pressure'' during competition, pressure is not the only factor that must be dealt with. During ``choking under pressure'' situations, many factors other than pressure may be involved. ``Choking under pressure'' is likely to be a result of the interaction between these many factors. However, due to its complexity, the process in which pressure negatively aŠects performance is still mostly unknown. In order to more eŠectively prevent and treat ``choking under pressure,'' the factors that are involved must be identi-ˆed, and the process that leads to declined performance must be made clear.</p><p>``Choking under pressure'' has been a frequent topic of research in the ˆeld of sport psychology. Experimental studies have been conducted on the psychological, physiological, and behavioral changes that occur when an athlete is under pressure. Psychological aspects that have been studied include an increase in anxiety state <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Tanaka and Sekiya, 2006)</ref>, decrease in self-e‹cacy <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Williams et al., 2002)</ref>, changes in perception <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Pijpers et al., 2006)</ref> and changes in attention <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Beilock and Carr, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Lewis and Linder, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Mullen et al., 2005)</ref>. Physiological aspects include increase in heart-rate <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Landers et al., 1985)</ref> and increase in systolic bloodpressure <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Noteboom et al., 2001)</ref>. These ˆndings indicate physiological stimulation resulting from changes in the autonomic nervous system as well as the endocrine system. In regards to the endocrine system, there is a report that demonstrated increases in cortisol secretion <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Salvador et al., 2003)</ref>. Moreover, behavioral changes include decrease in movement displacement <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Beuter et al., 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Higuchi et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tanaka and</ref><ref type="bibr">Sekiya, 2010a, 2011)</ref>, increase in variability of movement displacement <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Tanaka and Sekiya, 2006)</ref>, decrease in variability of movement displacement <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Higuchi, 2000)</ref>, increase in variability of timing <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Gray, 2004)</ref> and increase in the length of time for movement execution <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Beuter and Duda, 1985)</ref>.</p><p>In some cases, studies have utilized questionnaire surveys to study ``choking under pressure.'' For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Ichimura (1965)</ref> conducted a questionnaire survey regarding experiences of ``choking under pressure.'' Factor analysis identiˆed the following factors: activation of the sympathetic nervous system, decrease in psychological tension, confusion of motor skills, and anxiety. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Arimitsu and Imada (1999)</ref> identiˆed a factor characterized by increased awareness of one's situation. This factor is composed of feelings of self-imperfection, sense of responsibility, and awareness of others. In addition, questionnaire surveys revealed that anxiety increases before a competitive match <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Cerin, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">de Moj àa and de Moj àa, 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Hanton et al., 2004)</ref>.</p><p>Recently, some studies have focused on the causes of ``choking under pressure'' and propose a hypothesis that ``choking under pressure'' results from a change in attention. Several similar hypotheses explain the phenomenon from a cognitive point of view. These hypotheses can be divided into two groups: The conscious processing hypothesis which attributes the decrease in performance to extra attention to one's own physical movements (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Hardy et al., 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Masters, 1992)</ref> and the processing e‹ciency hypothesis which attributes the decrease in performance to a lack of attention to one's own physical movements (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Eysenck and Calvo, 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Wine, 1971)</ref>. These two hypotheses explain ``choking under pressure'' with opposite cognitive changes.</p><p>Therefore, studies on ``choking under pressure'' have clariˆed many psychological, physiological and behavioral changes and symptoms as well as changes in attention that occur under pressure. However, there are still many issues that remain unresolved regarding the process that leads to ``choking under pressure.'' One issue is the reproducibility of ``choking under pressure.'' Most of the previous studies that attributed ``choking under pressure'' to changes in attention had aimed to test whether the conscious processing hypothesis or the processing e‹ciency hypothesis was correct. These studies experimentally created situations of relatively low levels of pressure in the laboratory. However, ``choking under pressure'' during competition generally involves high levels of pressure and various factors which form complex interactions. Therefore, it is di‹cult to reproduce the phenomenon of ``choking under pressure'' in the laboratory. The di‹culty in reproducing high levels of pressure in the laboratory has been reported (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Williams et al., 2002)</ref>. To address this issue, the conscious processing hypothesis and processing e‹ciency hypothesis need to be tested in real ``choking under pressure'' situations.</p><p>The second issue is to determine the relations between factors that are involved in ``choking under pressure.'' In addition to changes in attention, vari-ous psychological, physiological and behavioral changes occur when people ``choke'' under pressure. The changes that occur in each aspect may be directly induced by pressure, or could be indirectly induced via changes in a diŠerent aspect. Therefore it is unlikely that changes in attention singly control the decrease in performance. In order to fully understand the process of ``choking under pressure,'' we must study the relations between the factors that are involved.</p><p>A valid method to address these two issues is to create questionnaire surveys for actual ``choking under pressure'' situations. An advantage of experimental studies is that measurements can be made objectively, and changes can be measured that the participants are not directly aware of. However, it is di‹cult to address the issue of the reproducibility of ``choking under pressure.'' On the other hand, questionnaire surveys can identify participants who have experienced ``choking under pressure'' and can determine if changes in attention accompany the experience. In contrast to experimental studies, questionnaire surveys utilize subjective data and cannot measure changes that the participant is not aware of. However, whether the participant directed his/her attention toward his/her own physical movements or something aside from his/her own physical movements is a change that is perceived by the participant. It is reasonable to expect participants to be able to recall such changes in attention using a questionnaire. By incorporating question items regarding changes in attention, we aim to examine the validity of the two hypotheses that explain ``choking under pressure.''</p><p>The previously mentioned questionnaire surveys regarding ``choking under pressure'' did not investigate the changes in attention that occur when people ``choke'' under pressure. In addition, there are few studies that have focused on the relations between the factors involved in ``choking under pressure.'' A study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Tanaka and Sekiya (2011)</ref> that employs a golf-putting task demonstrated that increased attention towards a movement causes increases in the variability of the time and speed of the movement. The study also indicates that increased heart rate and negative emotions cause increased acceleration of the movement and decreased grip strength. These ˆndings show that psychological and physiological aspects in‰uence the behavioral aspect. Recent experimental studies have shown that kinematic and kinetic changes that occur under pressure situations directly cause decreases in performance (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Tanaka and Sekiya, 2006)</ref>. However, the issue of reproducibility can be raised for experimental studies. <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Murayama et al. (2009)</ref> utilized the grounded theory approach, a qualitative method to determine the process of ``choking under pressure.'' This inductive reasoning approach was employed to examine the relations between the psychological, physiological and behavioral aspects. The study analyzed interview responses from 13 participants who experienced ``choking under pressure.'' Results indicated that changes in perception and motor control, risk-aversive strategy, and physical fatigue are factors besides changes in attention that are directly correlated to a decline in performance. This study also identiˆed a factor related to changes in motor control as one of the factors involved in declined performance. In addition, psychological changes such as irrational thoughts, negative emotions, and strategy changes as well as physiological changes such as activation of the sympathetic nervous system in‰uence the process of declined performance. It may seem as though this study addresses both of the aforementioned issues, but changes in perception, risk-aversive strategy and physical fatigue are factors that were identiˆed from a small number of respondents. It is necessary to examine whether these factors arise for most athletes who experience ``choking under pressure.'' Furthermore, there are reports that claim personality traits play a role in ``choking under pressure.'' The personality traits that have been reported to be correlated with ``choking under pressure'' are neuroticism <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Fumoto et al., 1992)</ref>, sense of self-consciousness <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Baumeister, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Wang et al., 2004)</ref>, trait anxiety <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Hashimoto and Tokunaga, 2000)</ref>. Self-consciousness is a trait that is highly related to introversion <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Kimura et al., 2008)</ref> and has been demonstrated to be correlated with conscious processing (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Baumeister, 1984)</ref>. These personality traits are implicated with changes in the three aspects that aŠect ``choking under pressure,'' but the possible relations with the factors within the three aspects is unknown.</p><p>Although several studies have focused on the relations between the factors that are involved in ``choking under pressure,'' the two aforementioned issues remain along with methodological constraints such as sample size. In order to obtain a comprehensive understanding of the phenomenon, actual ``choking under pressure'' situations must be studied with a large sample size and causes of ``choking under pressure'' such as perception, strategy, fatigue and personality traits must be investigated in addition to changes in attention. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Murayama et al. (2010)</ref> conducted one of the few studies to determine the factors involved in ``choking under pressure.'' A questionnaire survey was conducted for many athletes regarding attention, perception, strategy, fatigue, and personality traits. Factor analysis of the survey results revealed the following seven factors: negative thoughts/feelings, motor control changes, increased physiological arousal, communication failure, nervous personality, pre-competition condition, and abnormal somatic sensation. However, this study did not investigate the relations between the factors which remain an unresolved issue for elucidating the process of ``choking under pressure.''</p><p>Covariance structure analysis has recently gained attention as a method to investigate the relations between factors. Covariance structure analysis enables the statistical validity testing of relations between latent variables implicated by previous studies. Although, the relations between all latent variables cannot be tested, but the covariance structure analysis provides a method to test theorized models based on hypotheses. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Shimamoto and Ishii (2009)</ref> conducted a questionnaire survey to determine the eŠects of sports experiences during physical education classes on the acquisition of life skills. The results of the covariance structure analysis demonstrated that selfdisclosure and goal-achievement are factors that aŠect the acquisition of life skills. Covariance structure analysis is an eŠective tool for testing the relations between factors involved in a speciˆc phenomenon. For the ``choking under pressure'' phenomenon, the factors involved in decreased motor performance and the relations between factors can be hypothesized as a model. Testing this model using covariance structure analysis may clarify the process of performance decline. For this phenomenon, we can predict that psychological and physiological aspects in‰uence the behavioral aspect. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Yamadori (2008)</ref>, aŠective physical states precede emotions, thus pointing towards a high likelihood of the physiological aspect aŠecting the psychological aspect. Besides, according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Murayama et al. (2009)</ref>, changes in motor control are in‰uenced by psychological factors such as irrational thoughts, negative feelings and risk-aversive strategies, and fa-tigue as well as physiological factors such as activation of the sympathetic nervous system. Particularly, the eŠects of changes in strategy and fatigue on motor control and decreases in motor performance must be tested using covariance structure analysis. Moreover, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Baumeister (1984)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Wang et al. (2004)</ref> have indicated that athletes with a high sense of self-consciousness have a stronger sense of internally-directed attention. The eŠects of personality traits on changes in attention must be tested.</p><p>Taking these aspects into account, the process of ``choking under pressure'' may be clariˆed by testing the eŠects of the psychological and physiological aspects on behavioral changes using covariance structure analysis. The purpose of this study is to determine the factors and relations between the factors involved in ``choking under pressure'' by using covariance structure analysis. Athletes who have experienced ``choking under pressure'' situations are the respondents of this study. This study aims to conduct a questionnaire study that not only focus on changes in attention but also perception, strategy, fatigue, and personality traits which have been implicated by previous experimental studies, questionnaire surveys and qualitative studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Respondents</head><p>A questionnaire survey was conducted for 786 university students involved in athletic teams or athletic clubs to investigate ``choking under pressure'' during athletic competition. Incomplete, misconstrued or biased responses were omitted for a total of 696 valid responses (511 male; 185 female). The valid response rate was 88.5 z. The present study required respondents to be able to respond regarding a ``choking under pressure'' situation. Therefore, only respondents who had experienced a ``choking under pressure'' situation were subjected to analysis. Results of the survey indicated 161 out of the 696 valid respondents had not experienced a ``choking under pressure'' situation within the past year. This study subjected data from 535 respondents (393 male; 142 female) for further analysis. The average age of respondents was 20.2±1.3 years.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Data collection 1) Survey period</head><p>Data collection was conducted for one year and seven months between October, 2009 and May, 2011.</p><p>2) Questionnaire items and procedure</p><p>The questionnaire was distributed to members of athletic teams and athletic clubs. The questionnaire asked respondents to provide basic personal information and respond to 17 question items regarding personal characteristics during their daily lives. These question items intended to measure personality and thus were abbreviated P1-P17. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Arimitsu (1999)</ref>, public self-consciousness, emotional instability and shyness are raised as personality traits that are deeply correlated with ``choking under pressure.'' This study created 17 question items based on previous questionnaires to measure public self-consciousness <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Sugawara, 1984)</ref>, emotional instability <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Wada, 1996)</ref> and shyness <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Aikawa, 1991)</ref>. For the purposes of this study, we deˆne ``choking under pressure'' as ``performance decrements under circumstances that increase the importance of good or improved performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Baumeister, 1984)</ref>.'' This deˆnition was used to determine if respondents experienced ``choking under pressure.'' The questionnaire asked respondents to specify the sport in which the experience occurred and the respondents' athletic experience and performance history. The respondents who had experienced a ``choking under pressure'' situation during a university athletic event were asked to describe the situation and respond to 105 question items. Respondents who had not experienced a ``choking under pressure'' situation were omitted from analysis.</p><p>The question items were created to investigate all factors that had been implicated in ``choking under pressure'' from previous questionnaire and experimental studies. The question items were based on questionnaire surveys conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Ichimura (1965)</ref> regarding activation of the sympathetic nervous system, decrease in psychological tension, confusion of motor skills, and anxiety as well as <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Arimitsu and Imada (1999)</ref> regarding feelings of self-imperfection, physical imperfection, shaking, sense of responsibility, physiological response and awareness of others. In addition, question items were created to include <ref type="bibr">Murayama et al.'s (2009)</ref> qualitative study which reported that risk-aversive strategy, physical fatigue, pre-competition conditioning status, vicious circle of ``choking under pressure'' and decrease in motor performance are factors that may be involved. Question items regarding changes in attention were added to address experimental ˆndings regarding ``choking under pressure.'' Taking these factors into account, a questionnaire of 122 question items was created. Excluding the basic personal information questions and questions regarding athletic history, all questions were created with ˆve Likert-type choices: 1. Does not apply, 2. Somewhat does not apply, 3. Neither applies nor does not apply, 4. Somewhat applies, 5. Very much applies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Data analysis</head><p>Exploratory factor analysis (Maximum likelihood method, Promax rotation) was conducted on the results from the 122 questions (P1-P17, Q1-Q105) regarding ``choking under pressure'' to determine common factors of the results. An analysis model was created based on correlations between factors and previous studies on ``choking under pressure.'' The analysis model was tested using covariance structure analysis whether it could explain the ``choking under pressure'' phenomenon. The goodness of ˆt of the data were measured using GFI (Goodness of Fit Index), CFI (Comparative Fit Index), AGFI (Adjusted Goodness of Fit Index), and RMSEA (Root Mean Square Error of Approximation) based on indices cited by <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Oshio (2004)</ref>. The level of statistical signiˆcance was set as 5 z. For exploratory factor analysis, SPSS Statistics Ver. 19 (IBM) was used and for covariance structure analysis, Amos 16.0 (SPSS) was used for statistical analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Identiˆcation of factors related to ``choking under pressure''</head><p>Results from exploratory factor analysis identiˆed 11 factors: F1 ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles,'' F2 ``Abnormal physical sensations,'' F3 ``Perceptual and cognitive confusion,'' F4 ``Introversion,'' F5 ``Self-consciousness,'' F6 ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness,'' F7 ``Conscious processing (attention to movements),''  <ref type="bibr">.27 .31 .31 F5 .46 .21 .37 .43 F6 .52 .48 .37 .28 .23 F7 .48 .29 .25 .09 .28 .32 F8 .53 .20 .20 .14 .22 .51 .36 F9 .30 .32 .22 .12 .11 .30 .33 .27 F10 .46 .21 .27 .16 .17 .28 .20 .35 .17 F11 .19 .34 .29 .12 .17 .27 .31 .09 .29 .22</ref> Rounded oŠ to two decimal places 6 Takayuki Murayama and Hiroshi Sekiya F8 ``Passivity,'' F9 ``Feelings of physical fatigue,'' F10 ``Safety-oriented strategies,'' and F11 ``Heat sensation.'' The names of the factors were based on questionnaire studies conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Ichimura (1965)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Arimitsu and Imada (1999)</ref> as well as the qualitative study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Murayama et al. (2009)</ref>. The number of factors was based on eigenvalues and cumulative contribution ratios, as a result, 11 factors and 77 question items were extracted. The cumulative contribution ratio for the 11 factors was 46.8z. The Cronback's acoe‹cients for each factor are as follows: F1＝.93, F2＝.87, F3＝.81, F4＝.81, F5＝.76, F6＝.84, F7＝.74, F8＝.83, F9＝.83, F10 ＝.77, F11＝.78. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> displays the correlation matrix for the 11 factors.</p><p>The 22 question items for F1 related to changes in motor control and promoted ``choking under pressure'' including movement confusion, abnormal plays or increased mistakes, and rushing. The factor was named ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles.'' The 12 question items for F2 related to abnormal physical sensations involved with ``choking under pressure'' such as ‰oating sensations or shaking, and abnormal breathing patterns. The factor was named ``Abnormal physical sensations.'' The 10 question items for F3 related to resignation to perform well or apprehension for performing poorly, and negative perceptions or awareness towards environment. The factor was named ``Perceptual and cognitive confusion.'' The six question items for F4 related to passive and evasive thoughts as well as irrational thoughts. The items indicated the introverted personality traits of respondents. The factor was named ``Introversion.'' The ˆve question items for F5 related to awareness of evaluation by others, worrying and tension. The items indicated the level of self-consciousness of respondents. The factor was named ``Self-consciousness.'' The four question items for F6 related to feelings of heaviness of hands and feet as well as incomplete control over strength. The factor was named ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness.'' The four question items for F7 related to increased attention towards one's own movements and form during ``choking under pressure'' situations as well as increased mental eŠort to control one's own movements. The factor was named ``Conscious processing.'' The ˆve question items for F8 related to increased hesitation or halfhearted plays and passive movements. The factor was named ``Passivity.'' The three question items for F9 related to physical fatigue. The factor was named ``Feelings of physical fatigue.'' The four question items for F10 related to risk-aversive movements or plays and changes to safe strategies. The factor was named ``Safety-oriented strategies.'' The two question items for F11 related to a heat sensation that takes over the body. The factor was named ``Heat sensation.''</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Correlations between latent variables</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1) Hypothesized analysis model</head><p>The identiˆed factors from exploratory factor analysis were set as latent variables to create an analysis model to hypothesize the relations between the latent variables. When creating the analysis model, the relations between factors that demonstrated correlation coe‹cients greater than .40 were focused on. The cause and eŠect relations were predicted from ˆndings of previous studies on ``choking under pressure.'' The correlation coe‹cients for ``Feelings of physical fatigue'' and ``Heat sensation'' with ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles'' were .30 and .19, respectively. These values were relatively low, and the two factors only weakly correlated with other factors. These two factors were therefore omitted from further analysis. The remaining nine factors were used as latent variables to create an analysis model assuming correlations between the variables (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</p><p>``Introversion'' and ``Self-consciousness'' are factors related to the respondents' personality traits. Introversion and public self-consciousness are reported to be closely related personality traits <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Kimura et al., 2008)</ref>. ``Self-consciousness'' can The Mechanism of Choking under Pressure possibly lead to internally-directed attention to one's movement or form and we predicted that ``Self-consciousness'' is aŠected by ``Introversion.'' <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Baumeister (1984)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Wang et al. (2004)</ref> have demonstrated that athletes with a greater sense of self-consciousness tend to exert more internally-directed attention. Taking these ˆndings into account, we predicted ``Introversion'' and ``Self-consciousness'' to aŠect ``Conscious processing.'' We further hypothesized ``Conscious processing'' to aŠect ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles'' and ``Passivity.'' As previously mentioned, aŠective physical states precede emotions (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Yamadori, 2008)</ref>. Therefore we predicted ``Abnormal physical sensations'' to aŠect ``Conscious processing,'' ``Perceptual and cognitive confusion'' and ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness.'' We assumed that ``Perceptual and cognitive confusion'' arises from the abnormal ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness.'' Furthermore, changes in motor control that involves ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness'' may bring about ``Safetyoriented strategies.'' ``Safety-oriented strategies'' may be promoted by ``Passivity.'' Thus, we predict that ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness'' aŠect ``Passivity,'' and ``Passivity'' and ``Safetyoriented strategies'' lead to ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles.'' 2) Evaluation and reconstruction of analysis model</p><p>This study utilized the rating methods mentioned by <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Oshio (2004)</ref>. The standard to adopt the model was set at .90 for the CFI, GFI and AGFI. The covariance structure analysis of the analysis model provided goodness of ˆt values as follows: RMSEA ＝.05, GFI＝.74, AGFI＝.72, CFI＝.77. The observable variable was 77 for this study. <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Toyoda (2002)</ref> suggests the use of RMSEA to measure the degree of dissociation for each degree of freedom for situations in which the observable variable is greater than 30. We therefore mainly used the RMSEA to measure the goodness of ˆt of our model with the data. Using <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Browne and Cudeck's (1993)</ref> study as a reference, we set the standard value for the acceptance of the model at below .08. Our model did not achieve the minimum standard for model acceptance above .90 for the GFI, AGFI, or CFI indices, but it passed the minimum standard of below .08 for the RMSEA index. The following path coe‹cients between latent variables did not demonstrate a signiˆcant relation: ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness'' to ``Perceptual and cognitive confusion'' (path coe‹cient＝.07), ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness'' to ``Conscious processing'' (path coe‹cient＝.17), ``Introversion'' to ``Conscious processing'' (path coe‹cient＝ -.11), ``Self-consciousness'' to ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles'' (path coe‹cient＝.11), ``Abnormal physical sensations'' to ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles'' (path coe‹cient ＝.16), and ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness'' to ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles'' (path coe‹cient＝-.07). For covariance structure analysis, the deletion of statistically insigniˆcant paths or the addition of new paths can improve the goodness of ˆt of the model. We deleted the following paths and subjected the model for covariance structure analysis: ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness'' to ``Perceptual and cognitive confusion,'' ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness'' to ``Conscious processing,'' ``Introversion'' to ``Conscious processing,'' ``Selfconsciousness'' to ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles,'' ``Abnormal physical sensations'' to ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles,'' and ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness'' to ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles.'' Results indicated that all path coe‹cients between latent variables were statistically signiˆcant (p ＜.001). The goodness of ˆt values were as follows: RMSEA＝.05, GFI＝.74, AGFI＝.72, and CFI ＝.77. Conˆrmatory factor analysis indicated that the in‰uence index for ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles'' on Q90 and Q85 were .29, relatively low values. These two question items were omitted and covariance structure analysis was conducted. The goodness of ˆt values were as follows: RMSEA＝.05, GFI＝.75, AGFI＝.73, and CFI ＝.79. Our model did not achieve the minimum standard for model acceptance above .90 for the GFI, AGFI, or CFI indices, but it passed the minimum standard of below .08 for the RMSEA index. For the purposes of this study, we judged the analysis model as valid due to its goodness of ˆt value falling within the acceptance range for the RMSEA index. Conˆrmatory factor analysis indicated that each latent variable had a signiˆcant eŠect on the observable variable with in‰uence index scores above .40 (p ＜.001). Taking these results into account, the statistical analyses suggest that the relations between the latent variables and the observable variables are appropriate. We present the model which describes the process of ``choking under pressure'' in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>. We have noted the path coe‹cients for each path between latent variables. We have also indicated speciˆc eŠects from a latent variable to another latent variable by presenting the multiple coe‹cient of determination on the upper right of the latent variable. In Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>, we list the 11 factors identiˆed by exploratory factor analysis along with factor loading, communality and in‰uence index values for nine latent variables on observable variables from covariance structure analysis. The question items omitted during the process of covariance structure analysis are indicated with a ``-.'' The observable variables are only listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> to simplify Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> to show only latent variables.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p>The purpose of this study is to identify the factors .71 1.00 -Factor loading, communality and in‰uence index were rounded oŠ to two decimal places related to ``choking under pressure'' during sports and to determine the relations between the involved factors. The participants of this study were university athletes. Exploratory factor analysis identiˆed the following 11 factors: ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles,'' ``Abnormal physical sensations,'' ``Perceptual and cognitive confusion,'' ``Introversion,'' ``Self-consciousness,'' ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness,'' ``Conscious processing (attention to movements),'' ``Passivity,'' ``Feelings of physical fatigue,'' ``Safety-oriented strategies,'' and ``Heat sensation.'' The nine factors excluding ``Feelings of physical fatigue'' and ``Heat sensation'' were set as latent variables to create an analysis model. The validity of this analysis model to describe the process of ``choking under pressure'' was conˆrmed from statistical analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Personality traits and attention in the context of pressure</head><p>Our questionnaire survey incorporated questions regarding changes in attention. Survey results demonstrated that a change in attention described as ``Conscious processing'' occurs during ``choking under pressure'' situations. In addition, a relation between ``Conscious processing'' and personality traits was revealed. Our model demonstrates that ``Introversion'' aŠects ``Self-consciousness'' and high levels of ``Self-consciousness'' promote ``Conscious processing'' which leads to changes in motor control and the vicious circle of ``choking under pressure.' <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">' Baumeister (1984)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Wang et al. (2004)</ref> have reported that athletes with higher senses of selfconsciousness have increased levels of conscious processing. However, we have shown for the ˆrst time that ``Introversion'' aŠects ``Self-consciousness.' <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">' Fenigstein et al. (1975)</ref> divides self-consciousness into three factors. The ˆrst factor is private selfconsciousness which directs one's attention towards the inner unshared part of the self. The second factor is public self-consciousness which directs attention towards how others view the self. The third factor is social anxiety which include anxiety, shyness and embarrassment. ``Self-consciousness'' in the context of this study deals with tendencies to become more aware of others' evaluations or rumors concerning oneself as well as increased anxiety from personality traits such as neuroticism or being worrisome. Therefore, ``self-consciousness'' in this study indicates public self-consciousness and social anxiety. Public self-consciousness and social anxiety are closely correlated personality traits <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Sugawara, 1984)</ref> and bring about ``choking under pressure'' or make a person prone to ``choking under pressure'' <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Arimitsu, 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Tsutsumi, 2006)</ref>.</p><p>The levels of public self-consciousness and social anxiety also aŠect attention and awareness. It has been reported that those with higher levels of public self-consciousness are more sensitive towards others' critical attitudes <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Fenigstein, 1979)</ref>. We can predict that the ``self-consciousness'' we refer to in this study is a personality trait that promotes attention and awareness towards others. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Tsutsumi (2006)</ref>, ``choking under pressure'' occurs when one's consciousness becomes directed towards others and one's control over the self becomes lost. <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Tsutsumi (2006)</ref> further argues that directing one's consciousness back to the self and creating one's own world can reduce ``choking under pressure.'' ``Self-consciousness'' is a personality trait that is closely related to ``choking under pressure,'' particularly the public self-consciousness which directs awareness towards the external environment is the factor that most closely correlates with ``choking under pressure.'' In our study, ``Introversion'' is a factor that regulates ``Self-consciousness.'' Athletes with higher levels of ``Introversion'' have been reported to be more sensitive towards external stimuli and more prone to be excessively motivated during competition <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Sugihara, 1987)</ref>. Taking these ˆndings into account, we predict that under pressure situations, athletes with high levels of ``Introversion'' tend to become excessively motivated and develop a heightened sense of ``self-consciousness'' leading to increased attention and awareness towards external stimuli.</p><p>In our study, we identiˆed ``Self-consciousness,'' a factor known to promote attention towards external stimuli as a factor that controls ``Conscious processing,'' a factor that represents excessive internally directed attention towards movements. These results may seem contradictory at ˆrst glance regarding the relation between self-consciousness and changes in attention. However, <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Sugawara (1984)</ref> demonstrated that public self-consciousness and exhibitionism are correlated and that someone with a high level of exhibitionism tends to either take selfpresentation behaviors or defensive, evasive behaviors. Self-presentation behaviors give rise to a strong sense of awareness of how one is perceived by others and thus may increase a sense of internally directed attention. ``Self-consciousness'' in this study is a characteristic that promotes awareness and attention directed at others, but increased levels of selfpresentation may lead to ``Conscious processing,'' an internally directed form of attention and thus alter motor control leading to decreased performance.</p><p>The eŠect of public self-consciousness on conscious processing is a new ˆnding that has not been previously reported. Change in attention has been studied by many experimental studies and demonstrated to negatively aŠect performance. However, it remained unknown whether this phenomenon occurred during ``choking under pressure'' situations. Questionnaire surveys on ``choking under pressure'' (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Ichimura, 1965)</ref> have studied the symptoms of ``choking under pressure'' but had not addressed whether changes in attention or if personality traits played a role. Therefore, the sig-niˆcance of this study is that changes in attention occur during actual ``choking under pressure'' situations and changes in attention is correlated with personality traits.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Interaction between emotion and cognition</head><p>Our model demonstrated that ``Abnormal physical sensations'' is a factor that controls ``Conscious processing.'' ``Abnormal physical sensations'' refers to ‰oating sensations or shaking, and abnormal breathing patterns. The factor also controls ``Perceptual and cognitive confusion'' and ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness.'' The path coe‹cient for ``Abnormal physical sensations'' to ``Perceptual and cognitive confusion'' is .59 and ``Abnormal physical sensations'' to ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness'' is .77, both relatively high values. ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness'' is a factor that refers to feelings of heaviness of hands and feet as well as incomplete control over strength. During ``choking under pressure'' situations, many changes occur including altered attention leading to conscious processing of movement, despair, resignation, negative perceptions and awareness of environment, and feelings of heaviness or loss of strength of hands and feet. These changes are more likely to occur when ``Abnormal physical sensations'' are at a high level.</p><p>``Abnormal physical sensations'' is an abnormal sensation based on an aŠective physical state re‰ecting the in‰uences of the physiological aspect. According to the catastrophe model which explains ``choking under pressure'' as an interaction between physiological activation and cognitive anxiety <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Hardy, 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Hardy and Parˆtt, 1991)</ref>, high levels of physiological activation and increased cognitive anxiety lead to decreased performance. Although it has been demonstrated that aŠective physical states precede emotions <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Yamadori, 2008)</ref>, the relations between ``Abnormal physical sensations,'' an aŠective physical state, and ``Conscious processing'' or ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness'' have not been reported. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Calvo and Miguel-Tobal (1998)</ref> point out that clear changes in heart rate or galvanic skin responses promote perceptions of internal feelings and thus make it more likely for respondents to report feelings of anxiety. However they did not mention whether those changes relate to conscious processing.</p><p>Our study demonstrates that higher levels of ``Abnormal physical sensations'' promote ``Conscious processing,'' ``Perceptual and cognitive confusion,'' and ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness.'' These results indicate that the interactions between emotions and cognitions underpin ``choking under pressure.'' By the way, in this study, we did not identify reduction in processing e‹ciency as a factor. It is possible that ``Abnormal physical sensations'' played a role in this result. Cognitive changes such as processing e‹ciency and conscious processing have been tested experimentally in the context of ``choking under pressure.'' However, the ``choking under pressure'' situations created in the lab are likely not as strong as the situations that involve abnormal physical sensations such as ‰oating sensations or shaking. It is likely that ``choking under pressure'' situations in the lab are clearly diŠerent from actual situations in terms of the physical aŠective response. Strong aŠective physical responses may cause an athlete to focus on one's own physical state or movement instead of external spectators or results. However, there are very few studies that have speciˆcally studied changes in attention for high levels of pressure. It remains unclear whether actual ``choking under pressure'' situations entail decreased processing e‹ciency. Future studies will need to be conducted to test the changes in attention that occur for high levels of pressure.</p><p>It is di‹cult to explain ``choking under pressure'' from only a cognitive perspective. The results from this study incorporate factors other than changes in attention to explain ``choking under pressure'' and present the importance of clarifying the relations between the involved factors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Factors that aŠect motor control</head><p>This study identiˆed that ``Abnormal physical sensations'' promote ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness,'' and promoted ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness'' aŠect ``Passivity.'' ``Passivity'' refers to decreased decision-making skills, increased hesitation, and passive movements. It also describes stiŠ, clumsy movements. We assumed ``Passivity'' and ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness'' are closely correlated with abnormal motor control during ``choking under pressure'' situations. ``Passivity'' was determined to be a factor that controls ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles,'' the factor directly leading to decreased performance. Recent experimental studies have shown that kinematic and kinetic changes that occur under pressure situations directly cause decreases in performance (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Tanaka and Sekiya, 2006)</ref>. It has been reported that increased heart rate may lead to behavioral changes <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Tanaka and Sekiya, 2010b)</ref>. The results of this study support the notion that performance is in‰uenced by aŠective physical states but also demonstrate that there are perceptive and cognitive changes as well physical sensational changes such as heaviness of the hands and feet that are promoted by aŠective physical states. Furthermore, these changes give rise to passive behaviors and negatively aŠect performance by altering motor control.</p><p>We demonstrate that a greater level of ``Passivity'' makes it more likely for an athlete to employ a ``Safety-oriented strategies'' which in turn conducts ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles.'' ``Safety-oriented strategies'' refers to passive and safe methods (tactics/strategies) which minimize the risk of failure. These unusual strategies may lead to changes in motor control. The path coe‹cient from ``Passivity'' to ``Safety-oriented strategies'' is .71, a relatively high value. The changes in motor control that arise during ``choking under pressure'' situations are controlled by changes in strategy which stress risk-aversion as well as ``Passivity'' which refers to increased hesitation and half-hearted plays. Previous studies concerning ``choking under pressure'' have indicated that kinematic changes that occur under pressure are brought about by changes in strategy <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Gage et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Higuchi et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tanaka and</ref><ref type="bibr">Sekiya, 2006, 2010a</ref>). There has not been any study that has utilized questionnaire surveys to examine whether changes in strategy occur during actual ``choking under pressure'' situations.</p><p>In the present study, our results indicate that changes in the behavioral aspect make it more likely that an athlete employs a safety-oriented strategies. In order to fully grasp the phenomenon of ``choking under pressure,'' we must incorporate strategy into the current prevailing hypotheses which only account for changes in attention. One limitation in our study is that the athletes in our study participate in a variety of sports. It will be a topic for future study to determine if the employment of safety-oriented strategies during ``choking under pressure'' situations occurs for all sports. Studying the speciˆcs of safety-oriented strategies may lead to new methods to prevent changes in motor control.</p><p>In this study, we examined the relations between the factors involved in ``choking under pressure'' and present a model to describe the process of ``choking under pressure.'' Nine factors were identi-ˆed to be involved in ``choking under pressure,'' making it di‹cult to explain the process using one factor. The model may serve to suggest more eŠective methods to prevent the changes in attention or physical state that occur under pressure situations.</p><p>Assuming that ``Passivity'' and ``Safety-oriented strategies'' are factors that control performance, it is still di‹cult to test how these factors cause kinematic and kinetic changes. Questionnaire surveys in general base their analysis on subjective data, but it is possible that in actual ``choking under pressure'' situations, kinematic and kinetic changes occur as a result of unconscious events. In order to study the minute kinematic and kinetic changes that occur in the behavioral aspect, experimental studies are more applicable. Objective measurements of these changes under pressure situations can lead to elucidating behavioral changes that directly cause decreased performance or identifying psychological and physiological factors that in‰uence the behavioral changes. It is also impossible to identify all of the relations between latent variables using covari-ance structure analysis. As mentioned by <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Murayama et al. (2009)</ref>, it is likely that relations between factors are not unidirectional. During actual ``choking under pressure'' situations, a bidirectional interaction may occur. In the present study, we were able to create a valid analysis model based on ˆndings from previous studies, but it remains necessary to test the bidirectional interactions that may occur between factors. The questionnaire survey in the present study provided cross-sectional data, making it impossible to accurately predict the temporal orders between factors. In the future, we must study the cause and eŠect relations between the factors identi-ˆed in this study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p>The purpose of this study is to identify the factors related to ``choking under pressure'' during sports and to determine the relations between the involved factors. The participants of this study were university athletes. Exploratory factor analysis identiˆed the following 11 factors: ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles,'' ``Abnormal physical sensations,'' ``Perceptual and cognitive confusion,'' ``Introversion,'' ``Self-consciousness,'' ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness,'' ``Conscious processing,'' ``Passivity,'' ``Feelings of physical fatigue,'' ``Safety-oriented strategies,'' and ``Heat sensation.'' The nine factors excluding ``Feelings of physical fatigue'' and ``Heat sensation'' were set as latent variables to create an analysis model. The validity of this analysis model to describe the process of ``choking under pressure'' was conˆrmed from statistical analysis. According to our model that describes the process of ``choking under pressure,'' ``Self-consciousness'' and ``Abnormal physical sensations'' promote ``Conscious processing'' which in turn in‰uences ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles,'' a factor directly correlated with decreased performance. ``Abnormal physical sensations'' control ``Perceptual and cognitive confusion'' as well as ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness.'' Athletes with higher levels of ``Perceptual and cognitive confusion'' and ``Feelings of physical heaviness and weakness'' tend to have a greater sense of ``Passivity'' making an athlete more likely to employ a ``Safety-oriented strategies.'' The ``Safety-oriented strategies'' promotes ``Changes in motor control and vicious circles.'' In summary, the present study demonstrates that there are changes in the psychological, physiological and behavioral aspects that lead to decreased performance. It is di‹cult to explain the phenomenon of ``choking under pressure'' from only changes in attention. We present a model to describe the process of ``choking under pressure'' in which interactions between emotions and awareness as well as the employment of safety-oriented strategies control changes in motor control.</p><p>Note *1: ``Choking under pressure'' can be deˆned as ``A state of excessive mental and physical tension experienced during especially important matches or decisive moments <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Honma, 2008)</ref>'' or ``Experiences of awareness towards others, feelings of responsibility, self-imperfection, physical imperfection, physiological responses or shaking during situations which could entail negative evaluations of oneself such as elections or social evaluations. Generally, changes in awareness towards others or in sense of responsibility during certain situations <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Arimitsu, 2005)</ref>.'' ``Choking under pressure'' is sometimes referred to as ``stage fright <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Honma, 2008)</ref>.'' It has been pointed out that there is no ˆxed deˆnition or terminology when used in the context of psychology research <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Arimitsu, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Ichimura, 1965)</ref>. However, ``choking under pressure'' is frequently utilized in performance decrements for sports or motor skills (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Beilock and Carr, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Gucciardi et al., 2010)</ref>. Recent studies frequently use ``choking under pressure <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Murayama et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Tanaka and Sekiya, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Yoshie et al., 2011)</ref>.'' ``Especially important matches or decisive moments'' and ``elections or social evaluations which could entail negative evaluations of oneself'' can be construed to refer to ``pressure'' deˆned by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Baumeister (1984)</ref> as a factor that increases the importance of performing well. Taking these factors into account and following recent trends, we utilized ``choking under pressure.''</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1 Model for analyzing ``choking under pressure'' assuming a relationship between latent variables</figDesc><graphic coords="7,86.24,73.01,423.00,219.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2 Mechanism model of ``choking under pressure'' in sports adopted in this study</figDesc><graphic coords="8,95.88,73.10,402.99,241.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Factor correlation matrix for 11 factors.</figDesc><table><row><cell>F1 F2 F3 F4 F5 F6 F7 F8 F9 F10 F11</cell></row><row><cell>F1</cell></row><row><cell>F2 .48</cell></row><row><cell>F3 .52 .52</cell></row><row><cell>F4</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Factor loading and communality of 11 factors based on exploratory factor analysis; 9 latent variables, observable variables and in‰uence index based on covariance structure analysis</figDesc><table><row><cell>Question item content (latent variables and observable variables)</cell><cell>Factor loading</cell><cell>Communality</cell><cell>In‰uence index</cell></row><row><cell>F1: Changes in motor control and vicious circles</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Q104 I made more movements or plays that did not lead to positive results</cell><cell>.83</cell><cell>.65</cell><cell>.70</cell></row><row><cell>Q90 I was disappointed in myself</cell><cell>.79</cell><cell>.64</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Q80 I was unable to perform the correct movement or play</cell><cell>.78</cell><cell>.61</cell><cell>.67</cell></row><row><cell>Q103 My reaction time became delayed during play</cell><cell>.71</cell><cell>.65</cell><cell>.63</cell></row><row><cell>Q81 I felt embarrassed</cell><cell>.67</cell><cell>.61</cell><cell>.59</cell></row><row><cell>Q68 I could not move as I wanted to, which promoted ``choking under pressure''</cell><cell>.64</cell><cell>.78</cell><cell>.76</cell></row><row><cell>Q59 I became anxious following mistakes, which promoted ``choking under pressure''</cell><cell>.62</cell><cell>.63</cell><cell>.70</cell></row><row><cell>Q93 I had no conˆdence</cell><cell>.57</cell><cell>.66</cell><cell>.56</cell></row><row><cell>Q74 My play did not lead to positive results</cell><cell>.56</cell><cell>.64</cell><cell>.54</cell></row><row><cell>Q65 I put a lot of physical eŠort into the movement that usually comes natural</cell><cell>.52</cell><cell>.57</cell><cell>.59</cell></row><row><cell>Q61 I became conscious of my mistakes</cell><cell>.51</cell><cell>.58</cell><cell>.59</cell></row><row><cell>Q52 I made more mistakes than usual</cell><cell>.50</cell><cell>.54</cell><cell>.65</cell></row><row><cell>Q87 I rushed while trying to calm down</cell><cell>.50</cell><cell>.54</cell><cell>.64</cell></row><row><cell>Q79 I felt consumed by an inferiority complex</cell><cell>.46</cell><cell>.56</cell><cell>.57</cell></row><row><cell>Q71 I strained to make the movement (related to the body or movements)</cell><cell>.42</cell><cell>.49</cell><cell>.47</cell></row><row><cell>Q82 I became more aware of my surroundings</cell><cell>.41</cell><cell>.51</cell><cell>.47</cell></row><row><cell>Q69 I could not determine if my plays were good or bad</cell><cell>.39</cell><cell>.51</cell><cell>.62</cell></row><row><cell>Q28 I was rushing</cell><cell>.39</cell><cell>.58</cell><cell>.60</cell></row><row><cell>Q85 I was able to play without wavering</cell><cell>.38</cell><cell>.45</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Q54 I was consumed by the atmosphere</cell><cell>.38</cell><cell>.46</cell><cell>.53</cell></row><row><cell>Q41 I could only think of negative images</cell><cell>.36</cell><cell>.54</cell><cell>.61</cell></row><row><cell>Q18 I tried to control myself, but it ended up promoting ``choking under pressure''</cell><cell>.35</cell><cell>.66</cell><cell>.65</cell></row><row><cell>F2: Abnormal physical sensations</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Q101 I felt that my feet were not touching the ground</cell><cell>.75</cell><cell>.73</cell><cell>.64</cell></row><row><cell>Q89 I felt that my body was ‰oating</cell><cell>.70</cell><cell>.62</cell><cell>.62</cell></row><row><cell>Q75 I could not feel my hands or feet</cell><cell>.61</cell><cell>.63</cell><cell>.72</cell></row><row><cell>Q92 My breathing was irregular and I felt short of breath</cell><cell>.54</cell><cell>.53</cell><cell>.67</cell></row><row><cell>Q83 I felt a lump in my throat</cell><cell>.48</cell><cell>.72</cell><cell>.61</cell></row><row><cell>Q94 I could not move my hands and feet like I wanted</cell><cell>.46</cell><cell>.66</cell><cell>.69</cell></row><row><cell>Q88 I felt that my head was hot(and sweaty)</cell><cell>.45</cell><cell>.59</cell><cell>.58</cell></row><row><cell>Q84 I could not see the faces of the people around me</cell><cell>.43</cell><cell>.50</cell><cell>.60</cell></row><row><cell>Q86 My hands felt cold</cell><cell>.43</cell><cell>.44</cell><cell>.45</cell></row><row><cell>Q96 I did not want to speak with anyone</cell><cell>.39</cell><cell>.47</cell><cell>.51</cell></row><row><cell>Q35 My hands and feet were shaking</cell><cell>.35</cell><cell>.49</cell><cell>.54</cell></row><row><cell>Q76 I felt fear</cell><cell>.31</cell><cell>.61</cell><cell>.54</cell></row><row><cell>F3: Perceptual and cognitive confusion</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Q45 I had been feeling stress from things that my teammates on the club (university) team</cell><cell>.67</cell><cell>.57</cell><cell>.55</cell></row><row><cell>had said</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Q46 I began to not care about the results</cell><cell>.53</cell><cell>.46</cell><cell>.52</cell></row><row><cell>Q62 I thought that I would fail every time</cell><cell>.48</cell><cell>.65</cell><cell>.70</cell></row><row><cell>Q33 My technique was not at its best before the match (approximately one week before)</cell><cell>.47</cell><cell>.50</cell><cell>.46</cell></row><row><cell>Q55 My physical condition was not at its best before the match (approximately one week be-</cell><cell>.45</cell><cell>.50</cell><cell>.41</cell></row><row><cell>fore)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Q21 I had been losing conˆdence in the speciˆc event or task before the match (e.g., individ-</cell><cell>.45</cell><cell>.39</cell><cell>.51</cell></row><row><cell>ual/team, service/receive, PK, batting, etc.)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Q22 I felt that other people were all looking at me</cell><cell>.44</cell><cell>.55</cell><cell>.52</cell></row><row><cell>Q97 I felt irritated</cell><cell>.42</cell><cell>.48</cell><cell>.56</cell></row><row><cell>Q17 I saw surrounding objects as working against me (e.g., net looked higher, own court felt</cell><cell>.40</cell><cell>.43</cell><cell>.53</cell></row><row><cell>wider, etc.)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Q58 I felt detached from the surrounding environment</cell><cell>.36</cell><cell>.58</cell><cell>-</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A study on the reliability and validity of a scale to measure shyness as a trait</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jpn. J. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Agari&apos;&apos;yasui seikaku</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Arimitsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Personalities of getting easily nervous</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Shirš ƒzu ningen to seikaku: [Series of human beings and personalities</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Takuma</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Tokyo</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="178" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Agari&apos;&apos; to sono taishohou</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Arimitsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Stage fright and the way to deal with it</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Tokyo</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kawashima Shoten</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Situations and cognitive appraisals in `Agari&apos; experiences-Feature analysis of `Agari&apos; experiences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Arimitsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Imada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jpn. J. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Choking under pressure: Self-consciousness and paradoxical eŠects of incentives on skillful performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Baumeister</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Pers. Soc. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="610" to="620" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the fragility of skilled performance: What governs choking under pressure?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Beilock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Carr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Exp. Psychol. Gen</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="701" to="725" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of the arousal/motor performance relationship in children using movement kinematics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Beuter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Duda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Sport. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="243" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The eŠect of arousal on joint kinematics and kinetics in children</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Beuter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Duda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Widule</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Res. Q. Exerc. Sport</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="116" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alternative ways of assessing model ˆt</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Browne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cudeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Testing structural equation models</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bollen</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Newbury Park, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="136" to="162" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The anxiety response: Concordance among components</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Calvo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Miguel-Tobal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Motiv. Emot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="211" to="230" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anxiety versus fundamental emotions as predictors of perceived functionality of pre-competitive emotional states, threat, and challenge in individual sports</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cerin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Sport. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">State-trait anxiety and motocross performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>De Moj Àa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>De Moj Àa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Percept. Mot. Skills</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anxiety and performance: The processing e‹ciency theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Eysenck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Calvo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cognit. Emot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="409" to="434" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-consciousness, self-attention, and interaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fenigstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Pers. Soc. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="86" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Public and private self-consciousness: Assessment and theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fenigstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Scheier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Buss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Consult. Clin. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="522" to="527" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Personality and self estimation of agari (stage fright) tendency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Fumoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Yamaji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kaneko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bulletin of the Faculty of Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Hirosaki University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The allocation of attention during locomotion is altered by anxiety</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sleik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Polych</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mckenzie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exp. Brain. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">150</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="385" to="394" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Attending to the execution of a complex sensorimotor skill: Expertise diŠerences, choking, and slumps</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Exp. Psychol. Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="42" to="54" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experienced golfers&apos; perspectives on choking under pressure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gucciardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Longbottom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dimmock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Sport. Exerc. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Competitive anxiety responses in the week leading up to competition: The role of intensity, direction and frequency dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hanton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Maynard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol. Sport. Exerc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="181" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A catastrophe model of anxiety and performance in sport</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hardy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Stress and performance in sport</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hardy</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="106" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge and conscious control of motor actions under stress</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hardy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mullen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br. J. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="621" to="636" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A catastrophe model of anxiety and performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hardy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Parˆtt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br. J. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Examination of an analytical framework for predicting competitive performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hashimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tokunaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Health Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disruption of kinematic coordination in throwing under stress</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Higuchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jpn. Psychol. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="168" to="177" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Freezing degrees of freedom under stress: Kinematic evidence of constrained movement strategies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Higuchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Imanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hatayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mov. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="831" to="846" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Honma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Agari, fuan, kincho: [Stage fright</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Tokyo</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Taishukan Shoten</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="622" to="623" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Sup šotsu shinrigaku jiten. Encyclopedia of sport psychology. in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factor analitical study on the traits of stage fright in sports (1)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ichimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jpn. J. Physic. Educ. Health Sport Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relationship between personality and causal attribution of choking in sport</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Murayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sekiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bulletin of the Graduate School of Integrated Arts and Sciences I</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Hiroshima University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Peripheral narrowing among experienced and inexperienced ri‰e shooters under low-and high-stress conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Landers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Courtet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Res. Q. Exerc. Sport</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="122" to="130" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thinking about choking? Attentional processes and paradoxical performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Linder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pers. Soc. Psychol. Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="937" to="944" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge, knerves and know-how: The role of explicit versus implicit knowledge in the breakdown of a complex motor skill under pressure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S W</forename><surname>Masters</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br. J. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="343" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The eŠects of anxiety on motor performance: A test of the conscious processing hypothesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mullen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hardy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tattersall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Sport. Exerc. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="212" to="225" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Qualitative research on the mechanism of choking under pressure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Murayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sekiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jpn. J. Physic. Educ. Health Sport Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factor analysis of the mechanisms underlying ``choking under pressure&apos;&apos; in sports</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Murayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sekiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Asian. J. Exerc. Sports Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Activation of the arousal response and impairment of performance increase with anxiety and stressor intensity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Noteboom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Barnholt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Enoka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2093" to="2101" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">SPSS to Amos ni yoru shinri, chousa d šeta kaiseki: Inshi bunseki, kyoubunsan kouzou bunseki made: [Analysis of psychology and survey data using SPSS and Amos: Factor analysis and analysis of covariance]</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Oshio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<publisher>Tokyo Tosho</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of anxiety in perceiving and realizing aŠordances</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Pijpers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R D</forename><surname>Oudejans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Bakker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Beek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecol. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="161" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anticipatory cortisol, testosterone and psychological responses to judo competition in young men</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Salvador</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Suay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gonz Áalez-Bono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Serrano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychoneuroendocrinology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="364" to="375" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In‰uence of sport experience in physical education classes on life skills acquisition between athlete and non-athlete students</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Shimamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ishii</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jpn. J. Sport Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An attempting to construct the self-consciousness scale for Japanese</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sugawara</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jpn. J. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Douki-zuke to undou paf šomansu</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sugihara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Motivation and exercise performance</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Undo shinrigaku ny šumon</title>
		<editor>I. Matsuda &amp; T. Sugihara</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Taishukan Shoten</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="68" />
			<pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Guide to sport psychology. in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The in‰uence of acute psychological stress on golf putting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sekiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jpn. J. Sport Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The in‰uence of audience and monetary reward on the putting kinematics of expert and novice golfers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sekiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Res. Q. Exerc. Sport</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="416" to="424" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010a</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relationships between psychological/ physiological changes and behavioral/performance changes of a golf putting task under pressure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sekiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Sport Health. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010b</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The in‰uence of monetary reward and punishment on psychological, physiological behavioral, and performance aspects of a golf putting task</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sekiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mov. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1115" to="1128" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Notes for discussion of structural equation modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Toyoda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behaviormetrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="137" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The phenomenon of ``agari&apos;&apos; and self consciousness: A preliminary approach to social anxiety. Memoirs, Faculty of Education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tsutsumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="33" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Shimane University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Construction of the big ˆve scales of personality trait terms and concurrent validity with NPI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jpn. J. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selfconsciousness and trait anxiety as predictors of choking in sport</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Marchant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gibbs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Sci. Med. Sport</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="174" to="185" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The eŠects of anxiety on visual search, movement kinematics, and performance in table tennis: A test of Eysenck and Calvo&apos;s processing e‹ciency theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vickers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rodrigues</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Sport. Exerc. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="438" to="455" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Test anxiety and direction of attention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol. Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chi, jou, i no shinkei shinrigaku: [Neuropsychology of intellect, emotion and volition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Yamadori</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tokyo: Seitosha</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Doctoral Program, Graduate School of Biosphere Science, Hiroshima University 2003-2005 Master&apos;s Program, Graduate school of Education, Kanazawa University 1998-2002 Undergraduate Program, Faculty of Education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yoshie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Murayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kudo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sekiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Asian Journal of Exercise &amp; Sports Science</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>murayama</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sekiya</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2011. 2005-2012. 2010</date>
			<pubPlace>Kanazawa, Ishikawa; Health Service Center, Kanazawa University; Utsunomiya University Main Works</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Health Service Center, Kanazawa University Address: Kakuma-machi</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Jpn. J. Biomech. Sports Exerc.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Qualitative Research on the Mechanism of Choking under Pressure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>murayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sekiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Japan Journal of Physical Education, Health and Sport Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The in‰uence of time pressure on the execution of a motor skill</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>murayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Sugai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sekiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Membership in Learned Societies: International Society of Sport Psychology North American Society for Psychology of Sport and Physical Activity Japanese Society of Sport Psychology Japan Society of Physical Education, Health and Sport Sciences Japanese Society for Cognitive Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="451" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Japan Journal of Physical Education, Health and Sport Sciences</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
