<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation Method of Postgraduate Tutors&apos; Ethics and Style Based on Matter-Element Model</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Decang</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
							<email>lidecang1978@163.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Gansu Logistics and Transportation Equipment Information Technology Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>730070</postCode>
									<settlement>Lanzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zhaoji</forename><surname>Niu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Gansu Logistics and Transportation Equipment Information Technology Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>730070</postCode>
									<settlement>Lanzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Mechatronics T&amp;R Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lanzhou Jiaotong University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>730070</postCode>
									<settlement>Lanzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation Method of Postgraduate Tutors&apos; Ethics and Style Based on Matter-Element Model</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.4108/eai.13-10-2023.2341240</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T20:53+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Matter-element model</term>
					<term>Postgraduate tutor</term>
					<term>Ethics</term>
					<term>Index system</term>
					<term>Evaluation</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Aiming at the problems of data redundancy, multiple heterogeneity and low efficiency in the traditional manual evaluation process, this paper proposes a matterelement model based evaluation method for postgraduate tutor's ethics and style. Fishbone analysis diagram is used to obtain the influencing factors for the construction of postgraduate tutor's ethics and style, which are taken as elements in the matter-element model. The evaluation index system of graduate tutor's ethics and style is designed, and a comprehensive evaluation model is constructed to achieve the evaluation grade and result of postgraduate tutor's ethics and ethics evaluation. The example analysis proves the effectiveness of this method.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The construction of "double first-class" is a major strategic decision made by the CPC Central Committee and the State Council, and is a landmark project for the connotative development of higher education in the new era <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Before the National Conference on Postgraduate Education was held, General Secretary Xi Jinping gave important instructions on the work of postgraduate education, stressing that postgraduate education has an important role to play in cultivating innovative talents, improving innovation ability, serving economic and social development, and promoting the modernization of the national governance system and governance ability <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</p><p>As the first criterion to evaluate the quality of teachers, the accuracy and scientificity of the evaluation results are of great significance to the construction of graduate tutor's ethics and style. In recent years, different scholars have carried out relevant research on it from different perspectives. Han et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> took devotion to work, teaching and educating, rigorous study, and being a teacher as the four first-level evaluation indexes, and combined them with the Delphi method to construct the evaluation system of teacher ethics and teacher morale, and verified the feasibility of the evaluation system through practical tests. Liu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> put forward the path to enhance the talent cultivation capacity of colleges and universities with the construction of postgraduate tutors' teacher ethics.</p><p>In summary, it is found that a unified and better appraisal and evaluation system of teacher ethics has not yet been formed. Therefore, this paper proposes a teacher ethics assessment and evaluation method for graduate tutors based on the matter-element model, designs the teacher ethics assessment and evaluation index system for graduate tutors, and constructs a comprehensive teacher ethics assessment and evaluation model to realize the assessment and evaluation of graduate tutors' teacher ethics and provide a new way of thinking for the assessment and evaluation of teacher ethics and morality.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Construction of Evaluation Index System of Postgraduate Tutor's</head><p>Ethics and Style</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Fishbone Diagram Analysis of Influencing Factors in the Construction of Teacher Ethics and Style for Postgraduate Tutors</head><p>The construction of postgraduate tutors' ethics is a complex subject, and there are many factors affecting the construction of teachers' ethics. In view of the problem of more influencing factors in the process of teacher ethics construction of master's degree postgraduate tutors, the fishbone diagram analysis method is introduced. Taking the construction of teacher ethics as the central goal, combing out other subdivided factors affecting the corresponding construction of teacher ethics of postgraduate supervisors from five aspects, such as political ideology, teacher moral cultivation, academic literacy, teacher-student relationship, professional ethics and so on, and serving as the fishbone, respectively. The fishbone diagram of the influencing factors of teacher ethics construction is constructed, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Goal teacher moral cultivation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Teacher Ethics Assessment and Evaluation Index System</head><p>Due to the lack of unified index specification, a unified and better assessment and evaluation system of teacher ethics has not yet been formed, and the factors affecting the construction of teacher ethics are also various. This paper is based on the fishbone analysis diagram of the influencing factors of the construction of teachers' morality and teachers' style of postgraduate tutors, and constructs the evaluation index system of teachers' morality and teachers' style assessment of postgraduate tutors with the influencing factors as the source of index elements, as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Teacher Ethics Assessment and Evaluation Model Construction for Graduate Student Supervisors</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Classical Domain and Node Domain Matter-element Matrix</head><p>Matter-element analysis method is a new discipline founded by Chinese scholar Cai Wen in the 1980s, which is a study of the laws and methods of solving contradictory problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</p><p>According to the definition of object element <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, the matrix of object elements for teacher ethics assessment and evaluation can be expressed as: =( , , ) R N c v .The classical domain refers to the range of values of each evaluation level corresponding to each evaluation index in the system to be evaluated <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, and the matter-element of the classical domain is shown in Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">1</ref>).</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">      1 1 1 1 1 2 2 2 2</formula><p>, , ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">j j j j j j j j j n n j n n j n j N c v N c a b c v c a b R c v c a b                                <label>(1)</label></formula><p>where, N j is the jth evaluation level of the evaluation criteria classified by the assessment and evaluation of teacher ethics; c i is the ith indicator affecting the assessment and evaluation of teacher ethics. The interval v ij is the range of magnitude values obtained by N j with respect to c i . The node domain matter-element matrix is shown in Eq. ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>). </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">      1 1 1 1 1 2 2 2</formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">P c v N c c d c v c c d R c v c c d                                 (2)</formula><p>where, P is the tutor of all master's students to be evaluated; v pi is the value range of all the mentors P to be evaluated on the index c i , that is the subsection domain.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Correlation Functions</head><p>The correlation function is used to determine the correlation value of teacher's moral evaluation level <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> , as shown in Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">3</ref>).</p><p>(</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">i i j i i j ij j i i i j i i j i p i i i j v v v v v K v v v v v v v v v                <label>, ) , ( ) ( , ) , ( , ) ( , )</label></formula><p>where, K j (v i ) is the correlation function for the jth level of evaluation indicator i and ( , )( 1,2 , )</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">ij ij ij v a b i n   </formula><p>. Denote the value of the correlation function of the measurement condition K j (v i ) for each evaluation level is denoted as ( , )</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">i i i M c v </formula><p>, then the correlation degree of evaluation element R with evaluation grade j is shown in Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">4</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">( ) ( )</head><formula xml:id="formula_8">n j ij i i K R K v    <label>(4)</label></formula><p>where, ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">j K R</formula><p>is the integrated correlation of the object to be evaluated R with respect to each evaluation level j ; i  is the weighting coefficient of each system in the criterion layer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Determining the Evaluation Level of Teacher Ethics Assessment</head><p>According to the teacher morality assessment of the relevant rules and regulations <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, combined with the actual assessment of a university case, the teacher morality assessment grade quantified as "excellent, qualified, unqualified" three levels, of which J = 3 on behalf of the assessment "excellent", J=2 for the assessment of "qualified", J=1 for the assessment of "unqualified", the specific grade division as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>. 4 Case Study</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Data Sources</head><p>This paper takes the special evaluation data of a domestic university's 2022 teacher ethics assessment for graduate student instructors as an example (the content of the evaluation form is shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>), validates the constructed evaluation index system and evaluation model by example through evaluating one graduate student instructor's teacher ethics assessment. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Evaluation Process</head><p>According to Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> and Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>, we construct the evaluation level domain of master's graduate student tutors' teacher ethics; the evaluation factor sets of teacher ethics are takes the first-level index of "political ideology" and the second-level indexes of its subordinates as an example, and calculates the steps and processes as follows.</p><p>Step1:Determination of classical and nodal domains.</p><p>Step2:Determination of the actual score of the matter element to be assessed.</p><p>Based on the constructed teacher ethics assessment and evaluation index system, the weights of the indexes were calculated using the Analytic Hierarchy Process (AHP) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. According to the judgement matrix, the relative importance weights of the lowest level factors relative to the highest level are calculated, and the judgement matrix itself is derived from the scoring of experts, which relies on the experience and professional ability of the experts, and does not guarantee that the judgement matrix has complete consistency <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. Therefore, the calculation of the compatibility index CI (Consistency Index) is used as a measure of deviation from the consistency of the judgement matrix to improve the accuracy of the judgement, when the number of orders is greater than 2, the consistency of the judgement matrix is tested by calculating the compatibility ratio CR (Consistency Index), and if CR &lt; 0.1, it is considered that the judgement matrix meets the consistency requirements, as shown in Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">5</ref>).</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">max 1 n CI n CI CR RI            <label>(5)</label></formula><p>where, n is the number of matrix orders; max  is the largest characteristic root; CI is the calculated compatibility index; RI is the random consistency index.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1) Determination of weighting factors for the criterion layer</head><p>Based on the judgement results, the judgement matrix of the criterion layer C i (i=1,2,3,4,5) for the target layer Z is constructed, and the data are weighted according to the AHP method using MATLAB software, and the results of the weight calculation are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2) Determination of weighting factors for secondary indicators</head><p>The method of determinging the weight codfficient of the secondary index is the same as that of the criterion layer.</p><p>According to Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, the evaluation index system of teachers' morality of postgraduate tutors, combined with the actual situation of a university in China, it is determined that the value of the object to be evaluated under the second evaluation index "tutor's concept of the rule of law" is v 22 =96.</p><p>Step3:Calculating correlation According to Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">3</ref>), by combining the constructed classical and sectional domains of teacher ethics assessment and evaluation for postgraduate supervisors, the correlation degree of the second-level indexes about the evaluation grade of teacher ethics can be obtained.</p><p>the actual scores and correlation degrees of other secondary indicators of the appraisal and evaluation index system of graduate student instructors can be obtained, as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">5</ref>. Step4:Calculation of the relevance of level 1 indicators According to the correlation formula above, combined with the results of the correlation of each secondary indicator in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">5</ref>, we can derive the value of the correlation of the first-level indicator of the assessment and evaluation of graduate instructors' moral character.</p><p>Step5:Calculate the composite correlation According to Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">4</ref>), combined with the calculation results of the correlation degree of each level index in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">6</ref>, the value of the comprehensive correlation of the assessment and evaluation of the master's degree tutor's teacher ethics can be derived. The final result of the target layer topable evaluation is shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">6</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Results Analysis</head><p>As can be seen from Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">6</ref>, based on the object meta-topology method, the first-level indicators of the assessment and evaluation of teacher ethics in the case: "teacher moral cultivation", "professional ethics", "teacher-student concern", "academic quality" are all level 2, of which "political thought" accounts for the largest proportion in the overall teacher ethics assessment indicators, indicating that political thought is relatively important in assessing the teacher ethics assessment of master's degree tutors. The evaluation results are basically similar to those in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>, which shows that the evaluation method based on the object model is feasible to be used in the evaluation of teacher ethics of master's degree tutors. From the single-indicator correlation of the influencing factors calculated in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">5</ref>, it can be seen that the overall teacher ethics assessment of this postgraduate tutor is in the "qualified" category, whereas the traditional teacher ethics assessment assessment form relies too much on subjective judgement due to the use of manual evaluation, and therefore there is a certain discrepancy in the results of the assessment. In contrast, using the AHP method for the calculation of indicator weights can effectively use the actual data of the indicators, thus avoiding subjectivity, and the combination of the physical meta-model can produce more objective and effective evaluation results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Summary</head><p>In this paper, for the assessment and evaluation process of teacher ethics and teacher morality, the data of multiple indicators are complicated and uncertain, so we propose an assessment and evaluation method of teacher ethics and teacher morality of postgraduate supervisors based on the matter-element model. The method firstly obtains the influencing factors of teacher ethics construction of postgraduate tutors through the fishbone analysis diagram, and constructs the assessment and evaluation index system of postgraduate tutors on the basis of this; then constructs the assessment and evaluation model of teacher ethics for master's degree postgraduate tutors based on the matter-element analysis method, and calculates the classical domains, section domains, correlation degrees, etc. in the model, and determines the multiindicators' weights in the evaluation system through the AHP method, and finally obtains the correlation degree of each indicator on the evaluation grade and finally get the correlation degree of each index about the evaluation level. This method reduces all the uncertainties in the evaluation system to the minimum range, and better suppresses the problem of mutual incompatibility between each indicator, and quantifies the qualitative problems. Example results show that the evaluation model designed in this paper for the appraisal and evaluation of graduate tutors' teacher ethics and morality better overcomes the influence of the complicated parameters of the evaluation indicators, the uncertainty characteristics and the disturbance of the external environment in the evaluation process; this method not only meets the requirements for the appraisal and evaluation of the graduate tutors' teacher ethics and morality, but also applies to the evaluation of the appraisal of the teacher ethics and morality of all college and university teachers.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Fishbone diagram analysis of influencing factors in the construction of teachers' ethics for postgraduate tutors</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>,C ,C ,C } . Due to the limitation of space, this paper takes one of the graduate student tutors as an example, and</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Teacher ethics assessment and evaluation index system for postgraduate tutors</figDesc><table><row><cell>Target level</cell><cell>Criterion layer (Primary index)</cell><cell>Indicator level (Secondary indexs)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Have moral sentiments,speak and act gracefully(C11)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Teacher moral</cell><cell>Make oneself an example (C12)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>cultivation (C1)</cell><cell>Dedication, willing to contribute (C13)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Advocating science and purshing truth (C14)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Love the motherland, love the people (C21)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Political Ideology</cell><cell>Mentor's concept of the rule of law (C22)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(C2)</cell><cell>Core values of socialism(C23)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Understanding the development of the world (C24)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Respect for the results of student research (C31)</cell></row><row><cell>Graduate student</cell><cell>Professional ethics (C3)</cell><cell>Lead postgraduate to abide by academic ethics (C32) Regular checking students' research progress (C33)</cell></row><row><cell>instructors' teacher</cell><cell></cell><cell>Provide comprehensive guidance to students (C34)</cell></row><row><cell>ethics and morale building goals(Z)</cell><cell>Teacher-student</cell><cell>Fairness to all students (C41) Respect for students, no verbal or physical abuse of students (C42)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>relationship (C4)</cell><cell>Emphasis on language arts and treating students as</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>friends (C43)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Care and love for every student (C44)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Academic literacy</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(C5)</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><p>Fearless Research Spirit (C51) Maintaining a sense of independence and detachment (C52)</p>The value of mentors' adherence to the ethical underpinnings of the academic enterprise (C53) Diligent research attitude (C54)</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Grading scale of teacher ethics assessment for postgraduate tutors</figDesc><table><row><cell>total assessment score</cell><cell>appraisal level (J)</cell></row><row><cell>≤60</cell><cell>Unqualified (1)</cell></row><row><cell>61～95</cell><cell>Qualified (2)</cell></row><row><cell>≥96</cell><cell>Excellent (3)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Evaluation form of a university graduate tutor's ethics in 2022</figDesc><table><row><cell>serial number</cell><cell>Measurement items</cell><cell>Main content of the assessment</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>Firm political direction</cell><cell>Support the leadership of the CPC and implement the Party's educational policy.</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>Patriotic and law-abiding</cell><cell>Abide by laws and regulations, perform the duuties of teacher's according to law.</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>Spread fine culture</cell><cell>Promote the truth, goodness and beauty, and pass on positive energy.</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>Devote yourself to teaching</cell><cell>Implement the basic task of moral education, teaching students according to their aptitude,teaching and learning.</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>Care for students</cell><cell>Care for students, strict requirements for students, to be a good teacher and friend.</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>Insist on uprightly words and deeds</cell><cell>To be a model, to lead by example, to behave in a civilized and decent manner.</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>Adhere to academic norms</cell><cell>Rigorous research, the courage to explore, against academic misconduct.</cell></row><row><cell>8</cell><cell>Uphold fairness and good faith</cell><cell>Adhere to principles, do things fair, aboveboard, upright.</cell></row><row><cell>9</cell><cell>Uphold integrity and self-discipline</cell><cell>Be strict with oneself, clean and honest.</cell></row><row><cell>10</cell><cell>Activelyy contribute to society</cell><cell>Fulfill social responsibilities, contribute wisdom, and foster a correct view of justice and shared interests.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Criterion level judgement matrix(Z-Ci)</figDesc><table><row><cell>Z</cell><cell>C1</cell><cell>C 2</cell><cell>C 3</cell><cell>C 4</cell><cell>C 5</cell><cell>i</cell></row><row><cell>C1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1/4</cell><cell>1/3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0.14</cell></row><row><cell>C2</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0.47</cell></row><row><cell>C3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1 / 3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0 . 2 6</cell></row><row><cell>C4</cell><cell>1/4</cell><cell>1/6</cell><cell>1/5</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1/3</cell><cell>0.05</cell></row><row><cell>C5</cell><cell>1/3</cell><cell>1/5</cell><cell>1/4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0.08</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Teacher Ethics Assessment and Evaluation Indicator System and Values for Postgraduate Tutors</figDesc><table><row><cell>Primary index</cell><cell>Weight (1)</cell><cell>Secondary index</cell><cell>Weight (2)</cell><cell>Total score</cell><cell>Actual score</cell><cell>j=1</cell><cell cols="3">Correlation degree j=2</cell><cell>j=3</cell></row><row><cell>Teacher moral cultivation (C 1)</cell><cell>0.14</cell><cell>C 11 C 12 C 13 C 14</cell><cell>0.16 0.12 0.47 0.25</cell><cell>100(16) 100(12) 100(47) 100(25)</cell><cell cols="3">86(13.76) -0.6500 80(9.6) -0.5000 92(43.24) -0.8000 93(23.25) -0.8250</cell><cell>1.8000 3.0000 0.6000 0.4000</cell><cell>-0.3913 -0.4285 -0.2727 -0.2222</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>C 21</cell><cell>0.44</cell><cell>100(44)</cell><cell cols="3">97(42.68) -0.9250</cell><cell>-0.4000</cell><cell>2.0000</cell></row><row><cell>Political ideology</cell><cell>0.47</cell><cell>C 22</cell><cell>0.26</cell><cell>100(26)</cell><cell cols="3">96(24.96) -0.9000</cell><cell>-0.2000</cell><cell>0.3333</cell></row><row><cell>(C 2 )</cell><cell></cell><cell>C 23</cell><cell>0.19</cell><cell>100(19)</cell><cell cols="3">83(15.77) -0.5750</cell><cell>2.4000</cell><cell>-0.4137</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>C 24</cell><cell>0.11</cell><cell>100(11)</cell><cell>75(8.25)</cell><cell cols="2">-0.3750</cell><cell>4.0000</cell><cell>-0.4117</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>C 31</cell><cell>0.30</cell><cell>100(30)</cell><cell>90(27)</cell><cell cols="2">-0.7500</cell><cell>1.0000</cell><cell>-0.3333</cell></row><row><cell>Professional ethics (C 3 )</cell><cell>0.26</cell><cell>C 32 C 33</cell><cell>0.49 0.07</cell><cell>100(49) 100(7)</cell><cell cols="3">93(45.57) -0.8250 86(6.02) -0.6500</cell><cell>0.4000 1.8000</cell><cell>-0.2222 -0.3913</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>C 34</cell><cell>0.14</cell><cell>100(14)</cell><cell>90(12.6)</cell><cell cols="2">-0.7500</cell><cell>1.0000</cell><cell>-0.3333</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>C 41</cell><cell>0.42</cell><cell>100(42)</cell><cell cols="3">92(38.64) -0.8000</cell><cell>0.6000</cell><cell>-0.2727</cell></row><row><cell>Teacher-student relationship (C 4 )</cell><cell>0.05</cell><cell>C 42 C 43 C 44</cell><cell>0.17 0.14 0.27</cell><cell>100(17) 100(14) 100(27)</cell><cell cols="3">84(14.28) -0.6000 80(11.2) -0.5000 72(19.44) -0.3000</cell><cell>2.2000 3.0000 4.6000</cell><cell>-0.4074 -0.4285 -0.4509</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>C 51</cell><cell>0.15</cell><cell>100(15)</cell><cell cols="3">89(13.35) -0.7250</cell><cell>1.2000</cell><cell>-0.3529</cell></row><row><cell>Academic literacy (C 5 )</cell><cell>0.08</cell><cell>C 52 C 53</cell><cell>0.10 0.55</cell><cell>100(10) 100(55)</cell><cell>87(8.7) 90(49.5)</cell><cell cols="2">-0.6750 -0.7500</cell><cell>1.6000 1.0000</cell><cell>-0.3809 -0.3333</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>C 54</cell><cell>0.19</cell><cell>100(19)</cell><cell cols="3">91(17.29) -0.7750</cell><cell>0.8000</cell><cell>-0.3076</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Analysis of target layer extension evaluation results</figDesc><table><row><cell>Primary index</cell><cell>j=1</cell><cell>Correlation degree j=2</cell><cell>j=3</cell><cell>Weight (1)</cell><cell>J</cell></row><row><cell>C1</cell><cell>-0.7463</cell><cell>1.0300</cell><cell>-0.2977</cell><cell>0.14</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>C2</cell><cell>-0.7915</cell><cell>0.6680</cell><cell>0.8428</cell><cell>0.47</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>C3</cell><cell>-0.7797</cell><cell>0.7620</cell><cell>-0.2829</cell><cell>0.26</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>C4</cell><cell>-0.5890</cell><cell>2.2880</cell><cell>-0.3655</cell><cell>0.05</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>C5</cell><cell>-0.7360</cell><cell>1.0420</cell><cell>-0.3328</cell><cell>0.08</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>Z</cell><cell>-0.7675</cell><cell>0.8540</cell><cell>0.2360</cell><cell>/</cell><cell>2</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Acknowledgments. The authors would like to express thanks to the editor and anonymous reviewers for their help in revising the manuscript. This study is funded by the <rs type="institution">Special Research Projict of Teacher's Ethics Construction of Lanzhou Jiaotong University</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The construction path of graduate tutors&apos; ethics under the background of double first-class construction. Western China Quality Education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="19" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Research on graduate education in the construction of double first class. Enrollment and Examination in Hubei</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Xiong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="23" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Construction the evaluation index system of university teacher&apos;s ethics based on Delphi Method and Analytic Hierarchy Process . The Guide of Science &amp; Education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="86" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Strengthen the cultivation of talents in colleges with the construction of teacher&apos;s ethics. The Party Buildng and Ideological Education in Schools</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="19" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the construction path of postgraduate tutor&apos; ethics based on fishbone diagram analysis--A case study of HeBei University of Engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="96" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Hebei Universiy of Engineering</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How to make a decision: The analytic hierarchy process</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Saaty</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Oper. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<pubPlace>US</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Research on comprehensive evaluation method of power quality based on Cloud Matter Model and Variable Fueey Set</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>AnHui University</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Research on Evaluation of Green Manufacturing based on Metter-element Extension Model. Environment and Sustainable Development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="63" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The problems and countermeasures of the construction of teacher&apos;s ethics and style in colleges and universities. Shipbuilding Vocational Education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="66" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dicussion support system for thesis session pass recommendation using AHP method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Valentino</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Educ. Res. Social Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="221" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<pubPlace>Indonesia</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Comprehensive benefit evaluation of green buildings based on AHP and Matter Element Extension Model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>JiangXi University of Science and Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
