<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Work Motivation as an Intermediary Variable in the Relationship between Principal Transformational Leadership, School Climate, and Teacher Professionalism</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wina</forename><surname>Novita</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Muhyani</forename><surname>Rizalie</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master in Educational Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<address>
									<addrLine>555 0.007 0.586 0.738 0.418 Received</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Work Motivation as an Intermediary Variable in the Relationship between Principal Transformational Leadership, School Climate, and Teacher Professionalism</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-51</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received Received Received Received Table 3: Summary of Hypothesis Testing Decisions H 6 and H 7 Received Received As can be seen</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T21:43+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Transformational leadership</term>
					<term>school climate</term>
					<term>work motivation</term>
					<term>professionalism</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Teacher professionalism is an important aspect because it determines the quality of the teaching and learning process. However, the fact is that there are still many teachers who are considered to have professionalism that does not meet expectations. From the input-process-output perspective, factors that influence professionalism include transformational leadership, school climate, work motivation, and teacher professionalism. This study aims to determine and analyze the relationship between principals' transformational leadership, school climate, work motivation, and teacher professionalism, either directly or indirectly. This research is descriptive correlational research. The study population was 116 people, with a sample of 90 people who were selected using a proportionate random sampling technique. Data was collected using instruments consisting of transformational leadership (23 items), school climate (50 items), work motivation (44 items), and teacher professionalism (45 items) which had been tested for validity and reliability. The research data were analyzed descriptively and path analysis. The study results found that the principal's transformational leadership has a relationship with teacher professionalism, and the school climate has a relationship with teacher professionalism. The study results also showed the principal's transformational leadership has a relationship with work motivation, school climate has a relationship with work motivation, and work motivation has a relationship with teacher professionalism. Moreover, the work motivation of the teacher is the intermediary of the principal's transformational leadership relationship with teacher professionalism and the school climate relationship with work motivation.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Educational institution progress and decline are strongly influenced by the motivation of the individual teachers who serve in the institution. Likewise, the quality of education cannot be separated from teacher professionalism in improving the quality of education. No matter how high a person's ability is, he will not work professionally if he does not have high work motivation in doing his tasks. On the other hand, no matter how high a person's work motivation is, he will not work professionally if he does not have high abilities in carrying out his duties. This case aligns with Glickman's theory, which states that teachers have four prototypes for managing the learning process. According to him, the best teacher prototype is a professional teacher. A teacher can be classified as a professional prototype if he has a high ability (high level of abstract) and high work motivation (high level of commitment). <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Sahertian, 2014)</ref> . Based on this, a teacher must have and foster competence or abilities along with their skills and always foster work motivation in carrying out every professional task.</p><p>Professional teachers must be able to carry out the teaching and learning process as well as possible. Professional teachers must carry out their teaching duties well to prepare future students with the right scientific basis. Professional teachers are a must and urgent in implementing education because their duties are directly related to preparing the future young generation of the nation who are qualified, virtuous, and able to compete in the future. Professional teachers are also considered a key factor in realizing the stages of quality education <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Rusman, 2018)</ref>. In becoming a professional teacher, a teacher must be able to find his identity and actualize himself by following the abilities and rules of a professional teacher.</p><p>Professional teachers prioritize the quality and impact of the implementation of their teacher's duties. In carrying out his duties, a teacher must be able to meet the demands and expectations of society, the state, and job providers and must be able to explore the potential and abilities of the students. In their duties, teachers certainly face many challenges and problems. In facing situations like this, teachers must maintain and support student learning conditions that run well and optimally and can direct students properly and responsibly <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Rusman, 2018)</ref>.</p><p>The factors that influence teacher professionalism are seen from the Input-Process-Output perspective. What is meant by input perspective is things contained in the teacher's personality, including the qualifications or level of teacher education, years of service, work experience, training undertaken, mastery of social competence, pedagogy, and skills. In addition, there are also input factors that come from the environment around the teacher, such as the principal's transformational leadership <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Syarafudin &amp; Ikawati, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Transformational leadership has an important role in improving teacher professionalism. Good transformational leadership will be able to influence, move and bring change to subordinates to enhance their professionalism <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Sari, 2018)</ref>.</p><p>Apart from the principal's transformational leadership, another factor influencing teacher professionalism is the school climate <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Syarafudin &amp; Ikawati, 2020)</ref>. In effective schools, special attention is paid to creating and maintaining a school climate and culture that is conducive to learning. This situation is marked by creating a comfortable, safe and orderly learning environment so that learning takes place effectively. According to Toswend, a conducive climate is very important so that students feel happy and have a positive attitude towards their school so that teachers feel valued and parents and the community feel accepted and involved. This climate can be realized by cultivating positive norms and habits, harmonious relationships, and cooperation based on mutual respect. In addition, a conducive environment encourages every school member to act and do their best to lead to high student achievement <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Mulyasa, 2012)</ref>.</p><p>Other factors that affect teacher professionalism seen from the perspective of the teaching and learning process in the classroom include the teacher's high teaching and education motivation factor <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Syarafudin &amp; Ikawati, 2020)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Zulkifli (2014)</ref> states that work motivation plays an important role in efforts to improve the professionalism of a teacher. Harapan (2007) said that several factors influence professional ability, one of which is motivation. This statement is further strengthened by research conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Isnawati (2016)</ref>, which states that work motivation significantly affects teacher professionalism. Based on the description above, it can be concluded that teachers and their professionalism can be caused by various factors, including the principal's transformational leadership, the school climate, and the work motivation of the teacher himself.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHOD</head><p>This study aims to describe and analyze direct and indirect relationships between variables: principal transformational leadership and teacher professionalism, school climate and teacher professionalism, principal transformational leadership and work motivation, school climate, and work motivation, work motivation and teacher professionalism, leadership transformational and professionalism through work motivation, as well as school climate and professionalism through work motivation. This research includes correlational descriptive research. The population in this study were SDN teachers, Candi Laras Selatan District, Tapin Regency, and as many as 116 people. In a sample of 90 people, determining sample members was taken using the proportional random sampling technique. Data were collected through documentation and questionnaires with the principal's transformational leadership (idealized influence, inspirational motivation, intellectual stimulation, and individualized consideration), school climate (student support, affiliation, professional interest, staff freedom, participation decision making, innovation, resource adequacy, and work pressure ), work motivation (achievement, responsibility, work itself, recognition, growth, salary, working condition, relationship with peers, relationship with supervisor, company policy and administration, security, supervision, and status), teacher professionalism (pedagogical skills, personality, social and professional). The instrument was analyzed for validity and reliability with correlation and Cronbach's Alpha. The research data were analyzed using path analysis to see the direct and indirect relationship between the variables by first conducting the Normality test and Linearity test.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head><p>The results of the data normality test of the four variables using the One-Sample Kolmogorov-Smirnov showed that the four variables were normally distributed. The linearity test results show that the principal's transformational leadership relationship has a relationship with teacher professionalism, the school climate has a relationship with teacher professionalism, the principal's transformational leadership has a relationship with work motivation, the school climate has a relationship with work motivation, work motivation has a linear relationship with professionalism. The results of testing the analysis requirements have been met; the next stage is the interpretation of the path analysis results with a summary of the results in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.   <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> and<ref type="table">2</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, the hypothesis rejection in this study can be seen in Tables <ref type="table">3</ref> and<ref type="table">4</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 2: Summary of Hypothesis Testing Decisions H 1, H 2, H 3, H 4, and H 5 Hypothesis</head><p>p Decision H 1: there is a direct relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and teacher professionalism H 2: there is a direct relationship between school climate and teacher professionalism H 3: there is a direct relationship between work motivation and teacher professionalism H 4: there is a direct relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and work motivation H 5: there is a direct relationship between school climate and work motivation DISCUSSION A.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Direct Relationship between Principal Transformational Leadership and Teacher Professionalism</head><p>The results of the path analysis between the principal's transformational leadership and the professionalism of public elementary school teachers in Candi Laras Selatan District, Tapin Regency, obtained a beta value of 0.555 with a significance value of 0.000. It means that there is a direct moderate relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and the professional teacher.</p><p>As part of efforts to maximize teacher professionalism, the principal has a very important role because the success or failure of realizing the goals targeted by an educational institution is also determined by the principal's leadership. Therefore, one of the factors that support the achievement of teacher professionalism is the principal's transformational leadership <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Sari, 2018)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Windasari (2017)</ref> states that school principals' appropriate transformational leadership style in dealing with subordinates, in this case, teachers can increase the professionalism of teachers in the work environment concerned. The results of the research also show this relationship by <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Sudewa (2013)</ref>, which states that there is a significant influence between the principal's transformational leadership style on teacher professionalism. The above relationship is further strengthened by the results of Sari's research (2018), which states that the principal's transformational leadership affects teacher professionalism. Then it is further strengthened by Marzuki's research (2018) which states that there is an influence of the principal's transformational leadership style and work professionalism. The study by Adzkiya (2020) also states that there is an influence of transformational leadership on teacher professionalism.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Direct Relationship between School Climate and Teacher Professionalism</head><p>The results of the path analysis between school climate and the professionalism of public elementary school teachers in Candi Laras Selatan District, Tapin Regency, obtained a beta value of 0.189 with a significance value of 0.007. It means that there is directly a very weak relationship between school climate and the professionalism of public elementary school teachers in Candi Laras Selatan District, Tapin Regency.</p><p>School climate is felt to be an inseparable part of teacher professionalism. In a pleasant working atmosphere, teachers have a sense of security, a decent life, a sense of belonging, inclusion, and fair and honest treatment. A sense of ability, recognition, and appreciation, participating in policy formation, and opportunities to defend themselves are part of a school climate that can foster high teacher professionalism. Conversely, a less pleasant work atmosphere, no sense of security in the teacher, a sense of being excluded, unfair and dishonest treatment, teachers being considered incapable, and teachers are not recognized and appreciated. All of these circumstances will result in the teacher's performance getting worse. Bad.</p><p>The teachers feel the school climate to be an inseparable part of their profession of the teachers. The formation of a conducive climate in the workplace can be a supporting factor for increasing teacher motivation at work because comfort at work makes teachers think calmly and concentrate only on the task being carried out. If the work atmosphere is pleasant, teachers have a sense of security and decent life, a sense of inclusion, fair and honest treatment, competence, recognition, and appreciation. Taking part in policy formation and opportunities for self-defense are part of a school climate that can foster teacher professionalism is getting better. On the other hand, the work atmosphere is not pleasant, there is no sense of security in the teacher, the feeling of being excluded, unfair and dishonest treatment, the teacher is considered incapable, the teacher is not recognized and appreciated. All of these circumstances will result in the teacher's performance getting worse. Ugly.</p><p>This case is in line with Pratiwi's (2012) research, which shows that the school climate and teacher professionalism have a positive and significant relationship. This is further strengthened by the study conducted by Dewi (2017), which states that there is an influence between school climate and teacher professionalism, and research conducted by <ref type="bibr">Mariana</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Direct Relationship between Work Motivation and Teacher Professionalism</head><p>The path analysis between work motivation and professionalism of public elementary school teachers in Candi Laras Selatan District, Tapin Regency, obtained a beta value of 0.586 with a significance value of 0.000. It means that there is directly a moderate relationship between work motivation and professionalism of public elementary school teachers in Candi Laras Selatan District, Tapin Regency.</p><p>Teachers deal with tens or even hundreds of students every day, requiring high work motivation. Teacher motivation can be external or internal. External motivation comes from social status, income, awards, and honors the community gives. Internal motivation can be sourced from interests, talents, competencies, education, vocation, and sincere dedication to the profession he is living.</p><p>It is reinforced by research conducted by Zulkifli (2014), which states that work motivation plays an important role in efforts to improve the professionalism of a teacher. Harapan (2007) said that several factors influence professional ability, one of which is motivation. It is further strengthened by research conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Isnawati (2016)</ref>, which states that work motivation has a significant effect on teacher professionalism which is further supported by research by <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Triwibowo et al. (2019)</ref>, which states that there is an influence between work motivation on teacher professionalism, as research also conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Kastawi et al. (2021)</ref> who stated the same thing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Direct Relationship between Principal Transformational Leadership and Teacher Work Motivation</head><p>The results of the path analysis between the principal's transformational leadership and the work motivation of public elementary school teachers in Candi Laras Selatan District, Tapin Regency, obtained a beta value of 0.738 with a significance value of 0.000 which means that there is a strong direct relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and work motivation of public elementary school teachers in Candi Laras Selatan District, Tapin Regency.</p><p>Transformational leadership also directly affects employee motivation, in this case, teachers, as shown by research conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Kumalasari (2009)</ref>, which is strengthened by research by <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Dzulfadhil (2010)</ref>. It is also supported by the research results of Sugiarto, Wahidin &amp; Soefijanto (2020), which state that there is a positive direct relationship between transformational leadership and work motivation. Then the research conducted by Purwanti &amp; Cahyoadi (2021) stated a significant positive relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and work motivation as research conducted by Nur &amp; Sjahruddin (2019) stated the same thing. Then it was strengthened again by Prayudi's research (2020), which stated a relationship between transformational leadership and work motivation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. Direct Relationship between School Climate and Teacher Work Motivation</head><p>The results of path analysis between school climate and work motivation of public elementary school teachers in Candi Laras Selatan District, Tapin Regency, obtained a beta value of 0.418 with a significance value of 0.000 which means that there is a strong direct relationship between school climate and work motivation of elementary school teachers. State in Candi Laras Selatan District, Tapin Regency.</p><p>School climate is a situation or atmosphere that arises because of the relationship between fellow school members and is an environmental factor that affects teacher work motivation. The importance of teacher work motivation in carrying out their duties needs to be considered for an organization, including schools. Many things affect the work motivation of teachers both internally and externally. For external factors, the environment plays an important role. School climate, which is a situation or atmosphere that arises because of the relationship between fellow school members, is an environmental factor that affects teacher work motivation <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Hadiyanto, 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Ladyong (2014) states that organizational climate significantly affects teacher work motivation. Two organizational climate factors that significantly affect teacher work motivation are collegial leadership and the reciprocal relationship of school members. The findings of this study have implications for the role of administrators, especially in improving a positive school climate to increase teacher motivation.</p><p>Fujiaturrahman (2017) on the Relationship of School Climate with Teacher Work Motivation. It is reinforced by research conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Sucianti (2015)</ref> on the influence of school organizational climate on teacher work motivation. It is in line with Rahmawati's study (2016), which states that organizational climate significantly affects work motivation. It is reinforced by Selena's (2021) research which states that there is an influence between school climate and teacher work motivation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F. Indirect Relationship between Principal's Transformational Leadership and Teacher Professionalism through Work Motivation</head><p>The results of the path analysis between the principal's transformational leadership and teacher professionalism through the work motivation of elementary school teachers in Candi Laras Selatan District, Tapin Regency, obtained a value of 0.432, which means that there is an indirect relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and teacher professionalism. Through the work motivation of public elementary school teachers in Candi Laras Selatan District, Tapin Regency.</p><p>A good leader is a leader who has high work motivation. Motivation is a person's emotional impulse to act and behave in a certain way to achieve what is expected. Motivation is a way that can encourage the passion of teachers to want to work hard by giving all their abilities and skills in the process of achieving the goals that have been set. Thus, motivation is seen as a motor that creates energy in a person to be able to do something. If a leader has high work motivation, the teacher will follow the way the leader works so that a teacher who works well will become a professional teacher.</p><p>Transformational leadership also has a direct effect on employee work motivation, in this case, teachers, as shown by research conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Kumalasari (2009)</ref>, which found that principal leadership has a positive and strong effect on teacher work motivation with the category of good transformational leadership and high work motivation which is then strengthened. with research by Dzalfadhil (20201), Purwanti &amp; Cahyoadi (2021), Nur &amp; Sjahruddin (2019) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Prayudi (2020)</ref>.</p><p>Teachers deal with tens or even hundreds of students every day, requiring high work motivation. Teacher motivation can be external or internal. External motivation comes from social status, income, awards, and honors the community gives. Internal motivation can be sourced from interests, talents, competencies, education, vocation, and sincere dedication to the profession he is living. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Zulkifli (2014)</ref>  If there is a direct relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and teacher work motivation, there is a direct relationship between teacher motivation and teacher professionalism. So it can be concluded that there is an indirect relationship between the principal's transformational leadership and teacher professionalism through teacher motivation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G. Indirect Relationship between School Climate and Teacher Professionalism through Teacher Work Motivation</head><p>The results of the path analysis between school climate and teacher professionalism through the work School climate is felt to be an inseparable part of teacher professionalism. In a pleasant working atmosphere, teachers have a sense of security, a decent life, a sense of belonging, inclusion, fair and honest treatment, a sense of ability, recognition, and appreciation, taking part in policy formation, opportunities to defend themselves, are part of a school climate that can foster high teacher professionalism in schools. Conversely, a less pleasant work atmosphere, no sense of security in the teacher, a sense of being excluded, unfair and dishonest treatment, teachers being considered incapable, and teachers are not recognized and appreciated. All of these circumstances will result in the teacher's performance getting Ugly. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Pratiwi (2012)</ref> shows that the school climate and teacher professionalism have a positive and significant relationship. This result means that the higher the school climate, the higher the level of teacher professionalism, and conversely, the lower the school climate, the lower the teacher professionalism. It is as stated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Dewi (2017)</ref>, which states that there is an influence between school climate and teacher professionalism which is further strengthened by research by <ref type="bibr">Mariana</ref>  Teacher motivation can be external or internal. External motivation comes from social status, income, awards, and honors the community gives. Internal motivation can be sourced from interests, talents, competencies, education, vocation, and sincere dedication to the profession he is living. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Zulkifli (2014)</ref> states that work motivation plays an important role in efforts to improve the professionalism of a teacher. Harapan (2007) said that several factors influence professional ability, one of which is motivation.</p><p>Lewin <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Hadiyanto, 2016)</ref> argues that behavior results from the relationship between the personal staff/teacher and the environment. The existence of a direct influence between the school climate and the work motivation of teachers will certainly impact the professionalism of the teacher concerned.</p><p>Thus, if there is a direct relationship between school climate and teacher work motivation, and there is a direct relationship between teacher motivation and teacher professionalism. So it can be concluded that there is an indirect relationship between school climate and teacher professionalism through teacher work motivation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Based on the results of the analysis and discussion in this study, it can be concluded that there is a direct relationship between the principal's transformational leadership, work climate, and teacher professionalism through work motivation. In addition, there is an indirect relationship between the principal's transformational leadership, school climate, and teacher professionalism through work motivation.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Path Analysis Model X 1, X 2, Z, and Y</figDesc><graphic coords="3,95.50,137.40,404.45,132.10" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, Muhdi &amp; Miyono (2019) which states that there is the same effect between the two variables as research conducted by Ariyanti et al. (2019) who stated the same thing, were further strengthened by research conducted by Miyono &amp; Nanik (2021) which stated that the work climate contributed positively to teacher professionalism.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>states that work motivation plays an important role in efforts to improve the professionalism of a teacher. Harapan (2007) said that several factors influence professional ability, one of which is motivation. Then it was further strengthened by research conducted by Isnawati (2016), Triwibowo et al. (2019), and Kastawi et al. (2021), who also stated the same thing.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>et al. (2019), Ariyanti et al. (2019), and Miyono &amp; Nanik (2021), which state that same.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 : Summary of Pathway Analysis Results</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Structural Equation I</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Principal Transformational Leadership, School Climate, and Work Motivation on Teacher Professionalism</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Path Coefficient</cell><cell>t</cell><cell>Sig</cell><cell>R2 _</cell></row><row><cell>Principal's Transformational Leadership</cell><cell>0.555</cell><cell>8,263</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>0.252</cell></row><row><cell>School Climate</cell><cell>0.189</cell><cell>2,761</cell><cell>0.07</cell><cell>0.250</cell></row><row><cell>Work motivation</cell><cell>0.586</cell><cell>8144</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>0.586</cell></row><row><cell>Structural Equation II</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Work Motivation as an Intermediary Variable in the Relationship between Principal Transformational Leadership, School Climate, and Teacher Professionalism indirect</head><label></label><figDesc>motivation of State Elementary School teachers in Candi Laras Selatan District, Tapin Regency, obtained a value of 0.245. It means that there is an relationship between school climate and teacher professionalism through teacher work motivation. State Elementary School in Candi Laras Selatan District, Tapin Regency.</figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Principal Transformational Leadership Style, School Climate and Teacher Professional Commitment on Teacher Performance (Case Study at MTs Ma&apos;arif NU Banyumas Regency)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Adzkiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economics, Business and Accounting</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Principal Managerial Competence and Organizational Climate on the Professionalism of State Elementary School Teachers in Tengaran District, Semarang Regency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ariyanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Miyono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Retnaningdyastuti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>JMP) 8.2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Influence of Professional Teachers and School Climate on the Quality of Learning at SD Muhammadiyah Terpadu, Siman District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Philip</forename><surname>Dewi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Fatma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<pubPlace>Ponorogo Regency. UIN Ponorogo</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Relationship between Transformational Leadership and Teacher Motivation at Hasanuddin Lagoa High School</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Dzulfadhil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<pubPlace>North Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship between School Climate and Teacher Work Motivation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fujiaturrahman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Elementary FKIP UM Mataram</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hadiyanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Theory and Development of Classroom Climate and School Climate</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Jakarta</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kencana</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Post-Certification Teacher Performance (Study on Certification Recipient Teachers in South Sumatra Province)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hope</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of PPs National Seminar</title>
		<meeting>PPs National Seminar</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>PGRI University Palembang</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Influence of Principal Transformational Leadership and Work Motivation on Teacher Professionalism and Teacher Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Isnawati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Sanata Dharma University</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Yogyakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">In Thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Contribution of Work Motivation and the Role of the Principal on the Professionalism of High School Teachers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nurkolis</forename><surname>Kastawi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nugroho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Miyono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Influence of Principal Transformational Leadership on Work Motivation at the Integrated Islamic Elementary School (SDIT) Bina Amal Semarang</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kumalasari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<pubPlace>Semarang</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Semarang State University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">In Thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Organizational Climate and Teachers Work Motivation; A Case Study of Selected Schools in Prachinburi</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ladyong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thailand. Scholarly Journal of Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Principal Competence and School Climate on the Professionalism of State Junior High School Teachers in Rayon 06, Semarang Regency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mariana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Muhdi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Miyono</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Transformational Leadership Style and Work Professionalism on Employee Loyalty in LP3I Group</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Marzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jakarta: Business Lantern Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Contribution of Supervision and Work Climate to the Professionalism of Elementary School Teachers in Tahunan District of Jepara</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Miyono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Nanik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="173" />
			<pubPlace>Semarang</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>FPIPSKR Universitas PGRI Semarang</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Indonesian National Seminar (FPIPSKR</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mulyasa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Character Education Management. Jakarta: Earth Literacy</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Management Science Research: Philosophical and Practical Overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Noor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>Prenadamedia Group</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nurdin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Basyiruddin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Professional Teachers and Curriculum Implementation</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Jakarta</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Ciputat Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Professional Teachers and School Climate on the Quality of Learning at SD Muhamadiah Terpadu, Seman District, Ponorogo Regency</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ThesisPonorogoIAIN Ponorogo</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship between Teacher Professionalism and School Climate (Study on Teacher Professionalism at SMA 78 and SMA 112, West Jakarta)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Pratiwi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Thesis of the Faculty of Social and Political Sciences</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Depok</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Masters Program in Sociology</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Indonesia</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Transformational Leadership Style on Employee Performance with Work Motivation as an Intervening variable (Study on Employees at Binjai City Development)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Prayudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Principal&apos;s Transformational Leadership Style and Work Motivation on Teacher Competence (Study on Teachers of Vocational Schools in the Outskirts of Tulungagung Regency)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Purwanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cahyoadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Education (JPE)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Effect of Organizational Climate on Employee Work Motivation at the Regional Office of the Ministry of Religion of West Sumatra Province</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rahmawati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<pubPlace>Padang</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Padang State University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Learning Models Develop Teacher Professionalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rusman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Rajawali Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Basic Concepts &amp; Techniques of Educational Supervision in the Framework of Building Human Resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Piet</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sahertian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Rineka Cipta</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Influence of Principal Transformational Leadership and Work Motivation on the Professionalism of High School Economics Teachers in Yogyakarta City</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Sanata Dharma University</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Yogyakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Influence of Principal Transformational Leadership, Teacher Work Motivation, and School Climate on Teacher Performance in State Elementary Schools in Tulungagung Regency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Selena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Malang State University Repository</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Effect of School Organizational Climate on Teacher Work Motivation at Dabin I and II State Elementary Schools</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sucianti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>Kuwarasan District</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Kebumen Regency. Semarang</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Semarang State University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Influence of Principal&apos;s Transformational Leadership Style on Teacher Professionalism in Lovely Lovita Tanjungpinang Kindergarten</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sudewa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Raja Ali Haji Maritime University Publication Manuscript</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Principal Transformational Leadership and Work Motivation on Teacher Performance in North Jakarta State Vocational Schools</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wahidin</forename><surname>Sugiarto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Soefijanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">TADBIR: Journal of Educational Management Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="151" to="160" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Educational Management Research Variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Suhaimi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<pubPlace>Banjarmasin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Lambung Mangkurat University Printing</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factors Affecting Teacher Professionalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Syarafudin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ikawati</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mandalika Light</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Managerial Competence of Madrasah Principals and Work Motivation on Teacher Professionalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">&amp;</forename><surname>Triwibowo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Throne: Journal of Islamic Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Management: Theory, Practice and Research in Education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Usman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Earth Literacy</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Principal Leadership Style</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Windasari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Elementary Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="194" to="198" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Yukl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Leadership in Organizations. Jakarta: PT. Index</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Work Motivation, Certification, Welfare and Teacher Performance. Indonesian Psychology Journal Untag Surabaya</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Zulkifli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">There is an Open Access article, distributed under the term of the Creative Commons Attribution -Non Commercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>), which permits remixing, adapting and building upon the work for non-commercial use. provided the original work is properly cited</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
