<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Business ideology as a Reflection Reaction to socioeconomic Realities in conditions of constRuctive destaBilization</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Protsenko v. M., Bozhanova o. v., Protsenko a. v.</roleName><forename type="first">Prokhorova</forename><forename type="middle">V V</forename><surname>2022</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Candidate of Sciences (Economics)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Associate Professor</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bozhanova</forename><surname>Olena</surname></persName>
							<email>bozhanovaelena68@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Economics and Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Ukrainian State Univer- sity of Science and Technologies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Akademika Lazariana Str</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>49010</postCode>
									<settlement>Dnipro</settlement>
									<country key="UA">Ukraine</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Protsenko</forename><surname>Anastasiia</surname></persName>
							<email>protsenko_dinz@ukr.net</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Economics and Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Ukrainian State Univer- sity of Science and Technologies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Akademika Lazariana Str</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>49010</postCode>
									<settlement>Dnipro</settlement>
									<country key="UA">Ukraine</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Business ideology as a Reflection Reaction to socioeconomic Realities in conditions of constRuctive destaBilization</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.32983/2222-0712-2022-4-177-185</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T20:37+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>UDC 336 JEL Classification: D00</term>
					<term>D21 Prokhorova V. V., Protsenko V. M., Bozhanova O. V., Protsenko A. V. Business Ideology as a Reflection Reaction to Socioeconomic Realities in Conditions of Constructive Destabilization reflection, ideology of business, ideological influence, ideology, constructive destabilization UDC 336 JEL Classification: D00</term>
					<term>D21</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The aim of the study is to generalize the theoretical and applied aspects of the formation of an ideological space of a unified nature as a reflexive reaction of business to socioeconomic realities in conditions of constructive destabilization. Based on the carried out analysis of statistical data, it is proved that a fundamentally new direction comes into being for domestic economic science, i. e., studies of business behavior for the faster recovery of the country's economy, which requires the formalization of adequate instruments of a modern manager. Analyzing, systematizing and generalizing the scientific works of many scholars, the views of researchers on the definition of the concept of «ideology» were systematized, the principles of business ideology were allocated, the goal, types, signs, functions, principles, methods of ideological influence within the framework of building the ideology of management were defined. The presented publication forms theoretical and applied aspects of the ideological space of a unified nature as a reflexive reaction of business to socioeconomic realities. The issue of reflection as a system of reactions to socioeconomic realities is examined. The article considers the forms of reflection, the objective etiology of the formation of spheres of reflection through the prism of multidisciplinary connections. It is proved that the forms of reflection as a system of business reaction to socioeconomic realities in conditions of constructive destabilization have a tactical and strategic result. For a clear understanding and detailed analysis of the behavior of the problem under study, a block diagram of causal relationships is built. It is proved that reflection is an instrument for influencing the development of emotional intelligence, which explains the nature of the analytical choice of an alternative solution to the subject of economic relations and determines the possibilities of consolidated external information influence on this choice. Of practical importance is the universal model of the cognitive map of the behavioral model of business structures, which allows to explain the multi-vector format of development in rational, limited rational and irrational dimensions, combining the features of the model of constructive development of the destabilizing format and crisis phenomena.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Introduction. Subjects of socio-economic relations in Ukraine are currently operating in conditions of transformational changes in the business environment, caused by the influence of global trends in the development of the world ecosystem and large-scale penetration of digital technologies, which creates both significant opportunities and threats to stable functioning. Trends in the development of the global geopolitical environment confirm the existence of a problem of the functioning of business structures of a systemic nature depending on the field of origin and on this basis prove the permanent need to identify development imbalances from the point of view of the inconsistency of the parameters of their functioning with global growth trends in accordance with the existing strategic ideology of business as a reflection reaction to socio-economic realities in conditions of constructive destabilization.</p><p>Taking into account the urgent need to overcome existing imbalances in business development and taking into account the significant advantages of using digital technologies to achieve parameters of sustainable growth, it is advisable to consider a coherent approach to achieving a balance of static and dynamic parameters of development, which takes into account the multiplicative properties of the economic system under the conditions of overcoming the signs of constructive destabilization and achieving the state balance in the spatialprocess dimension through the mechanism of ensuring adaptive and harmonized changes.</p><p>In general, the causes of such changes are political, economic and social crisis phenomena at all levels of the national economy, which should become an impetus for the positive development of the management system of each individual busi-економіка та управління підприємствами ness structure, taking into account the peculiarities and specifics of their activities. It is expedient to consider the existing modern properties of parameterization of the socio-economic environment in the plane of the formation of signs of constructive destabilization. Today, the issue of finding ways out of the situation that has arisen due to the determination of the optimal safe level of positive development of business structures based on the balance of static and dynamic influencing factors is becoming relevant today.</p><p>Analysis of recent research and publications. Modern economic conditions, characterized by economic crisis and martial law in the country, contribute to the emergence of a complex of certain threats to the conduct of financial and economic activity of industrial enterprises of all sectors of the economy without exception.</p><p>It is impossible to say that the problems of business ideology, reflection and constructive destabilization of the economy are new, since different aspects of reflexia were the area of study by J. Locke, G. Leibniz, G. Hegel, as well as well-known natural researchers, financiers and economists, such as J. Soros, V. A. <ref type="bibr">Lefevr [11]</ref>, O. S. Anisimov [10], B. I. Birshtein, V. E. Lepsky <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[12]</ref>, D. A. Novikov and others. But now reflection forms of knowledge began to be applied to crisis processes taking place in the economy of the whole world, be trying to tie instability of political and socio-economic phenomena, taking place, to subjective knowledge about itself as a system. Annual international scientific and practical conferences with the presentation of research related to the in-depth study of the methodological foundations of reflexia are devoted to these aspects.</p><p>Undoubtedly, such experience of scientific and applied research in providing and revealing reflections instruments of development and management in the economy once again emphasizes the interdisciplinary aspect of such searches, which has already been mentioned in authors' works <ref type="bibr">[2]</ref>. It should also be emphasized that the components of reflexion are also connected with the questions of self-organization and self-government, to which more than one author's work was devoted <ref type="bibr">[3, p. 87-93; 4, p. 148-154; 5]</ref>, in particular, research of selforganization instruments in investment and innovation activity of enterprises <ref type="bibr">[6, p. 159-219; 7]</ref>.</p><p>The analysis of literary sources allows to conclude that the problems of constructive destabilization in different times were dealt with by such domestic scientists as Horal L. [13], Dzhedzhula V., Ivasechko O., Yepifanova I., Orel M., Onyshchenko O., , <ref type="bibr">Bozhanova,</ref><ref type="bibr">O. [14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">15]</ref>, Turchyn Y., Shkarlet S. and others. Among western researchers there is also a considerable scientific interest in this problem, in particular A. Molis, A. Yonushka, S. Klimanskis, L. Koyala, M. Lutvinskas, F. Umbah, etc.</p><p>Among the authors of fundamental studies on the methodology and theory of ideology should be noted the works of U. Outhwaite, R. Barth, N. Luhmann, K. Mannheim, K. Marx, Jose Ortega-y-Gasset, and M. Foucault. In modern domestic management thought of ideology's issues of management (management ideology) are explored in the works of Vikhanskyi O.S., Eyfremova V.S., Krasovskyi Yu. D., Naumova A. I., and others.</p><p>Combining these aspects into one scientific problem is very interesting from a scientific and practical point of view, because the ideology of business as an reflection reaction to socio-economic realities in the conditions of constructive destabilization is an important aspect of research of modern economic science.</p><p>The purpose of the study is to generalize the theoretical and practical aspects of the formation of an ideological space of a unified nature as a reflexive reaction of business to socio-economic realities in conditions of constructive destabilization.</p><p>Results. Modern socio-economic realities in which business is located are very complex. In the first months of the war, many business entities reduced production, stopped altogether or were completely destroyed due to the disruption of the logistics system. In addition, the blockade of the Black Sea seriously complicated the export of the main group of goods exported by the country. As a result of military operations, agricultural business did not receive the expected profit, the metallurgical industry suffered large losses. The population reduced spending on non-primary goods and services, thereby causing the collapse of certain businesses. As a result of the departure of a large number of people outside the country, consumer demand for goods and services decreased.</p><p>The government has taken a number of measures for supporting business, including lowering taxes, providing financial support to businesses and their employees, simplifying bureaucratic obstacles for business, and organizing assistance with moving to safer regions. The NBU has ensured the stable operation of banks and non-cash payment systems in non-occupied territories.</p><p>Enterprises operate in conditions of increasing external crisis phenomena and aggravation of internal development problems. The progressive aging of the fixed assets of most enterprises and the decrease in their innovative activity, the increase in personnel and investment «hunger», the discrepancy between the quality of service and the requirements of customers regarding the level of customer service significantly limit the potential for ensuring the stable growth of enterprises as business subjects and indicate the inconsistency of their development priorities with the modern dominant technological trends of modernization.</p><p>Deoccupation of territories is taking place today and there is an urgent need for renewable businesses. Currently, there is a need to change the ideology of business, as it is necessary to restore and develop the country, which is not possible without the development of small, medium and large businesses.</p><p>Socio-economic realities of sustainable growth prove the need to apply managerial innovations using the culminating influence of ideology as a basis for overcoming the existing destructive processes of functioning by implementing qualitative changes in the innovative-technological, intellectualpersonnel, investment and service-communication spheres of activities of enterprises of various economic sectors. In view of this, to ensure the balanced growth of domestic enterprises in the long term, it is necessary to implement a large-scale economic policy, built taking into account the reflection reactions of business to socio-economic realities in conditions of constructive destabilization, through the implementation of digital instruments for the transformation of the business model and the development of services, business processes and personnel competencies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>економіка та управління підприємствами</head><p>Today, the country's economy is in crisis, as business has not yet recovered from the challenges of the COVID-19 pandemic, when a full-scale invasion of Russian troops took place on the country's territory. There is a big drop of the economy regarding this. The State Statistics Service estimates a 37.2% drop in Ukraine's GDP in the second quarter of 2022. According to the results of April-July 2022, the real GDP of Ukraine decreased by 37.2% compared to the same period last year. At the same time, in the first quarter of 2022, a fall in GDP was observed by 15.1% on an annual basis. Inflation rates in Ukraine accelerated to 1.1% in August from 0.7% in July. Compared to August last year, prices in August 2022 increased by 23.8%. Core inflation accelerated to 2.1% in August 2022 from 1.2% in July. In 8 months of 2022, the inflation rate in Ukraine reached 19.5%.</p><p>The Ministry of Economy estimates the GDP decline in Ukraine by August 2022 at 35% in the annual calculation. The Ministry notes that the rate of economic decline is slowing down. The Ministry of Economy expects the GDP to fall to 33,2%, according to the results of 2022. The GMK Center reported that the National Bank of Ukraine predicts a 37.5% decline in the country's GDP in the second half of 2022 compared to the same period in 2021. In particular, in the third quarter of 2022, the country's economy will fall by 37.5%, and in the fourth -by 39.3%.</p><p>Thus, there is such a fundamentally new direction for domestic economic science as research of business behavior for the faster recovery of the country's economy. There is a need for formalization of adequate instruments of modern management.</p><p>As practice shows, no business can develop and be successful without setting strategic activity goals. The formulation of the business mission allows you to formalize actions and implement them on a systematic basis. A number of definitions of the concept of «mission» are used in management theory. B. Karloff emphasizes that the corporate mission characterizes the opportunity to do business, which the company focuses on taking into account market needs, the nature of consumers, product features and the presence of competitive advantages. The concept of a corporate mission has become widespread as an important element of the ideological base of the formation of an organization <ref type="bibr">[1, p. 63]</ref>.</p><p>A. Special attention is also paid to business ideology. In general, the term «ideology» was introduced in the 18th century by A. Destutt de Tracy, who, together with Etienne de Condillac, investigated the general principles of the formation of ideas. These scientists were the first to introduce this definition to denote the doctrine of ideas. This doctrine was supposed to act as the main principle for the development of science, as well as in socio-economic life. The concept of «ideology» was considered in their writings by such scientists as K. Mannheim, E. Fromm, D. Minor and others. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> shows the main definitions of the concept of «ideology2. A. mendra ideology is a system of expedient, scientifically based provisions designed to provide a clear explanation of social  reality [7]</p><p>The authors agree with the definition of O. V. Zolotaryova and O. Yu. Klementieva, who believe that «business ideology» is a collection of unordered ideas that express the interests of certain groups of people (business owners), and on the basis of which the relations of these communities to social truth in general and, in particular, between each member are understood and evaluated forms on this basis an assessment of the desirability or undesirability of this or that approach to management in, first of all, financial management through the transformation and overcoming of their inefficient elements (instruments).</p><p>Therefore, the process acts as an intellectual strategy and instructions (conclusions) for the further transformation of management in financial management, convinces and reorients to a new, more ideal vision of the prospects for the development of this business through an updated or new type of management <ref type="bibr">[8]</ref>.</p><p>The principles of business ideology should consist of systematicity, appropriateness of scale and intensity, continuity of influence, consistency of influence with other organizations and management processes.</p><p>The tools of business ideology are methods and techniques of implementing a certain ideology with clarification, creation of conditions for personal development of employees, relocation of employees taking into account ideological criteria (fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). In recent decades, the phenomenon of reflection is very interesting from the point of view of making managerial decisions in the economy. This is determined by the prerequisites for the formation of behavioral economics and outlined by the most important factors underlying decision-making by the business structure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>економіка та управління підприємствами</head><p>Reflection as a decision-making model explains the choice of one of the alternatives in conditions of bipolarity of choice and is an analytical instrument for determining the possibility of providing external informational influence on this choice (fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>).</p><p>Any business structure as an economic system is a social system and involves the presence of interacting economic entities that are both inside and outside this economic system.</p><p>Each subject of the management process (management activity) is to a certain extent self-sufficient, self-critical, professionally flawless, analytically focused in making objective strategic decisions. Moreover, these decisions are not necessarily consistent with the development strategy and goals of the economic system.</p><p>Economic decisions do not always correspond to the economic interests of business structures in the process of implementing the business model of their development. The motivation of human activity is far from being limited to economic interests, and the making of economic decisions is influenced by many other factors: cultural, moral, cognitive, psychological, informational, etc. Interesting, from a practical point of view, is the of issues of reflection as a system of reactions to social-economic realities.</p><p>Destabilization, as a component of the economic activity of business entities, is observed in market conditions due to the high level of uncertainty and globalization of economic processes. In this regard, in order to make effective management decisions, «it is necessary to clearly distinguish the main Re ection as a process of perception and response to changes in conditions in the conditions of destructive development Business structures are an economic system, a part of the production or economic process separated as a result of the social division of labor, capable of satisfying certain needs of potential consumers independently or in cooperation with other systems through the production of goods or services by this system.</p><p>Factors destabilizing the economic system are classified depending on the place of origin into external and internal. The most typical external factors are: measures of competitors, sudden changes in the economic situation of customers, crises, social events, structural changes in society, weather conditions, conditions on the labor market, legislation, regulatory acts, measures to regulate social processes, population migration, changes in money markets, changes in the international situation and related events, changes in the relations of political forces; new technologies, measures carried out by the trade union movement; activities of mass media, changes in positions and assessments. The most typical internal destabilizing factors include: personal relationships; overload at work; vacations, unplanned and forced; diseases; events held by the trade union movement; positive and negative unexpected situations; dismissal or hiring of new employees; expansion or reduction of the organization's activities; malfunctions of machines and equipment; customer or staff misconduct; actions of influential persons that contribute to or hinder the activities of the organization; factors of labor protection and safety; initiatives and ideas; information; interviews; thanks and reprimands; motivation <ref type="bibr">[9]</ref>.</p><p>It should be noted that the problems of researching issues of business ideology as a reflexive reaction to socio-economic realities in conditions of constructive destabilization are caused by a number of features. On the one hand, it is the multifacetedness and interconnectedness of the processes taking place. Because of this, it is impossible to single out and investigate individual phenomena in detail. Thus, all phenomena should be studied in aggregate, because the behavior of the economic system is a loosely structured process, the study of which features use scenario modeling as part of building cognitive models. On the other hand, there is a lack of sufficient quantitative information about the dynamics of economic processes, which is necessary for their modeling and forecasting.</p><p>For a clear understanding and detailed analysis of the behavior of the investigated problem, a necessary step is to build a structural diagram of cause-and-effect relationships. The construction of a cognitive map becomes an absolutely necessary element of the analysis of difficult to formalize factors of influence on the phenomenon under study. At the same time, factors are identified using content analysis, expert analysis, and statistical analysis of real data.</p><p>A detailed study of modern scientific developments regarding the cognitive modeling of the socio-economic development of business entities confirms the feasibility of constructing a cognitive map (fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>).</p><p>Thus, the use of the given dependencies allows you to develop alternative options for the development of events and adjust management decisions. At the same time, the lack of quantitative criteria for predicting development parameters is a drawback of the presented dependencies. In this connection, it is appropriate to combine the instruments of cognitive modeling with the achievements of the concept of a balanced system of indicators and to subordinate the planning system to such a combination. At the same time, it is advisable to implement the elements in the form of an indicative planning procedure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion.</head><p>The global ecosystem for the development of business entities has undergone significant changes. The liberalization of trade in goods and services, the transnationalization of capital and business, the informatization and technologization of the economy and society, the acceleration of the development of technological innovations and the increase in the market capitalization of companies in the aggregate led to the processes of destabilizing development and the search for configurations of constructive solutions as a reaction to the transformation of the economic environment. The popularization of the formation of an ideological space of a unified character as a reflection reaction of business entities caused a significant reformatting of the system of communication connections based on a reflexive approach. This kind of radical changes in the business environment qualitatively reformatted the activities of business structures, orienting their development trends to changing business models and modernizing key business processes.</p><p>Thus, reflection is an instrument of influence on the development of emotional intelligence, which explains the nature of the analytical choice of an alternative decision of the subject of economic relations and determines the possibilities of consolidated external information influence on this choice. The tactical task of the development of reflection as the basis of a reflexive approach in the study of the nature of decisionmaking is the development of a universal approach that will allow the use of a reflexive approach in the study of the economic process. The universal model of the cognitive structures of business is of immediate great practical importance, which will allow to explain the multi-vector format of development in the rational, limitedly rational and irrational dimensions, combining the features of the model of constructive development of the destabilizing format, crisis phenomena. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>LITERATURE</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FormationFig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Theoretical and applied aspects of the formation of an ideological space of a unified character as a reflexive response of business to socio-economic Source: author's development</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Reflection as a system of responses to social and economic realitiesSource: author's development</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Thompson and A. Strickland believes that «what the company is going to do and what it wants to become is the company's mission» [2, p. 47].</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 Definition of the concept «ideology» in economic literature Author Definition of the concept «ideology»</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note><p><p><p><p><p><p><p>K. mannheim</p>a biased reflection of social reality that expresses the interests of certain groups or classes that are in power and  seek to maintain the existing order of things</p>[3, p. 276]    </p>E. Fromm a ready-made «intellectual product» that is distributed by the press, speakers, and ideologues in order to  manipulate the mass of people with a goal that has nothing to do with ideology and very often is completely opposite to it [4, p. 20] D. minor a set of ideas with a certain «content», usually normative; the form of the internal logical structure characteristic  of the ideas in the set; «locus» of social interaction</p>[5, p. 318]    </p>y. mullins ideology consists of four basic characteristics: it must dominate cognitive ability, be able to guide evaluative  judgments, serve as an instruction for action, and be consistent</p>[6]    </p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1. карлоф Б. деловая стратегия. москва : Экономика, 1991. 239 с. 2. томпсон а. а., Стрикленд а. дж. Стратегический менеджмент. искусство разработки и реализации стратегии. москва : Банки и биржи, Юнити, 1998. 576 с. 3. маннгейм к. идеология и утопия. москва : Юрист, 1994. 704 с. 4. Фромм е. втеча від свободи. Харків : кСд, 2019. 288 с. 5. minar D. Ideology and Political Behavior. Midwest Journal of Political Science. 1961. no. 4. р. 317-331. 6. mullins W. the Concept of Ideology: An Analysis and Evaluation. URL: http://www.academia.edu/8972995/ management_and_Organisational_Behaviour_L_mullins_Pitman_ 7. мендра а. основы социологии. москва : nota Bene, 1998. 344 с. 8. Золотарьова о. в., клементьєва о. Ю. Зарубіжний досвід формування корпоративної культури та можливості його</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Source: author's development</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Багатоаспектність формування процесу управління безпекою розвитку промислового підприємства. Проблеми економіки. 2020. № 2. C. 240-246. 14. прохорова в., Божанова о., дуднєва Ю. конвергентнокогнітивні основи інноваційного розвитку промислових підприємств. Адаптивне управління: теорія і практика</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.33296/2707-0654-10(20)-07</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.economy.nayka.com.ua/?op=1&amp;z=59699" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Становлення стратегічних суб&apos;єктів: постановка проблеми рефлексії. Процеси рефлексій і управління</title>
		<title level="s">концептуальний підхід до рівнів формування економічної дестабілізації та класифікації її чинників. Економічний вісник Донбасу</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2009. 2004. 2003. 2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">496</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">С. 5-23. 13. гораль л. т.</note>
	<note>С. 57-66. 10. анисимова С. а. нелинейные модели теории рефлексивного управления. Известия вузов. Прикладная нелинейная динамика. Серія Економіка. 2021. № 10 (20</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">methodological aspects of assessing the sustainable development of energy companies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Prokhorova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Bozhanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Putro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Azizova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1088/1755-1315/628/1/012011</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">th International Scientific Conference on Sustainability in Energy and Environmental Science</title>
		<title level="s">Conference. Series: Earth and Environmental Science</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ivano-Frankivsk, Ukraine</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-10-22">2021. 21-22 October 2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">628</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12011</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Us yu. V. Formation of motivational mechanism in strategic management of a diversified enterprise. Naukovyi Visnyk Natsionalnoho Hirnychoho Universytetu</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Prokhorova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Zalutska</forename><surname>Kh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="185" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Transition to a new paradigm of human capital development in the dynamic environment of the knowledge economy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Pylypenko Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Pylypenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Prokhorova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dubiei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yu</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>Naukovyi Visnyk Natsionalnoho Hirnychoho Universytetu</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="170" to="176" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">nelineynyye modeli teorii refleksivnogo upravleniya</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Anisimova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>nonlinear models of the theory of Reflexive Control</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Prikladnaya nelineynaya dinamika</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Izvestiya Vuzov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="113" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Vtecha vid svobody</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fromm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Escape from Freedom</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bahatoaspektnist formuvannia protsesu upravlinnia bezpekoiu rozvytku promyslovoho pidpryiemstva&quot; [multifaceted nature of Forming the Process of management of Industrial Enterprise Development Security]</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kharkiv ; Horal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Problemy ekonomiky</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="240" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019. 2020</date>
			<publisher>KSD</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Kontseptualnyi pidkhid do rivniv formuvannia ekonomichnoi destabilizatsii ta klasyfikatsii yii chynnykiv&quot; [Conceptual Approach to the Levels of Formation of Economic Destabilization and Classification of Its Factors]</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Isaieva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>Ekonomichnyi visnyk Donbasu</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="66" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Delovaya strategiya [Business Strategy]. moscow: Ekonomika</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Karlof</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Stanovlennia stratehichnykh subiektiv: postanovka problemy refleksii</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lefevr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Refleksiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Kyiv: Kogito-tsentr, 2003. Lepskyi, V. ye. Formation of Strategic Subjects: Posing the Problem of Reflection</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ideologiya i utopiya [Ideology and Utopia]. moscow: yurist, 1994. mendra, A. Osnovy sotsiologii [Fundamentals of Sociology]. moscow: nota Bene, 1998. minar, D</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Manngeym</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Mullins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1088/1755-1315/628/1/012011</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.academia.edu/8972995/management_and_Or-ganisational_Behaviour_L_mullins_Pitman_Prokhorova" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Midwest Journal of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="317" to="331" />
			<date type="published" when="1961">2002. 1961. 2021. 2020</date>
			<pubPlace>Ivano-Frankivsk</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>methodological aspects of assessing the sustainable development of energy companies</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Formation of motivational mechanism in strategic management of a diversified enterprise</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Prokhorova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kh</forename><forename type="middle">Ya</forename><surname>Zalutska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yu</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Us</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="185" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Naukovyi Visnyk Natsionalnoho Hirnychoho Universytetu</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Konverhentno-kohnityvni osnovy innovatsiinoho rozvytku promyslovykh pidpryiemstv&quot; [Convergent and Cognitive Bases of Innovative Development of Industrial Enterprises]. Adaptyvne upravlinnia: teoriia i praktyka</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Prokhorova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Bozhanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yu</forename><surname>Dudnieva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.33296/2707-0654-10(20)-07</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Seriia Ekonomika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strategicheskiy menedzhment. Iskusstvo razrabotki i realizatsii strategii [Strategic management. the Art of Developing and Executing a Strategy]. moscow: Banki i birzhi; yunItI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yu</forename><surname>Pylypenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.economy.nayka.com.ua" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Foreign Experience in the Formation of Corporate Culture and the Possibility of its Adaptation by Domestic Business</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">2021. 1998. 2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="170" to="176" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Naukovyi Visnyk Natsionalnoho Hirnychoho Universytetu</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Zarubizhnyi dosvid formuvannia korporatyvnoi kultury ta mozhlyvosti yoho adaptatsii vitchyznianym biznesom. op=1&amp;z=5969 Стаття надійшла до редакції 12.11.2022 р</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
