<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Development of a control system for sorting agricultural products according to specified criteria</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sergey</forename><surname>Zakozhurnikov</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Higher Mathematics and Programming Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">MIREA -Russian Technological University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Prospect Vernadsky, 78</addrLine>
									<postCode>119454</postCode>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Galina</forename><surname>Zakozhurnikova</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Heat Engineering and Hydraulics Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Volgograd State Technical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Lenin avenue, 28</addrLine>
									<postCode>400005</postCode>
									<settlement>Volgograd</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Development of a control system for sorting agricultural products according to specified criteria</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1051/e3sconf/202339003019</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T20:36+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The article presents a process control system for sorting agricultural products. The technological process of sorting is described, the composition of the system is indicated, the sorting algorithm is developed. ProgramLab software was used as the modeling environment. Color and weight were selected as sorting criteria. The parameters at the input of the control object, which have the greatest influence on the process were selected. The output parameters were the conveyor speed and the final position of the sorting object. A scheme of cause-and-effect relationships of the sorting process is obtained. A block diagram of the sorting process has been developed. A mathematical model for calculating the speed of a conveyor depending on the distance between the robotic arm and the conveyor, as well as between the robotic arm and the parts unloading points was obtained. A 3d model of the sorting process has been developed. Three basic scenarios for the location of places for unloading agricultural products are considered. The introduction of the developed system will help reduce number of rejects during sorting, increase the efficiency of the sorting process and improve economic performance. Improving the sorting process will help reduce equipment wear and extend equipment life.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>In modern conditions, work on sorting objects at a number of agricultural enterprises is still carried out manually. Consequently, there is a large amount of defects and low efficiency. Automation of the sorting process is an urgent task for agriculture, food, pharmaceutical, and waste processing industries.</p><p>The aim of the work is to develop an automated control system for the process of sorting products according to several criteria <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[3]</ref>. Achieving this goal will lead to minimizing human participation in this process, therefore, the number of errors will decrease, and the sorting speed will also increase. The introduction of an automatic control system for the sorting process will make it possible to achieve a more efficient energy resources usage, and therefore a significant economic effect for the enterprise <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">5]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">The technological process description</head><p>A typical task is to sort agricultural products moving along a conveyor, depending on a number of predetermined parameters.</p><p>The system consists of several conveyor lines, each of which can move objects at different speeds, a Dobot Magician robotic arm, a diffuse photoelectric sensor (position sensor), a color sensor, and a mass sensor <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref>. The simulation of the system operation took place in the ProgramLab software. In the model representation, parallelepipeds of red, yellow, green and blue colors, having different masses, were considered as agricultural products. Color and weight were considered as sorting criteria. Depending on the signals received from the sensors, the control system decides whether the object corresponds to one or another given group and sends a control signal to the control device and to the conveyor.</p><p>The object is placed on the main conveyor and travels along it to the diffuse photoelectric sensor. The sensor is triggered, the controller <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref> reads the signal from it, sends a control action to the conveyor, after which it stops. Next, the robotic arm <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref> grabs the object with the help of a special nozzle and transfers it to the color sensor and the mass sensor. The robotic arm consists of the following parts (from bottom to top): base, arm, boom and working tool (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). All of them are interconnected by means of servo drives (connection 1, connection 2, connection 3, connection 4, respectively), which makes it possible to achieve a large volume of the working area of the robotic arm. Depending on the data read from the sensors, the robot-manipulator moves the object to a place determined by a given work algorithm. Next, the main conveyor is turned on again and the next object is processed. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Control system creation</head><p>For the correct operation of the control system, it is important to correctly select the influencing input and output parameters of the system <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9]</ref>. The initial position of the object, color and mass were chosen as input parameters. As output parameters conveyor speed and final position of the object were chosen. As a result, a scheme of cause-and-effect relationships of the sorting process was obtained (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>). Every control system includes a control object and a control device. Let us consider a conveyor as a control object, a controller as a control device, and a Dobot Magician robotic arm as an actuator. The processing of the signals received from the sensors, as well as the issuance of signals to the actuators, is carried out by the Owen controller and its auxiliary units. For the correct operation of the actuator, it is necessary to correctly set the robot arm to its original position and return to it, indicate the initial position of the object when it reaches the position sensor, and correctly indicate the coordinates of the places where objects are stored depending on the data received from the sensors. The scheme of the sorting process control system is shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>. Mathematical model for calculating conveyor speed Let the conveyor have a belt length L. The distance from the robotic arm to the conveyor is constant and equal to l 1 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>). The distance from the conveyor to shipping points 1, 2 and 3 is also constant and is equal to l 2 , l 3 and l 4 , respectively. The distances from the shipping points to the base of the robot will be denoted as l 5 , l 6 and l 7 , respectively. In the controller, we put the following algorithm for working with a robot manipulator: the robot arm travels the distance from the initial location point to the end of the main conveyor of the system (point 4) and captures the object. Then it goes either to point 1, or to point 2, or to point 3, depending on the readings of the color and mass sensors, and ships agricultural products. After that, the boom of the robotic arm returns to its original position on the base. The process is cyclical. Let's denote as t 54 the time of movement of the arrow of the robotic manipulator from point 5 to point 4, t 3 is the time spent on capturing one object. Let's denote as t Î” -the time required to transfer the object from point 4 to the point of shipment. Accordingly, t Î” can take one of three values: either t 41 , or t 42 , or t 43 . Where t 41 is the time spent on moving the object by the robot-manipulator from point 4 to point 1, t 42 is the time spent on moving the object by the robot-manipulator from point 4 to point 2, t 43 is the time spent on moving the object by the robot-manipulator from point 4 to point 3.</p><p>Let us assume that the capture of each object takes the same time t 3 . Therefore, t 3 = const 1 . We also assume that the shipment of one object takes the same time to each time. value t 0 = const 2 .</p><p>Let us represent the time of one cycle of the sorting system t 1c in the form (1):</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">t 1c = t 54 + t Ğ· + t Î” + t o + t Ğ² ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where t Î” can be determined from the expression (2):</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">t Î” ğ‘¡ , ğ‘–ğ‘“ ğ‘¡â„ğ‘’ ğ‘ğ‘œğ‘›ğ‘‘ğ‘–ğ‘¡ğ‘–ğ‘œğ‘› 1 ğ‘–ğ‘  ğ‘ ğ‘ğ‘¡ğ‘–ğ‘ ğ‘“ğ‘–ğ‘’ğ‘‘, ğ‘¡ , ğ‘–ğ‘“ ğ‘¡â„ğ‘’ ğ‘ğ‘œğ‘›ğ‘‘ğ‘–ğ‘¡ğ‘–ğ‘œğ‘› 2 ğ‘–ğ‘  ğ‘ ğ‘ğ‘¡ğ‘–ğ‘ ğ‘“ğ‘–ğ‘’ğ‘‘, ğ‘¡ , ğ‘–ğ‘“ ğ‘¡â„ğ‘’ ğ‘ğ‘œğ‘›ğ‘‘ğ‘–ğ‘¡ğ‘–ğ‘œğ‘› 3 ğ‘–ğ‘  ğ‘ ğ‘ğ‘¡ğ‘–ğ‘ ğ‘“ğ‘–ğ‘’ğ‘‘,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where condition 1: color is green, weight is more than 50 g, condition 2: color is not green, weight is more than 50 g, condition 3: any color, weight is less than 50 g. Parameter t Ğ² is the time required to return the robotic arm to its original position after the object has been shipped. It can be determined by relation (3):</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">t Ğ² ğ‘¡ , ğ‘–ğ‘“ ğ‘¡â„ğ‘’ ğ‘ğ‘œğ‘›ğ‘‘ğ‘–ğ‘¡ğ‘–ğ‘œğ‘› 1 ğ‘–ğ‘  ğ‘ ğ‘ğ‘¡ğ‘–ğ‘ ğ‘“ğ‘–ğ‘’ğ‘‘, ğ‘¡ , ğ‘–ğ‘“ ğ‘¡â„ğ‘’ ğ‘ğ‘œğ‘›ğ‘‘ğ‘–ğ‘¡ğ‘–ğ‘œğ‘› 2 ğ‘–ğ‘  ğ‘ ğ‘ğ‘¡ğ‘–ğ‘ ğ‘“ğ‘–ğ‘’ğ‘‘, ğ‘¡ , ğ‘–ğ‘“ ğ‘¡â„ğ‘’ ğ‘ğ‘œğ‘›ğ‘‘ğ‘–ğ‘¡ğ‘–ğ‘œğ‘› 3 ğ‘–ğ‘  ğ‘ ğ‘ğ‘¡ğ‘–ğ‘ ğ‘“ğ‘–ğ‘’ğ‘‘,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Let us take the speed of the robot-manipulator in each section of the sorting scheme to be constant and equal toV Ñ€Ğ¼ . Therefore, the times t 54 , t 41 , t 42 , t 43 can be expressed according to formulas (4)- <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(7)</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">t 54 = Ñ€Ğ¼ ,<label>(4)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">t 41 = Ñ€Ğ¼ ,<label>(5)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">t 42 = Ñ€Ğ¼ , (<label>6</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_6">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">t 43 = Ñ€Ğ¼ ,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>The return times t 15 , t 25 , t 35 can be determined by relations ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">8</ref>)- <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(10)</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">t 15 = Ñ€Ğ¼ , (<label>8</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_9">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">t 25 = Ñ€Ğ¼ , (<label>9</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">)</formula><p>E3S Web of Conferences 390, 03019 (2023) <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1051/e3sconf/202339003019">https://doi.org/10.1051/e3sconf/202339003019</ref> AGRITECH-VIII 2023</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">t 35 = Ñ€Ğ¼ ,<label>(10)</label></formula><p>Taking into account formulas ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">2</ref>) - <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(10)</ref>, expression (1) will take the form <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(11)</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">t 1c = Ñ€Ğ¼ + t Ğ· + Ñ€Ğ¼ + t o + Ñ€Ğ¼ , (<label>11</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">)</formula><p>where i is either 2, 3, or 4, j is either 5, 6, or 7.</p><p>The conveyor speed V k can be found from relation <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(12)</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">V k = Ñ ,<label>(12)</label></formula><p>Finally ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_16">13</ref>):</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">V k = Ñ€Ğ¼ Ğ· Ñ€Ğ¼ Ğ¾ Ñ€Ğ¼ , .<label>(13)</label></formula><p>Therefore, we have obtained a relationship between the speed of the conveyor line and the distances between the robotic arm and the conveyor, as well as between the robotic arm and the places for unloading objects. As a result, knowing the readings of the sensors and the sorting algorithm, you can get the optimal speed of the conveyor belt, thereby reducing equipment wear and extending its service life.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Sorting process 3d model</head><p>To check the adequacy of the mathematical model for calculating the speed of the conveyor belt, as well as to visualize the process under study, a 3d model was developed in the ProgramLab software (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>). The sorting system being simulated <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref> consists of a main conveyor and three distribution conveyors. To simulate the flow of objects entering the conveyor, an element called the Object Generator (the blue cube on the right side of the diagram) was added. Itcan create rectangular boxes with a random set of properties. They replace objects in the 3d model. Once created, the cuboid moves along the main conveyor belt. It passes through several sensors: a color sensor, a mass sensor and a diffuse photoelectric position sensor. In accordance with the information received from the sensors, the robot moves the box to one of the three branches of the conveyor according to the specified work algorithm described earlier. After that, the box hits an element called the Object Destroyer (one of the three orange cubes). Next, the Object Generator creates a new object with a random set of properties. The process is cyclical.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Improving the sorting process</head><p>It is necessary to find the optimal location of the places for unloading objects so that the unloading time is minimal. It is logical to assume that the unloading points should be located as close as possible to the robot and to each other. But physically, there may be difficulties associated with loading and unloading operations, emergencies, etc.</p><p>First, we impose restrictions on the process under consideration. Let the distance from the robot to the place of unloading in all three cases be not less than the fixed value "a". The value a &gt; 0. The sorting algorithm corresponds to the one described earlier. The probability of an object hitting the conveyor for each of the three cases described in the algorithm is the same.</p><p>Consider three basic scenarios.</p><p>In the first scenario, the unloading points are located at the vertices of a regular triangle (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>). The distance from each vertex to the robot is a = 28 cm. A full-scale experiment was carried out to unload three objects of different parameters. The unloading time was 12.4 s. In the second scenario, the unloading points are located on the same straight line (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7</ref>). The distance from the central unloading point to the robot is a, the distance from the remaining two places is respectively greater than a. The distance between adjacent places of unloading was also taken equal to a. The total time of the full-scale experiment on sorting three different objects was 10.3 s. In the third scenario, the unloading points are located on a circular arc (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8</ref>). The radius of the circle is a. The distance between adjacent places of unloading was also taken equal to a. The sorting time for this arrangement was 9.3 s. Scenario No. 3 was recognized as the most profitable, since the sorting time for it turned out to be the smallest.</p><p>The resulting sorting system can be improved in several ways, for example, by using a delta robot as an actuator. The delta robot from other types of robots in its higher speed <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref>. This allows it to excel in sorting and stacking a large flow of products. Also, the actual solution will be the introduction of a machine vision system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Conclusion</head><p>In the present work, a sorting process control system has been developed. A mathematical model for calculating the conveyor speed is proposed. A 3d model of the sorting process has been developed. The sorting process has been improved. Three options for the location of sorting places are proposed and the most time-efficient option is found. The introduction of the designed control system will increase the speed of sorting, reduce the amount of defects in production, increase the safety and reliability of the conveyor line.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Components of a robotic arm where J1, J2, J3, J4 are the connections of the main parts of the robot through servo drives.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,111.36,371.86,273.36,114.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Cause-and-effect relationships of the sorting system.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,117.36,68.26,260.64,125.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Sorting process control system.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,109.20,331.54,277.92,133.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Block diagram of the sorting system where A is a conveyor, B is a robotic arm, H is the starting point of the object's movement.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,116.40,68.26,263.52,113.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. The sorting system 3d model.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,104.88,341.92,285.78,245.04" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Scenario â„–1.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,160.80,349.06,174.24,206.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Scenario â„– 2.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,103.20,246.58,289.44,261.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Scenario â„–3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>E3S</head><label></label><figDesc>Web of Conferences 390, 03019 (2023) https://doi.org/10.1051/e3sconf/202339003019 AGRITECH-VIII 2023</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>E3S Web of Conferences 390, 03019 (2023) https://doi.org/10.1051/e3sconf/202339003019 AGRITECH-VIII 2023</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>E3s</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1051/e3sconf/202339003019AGRITECH-VIII2023</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1051/e3sconf/202339003019AGRITECH-VIII2023" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">390</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3019</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mammadova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Aliyeva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lect. Not. in Net. and Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">362</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lect. Not. on Dat. Eng. and Com. Tech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nekotorye voprosy sozdanija jelektronno-upravljajushhih sistem vrashhajushhihsja ob&apos;ektov, Innovative technologies in electronics and instrumentation: Collection of reports of the Russian scientific and technical conference with international participation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Merkulov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ju</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Haritonova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Zakozhurnikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<pubPlace>Moscow, Russian</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>MIREA -Russian Technological University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Umen&apos;shenie jenergopotreblenija putjom vnedrenija sistemy Â«umnyj domÂ». Radiojelektronika, jelektrotehnika i jenergetika: tezisy dokladov Dvadcat&apos; vos&apos;moj mezhdunarodnoj nauchno-tehnicheskoj konferencii studentov i aspirantov</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Raff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<publisher>Limited Liability Company Center for Printing Services RADUGA</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Moscow, Russian</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mousavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vyatkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Aut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Cons</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Primenenie fotojelektricheskih datchikov na proizvodstve, Opticheskie tehnologii, materialy i sistemy: Sbornik dokladov Mezhdunarodnoj nauchno-tehnicheskoj konferencii IPTIP RTU MIRJeA</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lavrenov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Zakozhurnikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<pubPlace>Moscow, Russian</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>MIREA -Russian Technological University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Renjini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Univ. J. of Scien</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">4 Russian (2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Romanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Russ. Tech. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Jingyu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cungen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yulong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lanyun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. of Cont</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">100759</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dorokhov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aksenov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sibirev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Agr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development of a Simulation Automated System for Address Sorting of Correspondence, Conference &quot;INTERAGROMASH 2021</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Morozov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kuzmin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vershinin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Precision Agriculture and Agricultural Machinery Industry</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Rostov-on-Don; Russian</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022. 2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Conference proceedings</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Automated Sorting Methods Modernization of Municipal Solid Waste Processing System</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Kokoulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Uzhakov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Tur</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings, International Russian Automation Conference</title>
		<meeting>International Russian Automation Conference<address><addrLine>RusAutoCon; Sochi, Russian</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020. 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tamizi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ahmadi Kashani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Azad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kalhor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Tale</forename><surname>Masouleh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. of Cont</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Azad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ansari Rad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hairi Yazdi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Tale</forename><surname>Masouleh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kalhor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mecc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Youssef</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bayoumy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Atia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1051/e3sconf/202339003019</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1051/e3sconf/202339003019" />
		<title level="m">Math. Mod. of Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">390</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3019</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Prob. 8, 5 (2021) E3S Web of Conferences</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Agritech-Viii</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
