<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Development of an Ecoliteracy Scale Intended for Adults and Testing an Alternative Model by Structural Equation Modelling</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Emel</forename><surname>Okur-Berberoglu</surname></persName>
							<email>emelokur17@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">LIC (Livestock Improvement Corporation)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hamilton</settlement>
									<country key="NZ">NEW ZEALAND</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Development of an Ecoliteracy Scale Intended for Adults and Testing an Alternative Model by Structural Equation Modelling</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">2146-0329</idno>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T17:43+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Ecoliteracy</term>
					<term>ecological intelligence</term>
					<term>emotional intelligence</term>
					<term>economy</term>
					<term>social intelligence</term>
					<term>green consumer behaviour</term>
					<term>explanatory factor analysis</term>
					<term>confirmatory factor analysis</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>To cite this article: Okur-Berberoğlu, E. (2018). Development of an ecoliteracy scale intended for adults and testing an alternative model by structural equation modelling. International Electronic Journal of Environmental Education, 8(2), 15-34 I have nomadic ancestors and we have learnt some of the knowledge by intergenerational oral and experiential transfers. Nevertheless, Shipibo indigenous people from Peru (Roberst&amp; Dev, 2015)  or Ubuntu philosophy from Africa (Shumba, 2011) have similar environmental and sustainable transfers in order to survive such as cooking, healing, appreciation, celebration. Shumba (2011) determines this kind of ethical and sustainable environmental issues as ecological intelligence.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>When I was a child, my grandmother wanted me to pick 'gundelia' (The local name at Mediterranean Mountains is 'kenger'; the Latin name is Gundelia tournefortii)' and 'purslane' (The local name at Mediterranean Mountains is 'tokmakan'; the Latin name is Portulaca oleracea) up from the mountains in order to make coffee and cook. We were living in a rural area and it was difficult to find any stuff easily. Later I learned that if there was a scarcity, people were using 'gundelia' as a kind of coffee and 'purslane' as a food resource. We were going to the mountains as a group of children and picking up what and how much we needed to gundelia and purslane therefore we knew that we could pick them up next seasons. These were informal sustainability learnings for me because I was 6 or 7 years-old at that time however I can still remember that gundelia and purslane are used in order to make coffee and food.</p><p>Moreover, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Goleman (2006</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Goleman ( , 2009) )</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">McCallum (2005)</ref> also enrich ecological intelligence concept with social intelligence, emotional intelligence and economy. Both researchers evaluate ecological intelligence in terms of Western perspective by economy. Similarly <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Esposito (2009)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kapogianni (2015)</ref> evaluate ecoliteracy within environment-economy relationship however these experimental studies are not enough to determine ecoliteracy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ecoliteracy</head><p>According to the literature, ecoliteracy is to understand and internalise sustainable ecological relationship in the nature and to transfer this sustainable lifestyle to daily life despite the fact that ecoliteracy does not have only one and unique definition <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Öhman, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">ESD, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kapogianni, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lira, Steinicke &amp; Garcia, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tursi, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">McBride, Brewer, Berkowitz and Borrie, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Esposito, 2009)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1. Alternative model of ecoliteracy</head><p>The core subject of ecoliteracy is sustainability <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Orr, 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Öhman, 2016)</ref> and ESD Report <ref type="bibr">(2015, p.38)</ref> especially emphasizes that everybody who works and studies on sustainable development should design indicators and metrics in order to evaluate ecoliteracy. The aim of this study, therefore, is to develop an ecoliteracy scale intended for adults and to test an alternative ecoliteracy model (Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). There has not been found yet any ecoliteracy scale or alternative model according to the literature review.</p><p>The common points of ecoliteracy are to have sustainable, affective, cognitive, behavioural roots <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Goleman et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">McBride et al, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Pilgrim, Smith &amp; Pretty, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Orr, 1992)</ref>.These roots refer to some subcomponents such as ecological intelligence, social intelligence, emotional intelligence, economy and green consumer behaviour. I designed an ecoliteracy model with these subcomponents according to the literature (Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). According to this model economy, emotional and social intelligences are subsets of ecological intelligence. Ecological intelligence has directly link to green consumer behaviours at the second stage of the model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Economy</head><p>Emotiona l intelligence Social intelligence</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ecological intelligence</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Green consumer behaviour</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ecological intelligence</head><p>One of the main subsets of ecoliteracy is ecological intelligence because this concept is related to either holistic perspective or sustainability. The main aims of ecological intelligence are to develop social and environmental responsibility <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Shumba, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Sterling, 2009)</ref> and awareness, to think critically <ref type="bibr">(Bowers, 2010)</ref>, to pursue cooperative learning <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Sterling, 2009)</ref>, and to bring about behavioural change in the long-term <ref type="bibr">(ESD, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Bowers, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Sterling, 2009)</ref>. Ecological intelligence is related to the cognitive and affective areas of the brain <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Shumba, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Sterling, 2009)</ref>; therefore both side of learners' brains should be supported. Ecological intelligence does not also ignore individual differences because individual background have an impact on social community <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Shumba, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Bowers, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Sterling, 2009)</ref>.</p><p>The other important point of ecological intelligence is to have holistic perspective because there are seen and unseen webs among biotic and abiotic factors in the world. Each behaviour, related to consumption or not, might have an impact directly or indirectly on the environment. People therefore should take responsibility for their each behaviour to their environments and social communities <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Goleman 2006</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Goleman , 2009;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">McCallum, 2005)</ref>. Individualism is unfortunately in the foreground due to capitalist perspective. However the human being is a social creature and s/he should not isolate herself/himself from the social area because ecological intelligence is a social and collective process. Each environmental acquisition is transferred by intergenerational communication such as language; therefore environmentally responsible behaviour also needs to involve responsible social and economic behaviours. <ref type="bibr">(Bowers, 2008</ref><ref type="bibr">(Bowers, , 2009</ref><ref type="bibr">(Bowers, , 2010;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Goleman 2006</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Goleman , 2009;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">McCallum, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Shumba, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Sterling, 2009)</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Social intelligence</head><p>The other important subset of ecoliteracy is social intelligence and social intelligence refers to social responsibilities of people in terms of sustainability. For instance, people should be able to think about how a stuff is produced or whether there is any environmental or social/human exploitation in this production process <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Goleman 2006</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Goleman , 2009;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">McCallum, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Orr, 2002)</ref>. However the improvement of social intelligence is not easy due to migration because there are two sides of the migration; migrants and host cities/countries. Migrants are cheap labour sources for host cities/countries and this is named as brown revolution <ref type="bibr">(Economist, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">FAO, 2003)</ref>.</p><p>The migrant population settles urban area and this massive population also stresses on urban life especially in Asia, Sub-Sahran Africa, Latin America <ref type="bibr">(FAO, 2015)</ref>. The rural population is also exposed to nonadaptation in urban social life and a gap is become between expectation and reality in terms of social and economic lives. On the one hand the Economist <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(2002)</ref> says that the brown revolution is unstoppable. On the other hand, the stopping the brown revolution is not desirable in terms of economic perspective; however it might be slowed <ref type="bibr">(FAO, 2003)</ref>. FAO 2015 Report utters that governments should support the rural population life with internal and external policies. The Economist <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(2002)</ref> emphasizes the revival of rural population as 'green revolution' because ecologic development of rural area related to the economy <ref type="bibr">(FAO Report, 2003)</ref> Economy One other subset of ecoliteracy is economy. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">McCallum (2005)</ref> and Orr <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(2002)</ref> recall that the history of Western science has negatively affected to understand the natural environment; therefore ecology and economy are considered as two different subjects. On the contrary, they should actually be considered as complementing to each other <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Goleman, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kahn, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Orr, 2002)</ref> because economy needs environmental and human resources in order to continue the development <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Kumar &amp; Budin, 2006)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kahn (2010)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Orr (2002)</ref> especially emphasize that economy should be based on sustainable development instead of exploitation of environmental and human resources such as brown revolution. People should be able to think that all their needs they bought such as foods, clothes, shelters are based on the natural resources; therefore we have to think and sense about our effects on the environment. The sense of environment refers to emotional intelligence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Emotional intelligence</head><p>Emotional intelligence is one of the important subset ecoliteracy and Goleman, Bennett and Barlow (2012) merge ecological, social and emotional intelligences under ecoliteracy. In terms of emotional intelligence, people should be able to sense what their negative impacts are on other people, natural environment and the other living organisms. <ref type="bibr">McBride et al. (2013, p. 14)</ref> determine also this kind of ecologic, affective, and cognitive relationship within ecoliteracy as "head, heart, hands and spirit" connections.</p><p>Emotional intelligence is the affective side of ecoliteracy and it is related to human senses <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Schutte, Malouff, Hall, Haggerty, Cooper, Golden, &amp; Dornheim, 1998)</ref>. People have feelings and emotions however they might not be aware of them or know how to express them. In terms of environmental subjects, if people feel (such as pain, hurt, anxiety, fear, empathy) the natural environment, then they might have a connection with the environment <ref type="bibr">(Haskell, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lazarus &amp; Cohen, 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr">Martin, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ozdemir, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Reis &amp; Roth, 2009)</ref>. The main subject here is if human activities disturb lives of other living things what s/he feels and whether they have empathy. Ringness (1975) also points out that adults are not very open to change, explore and express their feelings like children; therefore affective domains of adults should be developed in order to be able to deal with the social and consumption problems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Green consumer behaviour</head><p>Due to increasing consumerism, adults tend to spend and consume more regardless of whether they actually need to do so <ref type="bibr">(Aracıoglu &amp; Tatlıdil, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Esposito, 2009)</ref>. However, they barely think over what raw materials have been used during the making of these goods and commodities and how the nature has been affected by the production process <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Goleman, 2009)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Goleman (2009)</ref> recalls that what needs to be done in order to minimize the damage is to purchase ecological products. It is also stressed that ecological items are more expensive than others <ref type="bibr">(Aracıoğlu &amp; Tatlıdil, 2009)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Goleman (2009)</ref> underlines that even though ecological products are more expensive, the producers will market more ecological products if the consumers tend to buy these products, leading to harmonization with the nature. As a result, industrial production will not do any harm to the nature. What needs to be stressed here is collective action; in other words, public awareness on use of ecological products will be of great help. The collective action of green consumers refers to ecoliteracy because environmental responsible behaviours or green consumer behaviours at the visible/observable side of ecoliteracy <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Kapogianni, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">McBride et al., 2003)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methodology</head><p>The study was approached quantitatively <ref type="bibr">(Yildirim &amp; Simsek, 2006)</ref>. Explanatory and confirmatory factor analysis were carried out within this approach. The explanatory factor analyses had inductive perspective <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Buyukozturk, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Sencan, 2005)</ref> while the confirmatory factor analyses had deductive perspective <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Simsek, 2007)</ref>. It is aimed that to have more reliable scale which has strong theoretical background, reliable and validity within these two perspectives.</p><p>The study consists of three stages including The literature was reviewed and 30 items and five themes were determined. Secondly the ecoliteracy model was designed (Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). These items were evaluated as potential indicators of ecological intelligence by an ecology specialist and an environmental education specialist.</p><p>b. Preparation and implementation of the scale</p><p>The trial scale was designed based on 5 Likert style. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Simsek (2007)</ref> emphasized that 5 Likert style was a good option in order to test any model and one of the step of this study was to test alternative ecoliteracy model. It was, therefore, decided to use 5 Likert style scale.</p><p>The affirmative items were scored as 1-Completely disagree, 2-Partly disagree, 3-Not sure, 4-Partly agree, and 5-Completely agree. A complete reverse scoring was applied to the negative set of items. The scale was completed by 405 adults between 18-65 years of age via Google drive and QR code. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Sencan (2005)</ref> notes that the sample size was acceptable if it was sufficient to ensure at least five events per entry, therefore a sample size of 405 respondents was satisfactory for this study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>c. Measurement of the reliability and validity</head><p>For the analysis of the scale, the verified correlation value between the Cronbach Alpha reliability coefficient and the entries was reviewed by relying on the SPSS 13 software.</p><p>The scale was evaluated as reliable if the Cronbach Alpha coefficient level was more than 0.70 <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Buyukozturk, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Sencan, 2005)</ref>. Entries with a correlation value below 0.30 were removed from the analysis. The explanatory factor analysis was run in order to locate the validity of the scale and to dimension the entries included in the scale after determination of their factor loads. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Buyukozturk (2007)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Sencan (2005)</ref> stressed that the factor load value should be 0.40 or higher when sorting the entries. It was noted that when the principal axis factoring and direct oblimin analysis were used together, they would facilitate formation of factors in the presence of an assumption of correlation within the factor <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Hill, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Creed &amp; Machin, 2003)</ref>. Principal axis factoring and direct oblimin were preferred in this study considering that this was the first work to develop a scale <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Simsek, 2007)</ref>.</p><p>In the explanatory factor analysis, the Kaiser-Meyer-Olkin (KMO) coefficient and Bartlett test were analysed together. It was noted that a KMO value over 0.60 and a significant Bartlett test (p&lt;0.05) indicated that a factor could be derived from the data <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Buyukozturk, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Sencan, 2005)</ref>.</p><p>Subsequent to the explanatory factor analysis, the confirmatory factor analysis was run with LISREL 8.0 <ref type="bibr">(Joreskog and Sorbom, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr">cited at Simsek, 2007)</ref> statistics software.</p><p>In the review of the confirmatory factor analysis, diagram and goodness of fit criterias and correction recommendations were considered.</p><p>In the diagram evaluation, the standardized values and the t value were taken into account. The standardized values were evaluated for the ability of each entry to represent its variable. The t value was reviewed to check the relevant entry had p&lt; 0.05 significance.</p><p>With respect to the goodness of fit, the harmony between the relations in the model and the data was considered <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Simsek, 2007)</ref>. Here the ratio between the Chi square and the degree of freedom was evaluated. This ratio was expected to be a maximum 3-4. The other criteria included RMSEA (Root Mean Square of Approximation), CFI (Comparative fit index), IFI (Incremental fit index), standardized RMR (SRMR), GFI (Goodness-of-fit index) and AGFI (Adjusted goodness of fit index). Some researches <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Simsek, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Fossati et al., 2003)</ref> note that the RMSEA and SRMR may fall below 0.08 and argued that a value below 0.05 could indicate a better fitness. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Simsek (2007)</ref> noted that CFI and IFI values above 0.80 referred to a better fitness while Doll, Xia and Torkzadeh noted that GFI and AGFI values between 0.80 and 0.89 referred to a reasonable fit.</p><p>In the correction recommendations, the ratio between the Chi-square and the degree of freedom was considered. The impact of the correction on the decrease of the Chi-square value indicated an improved model. The factor loads of the dimensioned items were evaluated to develop a five-dimensional scale inclusive of 20 items.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participants</head><p>One of the most important points for the study was to decide the sample group. My aim was to reach adults who had different backgrounds. The sample group of this study included housewives, undergraduate students, in-service teachers, academicians, engineers, health and media employees, the other government employees and laboratory technicians (App 3). The literature did not specify the importance of an individual group. Nevertheless <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Goleman (2006</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Goleman ( , 2009) )</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">McCallum (2005)</ref> mentioned the importance of adults on the economy, environment and social interactions, therefore data was collected from adults.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Findings</head><p>According to Cronbach Alpha reliability analysis and factor analysis, 10 items had low correlation values and factor loads were under 0.40, so were removed from the scale. These 20 items were run by the confirmatory factor analysis. The 14 th item which's factor load was under 0.40 was only kept in the analysis due to the decision of the environmental education specialist. All goodness of fit values can be seen at Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</p><p>Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The goodness of fit results of explanatory and confirmatory factor analysis</head><p>As can be seen from Table <ref type="table">1</ref>, KMO was greater than 0.60, indicating the presence of themes in this scale. The Bartlett test was less than 0.05 and it showed that the sample size was sufficient to determine the themes. The scree plot graph (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>) showed five sharp drops, indicating the presence five themes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Goodness of fit values Recommende d values</head><p>The  The first theme as indicated sharp drop had a percentage variance related to eigenvalue of 23.914. The second theme's percentage of variance was 11.206; the third theme's percentage of variance was 7.366; the fourth theme's percentage of variance was 6.617 while the fifth theme's percentage of variance was 5.292 according to explanatory factor analysis. The other drops were very close to each other. According to the results, it was decided that the ecoliteracy scale had five themes: ecological intelligence, social intelligence, emotional intelligence, economy and green consumer behaviour (App 2) and these five themes have also respectable Cronbach alpha values either for each theme or for the whole scale (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>). intelligence, ecological intelligence and green consumer behaviour were respectively 0.654, 0.562, 0.715, 0.632, and 0.624. These results indicated that the reliability scores were at a satisfactory level. The factor loads were more than 0.40 except the 14 th item. The 14 th item factor load was under 0.40 however the environmental education specialist suggested that this item represented the social intelligence theme very well. This meant that each item represented that theme very well. Table <ref type="table">1</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> showed that the ecoliteracy scale had goodness of fit values. All the results were confirmed by recommended values. According to Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>, each item represented a theme very well due to of standardised solutions being greater than 0.40 and t results less than 0.05 (App 1). The scale was reliable, had validity and strong theoretical background.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Testing of an alternative ecoliteracy model</head><p>According to the literature review, I thought that the main item of ecoliteracy was ecological intelligence. Ecological intelligence had three subsets (economy, emotional and social intelligences) and if ecological intelligence was improved then it would effect on the green consumer behaviour (Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). I tested Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> on confirmatory factor analysis one more time and Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>   As can be seen Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>, the model did not give any red signal and it meant that the significant levels among observable variables and latent variables were less than 0.05. The model only gave two correction warnings between the second-the third items and the ninth-the sixteenth items (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>). The first warning between the second-the third items also happened at the first stage of the scale analysis (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>). The second warning happened at the alternative model analysis. As can be seen from Table <ref type="table">1</ref>, goodness of fit values of ecoliteracy model were at a satisfactory level and very close to ecoliteracy scale's values after the correction analysis. When it was compared Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>, it could be clearly seen that both model overlapped. In terms of inductive and deductive perspective, this study showed that ecoliteracy scale and alternative model had strong theoretical background.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>According to the literature in introduction, five themes are determined for an ecoliteracy scale: ecological intelligence, social intelligence, emotional intelligence, economy and green consumer behaviour. At the first stage of the study, these five themes are confirmed as a subset of ecoliteracy (Table <ref type="table">1</ref> and<ref type="table">Figure</ref>  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>). All the analysis results are at a satisfactory level (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>, 2 and Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>). At the second stage of the study, an alternative ecoliteracy model is tested (Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). According to this model economy, emotional and social intelligences are subsets of ecological intelligence. Ecological intelligence has directly link to green consumer behaviours. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref> and 5 confirm that ecoliteracy model has a satisfactory level and strong theoretical background. As can be seen at Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>, there are two corrections on the models.</p><p>Ideally, there should not be any correction on the scale development process and if there were many correction warnings, it meant that the model had very weak theoretical background <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Simsek, 2007)</ref>. However there were only two corrections on the alternative ecoliteracy model. Nevertheless, there is a gap between theoretical and experimental research on ecoliteracy <ref type="bibr">(ESD, 2015)</ref>; this study, therefore, might be an important starting point for experimental ecoliteracy studies.</p><p>Ecoliteracy is not a new concept. Researchers have begun to discuss about this concept for the last two decades. The main problem here is that ecoliteracy does not have a common definition <ref type="bibr">(ESD, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kapogianni, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Lira et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tursi, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">McBride et al, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Esposito, 2009)</ref>. Experimental studies related to ecoliteracy are very limited <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Kapogianni, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tursi, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Esposito, 2009)</ref> and they are mostly based on economy-ecoliteracy relationship <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Kapogianni, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tursi, 2015)</ref>. These studies are used some surveys however ecoliteracy is only a subset of these surveys. It is obvious that the studies related to ecoliteracy have started to increase however there is a problem how to measure ecoliteracy <ref type="bibr">(ESD, 2015)</ref>. This study, therefore, refers to fill an important gap between theory and practice in terms of ecoliteracy.</p><p>Despite the fact that it is determined five subsets for ecoliteracy, the main aim of these subsets and ecoliteracy is sustainability <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Goleman, 2006)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Goleman (2006)</ref> also names ecolitearcy as sustainability literacy. The most popular definition of ecoliteracy is to use existing natural resources while considering next generations <ref type="bibr">(UN Brundtland Declaration, 1987)</ref>. This definition has been enriched with 'global citizenship' concept recently <ref type="bibr">(Öhman, 2016)</ref>. Many research mention theoretical background of ecoliteracy such as environmental knowledge, attitude, awareness, consciousness <ref type="bibr">(ESD, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kapogianni, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lira, Steinicke &amp; Garcia, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tursi, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">McBride, Brewer, Berkowitz and Borrie, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Esposito, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Orr, 1992</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Orr, , 2002))</ref>. However it is not clear how to achieve sustainability learning and to transfer sustainability applications to the real life. It is clear that formal education is not enough to improve sustainability learning.</p><p>As can be seen from my case study at the beginning of the paper, informal learning and local culture are also very important in order to achieve sustainability and global citizenship. My grandmother, I and my friends did not know the meanings of sustainability or global citizenship but our behaviours were very coherent with sustainability. On the one hand the main subject here is to behave according to the local environment and local culture. This scale might be enriched with local cultures and information because one size does not fit all. I cannot say that this scale might work at research of all countries. It should be tested and improved. On the other hand there was an intergenerational transfer between my grandmother and grandchildren. In terms of local culture intergenerational transfers should not ignored because these transfers include collective acquisitions and systemic thinking <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Shumba, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Sterling, 2009)</ref>. Intergenerational transfers refer to informal learning and informal learning might be main subject and methodology in terms of education programme development.</p><p>Research usually goes to from theory (literature review) to praxis (experimental/experiential applications). In terms of ecoliteracy, this way might be thought from opposite side. Researchers might go to from praxis to theory. For example, there are many people like my grandmother in rural areas or indigenous people. Researcher might observe these people and learn how they transfer local acquisitions to next generations. This might a new learning model for ecoliteracy and sustainability education.</p><p>As a conclusion, ecoliteracy has five subsets: ecological intelligence, social intelligence, emotional intelligence, economy and green consumer behaviour. Social intelligence, emotional intelligence and economy has connection with ecological intelligence while ecological intelligence has relationship with green consumer behaviour. If social intelligence, emotional intelligence or economy subjects are improved then they might affect on the development of ecological intelligence and thereby they might be effective on green consumer behaviour according to the alternative ecoliteracy model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Implications</head><p>-This scale is not a perfect scale however it might be an important starting point for the other researchers. Researchers might try to develop another ecoliteracy scales with different subsets.</p><p>-This scale should be tested by other researchers. According to the results, the scale has very goodness of fit values however it is not clear whether it might work at different studies.</p><p>- </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>a. Literature review, determination of the scale items and development of the ecoliteracy model. b. Preparation and implementation of the scale c. Measurement of the reliability and validity. a. Literature review; determination of the scale items and development of the ecoliteracy model.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Scree plot-eigenvalue graph</figDesc><graphic coords="8,90.34,85.39,422.95,338.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Path graph based on standardised solution of the ecoliteracy scale</figDesc><graphic coords="10,90.34,166.09,407.25,390.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>occurred.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Path graph based on t values of the ecoliteracy model</figDesc><graphic coords="11,90.34,85.39,422.95,263.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Path graph based on standardised solution of the alternative model</figDesc><graphic coords="12,90.34,85.39,422.96,289.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="17,90.34,119.35,422.97,353.30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Themes and factor loads of the ecoliteracy scaleAs can be seen from Table2, the Cronbach Alpha reliability coefficient value of whole scale was 0.781 while the coefficient values for economy, emotional intelligence, social</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Themes and factor loads</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Scale</cell><cell>I</cell><cell>II</cell><cell>III</cell><cell>IV</cell><cell>V</cell></row><row><cell>items</cell><cell>(Economy)</cell><cell>(Emotional</cell><cell>(Social</cell><cell>(Ecological</cell><cell>(Green</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>intelligence)</cell><cell>Intelligence)</cell><cell>Intelligence)</cell><cell>Consumer)</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>0.799</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>0.791</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>8</cell><cell>0.720</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>0.620</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>23</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.667</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.665</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.528</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>18</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.522</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.859</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.836</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>17</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.672</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>14</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.357</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>28</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.677</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>13</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.515</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>12</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.498</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>16</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.439</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>11</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.729</cell></row><row><cell>10</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.684</cell></row><row><cell>15</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.679</cell></row><row><cell>9</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.560</cell></row><row><cell>Cronbach</cell><cell>0.654</cell><cell>0.562</cell><cell>0.715</cell><cell>0.632</cell><cell>0.624</cell></row><row><cell>alpha</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>coefficient</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>values of each</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>theme</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Cronbach</cell><cell>0.781</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>alpha</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>coefficient</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>value of whole</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>scale</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Local cultural information is very important in terms of ecoliteracy and sustainability. Other researchers might develop different ecoliteracy scales based on local cultures. -The main group of this study was adults. Future research could investigate different subsets of ecological intelligence among various demographics of backgrounds. The scale could be adapted for different age groups and various demographic backgrounds. Researchers could also develop new ecoliteracy scales for different age groups and various demographic backgrounds. Global companies flourish at the expense of local businesses. 7. Local businesses lay off workers when trying to compete with global companies, which is one of the reasons for migration to urban centres. 8. Immigration serves as a source of cheap labour for global companies. Social intelligence 2. I avoid cheap goods from overseas if I am aware that their production involves unjust labour conditions. 3. I avoid cheap goods from overseas if I am aware that their production involves the use of child labour. 14. I prefer to buy local produced vegetables and fruits. 17. I don't feel good when I learn that the production of a good I bought involved unjust labour conditions. Emotional intelligence 4. I try to emulate individuals who live sustainably. 5. I believe that environmental education is one of the ways to combat obesity. 18. I feel bad when I notice that nature has the power to defeat human progress. 23. I would be a much more laid-back person if I knew nothing about environmental issues. I try to reuse plastic bags. 10. I try to avoid using plastic bags when I go shopping. 11. I have my own water bottle with me at all times. 15. I try to extend the life of my clothes by sewing and patching them. Ecological intelligence 12. Environmental disasters can unfold in several parts of the world simultaneously. 13. The effects of an environmental disaster are not limited to the area where it took place. 16. I worry when I learn about increase in incidents of cancer among people living in industrial areas Appendix 3. Number and percentage of participants</figDesc><table><row><cell>Themes Economy 6. Green Items 1. I cannot afford sustainably produced goods. consu mer our behavi N Undergraduate students 132 In-service teacher 97 Civil servant 48 Housewife 46 Academician 37 Health sector employee 16 Media sector employee 11 Engineer 9 Laboratory technician 9 9. Participants Total 405</cell><cell>% 32.6 24.0 11.9 11.4 9.1 4.0 2.7 2.2 2.2 100</cell><cell>Strongly</cell><cell>Agree</cell><cell>Agree</cell><cell>Neither agree</cell><cell>nor disagree</cell><cell>Disagree</cell><cell>Strongly</cell><cell>Disagree</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Appendix 1. Path graph based on t values of the ecoliteracy scale</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>I would like to thank all participants who filled the scale out patiently; <rs type="person">Dr. Sezen Apaydın</rs>, <rs type="person">Dr. Zeynep Çetinkaya-Edizer</rs>, <rs type="person">Dr. Sevil Yalçın</rs>, <rs type="person">Dr. Şükran Yalçın-Özdilek</rs>, <rs type="person">Psychologist Nudan Hızlı</rs>, <rs type="institution">Paramedic Neslihan Kara-Ateş, AFAD Technician Necati Okur, Correspondent Şule Sağlam-Ridha</rs>, <rs type="person">Housewife Nigar Sönmez</rs> and <rs type="person">Laboratory Technician Francesca Lomas</rs> for helping me to collect the data and to write this article.</p><p>. . .</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of environmental consciousness over consumers&apos; purchasing behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Aracıoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Talıdil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://eab.ege.edu.tr/pdf/9_2/C9-S2-M5.pdf,10.12.2010" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ege Akademic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="435" to="461" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Handbook of data analysis for social scientists</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Buyukozturk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>Pegem A Publication</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Ankara</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multidimensional properties of the access to categories of experience scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Creed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Machin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Psychological Assessment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="91" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A confirmatory factor analysis of the enduser computing satisfaction instrument</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Doll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Torkzadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mis Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="453" to="461" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The status of education for sustainable development in the United States: A 2015 report to the US Department of State</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.sustainabilityprofessionals.org/sites/default/files/ESD%20" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-05">May. 2002. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The Brown Revolution, the news dated 09. in%20the %20United%20States%20final.pdf</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Promoting ecoliteracy and ecosystem management for sustainability through ecological economic tools. Graduate College Dissertations and Theses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Esposito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.fao.org/fileadmin/user_upload/esag/docs/y4252e.pdf,22.06" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">World Agriculture: Towards</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2009. 2003. 2015/2030. 2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The state of food insecurity in the World</title>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">FAO Report</orgName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.fao.org/3/a-i4646e.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multigroup confirmatory component and factor analyses of the Italian version of the Aggression Questionnaire</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fossati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Maffei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Acquarini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Di Ceglie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Psychological Assessment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">54</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Social intelligence: The new science of human relationship</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Goleman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>Bantam Book</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ecological intelligence: How knowing the hidden impacts of what we buy can change everything</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Goleman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>Broadway Books</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ecoliterate: How educators are cultivating emotional, social, and ecological intelligence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Goleman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Barlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Affiliation motivation: people who need people…but in different ways</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Penology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1008" to="1018" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Critical pedagogy, ecoliteracy &amp; planetary crisis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Peter Lang Publishing, Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Attitudes and intention toward organic cosmetics in Greece: an exploratory study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kapogianni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://repository.ihu.edu.gr/xmlui/bitstream/handle/11544/331/dissertation%20maria%20kapogianni.pdf?sequence=1" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>International Hellenistic University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Master Thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prevention and management of product recalls in the processed food industry: a case study based on an exporter&apos;s perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Budin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Steinicke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>García</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://140.130.204.27/course/download/slhsu/recall%20management.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Environmental, Chemical, Ecological, Geological and Geophysical Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1126" to="1131" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>World Academy of Science, Engineering and Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technovation</note>
	<note>Eco-Literacy and Pedagogical Praxis in the Multidisciplinary University Greenhouse toward the Food Security Strengthening</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mcbride</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brewer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Berkowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Borrie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1890/ES13-00075.1</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1890/ES13-00075.1" />
		<title level="m">Environmental literacy, ecological literacy, ecoliteracy: What do we mean and how did we get here? Ecosphere</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">67</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ecological intelligence: Rediscovering ourselves in nature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Mccallum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Africa Geographic</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cape Town</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ecological literacy: Education and the transition to a postmodern world</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Orr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<publisher>State University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The nature of design: ecology, culture, and human intention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Orr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New ethical challenges within environmental and sustainability education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Öhman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/13504622.2016.1165800</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environmental Education Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="765" to="770" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pilgrim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pretty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1890/06-1358.1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A cross-regional assessment of the factors affecting ecoliteracy: Implications for policy and practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1742" to="1751" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Learning from the Peruvian Amazon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.roffeypark.com/wp-content/uploads2/Learning-from-the-Peruvian-Amazon.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development and validation of a measure of emotional intelligence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Schutte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Malouff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Haggerty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Golden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dornheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and individual differences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="177" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Reliability and validity in social and behavioural measurements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sencan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Seçkin Publication</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Ankara</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Commons thinking, Ecological intelligence and the ethical and moral framework of Ubuntu: An imperative for sustainable development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Shumba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.academicjournals.org/article/article1380106358_Shumba.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Media and Communication Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="84" to="96" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to structural equality modeling: basic principles and LISREL applications: Ekinoks Education and counseling services)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ö</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Simsek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>Siyasal Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Ankara</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">DIPR: Holistic Education Integrating Sustainability and Ecoliteracy into K-12 education in the US (Doctoral dissertation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sterling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.un-documents.net/ocf-02.htm" />
		<editor>Tursi, J. M.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">2009. 2015. 1987</date>
			<publisher>United Nation) Brundtland Declaration</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="83" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Philadelphia University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Our common future</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Qualitative research methods in social science</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Yıldırım</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Şimşek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>Seçkin Publication</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Ankara</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Bu nedenle bu çalışmanın bir amacı, alt bileşenleri ekolojik zeka, sosyal zeka, duygusal zeka, ekonomi ve yeşil tüketici davranışı olan yetişkinlere yönelik bir ekolojik okur-tazarlık ölçeği geliştirmektir. Çalışmanın bir diğer amacı, bu alt bişenler arasındaki ilişkiyi gösteren bir modeli test etmektir. Bu modele göre ekonomi, duygusal ve sosyal zeka ekolojik zekanın alt bileşenleridir. Modelin ikinci aşamasında ise ekolojik zeka, doğrudan yeşil tüketici davranışı ile bağlantılıdır. Doğrulayıcı ve açıklayıcı faktör analizine göre uyum iyiliği değerleri</title>
		<idno>SRMR: 0.0783</idno>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>Hamilton, NEW ZEALAND</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Yetişkinlere Yönelik Ekolojik-Zeka Ölçeğinin Geliştirilmesi ve Alternatif Bir Modelin Doğrulaycı Faktör Analizi ile Test Edilmesi Emel OKUR-BERBEROGLU LIC (Livestock Improvement Corporation</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Özet Ekolojik okur-yazarlığın tek bir tanımlaması olmamasına rağmen ekolojik okur-yazarlık, doğadaki sürdürülebilir ekolojik ilişkilerin anlaşılması, içselleştirilmesi ve bu sürdürülebilir yaşam şeklinin, günlük hayata aktarılabilmesi olarak tanımlanabilir. kabul edilebilir düzeydedir. Bu değerler Cronbach alpha: 0.78; KMO: 0.830; X 2 /df: 4.09; RMSEA: 0.087</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Agfi</forename><surname>Gfi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">IFI, ve CFI ≥ 0.80 şeklindedir. Ölçekte 20 madde bulunmaktadır</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ekolojik okur-yazarlık, ekolojik zeka, duygusal zeka, sosyal zeka, ekonomi, yeşil tüketici davranışı, doğrulayıcı faktör analizi</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anahtar</forename><surname>Kelimeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>açıklayıcı faktör analizi</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
