<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Discipline and Work Motivation on Teacher Performance at Private Vocational Schools in Banjarbaru</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wahyu</forename><surname>Wardani</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master of Education Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitas Lambung Mangkurat</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Ngadimun</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master of Education Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitas Lambung Mangkurat</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Discipline and Work Motivation on Teacher Performance at Private Vocational Schools in Banjarbaru</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i12-08</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T21:40+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>instructional leadership</term>
					<term>discipline</term>
					<term>motivation</term>
					<term>performance</term>
					<term>teachers</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This study's objective was to examine the direct and indirect effects of instructional leadership, work discipline, and work motivation on the performance of private vocational school teachers in Banjarbaru. This study employed a correlational strategy with a quantitative approach that is formalized as a path analysis model. The study population consisted of 245 teachers from nine private vocational schools in the city of Banjarbaru, and the Slovin method was used to choose 152 respondents as the research sample. There are thirty items of the principal's instructional leadership. Thirty five items on the work discipline and 36 items on work motivation. Then, the teacher performance included 52 items of the questionnaires. There were 153 items in total used for the data collection. Descriptive analysis, classical assumption test, analysis correlation, path analysis and hypothesis testing were employed for analyzing the data. Using the product moment person correlation test, the validity and reliability of this research instrument were evaluated. The path analysis was applied to research data to determine the direct and indirect effects among variables by first applying the tests for normality, homogeneity, linearity, multicollinearity, and heteroscedasticity. The results of this study indicated that the instructional leadership, work discipline, and work motivation of the principal have a direct and indirect effect on teacher performance.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>The strength of a nation is no longer determined by the quantity of its natural resources, instead by its Human Resources (HR). the preparation of quality human resources is inseparable from the educational factor because as stated in Article 3 of the Law of the Republic of Indonesia Number 20 of 2003 on the National Education System, national education aims to develop the potential of students to become productive members of society <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Perdana, 2010)</ref>,. In regard to Indonesia as a country, multiple factors contribute to the low quality of education in Indonesia. First, the organizers' policy is overly output-and input-focused, thus they pay little attention to the process. Even if the objective of education is the process of developing behavioral and personality changes as well as the application of acquired knowledge in the real world. In the meantime, the educator is the holder of the educational process; if the process does not receive attention, neither does the educator <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Kholis, 2003)</ref>. Second, education administration has thus far been dominated by bureaucratic ranks at the central level. Consequently, school principals and teachers are less successful at directing instruction in schools. At the micro level of the school, many factors predicted at the macro central level do not exist or do not function as expected. Third, the absence of a role for the community, particularly the parents of students, in the academic and non-academic implementation of education. In the context of developing community-based education, this is what hampers the school's relationship with parents and the community, especially the paradigm of an educational approach that is from, by and for the community. According to Fuad (2014), community-based education is viewed as one of the most appropriate and adequate solutions for satisfying national demands. Considering these issues, it appears that everything essentially refers to the existence and responsibilities of the teachers in carrying out their teaching duties and other activities. The growth of an educational institution is significantly influenced by the performance of the teachers. Likewise, the function of teacher performance in enhancing the quality of education cannot be isolated from the quality of education. Without superior performance, the objective of quality enhancement cannot be met. Consequently, teacher effectiveness is crucial and essential in the field of education <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Winarto et al., 2020)</ref>. Education is a human endeavor to generate more valuable human resources. Thus, one of the government's attempts to promote a nation is to increase the overall quality of education. The teacher is one of the decisive variables for the success of enhancing the quality of education. Teachers are essential human resources when interactions between teaching and learning occur. This indicates that teachers and other education staff must initiate initiatives to improve the quality of education. In order to attain school performance effectively and efficiently, excellent principals must be able to impact, move, encourage, invite, direct, advise, guide, order, forbid, and even discipline teachers' teaching performance. By increasing the teaching performance of instructors in carrying out their responsibilities and tasks, it is anticipated that optimal results will be achieved. The low quality of education is one of the challenges faced by the Indonesian people in relation to their efforts to develop excellent human resources. There are several reasons why there is a low quality of education in Indonesia. First, the policy of the organizers is too oriented and focused on output and input, so they pay little attention to the process. Second, the management of education so far has been centralized, governed by bureaucratic ranks at the central level. Third, the lack of the role of society, especially parents of students in the implementation of education, both academically and non-academically. Increasing teacher professionalism requires coaching that must be carried out in a planned and sustainable manner, this is intended so that teachers do a better job. One of the motivations for someone to do a particular job or activity is the motivation behind it.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. METHOD</head><p>The study used a quantitative descriptive method. It describes the effect of the principal's instructional leadership, work discipline and work motivation on the performance of teachers in private vocational schools in Banjarbaru, South Kalimantan. The research population is all private vocational school teachers in Banjarbaru consisting of 9 private vocational schools with a total of 245 people. The research sample was 152 teachers. The data was collected using a Likert scale model questionnaire that had been tested for validity and reliability by selecting one to five answers that best fit the actual conditions. The research instrument consisted of teacher performance assessment instruments, principal instructional leadership questionnaires, work discipline, and teacher work motivation. The researchers used path analysis to answer seven research hypotheses in this study, namely: H1: there is a direct effect of the principal's instructional leadership on teacher performance in private vocational schools in Banjarbaru; H2: there is a direct effect of the principal's instructional leadership on work discipline in private vocational schools in Banjarbaru; H3: there is a direct effect of the principal's instructional leadership on work motivation in private vocational schools in Banjarbaru; H4: there is a direct effect of work discipline on the performance of teachers in private vocational schools in Banjarbaru; H5: there is a direct effect of work motivation on teacher performance in private vocational schools in Banjarbaru; H6: there is an indirect effect of the principal's instructional leadership on teacher performance through work discipline in private vocational schools in Banjarbaru; and H7: there is an indirect effect of the principal's instructional leadership on teacher performance through work motivation in private vocational schools in Banjarbaru.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head><p>Based on the results of data analysis, direct and indirect correlation coefficients were found as described below:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 1. Summary of Hypothesis Testing Decisions H1, H2, H3, H4, &amp; H5</head><p>Hypothesis p.s Decision H1 There is a direct effect of the principal's instructional leadership on teacher performance. 0.006 Accepted H2 There is a direct effect of the principal's instructional leadership on work discipline. 0.001 Accepted H3 There is a direct effect of the principal's instructional leadership on work motivation. 0.001 Accepted H4 There is a direct effect of work discipline on teacher performance. 0.001 Accepted H5 There is a direct effect of work motivation on teacher performance. 0.004 Accepted  <ref type="table">1</ref> is a summary of the hypotheses testing decisions H1, H2, H3, H4, &amp; H5 with a significance value of less than 0.05. Thus, all of the hypotheses are accepted. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref> is the summary of the decisions for testing the hypotheses H6 and H7 with the stipulation that if the coefficient of the direct correlation is smaller than the coefficient of the indirect correlation, then the hypothesis is accepted. Based on the results of the analysis in Tables <ref type="table">1</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref>, in this study a correlation was found between variables which can be explained as follows.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. The effect of the Principal's Instructional Leadership on the Performance of Private Vocational School Teachers in Banjarbaru</head><p>The direct effect of the principal's instructional leadership on the performance of private vocational school teachers in Banjarbaru is shown by the Standardized Coefficients Beta value of 0.265 with a significance value of 0.006 &lt;0.05. Thus, Ho1 is rejected. There is a direct effect of the Principal's Instructional Leadership on the Performance of Private Vocational School Teachers in Banjarbaru. From this analysis, it shows that the better the Principal's Instructional Leadership, the teacher's teaching performance will increase. The results of this study indicate that the better the Principal's Instructional Leadership in schools will affect teacher behavior. The principal's instructional leadership effects teacher teaching performance, due to the principal's activities that really focus on improving student learning processes and outcomes through the teacher. This means that instructional leadership empowers all of the teacher's abilities in teaching, so that the teacher's teaching performance increases. Quality teacher teaching performance will in turn improve student learning processes and outcomes because student learning outcomes do not come directly from the principal's instructional leadership, but through the teaching process carried out by the teacher. This statement is supported by the results of research by Leitwood et al. in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Usman (2018)</ref> who found that the principal's leadership had an indirect effect on student learning outcomes, but it is through the teachers. This study confirms the findings of Syarifudin et al. (2022) that the greater the principal's instructional leadership, the greater the improvement in teacher performance. The findings of this study support the findings of \Normaini et al. (2022) that leadership elements play a crucial part in enhancing performance since effective leadership has a beneficial impact on all instructors' efforts to achieve goals. This study's findings support prior studies by <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Birhasani (2022)</ref>. The findings of testing hypotheses indicate a direct relationship between instructional leadership and teacher performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. The Effect of Principal Instructional Leadership on the Work Discipline of Private Vocational School Teachers in Banjarbaru</head><p>The Standardized Coefficients Beta value of 0.330 with a significance value of 0.001 0.05 demonstrates the direct effect of the principal's instructional leadership on the performance of private vocational school teachers in Banjarbaru; therefore, Ho2 is rejected. There is a direct effect of the Principal's Instructional Leadership on the Work Discipline of Private Vocational School Teachers in Banjarbaru. This investigation indicates that the more the school principal's instructional leadership, the more disciplined the teachers' work. Thus, the instructional leadership of the principal is one of the variables influencing the teacher's work discipline. The relationship between the leadership role and work discipline can also be observed through the leader's intrinsic monitoring. The most appropriate and suitable individual to oversee discipline is the immediate supervisor of the organization member or employee in question. This is because superiors are the individuals who are closest to, most familiar with, and most knowledgeable about their subordinates. This superior's supervision is a tool for regulating employee conduct and fostering a strict work environment. This is consistent with the findings of Ngadimun (2019) study titled the influence of leadership, work climate, and enthusiasm on the discipline of elementary school teachers in the Tanah Laut District. According to the findings of this study, the correlation between leadership and work discipline is 0.523. This study's findings support the findings of <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Emilia (2022)</ref>. According to the results of the path analysis between the learning leadership of school principals and teacher work discipline, the path coefficient value is 0.856 with a t count of 14.316 and a significance of 0.000, which is less than 0.05.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. The effect of the Principal's Instructional Leadership on the Work Motivation of Private Vocational School Teachers in Banjarbaru</head><p>The Standardized Coefficients Beta value of 0.332 with a significance value of 0.001 0.05 demonstrates the direct effect of the principal's instructional leadership on the performance of private vocational school teachers in Banjarbaru. Therefore, Ho3 is rejected. Thus, there is a direct effect of the Principal's Instructional Leadership on the Work Motivation of Private Vocational School Teachers in Banjarbaru. This analysis indicates that teacher motivation will grow proportionally to the quality of the principal's instructional leadership. As a result, the instructional leadership of the principal is one of the factors that influence teacher motivation. As the school's most senior leader, the school principal has a significant impact on his subordinates and is crucial to the institution's development. Therefore, the principal plays a crucial role in boosting teacher job motivation, since it is one of the markers for teacher evaluation and development, as well as for good service in learning. The significant relationship between principal instructional leadership and teacher motivation shows that these two factors play a crucial role in determining teacher motivation. This is because the instructional leadership of the principal and the job motivation of the teachers focus on curriculum implementation and teacher development. This study's findings support the studies of <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Karyadi et al. (2022)</ref>, who discovered that the principal's leadership had a direct impact on work motivation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. The Effect of Work Discipline on the Performance of Private Vocational School Teachers in Banjarbaru</head><p>The direct effect of Work Discipline on Teacher Performance at Private Vocational Schools throughout Banjarbaru is shown by the Standardized Coefficients Beta value of 0.306 with a significance value of 0.001 &lt;0.05, then Ho4 is rejected. Thus, there is a direct effect of Work Discipline on the Performance of Private Vocational School Teachers in Banjarbaru. This analysis indicates that a teacher's performance will improve in proportion to his or her level of work discipline. Thus, work discipline is one of the aspects that influence the performance of teachers. This is consistent with the findings of <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Suhaimi (2019)</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>research study indicating that</head><p>The Effect of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Discipline and Work Motivation on Teacher Performance at Private Vocational Schools in Banjarbaru teacher work discipline is closely associated to teacher performance. The path coefficient of 0.688 demonstrates that there is a high association between work discipline and teacher performance at Labuan Amas Selatan Elementary School. This study's findings support prior studies by <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Saleh (2019)</ref>. They showed that there is a direct relationship between work discipline and teacher performance. This study's findings support prior work by <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Baihaki, A. Muhyani Rizalie, 2022)</ref>. The route coefficient value is derived from the findings of the path analysis between teacher work discipline and teacher performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. The Effect of Work Motivation on the Performance of Private Vocational School Teachers in Banjarbaru</head><p>The Standardized Coefficients Beta value of 0.276 with a significance value of 0.004 0.05 demonstrates the direct effect of work discipline on teacher performance in Private Vocational Schools in Banjarbaru; therefore, Ho5 is rejected. There is a direct effect of work motivation on the performance of private vocational school teachers in Banjarbaru. According to the findings of this study, motivation is the driving force behind carrying out actions in order to achieve success. If the instructor has a high level of work motivation, it can be assumed that the employee also has a high level of performance. On the other hand, if there is poor work motivation, it may be determined that the teacher's performance is also low. The lack of motivation from the school environment is not conducive to achieving the best outcomes. This conclusion supports the findings of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Kailola, 2016</ref>) study concerning the association of principal leadership and work motivation with teacher performance at Putussibau-Kapuas Hulu State Vocational School. This analysis revealed that the correlation coefficient had a magnitude of 0.634 and a value of 0.402. The impact of work motivation on teacher performance is 40.20 percent. This indicates that the teacher's performance will be greater the bigger the teacher's job motivation. This study's findings are in line with prior studies by <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Normaini et al. (2022)</ref>. Their study suggests that the perception of work motivation correlates positively with performance, and vice versa: the perception of work motivation correlates negatively with performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F. The Effect of the Principal's Instructional Leadership on Teacher Performance through Work Discipline</head><p>The effect of the instructional leadership of the principal on teacher performance as measured by work discipline is analyzed using direct and indirect effects, namely a direct effect of 0.339 and an indirect effect of 0.431. The direct effect is superior to the indirect effect. This suggests that the instructional leadership of the principal has a major impact on teacher performance through work discipline. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Suriansyah, 2017)</ref> states that the presence of a leadership model in an educational institution is one of the variables that influence a person's job discipline. This is consistent with the findings of S.I (2011), whose path analysis revealed that instructional leadership has an effect on teacher discipline and that teacher discipline has an indirect effect on teacher performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G. The Effect of Principal Instructional Leadership on Teacher Performance through Work Motivation</head><p>Analysis of the effect of the principal's instructional leadership on teacher performance through work motivation was done through direct effect plus indirect effect, namely a direct effect of 0.332 and an indirect effect of 0.424. The direct effect is smaller than the indirect effect. This shows indirectly that the principal's instructional leadership has a significant effect on teacher performance through work motivation. Motivation is someone's encouragement to act in a certain way. Motivation is basically a mental condition that encourages a person to do something, delay or activity and provide strength that leads to achieving the fulfillment of desires, needs, giving satisfaction, or reducing imbalances <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Danim, 2014)</ref>. The results of this study reinforce previous research by <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Normaini et al. (2022)</ref>. This study shows that there is the indirect effect of transformational leadership through work motivation on teacher performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. CONCLUSION</head><p>There is both a direct and indirect relationship among the principal instructional leadership, work discipline, and work motivation of the principal and teacher performance. Teachers should increase their mastery of the basic competencies of the subjects they teach, namely by first studying the basic competencies of each subject in order to accomplish the learning objectives. The school principal should adopt a more personal approach with the teachers. It aims to increase the effect of the principal on the teachers who are his subordinates so that in the future it will be easier for the principal to mobilize teachers.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .The</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1 . The Analysis of the direct and indirect correlation s</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 2 . Summary of Hypothesis Testing Decisions H6 and H7</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Hypothesis</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Implementation of the Adiwiyata School Program in the Implementation of Environment-Based Curriculum</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Baihaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R S</forename><surname>Muhyani Rizalie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-61</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-61" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science And Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2364" to="2369" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation Between Principal Instructional Leadership, Achievement Motivation and Teacher Performance through Job Satisfaction in State Elementary Schools in Kandangan District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Birhasani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-71</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-71" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science And Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<pubPlace>Hulu Sungai Selatan Regency</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Motivasi Kepemimpinan dan Efektivitas Kelompok</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Danim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Rineka Cipta</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation among Instructional Leadership, Work Commitment, and Teacher Work Discipline toward Students Learning Achievement at Elementary Schools in Haur Gading District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Emilia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Fuad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-745</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-745" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science And Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2022. 2014</date>
			<publisher>PT Rajagrafindo Persada</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Manajemen Pendidikan Berbasis Masyarakat</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hubungan Kepemimpinan Kepala Sekolah Dan Motivasi Kerja Dengan Kinerja Guru di SMK Negeri Putussibau-Kapuas Hulu</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kailola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Manajemen Pendidikan</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Climate and Work Motivation on Teachers&apos; Organizational Citizenship Behavior in MTsN throughout Hulu Sungai Selatan Regency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Karyadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wahyu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Metroyadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-28</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-28" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kholis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Manajemen Berbasis Sekolah, Teori, Model, dan Aplikasi</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Grasindo</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Leadership, Work Climate and Spirit on Elementary School Teacher&apos;s Discipline in Batu Ambar District Tanah Laut Regency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ngadimun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Education, and Management (jK</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="86" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Journal of K</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Principal Transformational Leadership, Job Satisfaction and Work Motivation on the Performance of Elementary School Teachers in Halong District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aslamiah</forename><surname>Normaini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sulaiman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-39</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-39" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pengaruh motivasi kerja, kepemimpinan dan kesempatan pengembangan karir terhadap kinerja karyawan di PT</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Perdana</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nyonya Meneer Semarang. Jurnal Penelitian</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Pengaruh Kepemimpinan Instruksional Kepala Sekolah, motivasi dan disiplin kerja terhadap kinerja guru SMA Negeri Kecamatan Pujud</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Kabupaten Rokan Hilir, Riau. universitas Muhammadiyah Sumatera Utara</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship between the Principal Role, Motivation and Satisfaction with the Performance of Elementary School Teachers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Saleh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Education, and Management (J-K</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Journal of K</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship of Transformational Leaders of Princoipal, Teacher Motivation, Teacher Organization Commitments With Performance of Primary School Teachers In Labuan Amas Selatan, Indonesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Suhaimi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Education Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Implementation of the Total Quality Management model to support quality of work culture at primary school teacher education programs in Lambung Mangkurat University Indonesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Suriansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Australian Journal of Basic and Applied Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="186" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Environment and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance in State Elementary Schools in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru City</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Syarifudin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Suriansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ngadimun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-34</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-34" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Menjadi Guru Profesional</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Usman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Remaja Rosdakarya</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effectiveness the use of audio visual media in teaching islamic religious education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Winarto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Syahid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Saguni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Contemporary Islamic Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="107" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>There is an Open Access article, distributed under the term of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0. which permits remixing, adapting and building upon the work for non-commercial use, provided the original work is properly cited</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
