<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Organizational Culture and Compensation on Employee Performance with Work Motivation as a Mediating Variable</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Ilzar</forename><surname>Daud</surname></persName>
							<email>ilzar_daud@yahoo.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Management Study Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Economics and Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitas Tanjungpura</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>78124</postCode>
									<settlement>Pontianak</settlement>
									<region>West Kalimantan</region>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Economics and Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitas Tanjungpura</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Pontianak</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Organizational Culture and Compensation on Employee Performance with Work Motivation as a Mediating Variable</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">2636-9168, e- 0128-2603</idno>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.35609/jmmr.2020.5.2(5)</idno>
					<note type="submission">Revised: March 12, 2020 Accepted: June 30, 2020</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T00:57+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Empirical. JEL Classification: L22, M12, M19 Organizational Culture</term>
					<term>Compensation</term>
					<term>Work Motivation</term>
					<term>Employee Performance</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Objective -This study examines the influence of organizational culture and compensation on employee performance with work motivation as a mediating variable. This study was conducted at the State Owned Bank of Pontianak, Indonesia. Methodology/Technique -The population in this study is 150 employees from a State-Owned Bank. The sampling method uses census techniques so that the number of samples used is 150 employees. The research data was collected using a questionnaire which is then analyzed using a path analysis technique using SPSS software to examine the relationships among the constructs, which are: organizational culture, compensation, work motivation and employee performance. Findings -The results show that, in the first substructure, organizational culture and compensation have a significant influence on work motivation. In the second substructure, organizational culture, compensation and work motivation have a significant influence on employee performance. The path analysis results show that work motivation does not mediate the relationship between organizational culture and employee performance, whereas the relationship between compensation and employee performance is mediated by work motivation. Novelty -Previous studies have been carried out in many western countries, raising doubts about generalizations in the same research results in developing countries such as Indonesia. Therefore, the novelty is that this study is carried out in the context of developing countries, especially in the State-Owned Bank in West Kalimantan, Indonesia.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Human resources are very important and cannot be separated from an organization or company. Human resources determines the development of an organization. _____________________________</p><p>As one of the functions in an organization, human resources must be managed properly to increase the effectiveness and efficiency of the organization. In this era of increasing business competition, the performance of human resources must increase. One step to maintain or improve the performance of human resources is to evaluate employee performance continuously and motivate employees to improve their performance and achieve organizational goals. If the goals of the organization can be achieved, this will have a positive impact on the organization's competitive position in the market.</p><p>Several factors can influence employee performance, such as: organizational culture, compensation, and work motivation. Organizational culture is the essence of what is important in the organization. The activity gives commands and prohibitions, and illustrates what can and cannot be done that will regulate the behavior of members. Hence, organizational culture dictates what we might do or not do, and is considered as a guide for organizational activities. In essence, corporate culture is a tool to unite every individual who carries out joint activities <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Beach, 1993)</ref>. Organizational culture is often portrayed in a shared sense <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Glaser et. al., 1987)</ref>.</p><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Mathis and Jackson (2000)</ref> increasing motivation and improving employee performance can be achieved through compensation. Dessler (2010) states that employee compensation refers to forms of payment for employees for their work. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Mondy (2008)</ref> states that compensation includes all gifts given to employees as a form of appreciation for their work. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Jones and George (2008)</ref> state that motivation is the encouragement of a person based on how they behave and how they work within organizations. <ref type="bibr">Robbins (2006)</ref> states that employee performance is a function of the interaction between ability and motivation. Hence, employee performance is the achievement of one's work as measured by the criteria set by the organization. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Susan et. al., (2012)</ref> state that work motivation affects employee performance. <ref type="bibr">Hameed e.t al., (2014), and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Soeters (2006)</ref> state that compensation affects employee performance. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Agwu (2014</ref><ref type="bibr">), Shazad et. al., (2013</ref><ref type="bibr">), Alyahyah et. al., (2013</ref><ref type="bibr">), Eeden (2012)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Daft (2010)</ref> state that organizational culture influences employee performance. This shows that most research on organizational culture issues, compensation, work motivation, and employee performance were carried out in western countries. Thus, there are doubts about generalizations based on the findings of previous studies applied in developing countries such as Indonesia. Further research on organizational culture, compensation, work motivation, and employee performance are therefore very important for developing countries such as Indonesia, especially for State Owned Banks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Literature Review</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Organizational Culture and Work Motivation</head><p>Organizational culture is a characteristic that is held in high esteem by the organization and is used to differentiate one organization from another <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Lee &amp; Yu, 2004)</ref>. Organizational culture refers to the values and norms of behavior that are accepted and understood together by members of the organization as a basis for the rules of behavior within the organization. Motive is defined as a tendency to move, starting from selfimpulse and ending with adjustment <ref type="bibr">(Sperling, 1987)</ref>. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Luthans (2002)</ref>, motivation is the process of producing and maintaining behavior and performance. One way to motivate individuals is to make employees more satisfied so that they are committed to their work. The organization will influence the level of employee motivation and will make employee motivation high to control and improve organizational culture <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Bagirova &amp; Vavilova, 2015)</ref>. Based on the explanation above, the following hypothesis is proposed: H1: Organizational Culture has a significant influence on Work Motivation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Compensation and Work Motivation</head><p>According to <ref type="bibr">Anthony et. al., (2000)</ref>, compensation can be used to encourage and motivate employees to achieve organizational goals. Motivation refers to a high willingness to achieve organizational goals, conditioned by the ability to meet individual needs. Previous studies on compensation and motivation carried out by <ref type="bibr">Ghazanfar et. al., (2011)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Khan and Mufti (2012)</ref> show that compensation has a significant effect on motivation. Therefore, the following hypothesis is proposed: H2: Compensation has a significant influence on work motivation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Organizational Culture and Employee Performance</head><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Daft (2010)</ref>, organizational culture can improve employee performance by motivating, shaping and channeling their behavior towards achieving company goals. Performance is the result of work that can be achieved by a person or group of people in an organization in accordance with their respective authorities and responsibilities. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Walker (2007)</ref>, performance as a result of work behavior from targeted achievement or part of tasks by each individual in the organization must be achieved. Some previous research also states that there is a relationship between organizational culture and performance <ref type="bibr">(Roos &amp; Eeden, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Alyahyah et. al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Shahzad et. al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Agwu, 2014)</ref>. Organizational culture also has an influence on employee performance. Based on the explanation above, the following hypothesis is proposed: H3: Organizational Culture has a significant influence on Employee Performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Compensation and Employee Performance</head><p>Compensation is a form of implementing human resource management functions that relate to all types of awards given to individuals for doing their work. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hameed et. al., (2014)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Teclemichael and Soeters (2006)</ref>, compensation has an effect on employee performance because the appropriate amount of compensation will improve performance. Therefore, the following hypothesis is proposed: H4: Compensation has a significant influence on Employee Performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Work Motivation and Employee Performance</head><p>Increased motivation leads to increased performance and decreased motivation causes a decrease in performance <ref type="bibr">(Kothari, 2008)</ref>. The higher the level of employee motivation in carrying out the work, the better the employee's performance will be. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Susan et. al., (2012)</ref> state that work motivation influences employee performance. Based on the above, the following hypothesis is proposed: H5: Work Motivation has a significant influence on Employee Performance.</p><p>The following conceptual research model was developed based on the theoretical and empirical evidence: J. Mgt. Mkt. Review 5 (2) 122 -128 (2020) </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Research Methodology</head><p>This research uses quantitative research methods with a survey research approach. According to <ref type="bibr">Kerlinger (2002)</ref>, survey research is research conducted on large and small populations. The population in this study is 150 employees of the State Owned Bank. The sampling method uses census technique because all populations are sampled so the number of samples taken is 150 employees. The data is collected using a questionnaire. After the data was collected, it is analyzed by a path analysis technique using SPSS software to examine the relationships among the constructs, which are: organizational culture, compensation, work motivation and employee performance.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Reliability Test</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Regression and Path Analysis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Discussion</head><p>The results show that, in the first substructure, organizational culture has a significant influence on work motivation with a significance of 0.002. The results of this study therefore support the results of research conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bagirova and Vavilova (2015)</ref>. Compensation has a significant influence on work motivation with a significance of 0.000. The results of this study therefore support the results of research conducted by <ref type="bibr">Ghazanfar et. al., (2011)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Khan and Mufti (2012)</ref>. Meanwhile, in the second substructure, the results show that organizational culture has a significant influence on employee performance with a significance of 0.004. The results of this study are therefore consistent with the results of research conducted by <ref type="bibr">Alyahyah et. al., (2013</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">), Shahzad et. al., (2013)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Agwu (2014)</ref>. Compensation has a significant influence on employee performance with a significance of 0.042. The results of this study are also in line with previous studies conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hameed et. al., (2014)</ref>.</p><p>Work motivation has a significant influence on employee performance with a significance of 0.015. The results of this study are strengthened by several previous studies, such as research conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Susan et. al., (2012)</ref>. The results of this study also indicate that work motivation does not mediate the relationship between organizational culture and employee performance, whilst the relationship between compensation and employee performance is mediated by work motivation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Conclusion</head><p>The results show that, in the first substructure, there was a significant influence between organizational culture and work motivation, and a significant influence between compensation and work motivation. In the second substructure, there is a significant influence between organizational culture and employee performance. There is also a significant influence between compensation and employee performance and between work motivation and employee performance. Furthermore, the results of this study also show that work motivation does not mediate the relationship between organizational culture and employee performance, whilst compensation for employee performance is mediated by work motivation.</p><p>In particular, this study implies that, in the context of the Indonesian State-Owned Bank, organizational culture and compensation have the power to influence the performance of employees to advance the organization. In addition, a leader can motivate their employees so that they will increase motivation in working for the organization and create a sense of satisfaction in work that will ultimately improve employee performance.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Conceptual Research Model</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>.1. Reliability Test</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Cronbach's Alpha</cell><cell>Conclusion</cell></row><row><cell>Organizational Culture</cell><cell>0,861</cell><cell>Good Reliability</cell></row><row><cell>Compensation</cell><cell>0,683</cell><cell>Good Reliability</cell></row><row><cell>Work Motivation</cell><cell>0,823</cell><cell>Good Reliability</cell></row><row><cell>Employee Performance</cell><cell>0,873</cell><cell>Good Reliability</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="4">.2. Regression Analysis First Substructure</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Coefficients a</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Unstandardized</cell><cell>Standardized</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model</cell><cell cols="2">Coefficients Std.</cell><cell>Coefficients</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>B</cell><cell>Error</cell><cell>Beta</cell><cell>T</cell><cell>Sig.</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>(Constant)</cell><cell cols="2">3,389 3,842</cell><cell cols="2">,882</cell><cell>,380</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>3. Regression Analysis Second Substructure Table 4.4. Direct Effect, Indirect Effect and Total Effect</figDesc><table><row><cell>Path</cell><cell></cell><cell>Direct Effect</cell><cell>Indirect Effect</cell><cell>Total Effect</cell></row><row><cell>Org. Culture Motivation</cell><cell>Work</cell><cell>0,343</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0,343</cell></row><row><cell>Compensation Motivation</cell><cell>Work</cell><cell>0,482</cell><cell>-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Org. Culture Performance Employee</cell><cell>0,339</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0,339</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Compensation Employee Performance</cell><cell>0,136</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0,136</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Work Motivation Employee Performance</cell><cell>0,469</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0,469</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Org. Culture Motivation Performance Employee Work</cell><cell>0,400</cell><cell>0,302 x 0,374 = 0,113</cell><cell>0,287</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Compensation Motivation Performance Employee Work</cell><cell>0,136</cell><cell>0,482 x 0,469 = 0,226</cell><cell>0,362</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>J. Mgt. Mkt.Review 5 (2) 122 -128 (2020)</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Organizational Culture and Employees Performance in the National Agency for Food and Drugs Administration and Control (Nafdac), Nigeria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Agwu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://journalofbusiness.org/index.php/GJMBR/article/view/1231" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global Journal of Management and Business Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of effectiveness of training and development: The Kirkpatrick model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Alyahya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Norsiah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Evaluation-of-effectiveness-of-training-and-The-Saad-Mat/277" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Asian Journal of Business and Management Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>be18db00ad0a429145c760fb5afe1ee7b980e</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Managerial Work Effectiveness and Organization Culture: Exploratory Study with Russian Banks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bagirova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vavilova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://books.google.com.pk/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=sYJmCwAAQBAJ&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA11&amp;dq=Bagirova,+A.,+%26+" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 11th European Conference on Management Leadership and Governance</title>
		<meeting>the 11th European Conference on Management Leadership and Governance</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Conferences and Publishing International Limited</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015-10">2015, October</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="19" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">+2015.+Managerial+Work+Effectiveness+and+Organization+Culture:+Exploratory+Study+With+Russia n+Banks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">+a</forename><surname>Vavilova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>+In+JC.+Dias+Rouco+</editor>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>+Proceedings+of+the+11th+European+Conference+on+Management+Leadershi p+and+Governance+(ECMLG+2015)+(pp.+&amp;ots=hgNSSrfQQN&amp;sig=rIdaWou_fAFTLAHCXJ3aaF0fc28&amp;redir_esc= y#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Making the right decision: Organizational culture, vision, and planning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Beach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>Prentice Hall</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Daft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">New Era of Management. 9th Edition, International Edition, CENGAGE Learning</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston. Dessler, G; London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Pearson Education Limited</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2010. 2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="130" to="147" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Human resource management</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">c8ad508aeccd7773be3fd/A-Study-of-Relationshipbetween-Satisfaction-with-Compensation-and-Work-Motivation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Glaser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zamanou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hacker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Faheem_Ghazanfar/publication/228752899_A_Study_of_Relationship_between_Satisfaction_with_Compensation_and_Work_Motivation/links/556" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management communication quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="122" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987. 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>pdf J. Mgt. Mkt. Review</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of compensation on employee performance (empirical evidence from banking sector of Pakistan)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hameed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ramzan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Zubair</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Business and Social Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evolution of management thought</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JE Bienal. Contemporary management</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of compensation on motivating employees in public and private banks of Peshawar (BOK and UBL)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Mufti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Effect-of-Compensation-on-Motivating-Employees-in-Khan-Mufti/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Basic and Applied Scientific Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4616" to="4623" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>dbef912a45a42674b1db01d7b1897a4a557f1293</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Foundations of Behavioral Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Kerlinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
			<publisher>Rinehart and Winston. Inc</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">410423</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Holt; New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kothari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Research methodology: Methods and techniques. New Age International</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Corporate culture and organizational performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1108/02683940410537927</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1108/02683940410537927" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of managerial psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Positive organizational behavior: Developing and managing psychological strengths</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Luthans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5465/ame.2002.6640181</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5465/ame.2002.6640181" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<publisher>Academy of Management Perspectives</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="72" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mathis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Human Resource Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<pubPlace>South</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human Resources Management, 10th Edition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mondy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Organizational Behavior, 12th Edition</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2008. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>McNeese State University Robbins</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relationship between employee motivation, job satisfaction and corporate culture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Roos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Van Eeden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SA Journal of Industrial Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of organizational culture on employee&apos;s job performance: An empirical study of software houses in Pakistan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Shahzad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Iqbal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gulzar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Studies Quarterly</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Sperling</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">56</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 834e/6a831733e3049aaef22e5dcacfebd3a3ca90. 2013</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Psychology: Made Simple</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influence of motivation on performance in the public security sector with a focus to the Police Force in Nairobi</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Susan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Gakure</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kiraithe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Waititu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Influence-of-Motivation-on-Performance-in-the" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Kenya. International Journal of Business and Social Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>with/c577d6a9cc2fca89a94ef05d128cfe5983f1de81</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Challenges and prospects of HRM in developing countries: testing the HRM-performance link in the Eritrean civil service</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Teclemichael Tessema</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Soeters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/09585190500366532</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/09585190500366532" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The international journal of human resource management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="105" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A-HA! Performance, 1st Edition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
