<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) Analysis of Organizational Commitment and Employee Performance in PT. Telekomunikasi Indonesia. Tbk</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kiki</forename><surname>Farida Ferine</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departemen of Master of Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitas Pembangunan Panca Budi</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Postgraduate Medan</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kiki</forename><surname>Soraya</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<address>
									<addrLine>Y2 ,155 ,099 ,081 147 ,237 000 ,000 299 ,000 ,000 678 ,000 ,000 000 ,644 ,000 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,964 ,000 000 ,639 ,000 000 ,960 ,000 000 ,000 ,964 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,000 ,591 000 ,000 ,962 000 ,000 ,598 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,000 ,000 000 ,000 ,964 000 ,000 ,591 000 ,000 ,962 000 ,000 ,598 803 ,000 ,000 295 ,000 ,000 680 ,000 ,000 093 ,071 ,056 085 ,064 ,051 098 ,075 ,059 057 ,043 ,034</addrLine>
									<postCode>097 000 000 Y1 211 -,080 000 000 K1 801 000 000 000 K2 000 000 000 K3 000 000 000 KK4 000 000 000 KI4 000 408 000 KI3 000 702 000 KI2 000 612 000 KI1 000 689 000 KO3 000 000 965 KO2 000 000 006 KO1 000 000 976 KK1 000 000 000 KK2 000 000 000 KK3 000 000 000 GK1 000 000 000 BO1 672 000 000 GK2 000 000 000 GK3 000 000 000 GK4 000 000 000 BO2 678 000 000 BO3 517 000 000 BO4 571 000 000 BO5 789 000 000 BO1 674 000 000 BO2 677 000 000 BO3 516 000 000 BO4 572 000 000 BO5 789 000 000 GK1 000 000 000 GK2 000 000 000 GK3 000 000 000 GK4 000 000 000 K1 000 000 000 K2 000 000 000 K3 000 000 000 KI1 062 148 676 KI2 056 134 614 KI3 065 156 712 KI4 038 090 412</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) Analysis of Organizational Commitment and Employee Performance in PT. Telekomunikasi Indonesia. Tbk</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">2581-3889</idno>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T23:52+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Structural equation Modelling (SEM)</term>
					<term>Organizational Commitment</term>
					<term>Employee Performance</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This research was conducted on telecommunications services companies where the company needs a lot of employees as well as high performance. However, the company's performance declined, so the company's target could not be achieved. The company's lack of targets is thought to be influenced by several factors, including organizational culture, leadership style, job satisfaction and compensation. The purpose of this study is to analyze the influence of organizational culture, leadership style, job satisfaction and compensation on performance with work commitment as intervening variables. The respondents in the study had 225 employees. The data analysis technique used is SEM (Structural equation Modelling) with LISREL program Version 8.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>PT. Telkom manages business through best practices by optimizing superior Human Resources, competitive use of technology, and building synergistic and mutually supportive partnerships. Companies that continue to grow and keep up with the changes that occur in the business environment are companies that will continue to enjoy profitability in the long run. The company has a rapid response rate of change. For a company that is unable to follow and does not respond to changes that occur in its business environment will certainly experience a decrease in both its profitability and the performance of its employees.</p><p>According to <ref type="bibr">Sedarmayanti (2011: 260)</ref> performance defenisi is a translation of performance which means the work of a worker, a management process or an organization as a whole, where the work must be able to be shown concretely and measurable evidence (compared to the specified standards). In an effort to win global competition, PT. Telkom is actively developing human resources (HR) professionals through certification programs and global talent programs. Pt. Telkom understands that HR has a strategic role and position in achieving its vision to become a global standard company. That's why PT. Telkom continues to develop existing human resources while building good employment relationships with employees. Therefore, employees are required to be more professional in order to achieve the company's goals.</p><p>Robbins and Judge (2015) define organizational culture as a shared system of meaning embraced by members that distinguishes the organization from other organizations. Leadership style is a pattern of behavior of a person to influence his subordinates in order to work together to achieve the goal, leadership style is also considered important to improve employee performance. A leader who is able to motivate and direct his subordinates will be very supportive of the company's activity plan. According to Winardi (2007), leadership style is an approach used to understand the success of leadership in relationships where we focus attention on what the leader is doing. Leadership success will be derived from the leadership style that arises when the leader leads his subordinates.</p><p>An employee can be said to be satisfied if he or she feels valued or gets the appropriate remunerati ity expected. The satisfaction of an employee will vary. Employees may be satisfied with high salaries or with employees with mediocre salaries but treated well. Organizational commitment is one of the many that will affect employee performance. The commitment can be the willingness of employees to exert maximum capability for the organization. However, so far</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) Analysis of Organizational Commitment and Employee Performance in PT……</head><p>employees have not fully worked with their abilities. So the employee's performance is not as expected. The low quality of work is inseparable from the organizational culture that exists in PT. Telkom. So far, the organization's culture has been violated by employees. Among them is the system of value system that exists in PT. telkom for example about the confidentiality of customers' data. often employees provide customer data to others. For example, selling customer data with the total value of savings to other parties.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II.</head><p>Literature Review 1. The Influence of Organizational Culture on Performance The culture of the organization will have significance for an employee. The culture of the organization that supports making an employee will work to the maximum, providing all his work skills and competencies. Research conducted by Haryati (2013), Ilham (2014) and Anwar (2016) stated that the culture of the organization has a positive and significant effect on employee performance. So when the culture of the organization gets better it will improve employee performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">The Influence of Leadership Style on Performance</head><p>A leader who has good competence and experience in directing his subordinates will be very helpful to the company in achieving the company's goals. The achievement of the company's goals is nothing but improved employee performance. Research conducted by Frans Sudirjo (2012), Siswanto and Hamid (2017), and Lestari and Mariyono (2017) shows that when leadership style has a positive and significant effect on employee performance. Where when the dream style gets better it will improve employee performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Effect of Job Satisfaction on Performance</head><p>The pleasure of working will make an employee comfortable in completing their tasks and responsibilities. Happy in finding solutions to the problems faced reflects that employee satisfaction of work has been maximized. This will certainly have an impact on improving employee performance. Research conducted by Khairiyah and Annisa (2013), Lestari and Mariyono (2017) and Changgriawan (2017) proved that job satisfaction has a positive and significant effect on employee performance. So it can be concluded that when worker satisfaction is improved it will improve employee performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">The Effect of Compensation On Performance</head><p>Compensation provided by PT. Telekomunikasi Indonesia affects employee performance. Compensation is what can drive employees' performance. Pt. Telekomunikasi Indonesia already provides work compensation such as holiday benefits, but employees are not satisfied with the benefits already provided by the company, employees want other benefits such as old day allowance and meal allowance. Compensation is as a bond of cooperation, job satisfaction, effective procurement, motivation, employee stability, discipline, and influence of trade unions and governments as stated by <ref type="bibr">Hasibuan (2001)</ref>. To improve employee performance, compensation must be in accordance with the system already planned by the company because the more appropriate the compensation provided by the company then the employee will be more comfortable to stay in the company. Appropriate compensation can also encourage employees to work better so that their performance will improve so that the company can achieve its target. This is supported by previous research conducted by Ririvega Kasenda (2013), which showed that compensation has a significant effect on employee performance with coefficient value is positive.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Organizational Cultural Influence, Leadership Style and Job Satisfaction, Compensation for Employee Performance</head><p>Through Organizational Commitment Companies that are able to maximize organizational culture, leadership style and job satisfaction and Employee compensation will certainly have an advantage compared to other companies. These efforts can be made through improving the organization's commitment. So a good organizational culture, attractive leadership style and improved job satisfaction and appropriate compensation will also have a good impact on improving employee performance. Research conducted by Eva Kris Diana Devi (2009), Frans Sudirjo (2012) and Ilham Sugiri (2014) stated that organizational culture, leadership style and job satisfaction have a positive and significant effect on employee performance through organizational commitment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III.</head><p>Methodology According to Rusiadi (2013: 14), the research approach used in this study is quantitative, i.e. research that aims to know the relationship between two or more variables with this study will be built a theory that serves to explain, predict and Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) Analysis of Organizational Commitment and Employee Performance in PT…… control a symptom. The population in this study is a permanent employee and contract of PT Telekomunikasi Indonesia Medan which numbered 225 people. In a SEM model a latent variable can function as an exogenous variable or an endogenous variable. An exogenous variable is an independent variable that affects dependent variables. In the SEM model the exogenous variable is indicated by the absence of arrows derived from those variables towards the endogenous variable. Where an endogenous variable is a dependent variable that is affected by an independent variable. In the SEM model the exogenous variable is indicated by the arrow leading to that variable. In general a SEM model can be divided into two main parts namely Measurement Model and Strutural Model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Evaluation of Normality Assumptions of Evaluation Data On Outliers</head><p>The normality of unis and multivariate data used in this analysis was tested using AMOS 22. The results of the analysis can be seen in the Appendix on assessment normality. The reference reference referenced to state the assumption of data normality is the value in the C.R (critical ratio) column.</p><p>Estimates of maximum likelihood with structural equation models require some assumptions that must be met by data. These assumptions include the data used having a normal distribution, free of data outliers, and no multicolinearity <ref type="bibr">(Ghozali 2005</ref><ref type="bibr">(Ghozali , 2008))</ref>. Testing of data normality is carried out by taking into account the skweness and kurtosis values of the indicators and the research variables. The criteria used are critical ratio skewness (C.R) and kurtosis of ± 2.58 at a significance level of 0.01. A data can be concluded to have a normal distribution if the C.R value of kurtosis does not exceed the absolute price of 2.58 <ref type="bibr">(Ghozali, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">2008)</ref>. The results of this test are demonstrated through the assessment of normality of the AMOS output.</p><p>An outlier is an observational condition of a data that has unique characteristics that look very different from other observations and appear in extreme values, either for a single variable or combination variables <ref type="bibr">(Hair et al, 1998)</ref>. Analysis of outlier data is evaluated in two ways: analysis of univariate outliers and multivariate outliers. Evaluation of univariat outliers is carried out by first converting the value of the data into a standard score or z-score i.e. data that has an average equal to zero and a standard deviation equal to one. Evaluation of the presence of univariate outlier is shown by the size of z score range ± 3 to ± 4 <ref type="bibr">(Hair, et al., 1998)</ref>. The criteria used are if the score contained in column C.R is greater than 2.58 or smaller than minus 2.58 (-2.58) then it is proven that the distribution of data is normal. The study used a total of 225 observational data, so it can be said that normality assumptions can be fulfilled.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Confirmatory Factor Analysis (CFA)</head><p>1. CFA Cultural Organization Variable  Compensation has no direct effect on organizational commitments and employee performance that has a value of 0.211&gt;0.05, and 0.155&gt;0.05. GK1 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 BO1 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 GK2 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 GK3 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 GK4 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 BO2 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 BO3 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 BO4 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 BO5 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. Conclusion 1.</head><p>There is a significant influence of Organizational Culture on Organizational Commitment, where the probability value is 0&gt; 0.05 2. There is a significant effect of Compensation on Organizational Commitment, where the probability value is 0 &lt; 0.05 3. There is a significant effect of Compensation on Employee Performance, where the probability value is 0 &gt; 0.05 4. There is a significant influence of Leadership Style on Organizational Commitment, where the probability value is 0 &gt; 0.05 5. There is a significant influence of Organizational Culture on Employee Performance, where the probability value is 0&gt; 0.05 6. There is a significant influence of Leadership Style on Employee Performance where the probability value is 0&gt; 0.05 7. There is an insignificant effect of Job Satisfaction on organizational commitments where the value is 0.267&gt;0.05 8. There is an insignificant effect of Job Satisfaction on Employee Performance with a probability value of 0.260&lt;0.05</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :Figure 2 :Figure 3 :Figure 5 :Figure 9 :</head><label>12359</label><figDesc>Figure 1: CFA Cultural Organization</figDesc><graphic coords="4,198.68,394.25,197.95,131.35" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 10 :Figure 11 :</head><label>1011</label><figDesc>Figure 10: Dirrect Effect Job Satisfaction</figDesc><graphic coords="8,171.80,215.47,192.85,107.45" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 12 :Figure 13 :</head><label>1213</label><figDesc>Figure 12: Indirrect Effect through Employee Performance</figDesc><graphic coords="9,204.60,233.93,195.15,166.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="6,137.90,361.98,319.50,318.05" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>List of Employees of PT Telekomunikasi Indonesia Medan</figDesc><table><row><cell>Parts</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Normality of Critical Ratio Value Data</figDesc><table><row><cell>Var</cell><cell>Min</cell><cell>max</cell><cell>Skew</cell><cell>c.r.</cell><cell cols="2">kurtosis c.r.</cell></row><row><cell>BO1</cell><cell>2,000</cell><cell>10,000</cell><cell>-7,38</cell><cell>-4,52</cell><cell>2,63</cell><cell>8,07</cell></row><row><cell>BO2</cell><cell>3,000</cell><cell>10,000</cell><cell>-4,89</cell><cell>-2,99</cell><cell>8,58</cell><cell>2,63</cell></row><row><cell>BO3</cell><cell>2,000</cell><cell>10,000</cell><cell>-7,57</cell><cell>-4,63</cell><cell>1,75</cell><cell>5,37</cell></row><row><cell>BO4</cell><cell>5,000</cell><cell>10,000</cell><cell>-3,45</cell><cell>-2,11</cell><cell>-2,11</cell><cell>-6,48</cell></row><row><cell>BO5</cell><cell>3,000</cell><cell>10,000</cell><cell>-5,61</cell><cell>-3,43</cell><cell>1,16</cell><cell>3,55</cell></row><row><cell>GK1</cell><cell>6,000</cell><cell>15,000</cell><cell>-8,10</cell><cell>-4,96</cell><cell>3,82</cell><cell>1,17</cell></row><row><cell>GK2</cell><cell>9,000</cell><cell>15,000</cell><cell>-3,20</cell><cell>-1,96</cell><cell>-6,01</cell><cell>-1,84</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Standardized Indirect Effects</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>X4</cell><cell>X3</cell><cell>X2</cell><cell>X1</cell><cell>Y2 Y1</cell></row><row><cell>Y1</cell><cell cols="2">,000 ,000</cell><cell cols="2">,000 ,000</cell><cell>,000</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell>Y2</cell><cell cols="4">,044 -,017 ,031 ,052</cell><cell>,000</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell>K1</cell><cell cols="2">,000 ,000</cell><cell cols="2">,000 ,000</cell><cell>,000</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell>K2</cell><cell cols="2">,000 ,000</cell><cell cols="2">,000 ,000</cell><cell>,000</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell>K3</cell><cell cols="2">,000 ,000</cell><cell cols="2">,000 ,000</cell><cell>,000</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">KK4 ,000 ,000</cell><cell cols="2">,000 ,000</cell><cell>,000</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell>KI4</cell><cell cols="2">,057 ,043</cell><cell cols="2">,034 ,038</cell><cell>,090</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell>KI3</cell><cell cols="2">,098 ,075</cell><cell cols="2">,059 ,065</cell><cell>,156</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell>KI2</cell><cell cols="2">,085 ,064</cell><cell cols="2">,051 ,056</cell><cell>,134</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell>KI1</cell><cell cols="2">,093 ,071</cell><cell cols="2">,056 ,062</cell><cell>,148</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">KO3 ,193 -,072 ,135 ,224</cell><cell>,000</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">KO2 ,001 -,001 ,001 ,002</cell><cell>,000</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">KO1 ,201 -,075 ,141 ,233</cell><cell>,000</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">KK1 ,000 ,000</cell><cell cols="2">,000 ,000</cell><cell>,000</cell><cell>,000</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">KK2 ,000 ,000</cell><cell cols="2">,000 ,000</cell><cell>,000</cell><cell>,000</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) Analysis of Organizational Commitment and Employee Performance in PT……</head><p>All indicators of construct-forming firs Commitment Organisai have a significant loading factor value, where the entire loading factor value exceeds the number 0.5. If all construct-forming indicators are significant then they can be used to represent data analysis.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">CFA Performance Variable</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Goodness of Fit Model</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) Analysis of Organizational Commitment and Employee Performance in PT……</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Direct Effects, Indirect Effects and Total Effects</head><p>The amount of influence of each standardized direct effect and the standardized total effect can be shown in the following table : 
Table <ref type="table">3</ref>:</p><p>Source: Amos Output</p><p>The results of direct influence on the table above can be spelled out as follows: Organizational Culture has no direct effect on organizational commitment and employee performance that has a value of 0.237 &gt;0.05, and 0.097&gt;0.05.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Equation Modeling (SEM) Analysis of Organizational Commitment and Employee Performance in PT…… KK1 ,000 ,965 ,000 ,000</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">000</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">0</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date>2 ,000 ,639 ,000 ,000 ,000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">0</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date>4 ,000 ,644 ,000 ,000 ,000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">0</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date>1 ,201 -,075 ,141 ,233</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">992</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">0</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date>2 ,001 -,001 ,001 ,002 ,007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">0</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date>193 -,072 ,135 ,224</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">0</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The total impact results in the table above can be spelled out as follows: References</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Prinsip-prinsip Perilaku Organisasi</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Darmawan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Pena Semesta</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Surabaya</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Edy</forename><surname>Sutrisno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Jakarta, Kencana</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Irham</forename><surname>Fahmi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Perilaku Organisasi: Teori, Aplikasi, dan Kasus. Cetakan Kedua. Bandung: CV. Alfabeta. Anggota IKAPI</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Malayu</forename><forename type="middle">S P</forename><surname>Hasibuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Edisi Revisi</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Bumi Aksara</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia. Jakarta: PT Bumi Aksara Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) Analysis of Organizational Commitment and Employee Performance in PT……</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Malayu</forename><surname>Hasibuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Organizations: Behavior, Structure, Processes</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Fourteenth edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mangkunegara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Anwar Prabu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Bandung</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>PT. Remaja Rosdakarya</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia, Reformasi Birokrasi Manajemen Pegawai Negeri Sipil</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sedarmayanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Rafika Aditama</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Bandung</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Metode Penelitian Pendidikan Pendekatan Kuantitatif Kualitatif, dan R&amp;D</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sugiyono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>CV Alfabeta</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Bandung</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Kepemimpinan dan Perilaku Organisasi Edisi Ketiga</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Deddy</forename><surname>Rivai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mulyadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>PT. Rajagrafindo Persada</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Robbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Timothy</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Judge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Perilaku Organisasi. Edisi keenam belas</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Jakarta</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Salemba Empat</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Robbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Timothy</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Judge</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perilaku Organisasi</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Salemba Empat</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Miftah</forename><surname>Thoha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Kepemimpinan Dalam Manajemen. Jakarta: PT Raja Grafindo Persada</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wibowo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Manajemen Kinerja. Jakarta: Rajawali Pers</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Disiplin Kerja dan Kompensasi terhadap Kinerja Karyawan (Studi pada LKMS BMT Jaringan Muamalat Center Indonesia Wilayah DIY). Jurusan Keuangan Islam. Fakultas Syari&apos;ah dan Hukum</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Siti ; Pengaruh</forename><surname>Mamudah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Budaya</forename><surname>Kepemimpinan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Organisasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lingkungan</forename><surname>Motivasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kerja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<pubPlace>Yogyakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Universitas Islam Negeri Sunan Kalijaga</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Pengaruh Budaya Organisasi dan Motivasi terhadap Produktivitas Kerja Karyawan pada Bank BNI Syariah cabang Cirebon. Kementerian Agama Republik Indonesia. Institut Agama Islam Negeri (IAIN)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dina</forename><surname>Yumaida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2102">2102</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Syekh Nurjati Cirebon</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alif Furqoni dan Eka Afnan Troena</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Aulia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Pengaruh Kompensasi Finansial dan Non Finansial Terhadap Motivasi Kerja Karyawan Universitas Brawijaya Hotel Kota Malang</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
