<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Construction of Mobile Internet Value Proposition Model: An Empirical Study Based on Cases and Structural Equation Modeling(SEM)</title>
				<funder ref="#_J92KHN3">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Xiaochu</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<email>zhangxc@zjhzcc.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Zhejiang Gongshang University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Hangzhou College of Commerce</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>66 Huancheng South Road</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Tonglu County, Hangzhou</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Zhejiang</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Construction of Mobile Internet Value Proposition Model: An Empirical Study Based on Cases and Structural Equation Modeling(SEM)</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1051/shsconf/202418103025</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T23:52+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The pervasive influence of mobile internet is fundamentally reshaping both professional and everyday life, resulting in significant alterations to customer value creation models. Grounded in an extensive literature review, this article employs a causal case study methodology, incorporating in-depth interviews with 57 Chinese mobile internet users, along with observational data. The study aims at illuminate the core essence of mobile internet value propositions, proposing a comprehensive measurement model for assessing these propositions. The empirical validation of this model is achieved through exploratory factor analysis of 87 preliminary questionnaires and confirmatory factor analysis of 902 final questionnaires. This empirical inquiry culminates in the development of a model delineating mobile internet value propositions, which encompasses the following key dimensions: ubiquity (accessibility anytime, anywhere, accommodating fragmented time), convenience (quick access, handy availability, easy operation), individualization (automatic recognition, personalized services, security), and localization (location-based, sending location, and acquiring location).</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Mobile internet, situated at the intersection of information technology and electronic commerce, has instigated a profound metamorphosis in the customer value creation model, introducing unprecedented challenges and opportunities for both governmental bodies and enterprises. Contemporary scholarship recognizes the existence of distinctive value propositions within the realm of mobile internet, often elucidated through case analyses. Nonetheless, there is a conspicuous research gap concerning the core nature of mobile internet value propositions, and quantitative empirical investigations are conspicuously scarce. This study endeavors to bridge these gaps by conducting case studies that delve into the inherent characteristics and business models of mobile internet. Additionally, structural equation validation is employed to formulate a comprehensive value proposition model for mobile internet.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Literature Review</head><p>This study defines mobile internet as a versatile realm of commercial activities, wherein organizations and individuals leverage mobile communication technology for flexible access to information and services, anytime and anywhere. This encompasses a wide spectrum of functions, spanning operations, management, transactions, and entertainment. In academic circles, prominent characteristics of mobile internet, such as 'ubiquity,' 'convenience,' and 'easy accessibility,' have been recognized by scholars like A. D. Nigatu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, who describes it as 'ubiquitous interaction' and a 'powerful conduit for marketing information.' Wong et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> emphasize 'convenience' and 'easy accessibility' through extensive case studies, while M. Simanjuntak et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> delve into the 'ubiquitous' nature of U-commerce (Ubiquitous, Universal, Unique, Unison). Additionally, I. Clarke III <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> condenses these attribute into 'ubiquity,' 'localization,' 'personalization,' and 'convenience.' It is these unique value propositions of mobile internet that profoundly impacts business models and the value creation process. Mobile internet, offering personalized, location-based, and ever-available services, presents its distinctive 'value proposition,' expected to surpass traditional e-commerce across all domains <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. This study aims to explore the intricacies of mobile internet characteristics within the context of mobile internet value propositions <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</p><p>A value proposition is a clear commitment made by a company to its customers, assuring the delivery of a specific set of value-creating benefits.' A value proposition consists of two tiers of content: first, it specifies the elements or combinations thereof that generate value, and then it articulates how value is derived from these elements or combinations. In the era of mobile internet, the business model exhibits new features characterized by deep integration with mobile social commerce <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p><p>In summary, scholars like A. D. Nigatu <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> underscore safety, location responsiveness, and instant value as three value-driving factors of mobile internet, introducing new freedoms and fostering more valuable relationships. Irvine Clarke III, in his paper 'Mobile Business Value Proposition' published in the Journal of Business Strategies, outlines four value propositions of mobile internet: 'ubiquity,' 'convenience,' 'localization,' and 'personalization.' However, I. Clarke III's research relies on case studies to illustrate mobile internet value propositions. Value propositions are recognized for their uniqueness, measurability, and sustainability. Challenges persist, such as the absence of empirical evidence, a standardized value proposition scale, and the complexities associated with linking various applications with different value propositions. This study is rooted in Clarke III's theory of the four-factor mobile internet value proposition and aims atempirically investigate mobile internet value propositions, with the goal of constructing a model for mobile internet value propositions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Research Method and Model Construction</head><p>This study is structured into two principal parts. The first part focuses on the construction of a measurement model for the mobile internet value proposition, while the second part is dedicated to the validation and determination of this model and the associated scale.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Research Method</head><p>In constructing the mobile internet value proposition measurement model, this study employs a causal multiple case research approach. It integrates multiple evidence sources, including secondary data and interviews, to ensure evidence coherence and construct validity. Through scrutiny of research outcomes against empirical theory and case data, adjustments are recommended enhancing internal validity. A comprehensive examination of mainstream mobile internet applications optimizes research effectiveness and external validity. By establishing a mobile internet application case database and precise research methods, this study aims to enhance research reliability and reproducibility. This ensures overall research trustworthiness, meeting validity and reliability requirements.</p><p>In the second part, the study aims to validate the mobile internet value proposition measurement model and scale. Following standard scale construction in management research, a measurement scale is developed for the four elements. With 87 collected samples, exploratory factor analysis and reliability analysis refine the measurement scale. Using a larger sample (902 samples), exploratory factor analysis identifies the scale structure, validated by confirmatory factor analysis. The resulting measurement model comprises 12 items, three for each element.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Model Construction Process</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Constructing Mobile Internet Value Proposition Connotation through case studies.</head><p>The realm of mobile internet encompasses a diverse array of application forms and content. In order to attain a comprehensive understanding of these applications and facilitate in-depth research on specific categories, it is imperative to establish a robust scientific classification framework. To ensure that our case studies encompass a majority of mobile internet service applications, thereby enhancing research effectiveness, mobile internet applications are categorized into three principal domains based on varying information application realms: Information Media, Social Entertainment, and Transaction Authentication. Within these categories, we selected cases representing the most popular applications.</p><p>This study meticulously compiled and summarized applications offered by various mobile operators, mobile internet service providers, and software manufacturers to identify the primary mobile internet applications. These encompass:</p><p>Information Media: Such as mobile newspapers, mobile web browsing, mobile email, mobile music, mobile reading, and mobile videos.</p><p>Social Entertainment: Encompassing mobile instant messaging, mobile social networks, and mobile games.</p><p>Transaction Authentication: Including mobile shopping, mobile payments, mobile banking, mobile securities, and mobile location services.</p><p>To ensure the comprehensiveness and relevance of our case studies, we diligently selected 1-2 representative cases within each primary application category, considering factors like a substantial customer base and high visibility. The chosen cases were characterized by their extended usage period (over a year) and continued active usage. We thus amassed a total of 24 cases representing the three categories of mobile internet applications: Information Media, Social Entertainment, and Transaction Authentication, as the focal subjects for our case studies.</p><p>The data collected from each application case underwent an initial analysis. Qualitative data analysis was employed to provide descriptions and insights into the ubiquity, convenience, personalization, and localization of value propositions within each case. The data were subsequently structured and coded for more profound and thorough analysis of the four value proposition variables. Building upon the initial data analysis from the 24 cases, this study embarked on both single-case and cross-case analyses within the three core application categories. The objective was to transcend the initial insights confined to individual cases and instead concentrate on the observation, analysis, and consolidation of causal relationships and the implications of value propositions within each case. This process was undertaken to facilitate the preliminary development of theoretical foundations.</p><p>Subsequently, further case analysis was conducted for the three principal application categories. The research consistently reviewed, refined, and synthesized the elements concerning the implications of value proposition variables across the 24 applications. Following a more in-depth examination of value proposition categorizations, this study presented a comprehensive breakdown of value proposition metrics tailored to each major application category. This culminated in the creation of a value proposition model, as illustrated in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>. dataset was assembled, and rigorous exploratory factor analysis and reliability assessments were executed to enhance the precision of the measurement scale. This meticulous process resulted in a structured scale comprising 12 items, with each of the four elements within the value proposition comprising three items, as detailed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>.</p><p>Employing the structural equation modeling (SEM) approach, we established a comprehensive measurement model for evaluating the mobile internet value proposition. Through the collection of a substantial sample (902 respondents in total), we conducted confirmatory factor analysis and reliability testing using the structural equation measurement method on the mobile internet value proposition scale generated through exploratory factor analysis. The goodness-of-fit results(as depicted in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4&amp;5</ref>) from the measurement equation demonstrate a strong fit of the mobile internet value proposition measurement scale, thus validating the four elements and connotations proposed in the case study.As a result, a measurement model for the mobile internet value proposition was obtained. The system can automatically identify me when I log in to this service. This service provides me with personalized information and services. Using this service on my personal mobile phone (mobile device) makes me feel more secure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mobile Internet Value Proposition -Localization</head><p>This service provides me with appropriate information and services based on my location. I do not need to actively provide information about my location. This service allows me to obtain location information and activity paths of myself or others (things). Acquiring Location 0.4939 0.9069 Subsequently, utilizing data gathered from the final scale, constructed post exploratory factor analysis and reliability testing, we performed confirmatory factor analysis on the four variables: ubiquity, convenience, individuality, and location of the mobile internet value proposition, employing LISREL software. The confirmatory factor analysis sample encompassed 902 valid questionnaires, which were entirely distinct from the earlier exploratory factor analysis dataset. This effort culminated in the realization of the mobile internet value proposition model (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">6</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Results and finding</head><p>The essence of Mobile Internet value propositions comprises four key dimensions: Ubiquity, Convenience, Individualization and Localization, as illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</p><p>Ubiquity represents the value derived from the pervasive nature of mobile communication networks, enabling information exchange and transaction processing from any location at any time, including the effective utilization of fragmented and idle time.</p><p>Convenience signifies the value arising from the ease of use of mobile devices. This is prominently characterized by rapid access to services, the seamless availability of mobile terminals, and the user-friendly operation of these devices.</p><p>Individualization pertains to the value attributed to the unique characteristics of mobile terminal owners. This is primarily demonstrated through the system's automatic recognition of individuals, the provision of personalized information and services, and the assurance of security for personal terminals.</p><p>Localization encompasses the value stemming from location-based services, prominently exemplified by delivering information and services tailored to the user's current location, without necessitating active location and path provisioning, and the capability to access the location and path of other users or objects. This research offers vital theoretical support to enterprises seeking to implement effective mobile internet strategies and carve out new market opportunities. In the formulation of these strategies, a fundamental first step involves the identification and capture of valuable prospects. Enterprises have two main avenues for introducing mobile internet strategies. The first avenue entails expanding market space through innovative business models during stages of strategic and value innovation. The second involves leveraging mobile technology to enhance services and product delivery, achieved through mobile internet-based product and service innovation or business model innovation. Two examination pathways are presented here: one examines novel business possibilities that mobile internet can bring, with a focus on areas capable of creating customer value and leveraging mobile internet advantages (e.g., mobile social networking services). The second pathway analyzes information processing elements within the enterprise's value activities (e.g., mobile customer relationship management). This study also sheds light on the role and essence of mobile internet value propositions. When integrating mobile internet strategies, enterprises must recognize and deepen their understanding of mobile internet value propositions within their products, services, and business models, with a goal to maximize the impact of these value propositions.</p><p>This study still possesses certain limitations. First, the empirical research adopted a convenience sampling method, which demanded substantial time and effort for both questionnaire distribution and retrieval. Although the sample size met the requirements, the over representation of younger individuals in the business community implies a non-random sample selection. Second, the study employed interviews and questionnaires to examine mobile internet value propositions, leaving room for enhanced rigor through the utilization of text mining methods in future research. Finally, a more extensive investigation into mobile internet value propositions within the context of mobile internet customer value creation mechanisms could offer valuable insights to organizations shaping their mobile internet strategies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Conclusion</head><p>Building upon existing theoretical research on mobile internet and value propositions, this study delved into the concept of mobile internet value propositions. Utilizing case studies, it aimed to define and measure the essence of mobile business value propositions. By conducting a large-scale empirical investigation, a comprehensive measurement scale, consisting of 12 items, was developed for mobile business value propositions. This transitioned the focus of research on mobile business value propositions from theoretical analysis to practical application, thereby unveiling the core significance of these propositions. The study effectively bridged the gap from conceptualization to variable establishment, culminating in a well-defined measurement framework. This research not only advances the theoretical understanding of mobile internet value creation but also holds considerable practical relevance for organizations implementing mobile internet applications and creating value for their customers. Furthermore, it provides a solid foundation for future theoretical investigations in this area.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Mobile Internet Value Proposition Model</figDesc><graphic coords="5,315.58,343.79,222.70,125.27" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Data Analysis of Value Proposition within the Case of Mobile Internet (Using Mobile WebBrowsing as an Example)</figDesc><table><row><cell>Case</cell><cell>Case Description</cell></row><row><cell>Mobile Internet</cell><cell>Users of mobile web browsing can use</cell></row><row><cell>Usage</cell><cell>handheld mobile devices to interact</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>with the internet, utilizing their spare</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>time or accessing information anytime</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>and anywhere.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Mobile Internet Value Proposition Connotation and Measurement Model</figDesc><table><row><cell>Elements</cell><cell>Connotation and Measurement</cell></row><row><cell>Ubiquity -Value</cell><cell>information and handle affairs</cell></row><row><cell>Generated by the</cell><cell>anytime and anywhere</cell></row><row><cell>Ubiquity of Mobile</cell><cell>Send and receive information and</cell></row><row><cell>Communication</cell><cell>handle affairs at any time</cell></row><row><cell>Networks Send and</cell><cell>Fully utilize fragmented time and</cell></row><row><cell>receive</cell><cell>idle time</cell></row><row><cell>Convenience -</cell><cell>access corresponding mobile</cell></row><row><cell>Value Generated by</cell><cell>internet services</cell></row><row><cell>the Convenience of</cell><cell>Mobile devices are always within</cell></row><row><cell>Mobile Terminals</cell><cell>reach</cell></row><row><cell>Mobile devices can</cell><cell>Mobile devices are easier and</cell></row><row><cell>quickly</cell><cell>more efficient to operate than</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>other tools</cell></row><row><cell>Individuality -</cell><cell>The system can automatically</cell></row><row><cell>Value Generated by</cell><cell>identify the login account when</cell></row><row><cell>the Individuality of</cell><cell>logging in to the corresponding</cell></row><row><cell>Mobile Terminal</cell><cell>mobile internet service</cell></row><row><cell>Owners</cell><cell>Mobile internet services can</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>provide personalized information</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>and services to customers</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Using mobile internet services on</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>personal mobile phones (mobile</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>devices) is safer than other means</cell></row><row><cell>Location -Value</cell><cell>Mobile internet services provide</cell></row><row><cell>Generated by</cell><cell>appropriate information and</cell></row><row><cell>Location-based</cell><cell>services based on customer</cell></row><row><cell>Services</cell><cell>location</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Customers (or mobile devices) do</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>not need to actively provide their</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>location information</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mobile internet services allow</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>customers to obtain location</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>information and activity paths of</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>others (things)</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p><p>3.2.2 Constructing a Measurement Scale of the Measurement Model and Testing</p>Adhering to established protocols for scale construction</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref></p>, a comprehensive measurement scale was formulated for the measurement model, featuring four distinct elements. Subsequently, an 87-sample</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Pre-measurement Scale of Mobile Internet Value Proposition</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Exploratory Factor Analysis Results of</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="4">Mobile Internet Value Propositions (N=87)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Items</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Factor Loadings</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(Abbr.)</cell><cell>Ubiquit</cell><cell>Conveni</cell><cell>Individ</cell><cell>Locali</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>y</cell><cell>-ence</cell><cell>-uality</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>zation</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Reliability Test of Mobile Internet Value Proposition Variables (N=87)</figDesc><table><row><cell>Item</cell><cell>Item-Total</cell><cell>Cronbach'</cell><cell>Cronbach</cell></row><row><cell>(Abbr.)</cell><cell>Correlatio</cell><cell>s α after</cell><cell>s α</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>n</cell><cell>Deleting</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>the Item</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ubiquity</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>-Anywhere</cell><cell>0.6972</cell><cell>0.8951</cell><cell>0.9055</cell></row><row><cell>-Anytime</cell><cell>0.6942</cell><cell>0.8955</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>-Fragmented</cell><cell>0.6239</cell><cell>0.8986</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Time</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Convenience</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Quick</cell><cell>0.5905</cell><cell>0.8997</cell><cell>0.8137</cell></row><row><cell>Access</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Handy</cell><cell>0.7301</cell><cell>0.8936</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Availability</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Easy</cell><cell>0.5991</cell><cell>0.8994</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Operation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Individuality</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Auto</cell><cell>0.6862</cell><cell>0.8950</cell><cell>0.8526</cell></row><row><cell>Identificatio</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>n</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Personalized</cell><cell>0.7178</cell><cell>0.8936</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Security</cell><cell>0.7201</cell><cell>0.8940</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Localization</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Location-</cell><cell>0.5961</cell><cell>0.9001</cell><cell>0.7595</cell></row><row><cell>Based</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sending</cell><cell>0.5587</cell><cell>0.9020</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Location</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Measurement Model Fit Results for Mobile Internet Value Propositions (N=902)</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Path Standardized</cell><cell>Path</cell><cell>T-</cell><cell>P</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Coefficie</cell><cell>valu</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>nt</cell><cell>e</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Anywhere</cell><cell>←Ubiquity</cell><cell>0.89</cell><cell>32.8</cell><cell>***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Anytime</cell><cell>←Ubiquity</cell><cell>0.92</cell><cell>34.8</cell><cell>***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>5</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Fragmented</cell><cell>←Ubiquity</cell><cell>0.69</cell><cell>23.0</cell><cell>***</cell></row><row><cell>Time</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>3</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Quick</cell><cell>←</cell><cell>0.85</cell><cell>30.6</cell><cell>***</cell></row><row><cell>Access</cell><cell>Convenience</cell><cell></cell><cell>7</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Handy</cell><cell>←</cell><cell>0.84</cell><cell>29.9</cell><cell>***</cell></row><row><cell>Availability</cell><cell>Convenience</cell><cell></cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Easy</cell><cell>←</cell><cell>0.77</cell><cell>26.3</cell><cell>***</cell></row><row><cell>Operation</cell><cell>Convenience</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Automatic</cell><cell>←</cell><cell>0.72</cell><cell>23.5</cell><cell>***</cell></row><row><cell>Recognition</cell><cell>Individualizati</cell><cell></cell><cell>7</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>on</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Personalizati</cell><cell>←</cell><cell>0.81</cell><cell>28.1</cell><cell>***</cell></row><row><cell>on</cell><cell>Individualizati</cell><cell></cell><cell>6</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>on</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Security</cell><cell>←</cell><cell>0.76</cell><cell>25.6</cell><cell>***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Individualizati</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>on</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Location-</cell><cell>←</cell><cell>0.82</cell><cell>27.6</cell><cell>***</cell></row><row><cell>Based</cell><cell>Localization</cell><cell></cell><cell>5</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Location</cell><cell>←</cell><cell>0.71</cell><cell>22.6</cell><cell>***</cell></row><row><cell>Retrieval</cell><cell>Localization</cell><cell></cell><cell>5</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Path</cell><cell>←</cell><cell>0.72</cell><cell>23.0</cell><cell>***</cell></row><row><cell>Retrieval</cell><cell>Localization</cell><cell></cell><cell>9</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>χ²</cell><cell>411.98</cell><cell>NFI</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.9</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>df</cell><cell>48</cell><cell>NNFI</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.9</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>χ²/ df</cell><cell>8.58</cell><cell>GFI</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.9</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>RMSEA</cell><cell>0.092</cell><cell>AGFI</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.8</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>SRMR</cell><cell>0.056</cell><cell>CFI</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.9</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Note: For t-values greater than 1.96, * denotes significance</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">level of P&lt;0.05; for t-values greater than 2.58, ** denotes</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">significance level of P&lt;0.01; for t-values greater than 3.29,</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">*** denotes significance level of P&lt;0.001.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>SHS Web of Conferences 181, 03025 (2024) https://doi.org/10.1051/shsconf/202418103025</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgment</head><p>The article was supported by the project of <rs type="projectName">Zhejiang Gongshang University Hangzhou College of Commerce</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">2222109</rs>).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_J92KHN3">
					<idno type="grant-number">2222109</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Zhejiang Gongshang University Hangzhou College of Commerce</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Understanding Customer Value in the Mobile Internet Era (hindawi.com)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Nigatu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2021</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of value co-creation in e-commerce to improve MSEM marketing performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Simanjuntak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sinaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A T</forename><surname>Simanjuntak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Proceeding Conference on Information Technology, Multimedia, Architecture, Design, and E-Business (IMADE)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expanding the Universe of Marketing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>U-Commerce</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">30</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002-10">October. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emerging value propositions for mcommerce</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Clarke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Iii</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Strategies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">M: Business.thuvienso.hoasen.edu.vn</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Oc Ferrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hirt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ferrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Customer value propositions in business markets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Narus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Van Rossum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Harvard Business Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">90</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Case study research: Design and methods</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage Publications</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>rd edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Multiple Regression and Beyond-An Introduction to Multiple Regression and Structural Equation Modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Timothy</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Keith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
