<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Appraising the Nexus between Influencers and Sustainability-Oriented Innovation Adoption in Affordable Housing Projects</title>
				<funder ref="#_gVXQffp #_J2E9A5H">
					<orgName type="full">Applications for Green Infrastructure</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_n57mJep #_usPuZzf #_EUp7qcV #_Y234WdX #_WeG3es8 #_WfHBH6n #_bxrT7kZ #_4sXKKxF #_p4kgdUV">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Appraising the Nexus between Influencers and Sustainability-Oriented Innovation Adoption in Affordable Housing Projects</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">0968-0802</idno>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1002/sd.2306</idno>
					<note type="submission">Document Version: Article (Accepted Version)</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T23:35+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Challenges</term>
					<term>Company characteristics</term>
					<term>Project Characteristics</term>
					<term>Sustainabilityoriented innovation</term>
					<term>Sustainable innovative affordable housing</term>
					<term>Sustainable development</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Appraising the nexus between influencers and sustainability-oriented innovation adoption in affordable housing projects. Sustainable Development.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Demands for improved sustainability performance, adoption of innovation and attainment project objectives have caused a positive paradigm shift in the construction industry through the emergence of innovative construction methods, materials and technologies <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Moghayedi et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Adabre and Chan, 2019)</ref>. Similarly, sustainability-oriented innovative practices within affordable housing projects have been identified as mechanisms that can engender cost reduction and improvement of housing quality whilst enhancing the environmental and social aspects of affordable housing deemed necessary for housing market continuity <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Winston, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Jamaludin et al., 2018)</ref>.</p><p>However, awareness of a particular sustainability-oriented innovative practice does not necessarily ensure its adoption, as a series of interrelated events are required for successful adoption <ref type="bibr">(Moghayedi et al., 2022)</ref>, thus supporting the general perception that the construction industry is penurious in the uptake of innovation <ref type="bibr">(Adafin et al., 2021)</ref>. Certain organizational and project characteristics have also been identified as influencing the rate of adoption of innovation in the construction industry <ref type="bibr">(Wei and</ref><ref type="bibr">Lam, 2021, Seng et al., 2020)</ref>. Several scholars espouse the need for a deep understanding of the key drivers and challenges which prevent the use of sustainability-oriented innovations (SOI) on affordable housing projects <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Moghayedi et al., 2021)</ref>. Patently, the ability to know how, why, and where home designers and developers adopt sustainability and innovation concepts is critical and empowers the industry players within the housing sector on how to expedite the adoption rate thereby enabling effective supply of SIAH.</p><p>In response to the foregoing, this study seeks to determine the key internal factors that influence the adoption of sustainability-oriented and innovation-related practices, materials, and technologies in affordable housing projects, both at company and project levels, and the external factors which might influence adoption levels. Furthermore, it seeks to determine the extant causality between these key drivers, challenges, and the extent of use of sustainable and innovative methods, materials, and technologies in affordable housing projects. Suffice to say that it seeks to establish how these factors and challenges impact on the extent of use of SOIs on affordable housing projects using a developing country exemplar. It is expected that such understanding and the emergent causal model will promote the use of these SOIs as catalysts for developing SIAH whilst providing valuable reference for affordable housing stakeholders and decision-makers on the adoption of various SOIs in similar contexts.</p><p>To achieve its aim, the following three research questions are answered by this study:</p><p>1. What are the internal drivers influencing the adoption of SOI on affordable housing projects at both company and project levels?</p><p>2. What are the challenges negating adoption of SOI during design and construction of affordable housing projects? 3. What is the impact of these internal drivers and challenges on the extent of use of SOI in affordable housing projects?</p><p>The rest of the paper is structured accordingly: Section 2 offers a literature review on SOI related to affordable housing projects and internal and external influences on adoption of SOIs, Section 3 puts forward the research hypothesis and the development of the causal model, Section 4 presents the methods used for data collection and analysis; Sections 5 and 6 offer the findings and the discussion; and the conclusion is provided in Section 7.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Literature review</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Sustainability-oriented innovations in affordable housing</head><p>Knowledge concerning the importance of sustainability and innovation in housing development is globally gaining traction, albeit slowly, within the affordable housing subsector, hampered mainly by client ignorance and lack of associated regulations <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Moghayedi et al., 2021)</ref>. For many developers, using conventional methods and materials to minimise housing construction cost, regardless of their associated negative financial effects on operation/maintenance of such houses, remains the norm. Also, the lack of incentives for developers to take the operating cost of the dwelling into consideration has resulted in a tendency for them to ignore critical facets such as sustainability and innovation when developing affordable houses <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Patel and Padhya, 2021)</ref>.</p><p>Innovation is considered an important criterion in affordable housing development. Innovation is about changing paradigms, creating new ideas; it is a process which inspires change and creates value, or more practically defined as the implementation of a new or significantly changed product or process <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Adams et al., 2016)</ref>. Within the affordable housing context, scholars admit to the potential of innovation to enhance the sustainability performance of the houses <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Moghayedi et al., 2021)</ref>. There are many types of innovations, each finding some application in the affordable housing sector. For instance, technological innovation is has been described as capacitating construction firms with new technologies that can appropriately transform and complement current technologies to achieve and sustain better levels of performance <ref type="bibr">(Osunsanmi et al., 2020)</ref>.</p><p>To significantly reduce the negative environmental impacts whilst improving the social and economic sustainability performance of buildings, innovations pertaining to construction methods, materials and technologies for housing delivery have become imperative <ref type="bibr">(Kornilov et al., 2020)</ref>. Hence, there is a need to determine and deploy these innovative practices, materials, and technologies during the design and development of affordable housing projects.</p><p>Likewise, it is necessary to identify the factors influencing the adoption of innovation in such housing projects, particularly at company and project levels.</p><p>SOIs like passive design, renewable energy, prefabrication, water harvesting and recycling, building information modelling (BIM), green recycled materials and many more are commonplace in the construction industry. Globally, scholars are continuously exploring SOIs to provide solutions to issues associated with housing delivery. For instance, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Panda et al., (2018)</ref> explored the contributions of 3D printing-enabled architecture and interior designs towards achieving sustainable residential houses.</p><p>Similarly, Modular Construction System (MCS) is gaining popularity in developed countries but remain nascent in developing countries. <ref type="bibr">Eng and Zainal (2021)</ref> explored MCS awareness levels among home developers and the challenges faced in the adoption of robotics within such systems. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Sertyesilisi et al., (2021)</ref> posit that sustainability performance of houses can be enhanced using BIM where the integration of energy simulation software allows improved energy efficiency as well as reduced lifecycle costs across various phases of the building lifecycle <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Sertyesilisi et al., 2021)</ref>.</p><p>From the foregoing, the role of SOIs in enabling SIAH can be discerned. Unfortunately, rising levels of dissatisfaction of occupants within the affordable housing space, point to the contributions of innovative practices, materials, and technologies to improve sustainability performance of construction projects, as being poorly understood by relevant stakeholders. The limited use of SOIs within the affordable housing context has been attributed to the challenge negating the adoption of these innovative practices, methods and technologies <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Jamaludin et al., 2018)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Afanasyeva et al., (2020)</ref> analysed the problems of socio-economic accessibility of innovative housing from the perspective of sustainable construction, using the lens of legislative norms and strategy implementation. The research showed that the lack of tools, legislation, and policies for efficient management of sustainable construction practices seeking to improve housing affordability, posed a salient challenge <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Afanasyeva et al., 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Therefore, the idea of sustainable innovative housing can and should become a national idea, playing an important role in determining state priorities and prospects for further housing reform <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Afanasyeva et al., 2020)</ref>.</p><p>In developing countries like South Africa, there is no widely accepted definition of the sustainable affordable housing concept <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Moghayedi et al., 2021)</ref>. This lack of a widely accepted definition for SIAH is reflective of the assertions made by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Afanasyeva et al., (2020)</ref> concerning the absence of governance and legislative frameworks and policies for adoption of innovation towards improving sustainability performance and affordability of such houses. The advocacy for SIAH remains largely business-driven by some large developers in the developing country context although the market remains lucrative for developers who are not keen on its implementation <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Patel and Padhya, 2021)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Internal influences on adopting sustainability-oriented innovation in affordable housing</head><p>Internal innovation enablers refer to the competency, commitment and actions within an organisation which motivates for innovation adoption as an essential commitment to pursue sustainable projects <ref type="bibr">(Martins and Saavedra Farias, 2019)</ref>. These enablers can be split into (i) commitment and interest, (ii) management and policies, and (iii) capability and resources. The characteristics of construction organisations either impede or expedite the adoption of SOIs on construction projects, where <ref type="bibr">Khurana et al., (2019)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Banihashemi et al., (2017)</ref> conclude that the awareness and familiarity of construction companies with sustainability and innovation concepts remained critical factors affecting the level of success in the adoption of appropriate SOIs in construction projects. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Banihashemi et al., (2017)</ref> argued for advancing sustainability and innovation whilst overcoming adoption-related challenges on construction projects through increased focus on the climate and structure of a construction company and project team, both of which were identified as impacting factors.</p><p>A well-established firm, with an open, receptive, and conducive organisational climate that highlights and supports efforts to explore and try new ideas as a core value and strategy, elicit greater efficiency and productivity from workers, thus benefitting from SOIs adoption <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Rahdari et al., 2016)</ref>. Drucker (2014) identified organizational climate and structure attributes such as establishment and size of company, experience of company with specific type of project, familiarity and awareness of company leadership and technical staff with sustainability and innovation as influencing the level of SOI adoption on projects. For example, large companies can adopt more sustainable and innovative practices because of their strong capital-base, wide-range of experience, full commitment from executive management, and expertise. Small companies tend to keep costs to the minimum and adopting innovation practices would invariably affect their profit margin <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Zakaria et al., 2018)</ref>.</p><p>At the project-level, Ozorhon and Oral, (2017), <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Zakaria et al., (2018)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Stanitsas et al., (2021)</ref> identified project attributes such as size of project, type of project, procurement method and type of client as posing a strong influence on the extent of SOI adoption on construction projects. Within the housing sector, different types of housing would require different types of SOIs due to differences in building typology, budget and cost, complexity and target client <ref type="bibr">(Olanrewaju et al., 2018)</ref>. Companies are also becoming increasingly concerned with establishing closer connections with customers through ensuring improved end user satisfaction. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Banihashemi et al., (2017)</ref> opined that project owners/clients serve a pivotal role in the SOIs capacity of a construction project.</p><p>Based on the foregoing, it is evident that company characteristics and project attributes influence the adoption of SOIs within the affordable housing context. Hence, the following hypotheses:</p><p>H1: There is a positive correlation between the company characteristics and the extent of use of SOI in affordable housing.</p><p>H2: There is a positive correlation between the project characteristics and the extent of use SOI in affordable housing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">External challenges on adoption of sustainability-oriented innovation in affordable housing</head><p>There are several challenges, occurring at project, company and industry-wide levels, that negate the adoption of SOI on affordable housing projects in developing countries <ref type="bibr">(Adabre et al., 2021)</ref>. It is administrative and policy barriers, such as the absence of policy and regulation, and the lack of incentives at all stages of design and construction lifecycle, that negatively affect the adoption of SOI in housing projects <ref type="bibr">(Kornilov et al., 2020)</ref>. The lack of incentives impedes effective collaboration between institutional enablers, stifling their readiness and commitment to adopt new ideas <ref type="bibr">( Martins and Saavedra Farias, 2019)</ref>. According to <ref type="bibr">Olanrewaju et al., (2018)</ref>, most developers in developing countries abide by the standard and minimum regulatory requirements with only a few showing any interest and capability to go beyond that due to the lack of incentives.</p><p>The adoption of SOIs in the housing sector is further constrained by the high cost of deployment, difficulty in obtaining local innovative materials and technologies, and lack of local technical skills to harness such innovations <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Patel and Padhya, 2021)</ref>. Most construction companies and home developers are comfortable with their business marketability and hence, reluctant to commit to something more sustainable and innovative since doing so requires higher capital investment upfront <ref type="bibr">(Li and Liu, 2019)</ref>. The deployment of SOIs like alternative production methods, new materials and technologies requires the development of new forms of competencies and knowledge. As such, the lack of technical knowledge and understanding constitute barriers to the successful deliver of sustainable and affordable housing <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Adabre and Chan, 2020)</ref>. Since most affordable housing projects in developing countries are constructed by small-to-medium sized enterprises (SMEs) with low internal knowledge and expertise about SOIs, housing developers tend to appoint external experts to assist thereby adding to overhead costs of projects and significantly impacting on the profitability of a development <ref type="bibr">(Pablo and London, 2020)</ref>. Innovation transfer endeavours within affordable housing projects are being severely hampered by a lack of proper understanding of innovation transfer issues and their interrelationships with company capabilities and processes, and the knowledge characteristics of the technologies being transferred <ref type="bibr">(Khan et al., 2019)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Moghayedi et al., (2022)</ref> stated that due to the paucity in development, manufacturing, and supply of local innovative construction materials in developing countries, most are imported at high cost compared to the conventional materials, thereby making it a challenge to be deployed in the affordable housing projects. Imported innovative products are often incompatible with local climatic conditions, necessitating some degree of customisation which may farther increase project costs.</p><p>From the foregoing, the challenges impeding the adoption of SOI in affordable housing projects can be discerned. This study will seek to examine the negatively mediating effect of these challenges on the correlation between the company and project characteristics and, the extent of use of SOIs (methods, materials, and technologies) in affordable housing. To achieve this, the following hypotheses have been articulated: H3: There is a negative correlation between the challenges and the extent of use of SOI in affordable housing projects. H4: Challenges are negatively mediating the correlation between the project characteristics and extend of use of SOI in affordable housing projects. H5: Challenges are negatively mediating the correlation between the company characteristics and extend of use of SOI in affordable housing projects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Modelling causality</head><p>Taking the literature review and formulated research hypotheses into consideration, a theoretical framework was developed detailing the causality between the company characteristics, project influential factors, challenges to adoption of SOI and extent of use of SOI (methods, materials, and technologies) in affordable housing projects, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. The company-related influential factors were theorised as consisting of company size, experience with housing projects, familiarity with SOI in housing projects and, establishment of the company. The project-related influential factors include project size, owner of the project, project procurement, type of housing projects. Based on the reviewed literature, the challenges to the adoption of SOI in affordable housing projects were established as; high cost (initial/ maintenance/ operation), lack of guidelines and standards, incompatibility with other methods/ materials/ technology, tendency to use conventional methods/ materials/ technologies, lack of incentives, lack of technical knowledge and skill, lack of awareness, lack of policy and regulation, low social acceptance, low availability in local market. Moreover, the extent of use of SOI in affordable housing projects is evaluated through the usance of sustainable new methods in design, sustainable alternative methods in construction, new building materials and innovative technologies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Research methods</head><p>A quantitative research design was adopted as the most appropriate approach to objectively model and verify the extant relationships among the variables. Quantitative models allow for deductive testing, thus offering protection against contradiction of bias and the generalisation and replication of findings. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Creswell and Creswell, 2017)</ref>. Accordingly, an online questionnaire survey was undertaken to establish the impact of the company and project characteristics as internal factors and challenges, as external factors, influencing the extent of use of SOIs by housing developers on affordable housing projects in South Africa. The study's constructs, the variables used in measuring the study constructs and its corresponding measurement scale are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. The study population consisted of 16,000 housing companies registered with the South African National Home Builders Registration Council (NHBRC). A total of 517 valid responses was collected across South Africa, representing a sufficient sample size (376) at a confidence level of 95% and confidence interval of 5.</p><p>The questionnaire comprised of three sections directed at the study objectives. The items in first section were focused on eliciting general background information of the home developer companies. The second section of the questionnaire comprised of four sub-sections and used</p><p>the Likert scale to obtain information on the extent of use of SOIs in designing and developing of latest affordable housing project completed by participants. The third section of the questionnaire was collected the level of impact of challenges on adoption of sustainable methods, new materials and innovative technologies in design and construction of their recent affordable housing project using Likert Scale.</p><p>The data collected was analysed using descriptive and inferential statistical techniques to determine the frequency and Relative Important Index (RII) of the study variables. Path Modification adjusts the model to improve model fitness. Finally, validation is the process of improving the reliability and stability of the model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Company characteristics</head><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> presents the company characteristics analysis of the 517 home developers participated in the study. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> indicates that majority of the developers (33.7%) established more than 5 years and 27.9% of companies established within 5 years. The results show 50% of companies have low experience with affordable housing projects (1 completed project). The findings on the size of companies show that most of the companies are small (38.5%) and micro (30.8%) size in regarding of employees/workers. About 65% of the housing developers are moderately or highly familiar with sustainable methods, new materials, and innovative technologies, while 10.6% of companies are unfamiliar with sustainability and innovation in design and construction. This suggests that the majority of the home developers belong to micro and small size categories with low experience in design and construction of affordable housing. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Project characteristics</head><p>A summary of the affordable housing project characteristics is shown in   The results concerning sustainable methods used in construction projects reveal the water efficient methods (EUC3), energy efficient methods (EUC9) and construction waste management (EUC5) were the most common construction methods adopted by home developers during construction of the affordable housing projects as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>.</p><p>Moreover, deconstruction/disassembly methods (EUC1), and less labour-intensive methods (EUC2) were not adopted by most developers.  home developers admitted to using mixed reality and augmented reality in design or construction of affordable housing. Despite these findings, most respondents indicated that drones have been used on majority (70%) of the sampled size housing projects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">Challenges negating adoption of sustainability-oriented innovation</head><p>The respondents were asked to rate the level of difficulty caused by 10 most critical challenges to adopt sustainable design and construction methods, new materials and innovative technologies in design and construction of their latest affordable housing project. These 10 critical challenges were identified from literature and validated by the NHBRC experts panel and small groups of developers through pre-testing of the questionnaire. RII is used to compare the level of difficulty of challenges made for adopting each sustainable methods, new materials, and innovative technologies. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5">Causal Model</head><p>To validate the developed SIAH causal model and association between the constructs, all identified variables (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>) were included to the initial mode in SmartPLS, and the hypothesised model was tested using collected data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5.1">Analysis of the measurement model</head><p>The measured variables were assessed for consistency, reliability and validity using confirmatory factor analysis. The results of the internal consistency, composite reliability, convergent validity tests and discriminant validity are summarised in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">5</ref>. The results of Cronbach's Alpha are between 0.7 and 0.95, which indicate a reliable internal consistency between the variables under the same constructs and that the variables are not highly inter-correlated. Furthermore, the coefficient rho-A test results between Cronbach's Alpha and Composite Reliability also prove the acceptable internal consistency between the variables of the study's sub-constructs. The composite reliability test results and Average</p><p>Variance Extracted (AVE) tests are above 0.7 and 0.5 respectively, which prove the reliability and convergent validity between variables of sub-constructs and indicating that the reliability of the developed model is acceptable. Furthermore, the square root of the AVE value of each measured variable is greater than the correlation coefficient between the variables as shown in Table <ref type="table">6</ref>, which indicates that measures of variables that theoretically should not be highly related to each other are, indeed, not found to be highly correlated to each other.</p><p>Following the reliability and validity checks, the fitness-for-purpose of the casual model of SIAH was evaluated. As shown in Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>, the R-squared values for the constructs are above 0.7 which indicate the strength relationship between developed model and the dependent variable, moreover the results from the analysis of the model show that all fit indices of model are above the recommended values (x 2 = 163.351; x 2 /DF = 1.677; p = 0.000, CFI = 0.934; GFI = 0.917; RMSEA = 0.031).</p><p>Finally, the path analysis for the causal model of SIAH was developed. As illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>, all loading factors of variables are greater than 0.8, indicating highly satisfactory relationships of variables in the reflective measurement of constructs and the model. Since all the variables are above the acceptable level, they were used to discuss the importance of each variable for the defined constructs in the model. This was to identify which variables should be focused on to yield higher extent of use of sustainable methods, new materials, and innovative technologies in affordable housing projects. Overall, the results of these tests prove that the collected data have high satisfactory validity, reliability, and internal consistency.  The Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref> shows the total effect coefficient among constructs. The project and company characteristics have small (e&lt;0.5) positive effect on the extent of use of sustainable methods in design and construction, new materials, and technologies in affordable housing projects. The results of total effect coefficient also reveal the challenges have moderate (-0.8&lt;e&lt;-0.5) negative effects on the extent of use of sustainable methods in construction, new materials, and technologies, although the challenges have a small (-0.5&lt;e&lt;-0.2) negative effect on the extent of use of sustainable methods in design.</p><p>Finally, the outer weights of each dependent variable are estimated, and the results are ranked according to the relative importance in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">7</ref>.  Overall, the outer weights of variables of each influence are very close (~0,280 for company characteristics, ~0.300 for project characteristics and ~0.120 for challenges), which validate the importance of all selected variables on the adoption of SOI on South African affordable housing, as listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">10</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Discussion</head><p>The main objectives of this study were to examine the causality and evaluate the effects of company and project characteristics as internal variables and challenges as external variables on the extent of use of SOIs on affordable housing projects. Based on the results from this evaluation, a SIAH causal model was developed and validated using SEM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Level of SOI adoption and associated challenges</head><p>The analysis of questionnaire responses revealed that the extent of use of SOIs in design and construction of South African affordable housing projects remained relatively low. This is because of the low levels of knowledge and expertise possessed by home designers and developers on sustainable methods of design and construction, new materials, and innovative technologies. This aligns with the findings of the studies by <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Jamaludin et al.,(2018)</ref> and Pablo and London (2020). The conventional procurement systems used in the South African housing sector further exasperate the adoption of SOIs on affordable housing projects, emulating the findings of <ref type="bibr">Karji et al. (2019)</ref>.</p><p>Further analysis of the data verified that the passive methods remained the most used sustainable method by designers because of low cost, high familiarity of designers with these methods and good amount of policy and incentives that encouraging use of these methods. The findings corroborated the observation in previous studies on the effect of high cost and lack of technical guidelines and standards on low adoption of new methods such as life-cycle carbon footprint assessment, renewable energy and lean design in affordable housing project <ref type="bibr">(Junior et al., 2017)</ref>.</p><p>The increasing consideration of environmental sustainability performance due to the negative impact of construction on the environment appear to have encouraged home developers to adopt several resource-efficient methods during the construction of affordable housing. <ref type="bibr">et al., (2022)</ref> suggests that the relatively high cost of water and energy in South Africa has also played a role. Current public incentives centre on labour-intensive construction practices to stem the high unemployment rate in South Africa <ref type="bibr">(Osunsanmi et al., 2020)</ref> thus explaining the limited use of automated construction methods by developers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Moghayedi</head><p>The high level of awareness of designers and developers and availability of local and light materials clarify the high level of use of these materials in affordable housing projects. Also, variables such as high cost, unfamiliarity of designers and developers, as well as reluctance to use new materials resulted in the low level of using new materials, such as nano and green materials in affordable housing projects <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Windapo et al., 2021)</ref>. The respondents perceived that legislative reform is need to prevent the existing regulations, guidelines and building standards to continue as significant barriers to the adoption of SOI in affordable housing projects, a phenomena observed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Jamaludin et al. (2018)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Patel and Padhya (2021)</ref> as well.</p><p>The main challenge, in delivery of SIAH, is how to make innovative and sustainable houses more affordable <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Moghayedi et al., 2021)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chan and Adabre (2019)</ref> conclude that appropriate innovation is able to bridge the gap between sustainable housing and affordable housing. For instance, in low-income affordable units, instead of incorporating costly and complex methods and innovative products, the focus could be on maximising natural resources in designing the affordable housing, such as passive design, efficient resources methods, inexpensive technologies and local materials, etc. as proven by level of extent of use of sustainability and innovation results.</p><p>Furthermore, the study established that SOI was not a priority as many home designers and developers are unwilling to push the boundaries in this regard particularly when it means having to move from the conventional way of construction and venture into an innovative realm of technology which may lead to increased upfront costs and skill. Producing or manufacturing materials and technologies locally can reduce the cost of new materials and consequently improve the local economy in developing countries. Therefore, local company and manufacturers need to be encouraged towards producing new materials and innovative technologies to cater for local demand.</p><p>However, to stay relevant and continue in the business, the home designers and developers would have to follow the market trend. If more private and public clients are demanding SIAH or if the market is lucrative, more designers and developers will use innovative methods, materials and technologies in both design and construction of affordable housing. By educating housing stakeholders including the clients and end users, public awareness regarding the longterm benefits of SIAH, will increase, and consequently enhance the demand for such housing.</p><p>To utilise knowledge from across many disciplinary boundaries in housing projects, all affordable housing stakeholders should collaborate effectively to facilitate the adoption of sustainable methods, new materials, and innovative technologies in affordable housing projects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Causal model of SOI on affordable housing</head><p>The results of the SEM show an acceptable validity of the developed model. The total effect coefficients in the final SIAH causal model, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, confirmed the positive small effect of internal variables on the extent of use of SOIs in affordable housing projects. The existence of positive relationships among company and project characteristics and extent of use mean that the level of use of sustainable methods, new materials and innovative technologies in affordable housing projects directly depends on the size of company and project, experience of company in affordable housing projects, familiarity and awareness of technical staff of company with SOIs, type of housing project, the client of project and project procurement.</p><p>The results of total effect coefficients in the final SIAH causal model also validated the small to moderate negative effect of challenges on the extent of use of SOI on affordable housing projects. Moreover, the comparison of path coefficient (Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>) and total effect coefficients (Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref>) proved the negative mediating effect of challenges on the relationship between internal variables (company and project characteristics) and extent of adoption of SOI on affordable housing projects. The negative relationships among challenges and extent of use of sustainability and innovation indicates that the extent of use of sustainable methods, new materials and innovative technologies could be increased by addressing the challenges on adoption. These aligned with the propositions in the developed causal model (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</p><p>However, the findings in total effect analysis and Table <ref type="table">6</ref> reveal that extent of use of SOI are strongly associated with external challenges. The implication of this finding is that by reducing the external challenges on SOI adoption, the extent of use will significantly improve. This is not only because of the direct negative effect of challenges on extent of use but also the negative mediator impact of challenges on relationship between internal variables and extents of use of SOIs. The findings are consistent with those of previous studies by <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Patel and Padhya, (2021)</ref> and Syed <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Jamaludin et al., (2018)</ref>, who acknowledge that the external variables challenges influence the level of adoption of innovation in construction projects and particularly housing projects, the most.</p><p>The influential factors at both company and project levels provide the resources and capability to enhance the sustainability of affordable housing and deliver SIAH. While government incentives and strategies create an environment which stimulates and enforces design and development of SIAH, educating housing stakeholders will affect the demand for SIAH.</p><p>The validation of the SIAH causal model attests to the applicability of this model as a mechanism for enhancing the extent of use of SOIs in affordable housing projects in furtherance to actualizing SIAH design and construction. Also, it implies that the model can be used to understand and identify the influential internal and external variables, and challenges negating the adoption of methods, materials, and technologies on affordable housing projects.</p><p>In practice, the model not only serves guideline for the affordable housing designers and developers in selecting methods, materials, and technologies in their projects, but also acts as a roadmap for local and national housing policymakers, to reduce the challenges preventing the adoption of SOIs in affordable housing projects.</p><p>The current study is one of the pioneer studies modelling the SOI adoption in affordable housing using SEM. The developed SIAH causal model was validated in part through hypotheses testing. Previous studies and models in this field mainly tested the existing theories.</p><p>In contrast, the current study used SEM as an appropriate method for the exploration of the SIAH conceptual model.</p><p>The research presents several practical and theoretical implications for researchers and practitioners. The findings of this study will provide valuable awareness of the critical role and effectiveness of technological innovations on the sustainability of affordable housing.</p><p>Practically, the findings of this research help understand the planning scope and organisational and project requirements towards a continuous and consistent SOI adoption to achieve superior sustainability in affordable housing. Theoretically, this research extends the postulations on the internal and external influences on SOIs adoption as the primary driver of developing SIAH.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Conclusions</head><p>The study establishes the existence of causality and effects between SIAH influential internal and external variables and validates the effect of these variables, on the extent of use of SOI on affordable housing projects; by empirically examining the nexus between company and project characteristics, challenges, and extent of use of sustainable methods, new materials, and innovative technologies.</p><p>The study's results show that; extent of use of SOI in affordable housing projects are positively associated with internal variables and negatively associated with external challenges. The positive correlation between company and project characteristics and extent of use makes it possible to conclude that the level of sustainability and innovation in affordable housing projects not only depend on the experience, knowledge and competency of designers and developers of affordable housing but also the size, type, and the client of projects. However, the finding of study reveals that company characteristics that contribute to experience and knowledge have a greater influence on extent of use, than project-specific factors such as project procurement.</p><p>To address current issues of affordable housing and enhance the level of sustainability performance of such houses and well-being of residents, the extent of use of appropriate sustainable methods, new materials and innovative technologies in affordable housing must be improved. Hence, the knowledge, advantages, and opportunities of adoption of SOI in affordable housing should spread among all housing stakeholders. Therefore, policymakers, designers and developers must ensure that the executives in the affordable housing sectors and their organisations become conversant with change and ensure that all parties acquire necessary understanding and awareness on adopting sustainability and innovation.</p><p>Furthermore, it can be concluded from the findings of this study that appropriate strategic national and local plans are required for design and develop SIAH by enhancing the extent of use of SOI on affordable housing projects. Government's strong commitment and political willingness is crucial in instigating affordable housing projects developers to contribute to responsible production through adoption of SOI on their projects.</p><p>The research contributes to sustainability of affordable housing by providing a new perspective for understanding SOI adoption and barriers in affordable housing projects. It brings about the insights that the development of SIAH cannot be prosperous until it ensures a continuous and consistent innovation adoption to resolve the sustainability issues of affordable housing projects.</p><p>Summarily, this study which focuses on the delivery of affordable housing within the South African context, makes a salient contribution to improving housing delivery efficiencies and enhancing cleaner production through the design of a framework for facilitating SOI adoption at company and project levels. However, this study is focused on South African affordable housing projects. Hence, it does not entirely represent the state of SOIs adoption in the housing sector or the construction industry in South Africa.</p><p>The research provides a systematic basis for future studies to assess the actual effectiveness of internal and external influences as well as challenges and barriers as a mediator on the sustainability performance of SIAH through a multi-case study approach. Future studies should also consider measuring the impact of various SOIs on the sustainability of affordable housing projects. Moreover, future studies could focus on the investigation of essential SOIs implementation strategies that overcome the barriers to SOIs adoption in affordable housing projects. A case study of the difficulties experienced by developers in adopting SOIs in affordable housing could contribute to deeper understanding of the findings of this research.</p><p>Finally, due to the high similarity of construction industry and affordable housing projects in developing countries, as shown in the study, the SIAH conceptual framework could be generalised in similar developing country contexts.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Causal model of SOI on SIAH The five hypotheses formulate the company and project characteristics as internal variables, directly influence the extent of adoption of SOI in delivery of affordable housing projects (H1 &amp; H2). The challenges have direct effect on the extent of use of SOI in affordable housing projects (H3). Moreover, the challenges mediate the effect of company and project characteristics on the extent of use of SOIs (H4 &amp; H5).</figDesc><graphic coords="9,72.10,140.09,451.10,194.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>analysis and confirmatory factors analysis were conducted to quantify the relationships among multiple variables and estimate latent constructs, respectively. Structural equation modelling (SEM) was used to test the five hypotheses of the study. SEM, as a multivariate technique that coheres networks of constructs to data with the capability to test and evaluate both direct and indirect effects of multivariate causal relationships, was used to validate the causal relationship between the constructs, using the maximum likelihood estimate and estimated latent variables based on the correlated variations of the dataset. Five analytical steps were utilised in SEM: model specification, identification, parameter estimation, evaluation, and modification. Model specification defines the hypothesized relationships among the variables. Model identification checks overall model fitness based on the fit indices for the test of a single path coefficient. Model evaluation assesses model performance, with quantitative indices calculated for the overall appropriacy of fit.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Extent of use of sustainable methods in construction of affordable housing projects</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Extent of use of technologies in design and construction of affordable housing projects As shown in Figure 5, Computer Aided Design (EUT1), Project portfolio management software (EUT7), engineering design software (EUT4) were the most common technologies used in the design or construction of South African affordable housing projects. Still, the level of adoption of innovative technologies in design and construction of affordable housing projects in South Africa are relatively low. For instance, only less than 10% of South African</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>419</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 :Figure 7 :</head><label>67</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Initial SIAH causal model (path analysis)</figDesc><graphic coords="20,120.58,181.49,354.15,484.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Outer weights are the results of a multiple regression of a construct on its set of indicators which assess each indicator's relative importance in formative measurement models. The outer weights of variables indicate that experience in affordable housing projects (CHC2), familiarity and awareness with innovation (CHC4), size of company (CHC1) and establishment of the company (CHC3) are the most effective company characteristics respectively whilst type of housing (CHP2), size of project (CHP1), client of project (CHP3) and procurement of project (CHP4) are the most important project characteristics. The most influential challenges consisted of high cost of methods and technology (CH1), lack of incentives (CH5), tendency to use conventional methods/ materials/ technologies (CH4) and lack of technical knowledge (CH6).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The familiarity of designers and developers with limited technologies such as Computer Aided Design (CAD) and Project portfolio management software, promoted the high extent of use of these technologies in housing projects. However, as suggested byAdabre et al. (2021), the high cost of technologies, lack of awareness and technical knowledge caused the limited used of other innovative technologies in the design and construction of affordable housing. Certainly, this illustrates that the level of adoption of technology in housing projects in developing countries is considerably limited as established by<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Patel and Padhya (2021</ref>), Eng and Zainal,   (2021) and Ge et al., (2020)  .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="23,72.00,72.00,367.80,513.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Variables used in measuring the study constructs</figDesc><table><row><cell>Constructs</cell><cell>Sub Constructs</cell><cell>Variables</cell><cell>Source</cell><cell>Measurement Scale</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Size of company (CHC1) Experience in affordable housing projects (CHC2)</cell><cell>2, 3, 5, 6, 7, 8, 10 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 10, 11</cell><cell>Respondents were asked to indicate the</cell></row><row><cell>Characteristics (CH)</cell><cell>Company (C) Project (P)</cell><cell>Establishment of the company (CHC3) Familiarity and awareness with innovative methods, technologies, and materials (CHC4) Size of project (CHP1) Type of housing (CHP2) Client of project (CHP3)</cell><cell>2, 3, 5, 6, 7, 8, 10 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 10, 11 3, 5, 7, 8, 9, 10 5, 6, 7, 8, 10 2, 3, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10</cell><cell>characteristics of their company and the latest completed affordable housing project by answering the semi-structured</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Procurement (CHP4)</cell><cell>10 3, 5, 7, 9,</cell><cell>questions.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>High cost (initial/ maintenance/</cell><cell>8, 11, 13,</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>operation) (CH1) Lack of technical guidelines and standards (CH2) Incompatibility with other methods/materials/technology (CH3)</cell><cell>14, 16, 17 8, 11, 13, 14, 16, 17 8, 11, 13, 14, 16, 17</cell><cell>Developers were asked to indicate the degree of impact of the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Tendency to use conventional methods/materials/technologies (CH4)</cell><cell>8, 11, 13, 14, 17</cell><cell>challenges on the use of</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Challenges on adoption (CH)</cell><cell>Lack of public incentives (CH5) Lack of technical knowledge and skill (CH6) Lack of awareness of the availability (CH7) Lack of policy and regulation (CH8) Low social acceptance (CH9) Low availability in local market (CH10)</cell><cell>8, 11, 13, 14, 16, 17 8, 11, 13, 14, 16, 17 8, 11, 13, 14, 16 8, 11, 13, 14, 16, 17 8, 11, 13, 14, 16 14, 16 8, 11, 13,</cell><cell>innovative methods, technologies, and materials in their latest completed affordable housing projects on a four-point Likert scale:</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p>1:</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Moghayedi et al., 2021)</ref></p>, 2:</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Banihashemi et al., 2017</ref>), 3: (Khurana et al., 2019)</p>, 4:</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Rahdari et al., 2016</ref>), 5: (Drucker, 2014), 6:(Ozorhon and Oral, 2017)</p>, 7:</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Stanitsas et al., 2021</ref>), 8: (Olanrewaju et al.,  2018)</p>, 9: (Naoum and Egbu, 2016), 10:</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Zakaria et al., 2018</ref>), 11: (Darko et al., 2018)</p>, 12: (Adabre and Chan, 2019a), 13: (Adabre and Chan, 2021), 14:</p>(Adabre et al., 2021)</p>, 15:</p>(Adabre and Chan, 2019b),  16: (Kornilov et al., 2020)</p>, 17:</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Patel and Padhya, 2021)</ref></p>, 18:</p>(Sidani et al., 2021), 19: (Li and Liu,  2019)</p>, 20:</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Song et al., 2017)</ref> </p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Company characteristics of housing developers</figDesc><table><row><cell>Establishment</cell><cell>Frequency</cell></row><row><cell>Less than 5 years</cell><cell>27.9%</cell></row><row><cell>6 to 10 years</cell><cell>33.7%</cell></row><row><cell>11 to 20 Years</cell><cell>26.0%</cell></row><row><cell>More than 20 years</cell><cell>12.5%</cell></row><row><cell>Experience with affordable housing projects</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>No experience (1 st project)</cell><cell>3.8%</cell></row><row><cell>Low</cell><cell>50.0%</cell></row><row><cell>Moderate</cell><cell>28.8%</cell></row><row><cell>High</cell><cell>17.3%</cell></row><row><cell>Size of company by employees/workers</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Micro</cell><cell>30.8%</cell></row><row><cell>Small</cell><cell>38.5%</cell></row><row><cell>Medium</cell><cell>18.3%</cell></row><row><cell>Large</cell><cell>12.5%</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Familiarity with innovative methods, technologies, and materials</cell></row><row><cell>Not at all</cell><cell>10.6%</cell></row><row><cell>Low</cell><cell>24.0%</cell></row><row><cell>Moderate</cell><cell>40.4%</cell></row><row><cell>High</cell><cell>25.0%</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note><p>. Most of the housing projects sizes range from small (33.7%) to medium (26.9%). Results indicate that 65.4% of projects are owned by private clients whilst 34.6% of projects had government as client, clearly illustrating the strong role of private developers and investors in middle-income affordable housing projects in South Africa.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Project characteristics</figDesc><table><row><cell>Size of project</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell>Very small (less than 5 units)</cell><cell>25.0%</cell></row><row><cell>Small (5-10 units)</cell><cell>33.7%</cell></row><row><cell>Medium (11-20 units)</cell><cell>26.9%</cell></row><row><cell>Large (more than 20units)</cell><cell>14.4%</cell></row><row><cell>Client of project</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Private</cell><cell>65.4%</cell></row><row><cell>Local government</cell><cell>20.2%</cell></row><row><cell>National government</cell><cell>14.4%</cell></row><row><cell>Type of housing</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Detached</cell><cell>26.9%</cell></row><row><cell>Semi-detached</cell><cell>32.7%</cell></row><row><cell>Apartment</cell><cell>14.4%</cell></row><row><cell>Mixed</cell><cell>26.0%</cell></row><row><cell>Procurement</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Design-Bid-Build</cell><cell>41.3%</cell></row><row><cell>Design &amp; Build</cell><cell>26.9%</cell></row><row><cell>Management contracting</cell><cell>24.0%</cell></row><row><cell>Others</cell><cell>7.7%</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Also, nano materials (EUM2) were the least used materials in affordable housing projects, due to high cost and lack of availability within South Africa.</figDesc><table><row><cell>58.80%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>48.70%</cell><cell cols="2">46.10% 45.50%45.30% 44.20%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>29.70%</cell><cell>25.90%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">19.60% 18.80% 13.00% 12.30% 10.90% 9.30%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>4.60% 1.80% 0.80%</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">EUT1 EUT7 EUT4 EUT17 EUT6 EUT10 EUT14 EUT15 EUT5 EUT13 EUT2 EUT11 EUT16 EUT12 EUT3 EUT9 EUT8</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Level of adoption</cell><cell cols="3">Not at all</cell><cell>Low</cell><cell>Average</cell><cell>High</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>58.40%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>48.40%</cell><cell cols="2">46.20%</cell><cell cols="2">40.20%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>31.50%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>3.30%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>EUM6</cell><cell>EUM4</cell><cell>EUM1</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">EUM3</cell><cell>EUM5</cell><cell>EUM2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Level of adoption</cell><cell cols="3">Not at all</cell><cell>Low</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Average</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">High</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">Figure 4: Extent of use of new building materials in construction of affordable housing</cell></row><row><cell>projects</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>The analysis of the extent of use of new materials highlights that local materials (EUM6), light materials (EUM4) and recycled materials (EUM1) were used more in the construction of affordable housing, which can be linked to availability of materials in local market and lower transportation cost.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Challenges negating adoption of SOI in affordable housing projects</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Sustainable methods in design</cell><cell cols="2">Sustainable methods in construction</cell><cell cols="4">New building materials Innovative technologies</cell></row><row><cell>Challenge</cell><cell>RII</cell><cell>Challenge</cell><cell>RII</cell><cell>Challenge</cell><cell>RII</cell><cell>Challenge</cell><cell>RII</cell></row><row><cell>CH1</cell><cell cols="2">63.09% CH1</cell><cell cols="2">56.50% CH1</cell><cell cols="2">55.87% CH1</cell><cell>55.61%</cell></row><row><cell>CH5</cell><cell cols="2">52.46% CH4</cell><cell cols="2">44.40% CH5</cell><cell cols="2">49.87% CH6</cell><cell>53.71%</cell></row><row><cell>CH2</cell><cell cols="2">50.32% CH2</cell><cell cols="2">43.90% CH4</cell><cell cols="2">48.92% CH4</cell><cell>44.82%</cell></row><row><cell>CH6</cell><cell cols="2">45.61% CH8</cell><cell cols="2">41.60% CH8</cell><cell cols="2">47.63% CH2</cell><cell>42.94%</cell></row><row><cell>CH8</cell><cell cols="2">44.71% CH5</cell><cell cols="2">40.70% CH10</cell><cell cols="2">45.73% CH7</cell><cell>39.89%</cell></row><row><cell>CH4</cell><cell cols="2">43.29% CH10</cell><cell cols="2">37.90% CH6</cell><cell cols="2">44.68% CH5</cell><cell>37.16%</cell></row><row><cell>CH7</cell><cell cols="2">33.09% CH3</cell><cell cols="2">33.30% CH2</cell><cell cols="2">43.67% CH8</cell><cell>36.88%</cell></row><row><cell>CH3</cell><cell cols="2">31.81% CH6</cell><cell cols="2">32.30% CH7</cell><cell cols="2">40.38% CH3</cell><cell>35.52%</cell></row><row><cell>CH10</cell><cell cols="2">24.09% CH7</cell><cell cols="2">31.20% CH9</cell><cell cols="2">38.42% CH9</cell><cell>29.39%</cell></row><row><cell>CH9</cell><cell cols="2">9.00% CH9</cell><cell cols="2">30.40% CH3</cell><cell cols="2">37.07% CH10</cell><cell>29.21%</cell></row><row><cell cols="8">The results of RII concerning adoption challenges impeding the use of sustainable methods in</cell></row><row><cell cols="8">design of affordable housing reveals that high cost (CH1), lack of incentives (CH5), lack of</cell></row><row><cell cols="8">technical guidance and standards (CH2) and lack of technical knowledge and skill (CH6) are</cell></row><row><cell cols="8">the most predominant barriers to adoption of sustainable methods in designing affordable</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">housing over all 14 sustainable design methods (EUDs) studied as listed in Table 4.</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>The results show high cost (CH1), tendency to use conventional methods (CH4), lack of technical guidelines and standards (CH2) and lack of policy and regulation (CH8) as the main barriers preventing the adoption of sustainable methods during the construction of affordable housing. Like challenges on adoption of sustainable methods in design and construction, high cost (CH1) of new materials, lack of public incentives (CH5), tendency to use conventional materials (CH4) and lack of policy and regulation (CH8) in using new materials are the key challenges on using new materials in South African affordable housing projects. Furthermore, high cost (CH1), lack of technical knowledge and skill (CH6), reluctance to use innovative technologies (CH4) and lack of technical guidelines and standards (CH2) are the most predominant challenges on adopting innovative technologies in design and construction of affordable housing in South Africa.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Consistency, reliability and validity of the constructs and variables</figDesc><table><row><cell>Construct</cell><cell>variables</cell><cell>NO of variables</cell><cell cols="2">Characteristics Challenges CHC CHP CH</cell><cell>Extend of use EUD EUC EUM EUT</cell></row><row><cell>Characteristics</cell><cell>CHC CHP</cell><cell>4 4</cell><cell>0.892 0.828 0.855</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Challenges (CH)</cell><cell></cell><cell>10</cell><cell>-0.855 -0.837</cell><cell>0.853</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>EUD</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>0.886 0.827</cell><cell>-0.827</cell><cell>0.852</cell></row><row><cell>Extend of use</cell><cell>EUC EUM</cell><cell>9 6</cell><cell>0.855 0.822 0.880 0.835</cell><cell>-0.836 -0.816</cell><cell>0.851 0.841 0.844 0.840 0.868</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>EUT</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>0.829 0.816</cell><cell>-0.828</cell><cell>0.839 0.838 0.837 0.848</cell></row><row><cell>Internal</cell><cell cols="2">Cronbach's Alpha</cell><cell>0.814 0.877</cell><cell>0.873</cell><cell>0.873 0.848 0.835 0.875</cell></row><row><cell>consistency</cell><cell>rho_A</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.818 0.886</cell><cell>0.874</cell><cell>0.873 0.849 0.835 0.876</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Composite Reliability</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.839 0.889</cell><cell>0.876</cell><cell>0.875 0.856 0.849 0.877</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Convergent validity (AVE)</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.795 0.731</cell><cell>0.728</cell><cell>0.726 0.708 0.754 0.719</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Outer weights of internal and external variables</figDesc><table><row><cell>Variables</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div><p>, which has been published in final form at <ref type="url" target="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/sd.2306">https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/sd.2306</ref>. This article may be used for non-commercial purposes in accordance with <rs type="institution">Wiley Terms and Conditions for Use of Self-Archived Versions</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><p>methods approaches. Sage publications. Darko, A., Chan, A.P.C., Yang, Y., Shan, M., He, B.J. and Gou, Z. 2018. Influences of barriers, drivers, and promotion strategies on green building technologies adoption in developing countries: The Ghanaian case. Journal of Cleaner Production, 200, pp.<rs type="grantNumber">687-703</rs>. Drucker, P. (2014) Innovation and entrepreneurship. Routledge. Eng, T. and Zainal, R. 2021. The <rs type="institution" subtype="infrastructure">Study of Modular Construction System (MCS) Application for Affordable Housing in Malaysia. Research in Management of Technology</rs> and <rs type="person">Business Vol</rs>. 2 No. 1 (2021) <rs type="grantNumber">794-811</rs> Ge, J., Zhao, Y., Luo, X. and Lin, M., 2020. Study on the suitability of green building technology for affordable housing: A case study on Zhejiang Province, China. Journal of Cleaner Production, 275, p.122685. Karji, A., Woldesenbet, A., Khanzadi, M. and Tafazzoli, M. 2019 '<rs type="projectName">Assessment of Social Sustainability Indicators in Mass Housing Construction: A Case Study of Mehr Housing Project</rs>', <rs type="person">Sustainable Cities</rs> and Society, 50. doi: 10.1016/j.scs.2019.101697. Khan, M.K., Zaleha, S., Rasid, A. and Bardai, B. 2019 '<rs type="projectName">Waqf Cooperative Housing Model (WCHM) as an Innovative Solution for Affordable Housing', International Journal of Innovation and Business Strategy</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">12(2</rs>), pp. <rs type="grantNumber">36-48</rs>. Khurana, S., Haleem, A. and Mannan, B. 2019 '<rs type="projectName">Determinants for integration of sustainability with innovation for Indian manufacturing enterprises: Empirical evidence in MSMEs</rs>', Journal of Cleaner Production, 229, pp. 374-386. Kornilov, P. P., <rs type="person">N Lapaev</rs>, <rs type="person">D. and Lapaeva</rs>, <rs type="person">O. N. 2020</rs> '<rs type="projectName">Housing innovation management: Strategic directions of development', International Journal</rs> of Management, 11(5), p. 525-549. Li, Y. and Liu, C. 2019 'Applications of multirotor drone technologies in construction management', International Journal of Construction Management, 19(5), pp. <rs type="grantNumber">401-412</rs>. Martins, A.N. and <rs type="person">Saavedra Farias</rs>, J., 2019. Inclusive sustainability within favela upgrading and incremental housing: The case of <rs type="institution">Rocinha in Rio de Janeiro</rs>. Sustainable Development, 27(2), pp.<rs type="grantNumber">205-213</rs>. Moghayedi, A., Jeune, K.L., Massyn, M. and Byron, P., 2022. Establishing the Indicators of Sustainable Building Materials. In CIGOS 2021, <rs type="person">Emerging Technologies</rs> and <rs type="funder">Applications for Green Infrastructure</rs> (pp. <rs type="grantNumber">617-625</rs>). Springer, <rs type="person">Singapore. Moghayedi</rs>, A., Awuzie, B., Omotayo, T., <rs type="person">Le Jeune</rs>, <rs type="person">K., Massyn</rs>, <rs type="person">M., Ekpo</rs>, C.O., Braune, M. and Byron, P., <rs type="grantNumber">2021</rs>. <rs type="projectName">A Critical Success Factor Framework for Implementing Sustainable Innovative and Affordable Housing: A Systematic Review and Bibliometric Analysis</rs>. Buildings, 11(8), p.317. Moghayedi, A. and Windapo, A. 2019 '<rs type="affiliation">Key Performance Criteria Influencing the Selection of Construction Methods Used for the Fabrication of Building Components in the Middle East', Sustainable Construction and Building Materials</rs>. doi: <rs type="grantNumber">10.5772/intechopen.81673</rs>. Naoum, S. G. and Egbu, C. 2016 'Modern selection criteria for procurement methods in construction: A state-of-the-art literature review and a survey', International Journal of Managing Projects in Business, 9(2), pp. 309-336. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1108/IJMPB-09-2015-">https://doi.org/10.1108/IJMPB-09-2015-</ref>0094. Olanrewaju, A., Tan, S.Y. and <rs type="person">Abdul-Aziz</rs>, A.R., 2018. Housing providers' insights on the benefits of sustainable affordable housing. Sustainable Development, 26(6), pp.847-858. Osunsanmi, T.O., Aigbavboa, C.O., Oke, A.E. and Liphadzi, M., 2020. Appraisal of stakeholders' willingness to adopt construction 4.0 technologies for construction projects. Built Environment Project and <rs type="person">Asset Management</rs>, Vol. 10 No. 4, pp. 547-565. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1108/BEPAM-12-2018-0159">https://doi.org/10.1108/BEPAM-12-2018-0159</ref>. Ozorhon, B. and Oral, K. 2017 'Drivers of innovation in construction projects', Journal of construction engineering and management, 143(4), p. 04016118.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_n57mJep">
					<idno type="grant-number">687-703</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_usPuZzf">
					<idno type="grant-number">794-811</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Assessment of Social Sustainability Indicators in Mass Housing Construction: A Case Study of Mehr Housing Project</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_EUp7qcV">
					<idno type="grant-number">12(2</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Waqf Cooperative Housing Model (WCHM) as an Innovative Solution for Affordable Housing&apos;, International Journal of Innovation and Business Strategy</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_Y234WdX">
					<idno type="grant-number">36-48</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Determinants for integration of sustainability with innovation for Indian manufacturing enterprises: Empirical evidence in MSMEs</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_WeG3es8">
					<idno type="grant-number">401-412</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Housing innovation management: Strategic directions of development&apos;, International Journal</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_gVXQffp">
					<idno type="grant-number">205-213</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_J2E9A5H">
					<idno type="grant-number">617-625</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_WfHBH6n">
					<idno type="grant-number">2021</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">A Critical Success Factor Framework for Implementing Sustainable Innovative and Affordable Housing: A Systematic Review and Bibliometric Analysis</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_bxrT7kZ">
					<idno type="grant-number">10.5772/intechopen.81673</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_4sXKKxF">
					<idno type="grant-number">10.1108/IJMPB-09-2015-0094</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_p4kgdUV">
					<idno type="grant-number">10.1108/BEPAM-12-2018-0159</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<listOrg type="infrastructure">
				<org type="infrastructure">					<orgName type="extracted">Study of Modular Construction System (MCS) Application for Affordable Housing in Malaysia. Research in Management of Technology</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>After the analysis of the measurement model, the research hypotheses were tested using T-424 Statistics. The resultant P-Values of all hypotheses (paths) test are less than 0.05, which indicate, all research hypotheses and their sub-hypotheses are statistically significant, as presented in Table <ref type="table">6</ref>. Moreover, the results of indirect effect testing of the research hypotheses proved that the challenges negatively mediating the effects of project and company characteristics on extent of use of methods, materials, and technologies. Therefore, the total effects of project and company characteristics were significantly reduced as illustrated in the final SIAH causal model in </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing Critical Risk Factors (CRFs) to Sustainable Housing: The Perspective of a sub-Saharan African Country</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Adabre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Adinyira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Building Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">102385</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The ends required to justify the means for sustainable affordable housing: A review on critical success criteria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Adabre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sustainable development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="781" to="794" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2019b &apos;Critical success factors (CSFs) for sustainable affordable housing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Adabre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.buildenv.2019.04.030</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Building and Environment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">156</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a sustainability assessment model for affordable housing projects: the perspective of professionals in Ghana</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Adabre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P C</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1108/ECAM-08-2019-0432</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Engineering, Construction and Architectural Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling the impact of barriers on sustainable housing in developing countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Adabre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P C</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Urban Planning and Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5020032</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sustainability-oriented innovation: A systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jeanrenaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bessant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Denyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Overy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Management Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="180" to="205" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Availability of innovative housing from the perspective of sustainable construction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Afanasyeva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fedorova1</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Yulbarisova</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IOP Conf. Ser.: Mater. Sci. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">890</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12182</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Critical success factors (CSFs) for integration of sustainability into construction project management practices in developing countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Banihashemi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hosseini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Golizadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sankaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International journal of project management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1103" to="1119" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bridging the gap between sustainable housing and affordable housing: The required critical success criteria (CSC)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P C</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Adabre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.buildenv.2019.01.029</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Building and Environment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">151</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stable relationality and dynamic innovation: two models of collaboration in SME-driven offsite manufacturing supply chains in housing construction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Creswell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Creswell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>London</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1108/ECAM-07-2019-0346</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Engineering, Construction and Architectural Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1553" to="1577" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Research design: Qualitative, quantitative, and mixed Pablo</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Current challenges and future potential of 3D concrete printing: Aktuelle Herausforderungen und Zukunftspotenziale des 3D-Druckens bei Beton</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Panda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">W D</forename><surname>Tay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Paul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Materialwissenschaft und Werkstofftechnik</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="666" to="673" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Challenges and Prospects of Sustainable &amp; Affordable Housing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Padhya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Research in Engineering and Science (IJRES)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Achieving sustainability through Schumpeterian social entrepreneurship: The role of social enterprises</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rahdari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sepasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moradi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cleaner Production</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="347" to="360" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BIM Dimensions and Application Areas for Enhancing Sustainability and Affordability of Affordable Housing: As a Key for Effective Housing Policies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sertyesilisi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sertyesilisik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Cetin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ocakoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Periodica Polytechnica Architecture</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021. 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recent tools and techniques of BIM-based virtual reality: A systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sidani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dinis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sanhudo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Duarte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Baptista</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Martins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Soeiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Archives of Computational Methods in Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="462" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trends and opportunities of BIM-GIS integration in the architecture, engineering and construction industry: a review from a spatio-temporal statistical perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sutrisna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hampson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ISPRS International Journal of Geo-Information</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">397</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrating sustainability indicators into project management: The case of construction industry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stanitsas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kirytopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Leopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cleaner Production</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">279</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">123774</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Challenges of Integrating Affordable and Sustainable Housing in Malaysia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Z H</forename><surname>Jamaludin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mahayuddin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H A</forename><surname>Hamid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1088/1755-1315/140/1/012001</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IOP Conference Series: Earth and Environmental Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Use and performance of conventional and sustainable building technologies in low-income housing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Windapo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Omopariola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Olugboyega</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Moghayedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>Sustainable Cities and Society</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">102606</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sustainable community development: Integrating social and environmental sustainability for sustainable housing and communities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Winston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/sd.223812WINSTON</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/sd.223812WINSTON" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sustainable Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Contextual, structural and behavioural factors influencing the adoption of industrialised building systems: a review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zakaria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gajendran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Brewer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Architectural Engineering and Design Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
