<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Fusing EEG and fMRI based on a bottom-up model: inferring activation and effective connectivity in neural masses</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2005-05-29">29 May 2005</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Riera</surname></persName>
							<email>riera@idac.tohoku.ac.jp</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Advanced Science and Technology of Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">NICHe</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Tohoku University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Aoba 10</addrLine>
									<postCode>980-8579</postCode>
									<settlement>Aramaki</settlement>
									<region>Aobaku Sendai</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Aubert</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Cuban Neuroscience Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Havana</settlement>
									<country key="CU">Cuba</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Iwata</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Advanced Science and Technology of Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">NICHe</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Tohoku University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Aoba 10</addrLine>
									<postCode>980-8579</postCode>
									<settlement>Aramaki</settlement>
									<region>Aobaku Sendai</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kawashima</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Advanced Science and Technology of Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">NICHe</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Tohoku University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Aoba 10</addrLine>
									<postCode>980-8579</postCode>
									<settlement>Aramaki</settlement>
									<region>Aobaku Sendai</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Advanced Science and Technology of Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">NICHe</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Tohoku University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Aoba 10</addrLine>
									<postCode>980-8579</postCode>
									<settlement>Aramaki</settlement>
									<region>Aobaku Sendai</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ozaki</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">The Institute of Statistical Mathematics</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Fusing EEG and fMRI based on a bottom-up model: inferring activation and effective connectivity in neural masses</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2005-05-29">29 May 2005</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1098/rstb.2005.1646</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T18:22+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>bottom-up models</term>
					<term>EEG and fMRI data fusion</term>
					<term>motor coordination</term>
					<term>autoregressive models</term>
					<term>dynamic systems</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The elucidation of the complex machinery used by the human brain to segregate and integrate information while performing high cognitive functions is a subject of imminent future consequences. The most significant contributions to date in this field, known as cognitive neuroscience, have been achieved by using innovative neuroimaging techniques, such as electroencephalogram (EEG) and functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI), which measure variations in both the time and the space of some interpretable physical magnitudes. Extraordinary maps of cerebral activation involving function-restricted brain areas, as well as graphs of the functional connectivity between them, have been obtained from EEG and fMRI data by solving some spatio-temporal inverse problems, which constitutes a top-down approach. However, in many cases, a natural bridge between these maps/graphs and the causal physiological processes is lacking, leading to some misunderstandings in their interpretation. Recent advances in the comprehension of the underlying physiological mechanisms associated with different cerebral scales have provided researchers with an excellent scenario to develop sophisticated biophysical models that permit an integration of these neuroimage modalities, which must share a common aetiology. This paper proposes a bottom-up approach, involving physiological parameters in a specific mesoscopic dynamic equations system. Further observation equations encapsulating the relationship between the mesostates and the EEG/f MRI data are obtained on the basis of the physical foundations of these techniques. A methodology for the estimation of parameters from fused EEG/fMRI data is also presented. In this context, the concepts of activation and effective connectivity are carefully revised. This new approach permits us to examine and discuss some future prospects for the integration of multimodal neuroimages.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Understanding how the brain operates while performing cognitive functions is a matter of remarkable importance that has been the focus of attention of many neuroscience researchers for a number of years. In spite of substantial advances, researchers have yet to establish whether some of the functional specializations during higher-level processing (i.e. motor coordination, language, perception, attention, etc.) are confined to well-delimited regions, or if they simply originate from neuronal masses interacting with diffuse spatial bounds (see Fuster 2000 for a very controversial discussion of modularity). What is more, it is still unclear whether the cognitive events emerge within neuronal masses as: (i) sequential episodes that include feed forward/back aspects of interactions or (ii) concomitant global modes of activations. Hence, it is of utmost importance in the cognitive neurosciences <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Gazzaniga 2000)</ref> to determine both the segregation (the functional isolated modules) and the integration (their interrelationships) of brain functions in a general context of causal dynamic systems (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Horwitz 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Lee et al. 2003</ref> for revisions of the state of the art). The recognized role that oscillations and synchronicity at the level of neuronal spiking play in cooperating and competing neuronal populations has brought into reflection the relationship that these theoretical concepts hold with basic cellular physiology.</p><p>The use of satisfactory psychophysiological paradigms has allowed the separation of a particular function into multiple single components that can be strictly localized in time and space. In the last few years, researchers working on theoretical issues of neuroscience have centred their attention on studying not only 'where' these components are generated inside the brain (i.e. 'activation' maps) but also 'what' natural influences they exert on each other while the original function is carried out (i.e. 'effective connectivity' maps). In humans, investigations about this issue have been possible by using non-invasive functional neuroimaging techniques, such as electroencephalogram (EEG) and functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI). The introduction of these techniques has allowed neuroscientists to assess the spatiotemporal variations of certain physical magnitudes inside the brain by simply exploring their external echo/macroscopic reflections, which are inevitably polluted by instrumental errors <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Baillet et al. 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Casey et al. 2002)</ref>. By using EEG and fMRI data together we are able to overcome the limitations that these techniques present in terms of their ability to localize single functional components in time and space, and at the same time, maximize the potential of both <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Makeig et al. 2002)</ref>. This is the main motivation for developing concurrent EEG and fMRI data recording systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Goldman et al. 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Salek-Haddadi et al. 2003)</ref>.</p><p>However, even at present, these techniques are being used independently to explore some aspects of both activations and effective connectivity maps during particular experimental paradigms (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Carew et al. 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Friston et al. 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Marrelec et al. 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Galka et al. 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Miwakeichi et al. 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Penny et al. 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Trujillo-Barreto et al. 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Yamashita et al. 2004)</ref>. There have been few attempts to develop methods that make use of the complementary potentialities of EEG and fMRI data that have recently emerged <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Dale et al. 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kruggel et al. 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Goldman et al. 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Martinez-Montes et al. 2004)</ref>. In these very impressive contemporary works, sophisticated statistical methods have been introduced to extract as much information as possible from a data-driven strategy (i.e. the authors tend to use what they refer to as a top-down approach). In many cases, the latter interpretation of the results is incomplete and the association with physiological parameters is overlooked completely. Fortunately, modern comprehension of many of the basic physiological mechanisms associated with brain functions <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Magistretti &amp; Pellerin 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Kim 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Leopold et al. 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr">Logothetis 2003a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Thompson et al. 2003)</ref>, ranging from the emerging electrical episodes in the neural circuitry to the imminent vascular changes induced mostly by metabolic and oxygen demands, has brought into light a tremendous opportunity to develop sophisticated biophysical models (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Attwell &amp; Iadecola 2002</ref> for an excellent discussion of the physiological basis of neuroimages). The main motivation of this paper is to create a first-order bottom-up approach, establishing a solid bridge between the physiological profiles and the EEG/ fMRI data that make posterior interpretations of the results possible. A bottom-up approach satisfies the foremost posture of the participants in a recent series of workshops on 'functional brain connectivity <ref type="bibr">' (i.e. organized in Du ¨sseldorf 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Cambridge 2003 and</ref><ref type="bibr">Havana 2004)</ref>, who strongly recommended that any macroscopic notion of activation and effective connectivity should be based on the underlying neuronal substrate. The physical foundations of EEG and fMRI are exposed below, in order to introduce to the readers the main motivations sustaining our novel model-driven strategy, permitting a natural establishment of some mesoscopic variables with physiological connotations.</p><p>The causal course of events during the execution of brain functions originates at the level of synapses, which constitute the basic ingredient for the crosstalk between neuronal assemblies. The local field potential in the vicinity of certain elemental volumes can be thought of as a magnitude that summarizes a large amount of rapidly varying (in the order of millisecond) processes occurring during synaptic transmissions (i.e. neurotransmitters migrating from the synaptic cleft, the membrane transport phenomena at the neuronastrocytes juncture, and the electrotonic propagation of postsynaptic potentials, etc.). Although the synapses are very small, the specific geometry and hierarchical organization of neurons in some cerebral structures facilitates the summation of synchronized local field potentials (henceforth this mesoscopic effect will be referred to as 'synaptic activity') additionally contaminated with physiological noise, which creates a significant primary current source that can be observed in remote places owing to the volume conductor properties of the head <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Nunez 1981;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Niedermeyer &amp; Lopes Da Silva 1999)</ref>. The EEG represents the voltage differences that these primary current sources produce between lead electrodes situated on the scalp. Unfortunately, the primary current sources yielded in differentiated locations inside the brain are blurred and mixed during the observation process, although the temporal structure of their dynamics is preserved due to the quasi-instantaneous propagation of the ohmic currents <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Plonsey &amp; Heppner 1967)</ref>. In order to obtain a threedimensional reconstruction of the density of primary current sources extending along the whole cerebral volume from the EEG signals (only recorded by a few sensors), an inverse problem must be solved. This problem has presented imaging engineers with a mammoth task that has occupied much of the last 30 years. The electrophysiological inverse problem, as it is referred to, does not have a unique solution (i.e. it is ill-posed, see <ref type="bibr">Riera et al. 1998</ref> for a theoretical viewpoint); hence, additional information must be used to constrain the possible meaningless solutions. Even now, there are intense debates about the competence of most of the methods proposed in the literature to solve the problem, a fact that has recently resulted in a lack of motivation among researchers using EEG data to localize functional components in the space. Even so, its high temporal resolution, low production cost and simplicity of use in experimental manipulations explain why the EEG has continued to be one of the most attractive techniques.</p><p>On the contrary, in the last few years, the use of suitable experimental manipulations with the fMRI technique has re-established a high level of enthusiasm among imagers, and a large amount of studies reporting on the accurate spatial localization of functional components have been published. The fMRI technique permits the direct observation of the blood oxygenation level dependent (BOLD) signal inside the brain with a very high spatial resolution, but is deficient in its definition of time (ws). The BOLD signal tracks the temporal evolution of a nonlinear competitive balance between the cerebral blood volume (CBV) and the content of deoxy haemoglobin (dHb) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Buxton et al. 1998)</ref>, both defined in an element of physical volume that mainly comprises post-capillary venous compartments. In the haemodynamic approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Friston et al. 2000)</ref>, dynamic changes in these two intrinsic physiological magnitudes are governed by an increase or decrease in the cerebral blood flow. A mesoscopic variable, henceforth referred to as haemodynamics, will be used to summarize these physical phenomena at the vascular level, which also contain physiological noise. Although the mechanisms for brain vascular control are yet to be completely understood, it is at present accepted that the local regulator role being played by nitric oxide release is closely coupled with synaptic activity during cerebral blood flow variations. In the last few years, motivated by the discovery that cholinergic axons from the basal forebrain may be connected to certain perivascular structures (i.e. smooth muscle bands or plastic strips at the arterioles and the pericytes-sphincter-like depressions at the pre-capillary branching points), it has been conjectured that a more global vascular controlling system of electrical origin may coexist <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Attwell &amp; Iadecola 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Harrison et al. 2002)</ref>. The interrelationship between the synaptic activity and the cerebral blood flow has been modelled locally and linearly in the haemodynamic approach by introducing a flow-inducing signal (maybe related to the nitric oxide release). In an EEG/fMRI fusion model, the linear assumption at the electro-vascular interface oversimplifies the local antagonist effect between excitatory and inhibitory postsynaptic potentials.</p><p>In this paper, a two-dimensional autoregressive model with exogenous variables (ARx) is introduced to describe both the self-dynamics of the 'mesoscopic' variables (i.e. synaptic activity and haemodynamics) and their interrelationships. A static nonlinear function is proposed to describe the electro-vascular coupling through a flow-inducing signal. The mesostates in the elemental volumes, containing a bunch of synapses and vascular networks, relate to EEG and fMRI data by means of 'macroscopic' observation equations, also formulated. There are recent findings <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Harrison et al. 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Logothetis 2003b</ref>) that give us confidence to hypothesize that the number of synapses highly correlate with the density of capillary beds in the cortex. This quasi-linear states model, put forward to account for the evolution of the electrophysiological and haemodynamic states, takes advantage of the EEG data to search for the temporal location and causal order of single functional components, while the fMRI data is utilized in a common strategy to achieve accurate spatial localizations. In the case of fMRI data, causal relationships between events are occulted inside BOLD because haemodynamic changes occur in a very slow temporal scale as a consequence of the pronounced low-pass filter of the vasomotor system. In the EEG data, spatial configurations of events are not distinguishable owing to the spreading effect produced by the volume conductor. However, both observation types share a common aetiology at the physiological level, which is a central premise in this paper. In addition, the simultaneous use of EEG and fMRI recordings allows us to obtain data in the same experimental conditions, and more importantly, enables us to develop a common model for the physiological noise. The least-square estimators of the mesostates and observational model parameters are presented in Appendix A.</p><p>The mesostates can be defined at different levels of the brain architecture; hence, the dimensionality of the ensuing identification problem depends on which physical scale is chosen to separate the individual components in time and space. The physical dimensions of the system can be extremely dissimilar, ranging from being a colossal problem when trying to identify voxel-wise dynamics, to a simpler problem when assuming a structure-wise organization (i.e. using a priori a model for the activation and effective connectivity maps on a set of macroscopic structures defined by standard brain atlases). Fortunately, the introduction in neuroscience of imaging techniques such as the anatomical MRI and the very new diffusion tensor imaging (a revision and discussions about the possible future implications can be found in this issue; <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Behrens &amp; Johansen-Berg 2005)</ref> has enriched the pool of accessible information about the structural design and organization of cerebral tissues. The use of these techniques has made the segmentation of different brain structures possible, as well as the characterization of the natural fibre tracks that physically bond them, without emphasizing the directionality of neuronal activity propagation (in this issue Parker &amp; Alexander 2005 used the 'persistent angular structure' method to determine, in practicable terms, the probabilistic density function of the fibres orientation). Recently, three-dimensional 'brain atlases' are being widely used as common standards in neuroscience research, in which precise statistical information about the variability of anatomical structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Mazziotta et al. 2001</ref>) is incorporated, along with grey matter connection graphs <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Wakana et al. 2004)</ref>. In this paper, regions of interest (ROI) with a structure-wise demarcation are introduced in the context of the structural probabilistic atlas developed at the McConnell Brain Imaging Centre, Montreal Neurological Institute, Montreal. Analysing only those structures involved during a task performance considerably reduces the dimensionality of the time-space identification problem in this case. Additionally, information about relevant nerve fibre tracks is used a priori to sidestep the estimation of the effective connectivity between brain structures physically disconnected (obtained from 'The Fiber Tract-Based Atlas', Research Center at Kennedy Krieger Institute, Johns Hopkins University Medical School, Baltimore).</p><p>Nevertheless, while trying to fuse EEG and fMRI data, a project of extreme computational complexity, several practical difficulties will inevitably present themselves. The most significant are: (i) in order to use multimodal data in a unified scenery, the coregistration concern remains a challenge in spite of the current technical advances; and (ii) large electrical field distortions inside a conductor will be produced by either a strong static magnetic field or a low radiofrequency perturbation. In this paper, the positions of electrodes and a few external landmarks were determined by using a three-dimensional positionsindicator system (Isotrack II, Polhemus Product).</p><p>The co-registration between the electrodes and the individual anatomical MRI, normalized to the Talairach coordinate system, was performed using affine transformations. An isotropic and piecewise homogeneous volume conductor model of the head was assumed, which included three compartments (i.e. the brain, the skull and the scalp). The surfaces limiting the compartments were tessellated using a simplified version of the method MacDonald (1997) employed, in which a triangulated sphere is deformed towards the target object. The electric lead field (ELF) was numerically calculated using a vector boundary elements method (BEM), which permitted a realistic description of the properties of the volume conductor <ref type="bibr">(Riera &amp; Fuentes 1998)</ref>. Furthermore, the pulse artefacts (owing to the ballistocardiogram) were detected using a method available in the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Ellingson et al. 2004)</ref>. In this paper, however, a novel method based on a wavelet-based strategy and an equivalent dipole model is proposed to account for both local blood-pulse transients and global effects on the EEG data induced by the ballistocardiogram, respectively. The scanner artefacts were removed using the methods provided by the BRAIN VISION ANALYSER software. The whole methodology was applied to EEG and fMRI data obtained simultaneously in a block-design experimental paradigm while a subject carried out a motor coordination task triggered by visual and auditory cues.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">METHODS (a) Experiment</head><p>A right-handed, normal volunteer (a 38 year old male) was used in the experiment. The subject was asked to perform a block design motor task consisting of synchronized finger tapping when indicated by cues flashing at a frequency of 2 Hz (lasting for 200 ms). A visual cue (a checkerboard) indicated that the subject should execute the task with the right-hand, while an auditory cue (tones) indicated lefthand tapping. In each task-block, the task lasted for 40 s, preceded by 30 s of resting condition indicated by a cross shown at the centre of the screen. The stimulus modality (either the checkerboard or tones) for each task-block appeared in a random sequence. The whole experiment consisted of 12 task-blocks (see figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>).</p><p>A 1.5 T scanner (Vision, Siemens, Erlangen, Germany) was used in this study. Comfortable foam padding around the posterior area of the head and ear fixation blocks were used to minimize head movement. The following parameters were used during fMRI data acquisition. The inter-scan interval was 1 s. Each volume consisted of eight slices from the top to bottom of the head, with a voxel size of 3 ! 3 mm in plane, of 10 mm slice thickness and with a 5 mm gap covering the whole brain. T2-weighted, gradient-echo, echo-planer imaging sequences (TEZ60 ms, flip angle (FA)Z90 degrees) were used. The anatomical reference was obtained with a spoiled gradient-echo sequence (recovery timeZ9.7 ms, echo time TEZ4 ms, FAZ12 degrees) consisting of 96 slices, each with a voxel size of 1.25 ! 0.9 ! 1.92 mm. The BrainAmp MR system was used to record EEG data (sampling interval 200 ms) concurrently with BOLD signals inside the MRI scanner environment. The parameters of the BrainAmp MR system were as follows: lower cut-off frequency (0.016 Hz), upper cut-off frequency (250 Hz), signal range/resolution (G16 mV/500 nV), in-phase suppression (O90 dB), input noise (2 mV pp) and input impedance (10 MU). A BUA-64 adapter box was used in addition to an external rechargeable battery. The 10/20 array of electrodes (see figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>  (b) Data pre-processing The individual fMRI images were realigned to remove movement-related artefacts, and the slice timing was adjusted to that of the middle slice. The anatomical reference and fMRI images were co-registered and spatially normalized to the Talairach coordinate system using affine transforms with both linear and nonlinear parameters (translations, rotations, zooms and shears). The scanner artefacts in the EEG recordings, those occurring because of strong changes in the magnetic fields inside the magnetic resonance tomograph, were automatically detected and corrected <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Allen et al. 2000)</ref> using BRAIN VISION ANALYSER V1.04 software (see figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3(a,</ref><ref type="figure">c</ref>)). The start of the scanning, detected by applying the gradient method, was used as a reference point or mark for setting a proper timing for the average of the global scan signal (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref>  (i) The coupled state equations The bottom-up approach includes two different levels of dynamics: the fast synaptic activity at the neuron-astrocytes interface and the slow haemodynamics at the micro-vascular building block (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>). The mesostates a v t , associated with the synaptic activity at the vth area (i.e. electrophysiological signalling), satisfy a fast dynamic subsystem (equation (2.1)).</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">a v t Z X k A v k a v tKk C e v t C 2 v t ; (2.1)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">e v t Z X v 0 sv X k F vv 0 k a v 0 tKk C X k 4 v k s tKk : (2.2)</formula><p>The magnitudes A v k determine the causal relationship for the self-dynamics of the vth area. The random process 2 v t wNð0; k v a Þ defines the physiological white noise introduced at the level of synaptic cleft, with variance k v a . The external force e v t , representing the evoked transient, is considered to be an exogenous variable to the subsystem (equation (2.2)). The evoked transient is made up of both types of influences, the one coming from supplementary brain areas (i.e. determined through the effective connectivity coefficients F vv 0 k , for all k-lag c kZ1;. ) and the excitation originated from afferent pathways, related to the stimulus. Notice that coefficients F vv 0 k do not account for nearest-neighbours synaptic activity, but the other extreme, they do describe long-range connections.</p><p>The mesostates b v t , associated with the haemodynamics at the level of vasculature, satisfy the slow dynamic subsystem (equation (2.3)) with two exogenous variables: (i) the flowinducing signal h v t and (ii) the stimulus sequence s t (with a physical delay d) being weighted by the factors q v k ; a term introduced to account for any vascular control mechanism which is not synaptically mediated (i.e. cholinergic fibres from the basal forebrain innervating some type of smooth muscles or pericytes; <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Attwell &amp; Iadecola 2002)</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">b v t Z X k B v k b v tKk C h v t C X k q v k s tKkKd C z v t ; (2.3)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">h v t Z X k c k f v ða v tKk Þ: (2.4)</formula><p>The random process z v t wNð0; k v b Þ defines the physiological white noise at the vascular level, with variance k v b . The parameters B v k will determine the haemodynamics response function and the auto-correlation function for the vascular subsystem <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Riera et al. 2004</ref>). The synaptic activity a v t is thought to be a trigger that induces variations in the flowinducing signal h v t , where the vasculature acts as a low-pass filter c k (equation (2.4)). The static-nonlinear function f v ($), relating the synaptic activity and the flow-inducing signal, is still enigmatic and the challenge to define it could motivate joint works between physiologists and theoreticians. It is the belief of the authors that both excitatory and inhibitory postsynaptic activities must induce a comparable increase of metabolic/oxygen consumption; hence, in our paper, this function is assumed to be both symmetric and positive f v ðaÞZ r v ð1K expðKa 2 =u v ÞÞ. The magnitude r v is directly related to an area-dependent scaling factor for the global synaptic activity while generating the haemodynamic response; consequently, it permits us to deal with the (a) a fast dynamics linear subsystem (the continuous-line box) emulating the neuron-astrocyte interrelationship at the synaptic interface, with a linearly filtered input 'the evoked transients e v t ' (i.e. the filter emulates an integrator at the electrophysiological level inside the neurons); and (b) a slow dynamics linear subsystem (the dashed-line box) that mimics haemodynamics at the level of the micro-vascular building block. The connection between the fast and slow subsystems is only in one direction (i.e. synaptic activity creates a metabolic/oxygen demand, and will, therefore, induce an increase of blood flow via vascular regulation mechanisms). The factors c k will define the linear filter relating f v ða v t Þ with the flow-inducing signal. The magnitudes r v and u v will determine the strength and sensitivity of the nonlinear effect at the electro-vascular coupling (function f v ($) on the top). The magnitude a v t reflects changes in the synaptic activation, and summarizes many phenomena at the synaptic level. The magnitude b v t captures fluctuations in the blood volume v at the post-capillary venous compartment owing to unbalanced inner f in and outer f out (v) blood flows, which could also include a dependency with the concentration of deoxy haemoglobin.</p><p>dissimilarities in the physical dimension between the EEG and fMRI data. The magnitude u v could be mainly associated with the susceptibility of the flow-inducing signal to fluctuations of a v t . The sensibility of the vth area to the stimulus sequence s t is summarized by the parameters 4 v k and q v k , whose spatial distributions are comparable to the q-MAP previously presented by <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Riera et al. (2004)</ref> to describe the activation of the primary brain areas in fMRI studies.</p><p>(ii) Observation equations By intuition, the magnitudes a v t and b v t are directly proportional to the amplitudes of the postsynaptic potentials (thus, to the primary current source) and of the vascular changes (thus, to the rate of CBV/dHb), respectively; a mesoscopic effect originating within certain ROI (henceforth referred as the vth area). These areas are assumed to be artificial spheres. It is assumed that each constituent structure in the probabilistic atlas of the McConnell Brain Imaging Centre (Montreal Neurological Institute, Montreal) encloses a single active area (although the model can be generalized to include multiple areas within a simple structure). The primary current source in each area is represented by a single dipole located at the centre of the sphere. In this paper, these centres, and also the radii of the spheres, were estimated by searching for the maximum and the extension (by the thresholding technique) of the on-off contrasts SPM99 t-test images within the particular structure (figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>). This construct facilitates the formalization of the mathematical equations that relate the EEG and fMRI observations with the mesostates. † The EEG observation equation is given by the solution of the forward problem for the particular volume conductor model (i.e. lead field vector K e (r v )), with m v being the normalized orientation of the dipole of the vth area and r v the location of its centre (equation (2.5)). Both dipole location and its normalized orientation do not depend on time. The EEG instrumental error is represented by the white noise 3 e t wNð0; s 2 e Þ. The time-series of voltage differences between the electrode e and a common reference is represented by V e t , with eZ1,.,N e . The number of electrodes and areas are labelled by N e and N v , respectively</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">V e t Z m e t C X N v vZ1 K e ðr v Þ,m v a v t C 3 e t (2.5)</formula><p>The magnitude m e t summarizes any nuisance effect on the EEG data (i.  The wavelet coefficients are calculated for each pulsation cycle with zero-padding. After some boundary conditions are assumed between subsequent cycles, a virtual timeseries of wavelet coefficients can be constructed. An m-dimensional embedding window moved along this time-series allows us to obtain a phase-diagram representation of the cardio-pulsation; hence, fluctuations around stable trajectories can be interpreted as coefficients associated with residual EEG signal. Finally, the EEG data is recovered after applying a filter in the inverse wavelet transformation, reducing the effect of the unforeseen wavelet coefficients. † The temporal dynamics of the BOLD signal y v i t in the voxel v i , belonging to the vth area, is related to the mesostates b v t in that area by equation (2.7), where the MRI instrumental error is defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">3 v i t wNð0; s 2 v Þ. y v i t Z m v i t C b v t C 3 v i t :</formula><p>(2.7)</p><p>The nuisance effects on the BOLD signals are included in the model using a voxel-dependent potential drift m v i t Z P d kZ0 g v i k t k , which is represented by a nonlinear polynomial series.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(d) Volume conductor model</head><p>The head was considered, in the first approximation, as a series of N mutually nonintersecting compartments (R 1 ,R 2 ,.,R N ), where each successive compartment is enclosed in the other, and the exterior compartment is R NC1 (air; see figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6(a)</ref>). The conductivity s j for any compartment R j was assumed constant (note that s NC1 Z0). This type of volume conductor is designated as a piecewise homogenous volume conductor. There is evidence of anisotropic properties in head tissues <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Hoeltzell &amp; Dykes 1979)</ref>; however, in this paper we shall consider only the isotropic case. The static approach for living tissues, which neglect displacement and eddy currents inside the head, was also assumed <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Plonsey &amp; Heppner 1967)</ref>. The surface S j, jC1 is the boundary separating the inner and outer compartments R j and R jC1 . The vector n j (r) denotes the normal for this surface at the position r. By convention, it was oriented from the inner to the outer compartment. The lead electrodes were co-registered with the anatomical reference by using a linear transformation that matches the positions of a set of four external landmarks (i.e. a red capsule containing nifedipine; Adalat from Bayer) in the anatomical reference system with Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>. The area (red sphere) in the postcentral gyrus in the left hemisphere. The centre of the area (which corresponds to the position of the equivalent dipole) coincides with the voxel with maximum value of the t-test. The extension of the area is also determined from the t-test. The green arrow indicates the normalized orientation of the dipole (estimated from data). Real values were used for this illustration. their relative positions in the Isotrack II reference system (see figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_16">6(b)</ref>).</p><p>The anatomical reference was used to obtain a threedimensional parametric representation of those surfaces delimiting the compartments (i.e. inner/outer skull and scalp, see figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6(c)</ref>). The tessellation of each surface was obtained by multiple deformation of a triangulated sphere towards the target object (MacDonald 1997). The number of triangles used for each surface was 1200, obtained from 602 nodes. The positions of the lead electrodes, external landmarks and the descriptors of the surfaces (i.e. triangles vertexes and normal vectors) were transformed to the Talairach coordinate system using the above-mentioned affine transformation obtained from SPM99.</p><p>An analytical expression for K e (r) is difficult to find directly. However, a procedure exists for obtaining the ELF by using the reciprocity theorem, which is formulated as follows:</p><p>(i) under passive conditions (no primary current source in any compartment R j ) a DC current I er applied to a lead electrode will induce for each compartment R j an ohmic current density J j (r), which can be calculated by solving a second kind of Fredholm integral equation system (equation (2.8)).</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">4pa j J j ðrÞ Z 4pJ N ðrÞ K X N kZ1 ðs k K s kC1 Þ s k # S k;kC1 V 0 1 jr K r 0 j !ð J k ðr 0 Þ !n k ðr 0 ÞÞdr 02 ;</formula><p>ð2:8Þ with a j Z1 for J j ðrÞ 2R j and a j Z ðs j C s jC1 Þ=2s j for J j ðrÞ 2S j;jC1 .The term J N (r) represents the induced ohmic current density if considering the volume conductor as an infinite and homogeneous medium</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">J N ðrÞ Z I er 4p ðr K r e Þ jr K r e j 3 K ðr K r r Þ jr K r r j 3 :</formula><p>The function J N (r) must be evaluated on the surface S N,NC1 avoiding the singularities in the lead electrode</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">J N ðrÞ ZH I er 4p</formula><p>ðr K r r;e Þ jr K r r;e j 3 if r Z r e;r :</p><p>(ii) The reciprocity theorem establishes K e ðrÞ Z K J 1 ðrÞ I er s j :</p><p>The ELF can be evaluated numerically by using a BEM (see <ref type="bibr">Riera &amp; Fuentes 1998 for details)</ref>.  </p><formula xml:id="formula_9">R N+1 R N R j R 1 S j,j+1 n j s N+1 s N s j s 1 (a) (b) (c)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">RESULTS (a) Determining active areas (ROI)</head><p>A standard SPM99 statistics analysis was performed, contrasting the 'on' condition (for both modalities of stimuli) with the 'off ' condition (representing the resting stage). The t-test SPM99 using 'glass images' (maximum intensity projections) is presented in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">7</ref> for both stimuli. The significant structures are also listed below.</p><p>In order to determine the areas involved during the performance of the motor task, the maximum value of the t-test and the extension of the surrounding neighbourhood was found for each structure (i.e. 71 segmented zones) of the probabilistic atlas. A list with the t-test value and the positions of the hotspots for the significant structures is presented in table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1 for</ref>  The dipole is localized very close to the main segment of the left internal carotid artery, which could be used to provide future physiological interpretations of the global effect on the EEG data produced by the ballistocardiogram. The DC shifts for these two channels are also shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">8</ref> (c F4 Z44.39 and c Cz ZK6.03). However, the ballistocardiogram cannot be modelled only by an equivalent dipole and a temporal DC. There are local blood-pulse transients that seem to be related to nonlinear and/or nonstationary components, which can be eliminated by using the wavelet-based methodology described above. Figure <ref type="figure">9a</ref> shows a segment of an EEG (channels F4  (i)   demonstrated using fMRI data <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Kawashima et al. 2000)</ref>. The postcentral gyrus (in blue) represents the most relevant structure owing to the fact that tapping with fingers requires the recruitment of a large number of neurons in the motor cortex. The subject was not allowed to look at the hands; hence, some sort of sensorial (precentral gyrus, in grey) feedback should be implied during settling on the fingers timing. The three-dimensional illustration of the structures used in the analysis is offered in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">11(c</ref>).</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">(ii) R R R R R R R R µV -</formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">µV R R R R R R R R R 1 s F4 Cz (a) (b)</formula><p>The 24-channel EEG and fMRI data, after being corrected by their specific nuisance effects (m e t / EEG and m v i t / fMRI), were used to estimate (equations (A 1)-(A 4)) the mesostates a v t and b v t (see the results of a single block in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">11(a)</ref>; a summary of the symbols is provided in Appendix B). For the particular case of BOLD signals, all voxels within each area were included. The standard deviations of the instrumental errors {s e ,s v } were determined from the non-explained EEG/fMRI data. Once the mesostates were calculated, a v t was evaluated in the static-nonlinear function f v ($) (the results are shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_16">11(b)</ref>). The entire timeseries corresponding to mesostates a v t shows stationary behaviour; hence, its variance was considered as an outstanding gauge of the parameter u v , mainly associated with the susceptibility of h v t to slight variations of a v t . In order to compare the amplitude of the synaptic activity in each area, the scaling factors were fixed r v Z1 for all structures. The flow-inducing signal was evaluated using the Kaiser class filter c k with windows parameter a!1, convolves with a boxcar of around 3 s in length (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">11(c)</ref>). The variations in the flowinducing signal for each structure do not obey the onoff patterns (the horizontal grey bars) in either the visual and auditory modality. In view of this magnitude being directly related to the local postsynaptic potentials, the convincing results reported previously, using simultaneous observations of fMRI and intracortical recordings of neural signals at a microscopic level in visual cortex of monkeys <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Logothetis et al. 2001)</ref>, are quite the opposite to our findings when employing echo/macroscopic observations in humans. However, single trials of either visual or auditory stimuli were repeated at a frequency of 2 Hz within a block, which permitted us to take out those events related responses from the synaptic activity (500 ms duration). It is proper to point out that significant signals, time-locked to the stimulus onset, coexist despite prominent physiological noise. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_16">11(b)</ref> shows the signals originating from averaging the single trials within a block for both stimulus modalities. These facts could motivate neuroscientists to reconsider the following questions: (i) is the electrophysiological sign (i.e. synaptic activity) an absolute and unique mechanism for triggering vascular changes? and (ii) are EEG and BOLD recordings strongly contaminated versions of more informative signalling inside the brain?</p><p>The estimated dipoles normalized orientations for both stimulus modalities, with indeterminate signs, are presented in table 2. The parameters for each area XZ fA v k ;</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">F vv 0 k ; 4 v k ; k v a ; B v k ; q v k ; k v b g</formula><p>were estimated from the mesostates timeseries a v t and b v t using the least-square estimators (see Appendix C in <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Riera et al. 2004</ref>) of the autoregressive model <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Brockwell &amp; Davis 1987)</ref> with exogenous variables (Appendix B in <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Riera et al. 2004</ref> for a revision of general theory of ARMAx). The main attributes of the impulse response and autocorrelation functions (determined by parameters A v k for synaptic activity and B v k for haemodynamics) were comparable with previous results obtained using autoregressive models at the levels of primary currents sources <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Yamashita et al. 2004</ref>) and haemodynamics <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Riera et al. 2004)</ref>.</p><p>Although it is possible to estimate the order of autoregressive models using various criteria for model selection, in our paper it was set up a priori in accordance with these previous studies. The haemodynamic was more sensitive to the condition on-off in the stimulus (  (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">12</ref> presents a summary using a grey scale) between the areas constitutes the most relevant result.</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">P k q v k [ P k 4 v k for</formula><p>A more faithful analysis can be performed using the definition of Granger-causality for autoregressive models <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Geweke 1984)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">DISCUSSION</head><p>This paper makes a significant contribution in terms of the methodology presented, which is a radical departure from the top-down approaches predominant in recent literature. However, it is inappropriate to make any conclusion based on our experimental results in view of the fact that data from only one subject was available in this study. It is abundantly clear to us that in the near future, the most challenging concern will be the elucidation of crosstalking mechanisms between the neural network and vascular systems. From this study, the complexity of this matter is predictable. Additionally, it is the authors' intent to address the following in the ongoing research:</p><p>(i) What is the consequence of having used a model of multiple dipoles instead of applying optimization strategies that search for locally distributed inverse solutions inside each structure (i.e. <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Trujillo-Barreto et al. 2004</ref>)? Such new methodologies will allow the use of multiples areas within a simple structure of the probabilistic atlas. (ii) There are doubts as to whether all ballistocardiogram components have been completely removed from the raw EEG, a fact that could dramatically affect the final results. How would the results differ if subjects perform the same experimental paradigm while their EEG signals are recorded outside the MRI scanner?</p><p>(iii) There are doubts about whether a DC shift in the EEG could somehow reflect in the cross talking between synaptic activity and the vasculature.</p><p>A consistent and reproducible temporal correlation between EEG DC shifts and changes in CBV has been reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Vanhataloa et al. 2003)</ref>.</p><p>Unfortunately, in this study, EEG amplifiers and off-line pre-processing have eliminated the DC shifts in the EEG signals. (iv) The interactions between brain areas have been modelled linearly in this paper by means of the effective connectivity coefficients F vv 0 k . In future works of our group, nonlinear types of interactions between brain areas will be considered. For example, in this issue, <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Robinson et al. (2005)</ref> presented a detailed neuronal mass model that includes cooperation and competition between cortico-cortico and thalamo-cortico populations via excitatory/inhibitory nonlinear interactions. (v) In our model, the geometry of neurons (i.e. pyramidal cells) involved in the genesis of EEG data has not been taken into consideration. In addition, the architectural properties at several levels (i.e. synapses, neurons, networks and neuronal masses) of the multipart brain circuitry have been ignored. (vi) Recent questions, for example 'do synchronized neuronal excitatory and inhibitory processes demand more oxygen than the same processes in a desynchronized state?' <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Makeig et al. 2002)</ref>, will soon refocus the attention of theoreticians. A model of EEG and fMRI fusion that includes two separate mesostates a v G ðtÞ to distinguish excitatory and inhibitory synaptic activity, as well as to allow for descriptions of their interactions within a neural mass, will be useful to understand the relationship between synchronization and haemodynamics in forthcoming studies. For example, the negative/positive correlations between EEG alpha-band power and fMRI signal found recently <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Goldman et al. 2002)</ref> could be interpreted in this context. The activation seen in functional imaging studies probably results from excitation rather than inhibition <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Waldvogel et al. 2000)</ref>, while EEG reflects a competitive balance between them. Some authors, though, have asserted that neuronal inhibitions can raise fMRI and PET measures under certain extreme conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Tagamets &amp; Horwitz 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Caesar et al. 2003)</ref>. In this issue, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Horwitz et al. (2005)</ref> evaluated the effect on PET and fMRI of using a large-scale excitatory and inhibitory computational model applied to a delayed matched-tosample task.</p><p>The authors would like to thank Dr Bosch from the Cuban Neuroscience Center, Havana, for significant contributions to this paper. This study has been supported by JST/RIS-TEX, the research and development promotion scheme for regional proposals promoted by TAO; and the 21st Century Center of Excellence (COE) Program (Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology) entitled 'A Strategic Research and Education Center for an Integrated Approach to Language and Cognition' (Tohoku University).</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">12</ref>. The estimated graph of effective connectivity between the areas is summarized using scale of greys (i.e. the connection is stronger for darker greys, white colour symbolizes a very weak connection). The white squares with a cross represent those connections that were a priori set to zero (using information obtained from the fibre tract-based atlas). The arrows represent directionality in the connection. The colours are the same as those used in the structures (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">11</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX A: MESOSTATES IDENTIFICATION</head><p>The estimation of mesostates from the fused EEG (T e samples) and fMRI (T v scans) data is performed by solving recursively the equations (A 1)-(A 8). Note that K ev Z K e ðr v Þ.</p><p>(a) The mesostates a v t and b v t for the vth area</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">âv t Z X N e eZ1 ðK ev , mv Þ 2 ! K1 X N e eZ1 ðK ev , mv Þ ! V e t K me t K X v 0 sv K ev 0 , mv 0 âv 0 t ! ; (A 1) mv Z X N e eZ1 ðK ev K 0 ev Þ X t ð âv t Þ 2 C l2 v I 3 ! K1 ! X N e eZ1</formula><p>X T e tZ1 âv t K ev V e t K me t K X v 0 sv K ev 0 , mv 0 âv 0 t ! :</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">(A 2)</formula><p>The Lagrange multiplicators l 2 v are used to constrain the dipole orientation to have unitary norm. These factors are determined by solving a small nonlinear optimization problem: respectively.</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">bv t Z 1 n v X n v v i Z1 ðy v i t K mv i t Þ: (A 4)</formula><p>The number of voxel inside the vth region is denoted by n v .  The vector notation g v i Z ðg v i 0 ; .; g v i d Þ 0 and T t Z ð1; t; t 2 ; .; t d Þ 0 has been used.  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a), 24 channels of EEG with a common left ear reference) was fixed to the head by means of the BrainCap-MR 64 channel-Melquest with 5 kU resistors (see figure2(b)). An abrasive electrolyte gel (Abralyt 2000) was applied to guarantee electrode impedance below 5 kU. The positions of the electrodes were accurately determined after running task</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure1. The experimental paradigm consists of 12 subsequent task-blocks. In a task-block, the stimuli lasted for 40 s, preceded by 30 s of resting condition. The subject was asked to perform either right-(checkerboard) or left-hand (tones) finger tapping synchronized with flickering cues (at a frequency of 2 Hz). The order of the stimuli mode was randomly distributed to avoid subject expectation during decision-making about which hand was to be used.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,134.53,62.10,312.00,238.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(b)). Additionally, baseline correction, downsampling to 200 Hz, signal recalibration and filters (low-pass and band-rejection) were applied to guarantee correct artefact elimination.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. The correction of the scan artefacts. (a) A channel of EEG contaminated by artefacts during three scanning intervals. (b) Each interval contains a sequence of an invariant waveform time-locked with the slice acquisition moment. (c) The EEG after artefact correction.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,124.29,342.96,368.64,267.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. The bottom-up biophysical model for the fusion of EEG and fMRI. The system includes two blocks (green shaded boxes):(a) a fast dynamics linear subsystem (the continuous-line box) emulating the neuron-astrocyte interrelationship at the synaptic interface, with a linearly filtered input 'the evoked transients e v t ' (i.e. the filter emulates an integrator at the electrophysiological level inside the neurons); and (b) a slow dynamics linear subsystem (the dashed-line box) that mimics haemodynamics at the level of the micro-vascular building block. The connection between the fast and slow subsystems is only in one direction (i.e. synaptic activity creates a metabolic/oxygen demand, and will, therefore, induce an increase of blood flow via vascular regulation mechanisms). The factors c k will define the linear filter relating f v ða v t Þ with the flow-inducing signal. The magnitudes r v and u v will determine the strength and sensitivity of the nonlinear effect at the electro-vascular coupling (function f v ($) on the top). The magnitude a v t reflects changes in the synaptic activation, and summarizes many phenomena at the synaptic level. The magnitude b v t captures fluctuations in the blood volume v at the post-capillary venous compartment owing to unbalanced inner f in and outer f out (v) blood flows, which could also include a dependency with the concentration of deoxy haemoglobin.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,101.99,61.72,374.45,208.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>e. a global effect of the ballistocardiogram and a temporal DC c e ). A single dipole, with fixed position r o and normalized orientation m o but time varying strength b t , is used to model the global effect in the ballistocardiogram (equation (2.6)).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>m e t Z K e ðr o Þ,m o b t C c e (2.6) A time-varying wavelet-based method is used a posteriori to remove the remaining nonlinear/non-stationary local blood-pulse transient in the EEG data (Wan et al. 2005).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. (a) A schematic of the isotropic and piecewise homogeneous volume conductor model. In the figure, different parameters of the model are presented (n j (r) normal of the surface S j,jC1 , the conductivity s j for compartment R j ). (b) A threedimensional visualization of the lead electrodes (see yellow spots), after being co-registered with the anatomical reference. The red capsules were used as external landmarks to obtain the linear transformation from the anatomical reference to the Isotrack II system. (c) The triangulated surfaces are overlapped in different three-dimensional views (obtained with a trial version of the MAGIC COMMUNICATOR software 'V2.3.0.7 for Intel X86').</figDesc><graphic coords="8,106.19,59.07,368.69,381.06" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>both visual (a) and auditory (b) modalities. (b) Removing ballistocardiogram and DC components from the EEG The ballistocardiogram was modelled as described in §2. Figure 8(a) shows (i ) an EEG channel contaminated with the ballistocardiogram. (ii ) The electrocardiogram (EKG) signal was used to automatically identify the latency of the QRS complex 1 . The minimum value of the R wave was used to determine the marks. The mark-locked averaged signal for the EEG and the EKG channels is shown on the right. There are significant differences between the waveform of averaged signal in the EKG channel and its corresponding magno-effect in any of the EEG channels. This illustrates that the physical basis underlying the contamination of EEG data by the ballistocardiogram is more complicated than a simple addition of passive signals synchronized with the heart's pulse. In figure 8(b), two channels (F4 and Cz) with different levels of the ballistocardiogram signal are presented. The original data (red) overlaps with the residual (black) obtained after removing the global effect, simulated in this case by a single dipole (i.e. the model identification procedure included fitting a single dipole and estimating the temporal DC). The leastsquare estimators of the dipole's parameters (r o ,m o ) and its time-varying amplitude b t , as well as the temporal DC c e are presented in Appendix A (equations (A 5)-(A 7)). The position and normalized orientation of the equivalent dipole for this experiment were r o Z ðK28; K30;K50Þ and m o Z ð0:93;K0:05; 0:37Þ, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. The output of the SPM99 Toolbox (i.e. t-test and design matrix for the experimental paradigm). The panels show the results from contrasting the checkerboard (a) and tones (b) stimulations with the resting condition.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,67.14,59.07,477.36,334.03" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8. (a) The time-series corresponding with (i ) an EEG and (ii ) the EKG channels, with the marks used to average the QRS complex (left side). (b) The EEG results after removing the global effect of the ballistocardiogram (i.e. described by a single dipole) and correcting the temporal DC. The DC values can be read on the right. The blue arrow shows the timing of some nonlinear/non-stationary transient that cannot be removed with the global equivalent dipole. One particular transient is distinguished with a blue circle.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,67.48,355.14,462.79,375.87" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10. The time-series corresponding to the hotspots of the active areas for the postcentral gyrus. (a) Postcentral gyrus left; (b) postcentral gyrus right. The potential drift (smooth curve) after model fitting is overlapped with the BOLD signal for these particular voxels. The experimental paradigm is presented below the graphs.</figDesc><graphic coords="12,139.26,59.07,314.88,319.32" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure 11</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11. (a) The time-series corresponding to the estimated mesostates dynamics (top panels), the evaluation of the staticnonlinear function f v ($) on the synaptic activities a v t (middle panels), and the flow-inducing signals h v t (bottom panels). The horizontal grey bars are used to highlight the task period inside the block. (b) The events-related synaptic activities are emphasized in isolated boxes. The stimulus for a single trial persists for 200 ms (horizontal black bar). The colours used for curves in all the panels are identical to those representing the structures (c).</figDesc><graphic coords="13,85.33,59.49,457.02,368.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>magnitudes u v k and d v k are the eigenvector and eigenvalue of the (3 ! 3) matrixX N e eZ1 ðK ev K 0 ev Þ X T e tZ1 ð âv t Þ 2 ;</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>( b )</head><label>b</label><figDesc>The estimator of nuisance effects m e t and m v i t For the EEG: me t Z K eo , mo bt C ĉe , where: factor l o will warrant that dipole orientation has unitary norm, and it can be estimated from min</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>APPENDIX B: SUMMARY OF THE DATA, INPUTS, VARIABLE AND PARAMETERS OF THE MODEL See tables 3 and 4. ENDNOTE 1 QRS represents a complexes wave constituted by three components: Q, R and S. The Q wave, when present, represents the small horizontal (left to right) current as the action potential travels through the interventricular septum. Very wide and deep Q waves do not have a septal origin, but indicate myocardial infarction. The R and S waves indicate contraction of the myocardium.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="11,69.17,235.64,469.51,319.21" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="11,69.17,71.81,470.95,128.91" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="14,49.32,59.07,228.52,219.57" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>A summary of the results for each structure in both hemispheres of the probabilistic atlas (The columns represent the names of the areas, the maximum values of the t-test inside the structures and the Talairach coordinates of the maximum.)</figDesc><table><row><cell>regions</cell><cell>right</cell><cell></cell><cell>left</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>t-test</cell><cell>position</cell><cell>t-test</cell><cell>position</cell></row><row><cell>(a) visual</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>postcentral gyrus</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>18.443 4</cell><cell>K42, K22, 56</cell></row><row><cell>lingual gyrus</cell><cell>15.639 8</cell><cell>6, K84, 0</cell><cell>14.813 1</cell><cell>K4, K80, K8</cell></row><row><cell>cuneus</cell><cell>15.257 1</cell><cell>4, K92, 14</cell><cell>14.088 9</cell><cell>K4, K98, 10</cell></row><row><cell>cerebellum</cell><cell>11.494 1</cell><cell>6, K72, K14</cell><cell>14.143 7</cell><cell>K28, K78, K24</cell></row><row><cell>med. occip. temp. gyrus</cell><cell>13.150 6</cell><cell>16, K74, K10</cell><cell>12.482 6</cell><cell>K28, K74, K16</cell></row><row><cell>occipital pole</cell><cell>12.234 6</cell><cell>22, K96, 35</cell><cell>11.720 7</cell><cell>K10, K100, 6</cell></row><row><cell>superior occip. gyrus</cell><cell>11.753 8</cell><cell>26, K92, 22</cell><cell>10.845 4</cell><cell>K6, K96, 20</cell></row><row><cell>lateral occip. temp. gyrus</cell><cell>10.859 9</cell><cell>28, K78, K20</cell><cell>11.260 5</cell><cell>K32, K68, K18</cell></row><row><cell>precentral gyrus</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>9.097 8</cell><cell>K32, K18, 66</cell></row><row><cell>(b) auditory</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>postcentral gyrus</cell><cell>17.554</cell><cell>40, K26, 60</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>precentral gyrus</cell><cell>10.371 8</cell><cell>36, K18, 48</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>cerebellum</cell><cell>5.262 1</cell><cell>32, K70, K38</cell><cell>9.471 5</cell><cell>K12, K50, K22</cell></row><row><cell>med. occip. temp. gyrus</cell><cell>4.041 8</cell><cell>14, K68, 10</cell><cell>8.302 8</cell><cell>K20, K52, K12</cell></row><row><cell>superior temp. gyrus</cell><cell>8.081 9</cell><cell>54, K14, 4</cell><cell>4.850 1</cell><cell>K48, K28, 12</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>The estimated dipole orientations (normalized) for each stimulus modality (The lingual gyri in both hemispheres are very close; therefore, an equivalent dipole (centred in the middle) was used. The SPM t-test (auditory modality) shows no significant values for the left superior temporal gyrus; therefore, a dipole was only used for the right superior temporal gyrus.)</figDesc><table><row><cell>regions</cell><cell>normalized dipole orientations</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>visual</cell><cell>auditory</cell></row><row><cell>postcentral gyrus</cell><cell>left: K0.23, K0.92, K0.32</cell><cell>right: 0.17, 0.94, 0.31</cell></row><row><cell>precentral gyrus</cell><cell>left: 0.34, 0.82, 0.46</cell><cell>right: 0.69, 0.67, 0.26</cell></row><row><cell>cerebellum (left)</cell><cell>0.50, 0.50, K0.70</cell><cell>0.12, K0.10, K0.99</cell></row><row><cell>lingual gyrus</cell><cell>average: K0.48, 0.16, K0.86</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>superior temp. gyrus</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>right: K0.54, K0.81, K0.22</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Mesoscopic level.For the fMRI: mv i t Z ĝv i ,T t</figDesc><table><row><cell>physiological meaning</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Echo/macroscopic level.</figDesc><table><row><cell>meaning</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>q 2005 The Royal Society</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>Phil. Trans. R.Soc. B (2005)   </p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="10" xml:id="foot_2"><p>cm, red 30 cm, blue 20 cm, blue 20 cm, black 20 cm, black 15 cm, blue 10 cm, green</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>and Cz) before and after correcting these transients (for details see the blue circle). The physical origin of these transients is thus not straightforward to understand. The EEG data after removing the global effects and local transients induced by the ballistocardiogram remain typical patterns (figure <ref type="figure">9b</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(c) Removing potential drift in the fMRI</head><p>The potential drifts of BOLD signals were estimated for all those voxels belonging to areas of the significant structures (see the least-square estimator in Appendix A; equation (A 8)). As an example, the BOLD signals corresponding to the hotspots of the postcentral gyrus in both hemispheres ((a) left hemisphere, (b) right hemisphere) are shown in figure <ref type="figure">10</ref>. The estimated potential drifts (smooth curves) are overlapped in these panels. The potential drift in fMRI signal could have a physiological interpretation (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Riera et al. 2004)</ref>. As it should be, there is a very clear correspondence between the time courses of the BOLD signal amplitudes in each hemisphere and the on-off stages of the particular stimulus modality.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(d) Identification of the mesostates and model parameters</head><p>The model identification was carried out after selecting the most significant structures involved in the execution of the particular brain function (motor coordination) from table 1. The lingual and superior temporal gyri (in red) were included in the analysis because visual and auditory stimuli were used to indicate to the subject which hand is to be used. The important role played by the cerebellum (in green) in memory-timed finger movements has been   </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A method for removing imaging artifact from continuous EEG recorded during functional MRI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Josephs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="230" to="239" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The neural basis of functional brain imaging signals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Attwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Iadecola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="621" to="625" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electromagnetic brain mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Baillet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mosher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leahy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Process. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relating connectional architecture to grey matter function using diffusion imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E J</forename><surname>Behrens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Johansen-Berg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1098/rstb.2005.1640</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">360</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="903" to="911" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduction to time series and forecasting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brockwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Springer texts in statistics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamics of blood flow and oxygenation changes during brain activation: the balloon model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Buxton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Frank</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Magn. Reson. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="855" to="864" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Context sensitivity of activity dependent increase in cerebral blood flow</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Caesar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lauritzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4239" to="4244" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal spline smoothing of fMRI time series by generalized cross-validation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Carew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wahba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Nordheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Meyerand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="950" to="961" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional magnetic resonance imaging basic principles of and applications to developmental sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Casey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Davidson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rosen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="301" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic statistical parametric mapping: combining fMRI and MEG for high-resolution imaging of cortical activity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Fischl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ballistocardiogram artifact reduction in the simultaneous acquisition of auditory ERPS and fMRI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ellingson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Liebenthal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Spanaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Prieto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Binder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ropellaa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1534" to="1542" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear responses in fMRI: the balloon model, volterra kernels, and other hemodynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Friston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mechelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="477" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic causal modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Friston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Penny</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1273" to="1302" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Book review: the module: crisis of a paradigm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fuster</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="53" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A solution to the dynamical inverse problem of EEG generation using spatiotemporal Kalman filtering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Galka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Yamashita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ozaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Biscay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Valdes-Sosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="435" to="453" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The new cognitive neurosciences, 2nd edn</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gazzaniga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inference and causality in economic time series</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Geweke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of econometrics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>North-Holland</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1101" to="1144" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acquiring simultaneous EEG and functional MRI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Goldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Engel</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Neurophysiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1974">2000. 1974-1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Goldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Engel</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Simultaneous EEG and fMRI of the alpha rhythm</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2487" to="2492" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Blood capillary distribution correlates with hemodynamicbased functional imaging in cerebral cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Harel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Panesar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mount</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cereb. Cortex</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conductivity in the somatosensory cortex of the cat. Evidence for cortical anisotropy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hoeltzell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Dykes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The elusive concept of brain connectivity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Horwitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="470" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigating the neural basis for functional and effective connectivity. Application to fMRI and PET</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Horwitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Warner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-A</forename><surname>Tagamets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Husain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1098/rstb.2005.1647</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">360</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1093" to="1108" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human cerebellum plays an important role in memory-timed finger movement: an fMRI study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kawashima</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurophysiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1079" to="1087" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Progress in understanding functional imaging signals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3550" to="3552" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hemodynamic and electroencephalographic responses to illusory figures: recording of the evoked potentials during functional MRI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Kruggel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wiggins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Von Cramon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1327" to="1336" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mechelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The functional brain connectivity workshop: report and commentary</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="R5" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Very slow activity fluctuations in monkey visual cortex: implications for functional brain imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Leopold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Murayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Logothetis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cereb. Cortex</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="422" to="433" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2003a The underpinnings of the BOLD functional magnetic resonance imaging signal</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Logothetis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3963" to="3971" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2003b MR imaging in the non-human primate: studies of function and of dynamic connectivity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Logothetis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Neurobiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="630" to="642" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neurophysiological investigation of the basis of the fMRI signal</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Logothetis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pauls</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Augath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Trinath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Oeltermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">412</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A method for identifying geometrically simple surfaces from three dimensional images</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Macdonald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-11">1997. November</date>
			<pubPlace>Montreal</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>School of Computer Science, McGill University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cellular mechanisms of brain energy metabolism and their relevance to functional brain imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Magistretti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pellerin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">354</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1155" to="1163" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Having your voxels and timing them too?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Makeig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T.-P</forename><surname>Jung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sejnowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Exploratory analysis and data modeling in functional neuroimaging</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Sommer</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wichert</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust Bayesian estimation of the hemodynamic response function in event-related BOLD MRI using basic physiological information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Marrelec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Benali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ciuciu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pe ´le ´grini-Issac</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Poline</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Brain Mapp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Concurrent EEG/fMRI analysis by multiway partial least squares</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Martinez-Montes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Valdes-Sosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Miwakeichi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Goldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1023" to="1034" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A four-dimensional probabilistic atlas of the human brain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mazziotta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="430" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Miwakeichi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Martinez-Montes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Valdes-Sosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nishiyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mizuhara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yamaguchia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decomposing EEG data into space-time-frequency components using parallel factor analysis</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1035" to="1045" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Electroencephalography: basic principles, clinical applications, and related fields, 4th edn</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Niedermeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lopes Da Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<publisher>Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Baltimore, MD</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Electric fields of the brain: the neurophysics of EEG</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Nunez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabilistic anatomical connectivity derived from the microscopic persistent angular structure of cerebral tissue</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J M</forename><surname>Parker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Alexander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1098/rstb.2005.1639</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">360</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="893" to="902" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparing dynamic causal models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Penny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Stephan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mechelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Friston</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1157" to="1172" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Considerations of quasistationarity in electrophysiological systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Plonsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Heppner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bull. Math. Biophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="657" to="664" />
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electric lead field for a piecewise homogeneous volume conductor model of the head</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Riera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Fuentes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Biomed. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="746" to="753" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Riera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Fuentes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Valde ´s</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Oha ´rriz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">EEG distributed inverse solutions for a spherical head model. Inverse Probl</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1009" to="1019" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">fMRI activation maps based on the NN-ARx model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Riera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bosch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Yamashita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kawashima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sadato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Okada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ozaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="680" to="697" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiscale brain modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rennie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>O'connor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gordon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1098/rstb.2005.1638</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">360</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1043" to="1050" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Studying spontaneous EEG activity with fMRI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Salek-Haddadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Friston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lemieux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Fish</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Res. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="110" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interpreting PET and fMRI measures of functional neural activity: the effects of synaptic inhibition on cortical activation in human imaging studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tagamets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Horwitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Res. Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="273" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Single-neuron activity and tissue oxygenation in the cerebral cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Peterson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Freeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">299</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1070" to="1072" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian model averaging in EEG/MEG imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Trujillo-Barreto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Aubert-Vazquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Valdes-Sosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1300" to="1319" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scalp-recorded slow EEG responses generated in response to hemodynamic changes in the human brain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vanhataloa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tallgrena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Beckerc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Holmesc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Millerc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kailaa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Voipioa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Neurophysiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1744" to="1754" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fiber tract-based atlas of human white matter anatomy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wakana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nagae-Poetscher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van Zijl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mori</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Radiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">230</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relative metabolic demand of inhibition and excitation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Waldvogel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Van Gelderen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Muellbacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">406</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="995" to="998" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Artifact reduction for EEG/fMRI recording part 1: nonlinear reduction of ballistocardiogram artifacts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Iwata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Riera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kitamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kawashima</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ISM Research Memorandum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">939</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<pubPlace>Tokyo, Japan</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>The Institute of Statistical Mathematics</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recursive penalized least squares solution for dynamical inverse problems of EEG generation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Yamashita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Galka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ozaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Biscay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Valdes-Sosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Brain Mapp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="235" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
