<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian network analysis incorporating genetic anchors complements conventional Mendelian randomization approaches for exploratory analysis of causal relationships in complex data</title>
				<funder ref="#_9QTJxVN">
					<orgName type="full">Wellcome Trust</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_7hVMNWC">
					<orgName type="full">Oak Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2020-03-02">March 2, 2020</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Howey</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Genetic Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Newcastle University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Newcastle</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">So-Youn</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Genetic Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Newcastle University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Newcastle</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">MRC Integrative Epidemiology Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bristol</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bristol</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Caroline</forename><surname>Relton</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">MRC Integrative Epidemiology Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bristol</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bristol</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Population Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bristol</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>196</postCode>
									<settlement>Bristol Healthcare Broadway Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>Massachusetts</region>
									<country>United Kingdom United States of America</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">George</forename><forename type="middle">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-1407-8314</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">MRC Integrative Epidemiology Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bristol</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bristol</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Population Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bristol</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>196</postCode>
									<settlement>Bristol Healthcare Broadway Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>Massachusetts</region>
									<country>United Kingdom United States of America</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Heather</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cordell</surname></persName>
							<email>heather.cordell@ncl.ac.uk</email>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-1879-5572</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Genetic Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Newcastle University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Newcastle</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Case Western Reserve University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="US">UNITED STATES</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian network analysis incorporating genetic anchors complements conventional Mendelian randomization approaches for exploratory analysis of causal relationships in complex data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2020-03-02">March 2, 2020</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008198</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: May 12, 2019 Accepted: January 21, 2020</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T18:19+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Mendelian randomization (MR) implemented through instrumental variables analysis is an increasingly popular causal inference tool used in genetic epidemiology. But it can have limitations for evaluating simultaneous causal relationships in complex data sets that include, for example, multiple genetic predictors and multiple potential risk factors associated with the same genetic variant. Here we use real and simulated data to investigate Bayesian network analysis (BN) with the incorporation of directed arcs, representing genetic anchors, as an alternative approach. A Bayesian network describes the conditional dependencies/independencies of variables using a graphical model (a directed acyclic graph) with an accompanying joint probability. In real data, we found BN could be used to infer simultaneous causal relationships that confirmed the individual causal relationships suggested by bi-directional MR, while allowing for the existence of potential horizontal pleiotropy (that would violate MR assumptions). In simulated data, BN with two directional anchors (mimicking genetic instruments) had greater power for a fixed type 1 error than bidirectional MR, while BN with a single directional anchor performed better than or as well as bi-directional MR. Both BN and MR could be adversely affected by violations of their underlying assumptions (such as genetic confounding due to unmeasured horizontal pleiotropy). BN with no directional anchor generated inference that was no better than by chance, emphasizing the importance of directional anchors in BN (as in MR). Under highly pleiotropic simulated scenarios, BN outperformed both MR (and its recent extensions) and two recently-proposed alternative approaches: a multi-SNP mediation intersection-union test (SMUT) and a latent causal variable (LCV) test. We conclude that BN incorporating genetic anchors is a useful complementary method to conventional MR for exploring</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Causal inference methods offer an attractive avenue for understanding complex mechanisms in disease development and identifying ways to intervene upon them. An observed association between a risk factor and disease outcome does not necessarily imply causation, as it may arise via an alternative mechanism such as reverse causation or confounding <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. A gold standard experimental approach for causal inference is to carry out a randomized controlled trial (RCT). By randomly allocating participants to intervention and control groups, an RCT can eliminate selection bias or confounding. However, it is an expensive and time-consuming process, and its result may imply a relatively short-term effect unless the trial is of long duration. Furthermore, intervention via an RCT is not always ethical, or (due to technical limitations) not feasible, for example when the potential risk factor involves DNA methylation or small metabolite variation.</p><p>Traditional non-experimental approaches for causal inference include discordant identical twin studies and longitudinal studies, which can be used to infer causal relationships under certain assumptions. Studies of identical twins are not subject to genetic confounding, and confounding by shared environmental factors is expected to be low (but reverse causationwhich is unshared, and a major distorter of observational estimates-may bias the findings). In longitudinal studies with many repeated measures, methods such as g-computation can be applied <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref>, but most longitudinal studies do not have the data measurements that allow the use of this approach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mendelian randomization</head><p>Mendelian randomization (MR) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref> is an alternative non-experimental approach for causal inference applicable to a general population. In its simplest form it utilizes a genetic variant whose robust association with a risk factor provides a directional causal anchor. The approach is based on the fact that there is only one fixed direction of causation between the genetic variant and the outcome. Use of the genetic variant (which is allocated at gamete formation during conception) has some analogies to the randomization procedure in an RCT. Hence, causal inference is made from the difference in the outcome seen between people with different genetic variants. MR was not originally introduced as an instrumental variable (IV) approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>, and genetic anchors can contribute to causal inference in some settings in which formal IV analysis cannot be applied. However, the main contemporary implementation of MR is in analyses in which genetic variants, usually single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs), are considered to operate as IVs, provided certain conditions are met <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>. Henceforth in this paper we use the abbreviation "MR" to refer to the now-conventional approach of applying IV analytical strategies to evaluate the evidence for causal relationships between genetically instrumented risk factors and phenotypic outcomes.</p><p>MR has been widely applied to evaluate the causal role of traditional risk factors in disease, such as HDL and LDL cholesterol in cardiovascular disease <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>. It has also been applied to identify innovative drug targets in early stage drug development or to discover novel risk factors at the molecular level by scanning "omics" data systemically <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. An advantage of MR is that individual-level data are not necessarily required; inference can be performed on the basis of summary statistics measuring the relationship between the genetic instrument(s) and the risk factor, and the relationship between the genetic instrument(s) and the outcome <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. This means that the summary statistics required to perform MR analysis can be derived from different studies, in an approach termed two-sample MR <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref>.</p><p>Nevertheless, MR has limitations. MR works only if there is a genetic variant robustly associated with the risk factor. It has relatively low statistical power and thus requires a large sample size. MR also has drawbacks in analysis of large-scale "omics" data. Such data often include a number of measured traits that are highly correlated with each other, and some of these may be associated with the same genetic variant(s) and the same outcome. If MR were naively applied for each of these correlated traits, this could violate the MR assumption that the genetic variant used as an instrument influences the outcome only via the risk factor tested.</p><p>To address this issue, several approaches that attempt to either detect or allow for pleiotropy in the context of MR, or to investigate more complex networks of relationships between variables, have been proposed <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[24]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref>. There has also been considerable interest in using MR in a "bi-directional"' or "reciprocal" fashion to determine the direction of causation between two variables, say X and Y <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">27]</ref>. In most of these approaches, an underlying hypothesized graphical structure representing the relationships between variables must be assumed (rather than being learned from the data). However a recently-proposed addition to bi-directional MR, known as MR Steiger <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>, moves a step further by first carrying out an initial determination of whether a genetic variable G is most suitable as an IV for variable X or Y, prior to conducting standard a MR analysis between them based on the determined relationship. This use of Steiger filtering in the context of bi-directional MR is an important component that improves correct directional identification. Another recent method <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref> addresses a similar goal through use of a latent causal variable (LCV) model to infer, for all pairs of traits of interest, the extent to which part or all of the genetic component of one trait is causal for another, suggesting (although not formally demonstrating) that one trait may itself be causal on the other.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bayesian network analysis</head><p>Bayesian networks can be used as the basis for an alternative set of non-experimental, statistical techniques for causal inference. First formalized and developed by Pearl <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">31]</ref>, Bayesian networks have now become widely applied in the social and natural sciences. Briefly, a Bayesian network describes the conditional dependencies of variables using a graphical model known as a directed acyclic graph (DAG) and an accompanying joint probability <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref>. In a DAG, the variables and their conditional relationships are represented as nodes and directional arcs or edges (arrows), respectively. The joint probability is decomposed as a product of local probabilities where the local probability of each variable is explained by its conditional dependencies on its immediate neighbours <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[33]</ref>. The local probability distribution can take any form, but usually a multinomial distribution is used for discrete variables and a multivariate normal distribution is used for continuous variables.</p><p>Although Bayesian networks are generally considered to encapsulate conditional dependencies (and independencies) between variables rather than necessarily implying causal relationships between them-resulting in a distinction between (probabilistic) "Bayesian networks" and "causal Bayesian networks" <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34]</ref>-a causal interpretation can be ascribed to a Bayesian network under three assumptions <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref>: 1) the causal Markov assumption, 2) the causal faithfulness assumption, and 3) the causal sufficiency assumption. The causal Markov assumption states that a variable is independent of all other variables, except for its effect or descendent ("child"/"grandchild" etc.) variables, conditional on its direct causal (or "parent") variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">35]</ref>. The causal faithfulness assumption states that the network structure and the causal Markov relations assumed represents all (and the only existing) conditional independence relationships among variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">36]</ref>. The causal sufficiency assumption corresponds to asserting that there are no external variables which are causes of two or more variables within the model, implying that all causes of the variables are included in the data and there are no unobserved confounding variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">36,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">37]</ref>. A further (sometimes unappreciated) assumption is that of no measurement error i.e. the variables are measured without any errors <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[36]</ref>. These assumptions are essential for causal inference, and are quite commonly assumed in other causal inference methods, but they are generally impossible to validate (and, indeed, may be considered unlikely to hold completely, raising the question of sensitivity to their violation). In the MR literature a large (and growing) set of sensitivity analyses allow relaxation of some of the assumptions required for identification <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[38]</ref>.</p><p>In Bayesian network analysis (BN), we try to infer the most plausible DAG (or a set of plausible DAGs), and thus potential causal relationships between variables, given data (measurements of the relevant variables). In this paper we use the abbreviation "BN" to refer (in principle) to a whole suite of different analysis approaches (employing different methods/algorithms) that use Bayesian networks for the purpose of inferring the most plausible DAG(s), although in our simulations and real data analyses we focus primarily on one specific (scorebased) algorithm (see Methods). Various algorithms have been developed to infer the DAG that best fits the data <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[39]</ref>. Constraint-based methods start with a fully connected graph and carry out a series of marginal and conditional independence tests to decide which edges to remove. These methods can be considered non-parametric, as they focus on testing conditional independence rather than requiring specification of a parametric likelihood. Scorebased methods require a likelihood and hence are parametric (unless all nodes are discrete); they move around through graph space in order to determine the most plausible DAG i.e. the DAG that has the best score (highest or lowest, depending on how the score function is defined), or the highest posterior probability, out of all possible DAGs. As the number of variables in the data set increases, the number of all possible DAGs increases and the enumeration of all possible DAGs becomes infeasible <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[40]</ref>. Thus, in many cases, the most likely DAG is estimated using a model search algorithm or a model averaging algorithm. As the DAG structure is learned/estimated, the parameters of the probability distributions are also learned/estimated from the data using a parameter search algorithm such as maximum likelihood estimation or Bayesian estimation. Note that the term "Bayesian" within BN refers to the fact that certain calculations rely heavily on Bayes' theorem, rather than implying the use of a Bayesian-as opposed to a frequentist-paradigm.</p><p>Intuitively, one would expect the search algorithms used in BN to perform better when directional anchors are available. Directional anchors prevent edges from coming towards certain nodes, which reduces the number of all possible DAGs dramatically and improves the model search process by distinguishing one possible DAG out of a statistically equivalent class of DAGs <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[36]</ref>. In analysis of "omics" data, genetic variants are natural instruments that can be used to define directional anchors.</p><p>BN has the ability to accommodate large complex data relatively flexibly. This feature is particularly useful when the study aims to address simultaneous causal relationships in "omics"scale data sets, for example in studies of gene expression <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[41]</ref> or metabolites <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[42]</ref>. Recent network-building methods have been developed that allow the analysis of potentially hundreds of variables, including both discrete and continuous data types, taking advantage of the ability of genetic variables to operate as causal anchors to help orient the direction of relationships between non-genetic variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[43]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[44]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[45]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[46]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[47]</ref>. These BN approaches could be considered complementary to the MR-based approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref> that enable the construction of such networks, as they use very different algorithms, are more restrictive in terms of requiring individual level input data, and produce different outputs, albeit in order to achieve similar goals. Nevertheless, BN has known limitations. The model search process for score-based algorithms, particularly with large numbers of variables, requires massive computational power and often elimination or pre-filtering of variables is required. The causal relationships implied by each tested model are only strictly valid in the (somewhat implausible) "no measurement error, no unmeasured confounding" situation (though this assumption may sometimes be defended by appealing to "prior background knowledge"); any violation of the assumed relationships will affect the calculation of the penalized log likelihood (or other criterion) used as the basis of the network scores. In particular, in common with several causal inference methods, results from BN may be biased in the presence of hidden confounding factors. This is due to violation of the causal sufficiency assumption.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>We applied MR and BN approaches to both real and simulated data, in order to investigate the properties and performance of the different approaches. Our simulations included scenarios where the assumptions for valid causal inference (using MR and/or BN) were violated, as we were interested in investigating the extent to which this would result in erroneous or misleading inferences. We also applied two recently-proposed methods, LCV <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref> and SMUT <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[48]</ref>, along with BN, MR and a recent MR extension <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref>, to data generated under a more complex simulation scenario involving extreme pleiotropy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Illustrative example: Fatty acids and BMI</head><p>As an initial motivating example, we investigated possible causal relationships between fatty acid metabolites and body mass index (BMI) using the TwinsUK study data <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[49]</ref>. We applied both MR and BN to these data, and compared the causal inferences obtained. We note that this example is intended as a (relatively straightforward) illustration of analysing data using both MR and BN approaches, rather than making any strong claims for the validity of the instruments (and thus for the robustness of the inferences obtained) in this particular case.</p><p>The metabolites considered were the omega-3 fatty acids eicosapentaenoate (EPA) and dihomo-linolenate (DGLA). For testing whether a causal relationship existed between these metabolites and BMI, genetic IVs for EPA and DGLA were chosen based on knowledge gained from prior investigation of this data set (along with an additional German cohort) <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[50]</ref>; we note that re-use of (some of) the same data used to identify the instruments can, in theory, run the risk of over-fitting. Based on these previous results, the SNP rs174556 in FADS1-2-3 was used as an IV for EPA, while the SNPs rs968567 in FADS1-2-3 and rs6498540 in PDXDC1 were used as IVs for DGLA.</p><p>rs174556 and rs968567 are in linkage disequilibrium (LD) i.e. correlated with an r 2 value of �0.52. It is conceivable that rs174556 is actually a causal variant for DGLA, and so could have an effect on BMI operating in parallel through both EPA and DGLA. This would violate one of the three assumptions required for the genetic variant to be used as an instrumental variable (IV) for EPA, namely the no-horizontal pleiotropy assumption that the IV has no effect on the outcome besides the effect mediated through the risk factor (EPA).</p><p>MR, based on the individual level data (rather than based on summary statistics via twosample MR), was used to test for a causal relationship between each metabolite and BMI. The rationale for using individual level data (rather than performing the asymptotically equivalent two-sample MR analysis) was to allow comparison with BN which (at least in its current implementations) requires access to individual level data. A causal relationship from BMI to each metabolite was also tested using MR with an instrumental variable for BMI given by a BMI allele score formed (on the basis of prior knowledge <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">52]</ref>) from 39 BMI-associated SNPs. Again, individual level data (and resulting individual level BMI allele scores) were used, although the weighting of the SNPs to construct the allele score variable could be considered to incorporate external information as "prior knowledge", being informed by previous results from larger studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">52]</ref>.</p><p>Table <ref type="table">1</ref> shows the results of applying Mendelian randomization to the TwinsUK data set. Both metabolites, EPA and DGLA, were inferred to have a causal relationship with BMI at the 0.05 significance level (p-values 0.0498 and 0.0327 respectively). Conversely, reverse causation (with BMI causing the metabolite levels) did not show such compelling p-values (0.6668 and 0.7082 respectively). Mendelian randomization between the metabolites provided somewhat conflicting results, with both directions achieving p-values &lt;0.05, but overall there seemed to be slightly stronger support for a causal effect from DGLA to EPA. Since rs174556 is used as an instrument for EPA, while rs968567 and rs6498540 are used simultaneously as instruments for DGLA, the LD between rs174556 and rs968567 violates the exclusion restriction (that an instrument only influences the outcome through the exposure) in both directions, complicating the interpretation of the results from MR, and thus perhaps motivating use of an alternative method such as BN, which avoids the problem of having an additional (unaccounted for) path between a genetic instrument and the outcome by simultaneously modelling the effects of all measured instruments and exposures.</p><p>Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1A</ref> shows the average network from BN when all variables are included, with the directional constraint that arrows are constrained to come out from (rather than go into) any nodes corresponding to genetic variables. The thickness of the edges indicates their strength or Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. Mendelian randomization results for TwinsUK data. The Instrument-risk factor p-value(s) are from the regression of the risk factor on the instrument(s), and the MR p-value is from the regression using the predicted value of the risk factor as an explanatory variable for the outcome variable, with the uncertainty in the predicted values from the first-stage regression taken into account through use of the R function ivreg().</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Instrument(s)</head><p>Risk probability of existence (i.e. frequency of edge presence in all replicates), providing a visual representation of the relative support for the possible causal effects. The red numbers indicate the probability of existence of the edge, and the numbers in brackets indicate the probability of the edge operating in direction shown, given that it exists. The edges for which both numbers are provided are those in which we are most interested, namely those that represent relationships between BMI and the metabolites. The other edges are annotated with only one number, their probability of existence, as they were already constrained such that edges from the SNPs  , the direction-ofedge probabilities between the three variables are all close to 0.5, illustrating the fact that, in the absence of any instrumental variables to anchor the network, all networks connecting all three variables are statistically equivalent, thus the likelihoods are equal and no directional preference can be determined.</p><p>Similarly to MR, BN also suggests a causal relationship from DGLA to EPA, with the estimated probability of the direction decreasing as the number of anchor variables is reduced.</p><p>The fits of the four models shown in Fig 1A <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">-1D</ref> are not directly comparable, as they contain (and thus model data at) different numbers of variables. However the fits of models that do or do not contain arrows between the genetic variables and the non-genetic variables can be examined by fitting networks equivalent to that shown in Fig 1A (so modelling data at all measured variables), but with certain arrows "blacklisted" to not be allowed to exist. The average network score based on the Bayesian information criterion (BIC) when all variables are included and both the SNPs and the BMI allele score are allowed to have children (equivalent to Overall, these results support the inference seen with this data set using MR. They also illustrate the advantage in BN of being able to easily include simultaneously anchor variables for both BMI and the metabolites-although removing one or other anchor still produced broadly similar inference concerning the direction of the relationships between the metabolites and BMI, we found the support for these relationships (as measured by the estimated probabilities of the directions of the relevant edges, see Fig 1B <ref type="figure"></ref>and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1C</ref>) was lowered.</p><p>In this example, we did not use BN to directly model LD between SNPs. It would, in fact, be possible to construct BN models that incorporate LD between variants by allowing arrows to connect genetic variables, with the practical constraints that arrows are only allowed between SNPs that lie relatively close together on the genome, and the directions of the arrows are constrained to go only in one direction (e.g. from smaller to larger base-pair positions). Whether this would offer any practical advantage in terms of elucidating the relationships between the non-genetic factors, or between genetic and non-genetic factors, would be an interesting topic for further investigation.</p><p>A different consequence of LD is the fact that none of the SNPs being used as instruments for EPA or DGLA are necessarily causal for the fatty acids (or for BMI); they may simply be surrogates for (i.e. correlated with) the true unmeasured causal variants. This would not be expected to invalidate the analysis for either MR or BN, but would result in weaker relationships between the measured SNPs and the fatty acids, and thus lower power for detection of network relationships. It is even conceivable that there is a single causal SNP affecting both EPA and DGLA, which is tagged to different extents by the three measured SNPs-although this seems unlikely in view of the fact that, in Fig 1A, rs968567 and rs6498540 are chosen as instruments for DGLA but not for EPA, while rs174556 is chosen as an instrument for both DGLA and EPA. (If there were, in fact, a single causal SNP affecting both EPA and DGLA, one would expect the same surrogate instruments, namely those most strongly correlated with the causal SNP, to be chosen for both EPA and DGLA). In principle, one could fit a graph with an additional latent node for an unmeasured causal SNP in order to explore this scenario.</p><p>Although not explored here, causal discovery methods such as the Fast Causal Inference (FCI) algorithm, that allow latent (unmeasured) nodes resulting in non-directed, bi-directed or partially-oriented edges between measured variables, do exist <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[33]</ref>, and would be an interesting topic for further investigation.    <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[39]</ref>) and S7-S9 Figs (for BN implemented via the deal algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[53]</ref>). Comparison of S4-S6 Figs with S7-S9 Figs shows the power of the deal algorithm to be consistently lower than that of the bnlearn algorithm (with no compensating advantage in terms of better type 1 error), and for this reason we discard the deal algorithm from any further consideration.</p><p>Direct comparison between MR/MR Steiger and BN is complicated as the most natural processes for determining if X is causal on Y (or for examining the extent of the evidence for X being causal on Y) are different for the three methods. For MR/MR Steiger, we make inference based on a type I error (p-value) threshold given by α (the probability of a false positive). Although we concur with the opinion <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[54]</ref> that, in real data analysis, use of absolute p-value thresholds should be avoided, we do not in fact propose that any particular threshold should be considered as "correct"; here we instead use the thresholds as heuristics and examine the performance of the methods (in terms of true and false detections of relationships) as the thresholds are varied. For BN, we make inference based on an estimated posterior probability that X is causal on Y, and again examine performance of the method as the threshold for declaring detection is varied. Given the lack of direct comparability between the methods, we use different thresholds (and different colours) for MR/MR Steiger and BN in the plots shown in Figs <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">3</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>, S1-S9 Figs: for MR/MR Steiger we use α values of 0.01, 0.05 and 0.1, while for BN we use probability thresholds of 0.7, 0.8 and 0.9. The resulting powers and type I errors are therefore not directly comparable, but they do give some indication of how the methods perform using thresholds that might be considered reasonable choices in practice.</p><p>For MR performed using instrumental variable regression, which takes into account the uncertainty of the predicted values in the first-stage regression, the type I error is seen to be somewhat conservative, except when G is used as the instrument and there is genetic confounding (Figs <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">3</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>, panels F and I; S3 Fig, <ref type="figure">panel A</ref>). In contrast, when the first-stage uncertainty is not taken into account, the correct type I error (corresponding to the chosen α level) is generally observed (Figs <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">3</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>, panels D, E, G, H; S1 and S2 Figs, panels G and J; S3 Fig, <ref type="figure">panel J</ref>), again except when G is used as the instrument and there is genetic confounding (Figs <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">3</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>, panels F and I; S3 Fig, <ref type="figure">panel G</ref>). This conservative behaviour of 'standard' instrumental variable regression-based MR seen in these simulations may relate to our use of a relatively weak instrument; we found that increasing the magnitude of the regression coefficient β GX used to generate the simulated data resulted in generally well-calibrated type I error.</p><p>When MR Steiger is used, the type I error and power are both reduced compared to MR (resulting in a conservative test, provided a valid instrument is available) due to the extra condition that a variable must pass a p-value threshold to be selected as a valid instrument, whereas in MR this is already assumed. Under model 3, MR Steiger with G used as a possible instrument can show inflated type 1 error (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref>, panel I), while for MR Steiger with Z used as a possible instrument, both the type I error and the power are generally zero due to Z never actually being chosen as a valid instrument for X in any of the 1000 simulation replicates (Figs <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">3</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>, panels C, F, I; S6 Fig, <ref type="figure">panels A,</ref><ref type="figure">C,</ref><ref type="figure">D</ref>). This behaviour of MR Steiger never actually choosing the proposed instrument is also seen under models 1 and 2, when Z is used as a possible instrument and we wish to test from X to Y (Figs <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">3</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>, panels D, E, G, H; S4 and S5 Figs, panels A and C), or when G is used as a possible instrument and we wish to test from Y to X (S4 and S5 Figs, panels B and D).</p><p>For BN, we find the power is generally higher when both G and Z are used together rather than using either alone (Figs <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">3</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>, panels A and B). Under model 1, the probability of making an incorrect inference is very low when testing Y to X when there is actually an effect from X to Y (S4 Fig, <ref type="figure">panel B</ref>) or vice versa (Figs <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">3</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>, panel G), and zero when there is no effect at all (Figs <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">3</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>, panel D; S4 Fig, <ref type="figure">panels C</ref> and<ref type="figure">D</ref>). Under model 2, there is a small chance of making an incorrect inference when testing X to Y (and no such effect exists,) particularly under strong confounding when Z is included as a possible explanatory variable (Fig 4 <ref type="figure">, panels  E</ref> and<ref type="figure">H</ref>). For model 3, there is a fairly large chance of making an incorrect inference when testing X to Y, if in fact there is an effect from Y to X (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref> The curves are constructed with respect to testing for a causal effect from X to Y, where the curves for true/false positives are constructed by gradually relaxing the detection threshold (based on type I error α for MR, or posterior probability of existence of an arrow for BN) used. For the top plots (panels A-C), false positives on the x-axis are counted using simulations when there is no effect (β XY = 0), while true positives on the yaxis are counted under simulations when there is an effect (β XY = 0.5). For the bottom plots (panels D-F), the false positive rate is calculated in a slightly different way, by simulating from a model where there is a causal effect from Y to X. Overall, the ROC curves are most appealing for BN, showing a generally higher power for a given type error rate. Similar conclusions apply when comparing BN with MR' and St' (performed using two-stage least squares regression without accounting for the uncertainty of the predicted values in the first-stage regression), see S10 and S11 Figs.</p><p>BN inference on direction of causality. To illustrate the ability of BN to infer the direction of causality, S12 Fig shows box plots of the probability estimates of X being causal on Y (top row) and of Y being causal on X (bottom row) given by BN, for data simulated under model 1 where X was causal on Y. As the true effect size β XY increases, the probability of correctly (top row) detecting an X to Y effect increases, while when β XY is zero, the probability of incorrectly detecting this effect is near zero. When both G and Z are included in the analysis For the top plots (panels A-C), false positives on the x-axis are counted using simulations when there is no effect (β XY = 0), while for the bottom plots (panels D-F), the false positive rate is calculated by simulating from a model where there is a causal effect from Y to X. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008198.g005">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008198.g005</ref> (panel A) the probability estimates are higher than when only one of these is included (panels B and C), illustrating the advantage of using the extra information from both variables. In addition, as the true effect size, β XY , increases, the probability of falsely (bottom row) detecting a Y to X effect decreases, with the lowest probability seen when both G and Z are included in the analysis (panel D), again illustrating the advantage of using the extra information from both variables. S13 Fig shows the BN box plots for data simulated under model 2, the nongenetic-confounding model. Here the probabilities are all closer to 0.5, illustrating that BN does not work quite as well in this scenario as under model 1. In particular, when there are no effects between X and Y, the probabilities are much further from zero, with a mean well above 0. S14 Fig shows the BN box plots for data simulated under model 3, the genetic-confounding model. This shows better estimates of near zero when there is no effect from X to Y. However, for the analysis with only G included, it can be seen the probability estimates approach 0.5 as the effect size increases, rather than increasing to above 0.5 as occurred for models 1 and 2. An overall summary of the performance of the methods based on Simulation Study 1 is given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>. Naturally, these conclusions pertain only to the (relatively simple) set of scenarios that we have investigated here. In particular, we have not investigated the presence of both genetic and non-genetic confounding, nor have we considered situations such as when β CX and β CY have opposite signs. The robustness of BN to such types of confounding would be an interesting topic for future investigation. One can certainly envisage many other more complex simulation scenarios that would be interesting to explore, but are beyond the scope of this initial investigation. More complicated scenarios involving more complex networks of variables including extreme pleiotropy are, however, investigated in Simulation Study 3 (below).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Simulation study 2</head><p>We also investigated the utility of BNs for performing causal inference in a binary trait setting. Discrete binary data was simulated for 5000 individuals using four models considered in recent work by Shih et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[55]</ref>, in the context of quantifying the effects of alcohol consumption and high alanine transaminase levels on hepatocellular carcinoma. Data were simulated according to <ref type="bibr">Fig 7,</ref><ref type="bibr"></ref> under four different scenarios with generating model parameter values as listed in Table <ref type="table">3</ref>. Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">8</ref> shows the average BN inferred when genetic variable Q was constrained to have no parents. For scenarios A and B, the only edges detected are those starting at (directed away from) Q, as the generating parameters for these causal relationships outweigh any others (the estimates of which do not meet the strength threshold to be plotted). The generating parameters under the other two models (panels C and D) are more evenly balanced, and this is reflected by most edges appearing in the average network with a probability strength of at least 0.4.</p><p>Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">8C</ref> shows an edge from Y to W with direction probability 0.72, which is in the opposite direction from how it was simulated. We explain this by noting that the two edges between Q and Y, and between Y and W, are much stronger than other edges in the model, each with probability strength 1, and so are always inferred to be in the model. The weak relationship between Q to W can be modelled by an additional edge from Q to W, but can also be modelled via the edges from Q to Y to W, which has the advantage of using 2 edges rather than 3 edges to model the entire system of relations between Q, Y and W. Therefore, although incorrect, this model was sometimes chosen as the best model on account of the fact that the BIC used in the bnlearn algorithm penalizes the number of edges in the network. , and the edge from Q to W is much stronger since it is now the best way to model the causal relationship between Q and Y. This highlights the fact that constraints (if known) should be added to provide better causal inference as well as to improve computational efficiency. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Simulation study 3</head><p>We also carried out a simulation study involving more complex networks of variables including extreme pleiotropy (see Methods). This included 4 metabolites ( Table <ref type="table">3</ref>. The parameter values for each scenario used to simulate discrete binary data. Models are described in detail by Shih et. al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[55]</ref>.   MR-BMA and B12 tested the relationships between Y and all 12 metabolites in one analysis. MR, B1 and B12 were used to test for a causal effect between metabolites and Y in either direction while MR-BMA could only be used to test from the metabolites to Y. The methods required different approaches to handle the 10,000 SNPs that were potentially causal on the metabolites or Y: for MR, B1 and B12 a weighted allele score was constructed (using SNPs passing a p-value threshold of p &lt; 5 × 10 -6 ), while SMUT and MR-BMA used a subset of SNPs passing a p-value threshold of p &lt; 5 × 10 -6 with any metabolite. For BN with only one risk factor (B1), there is very high power to detect a causal relationship in the correct direction when it is present, due to the use of genetic instruments for both the metabolite and Y. The type I error when there is a reverse effect is also very low, despite our previous observations (in Simulation Study 1) suggesting potential inflated type I error when there is genetic confounding and a reverse effect. This may be due to the effect sizes of the SNPs directly affecting the metabolite and those affecting Y being quite different, meaning that the complex nature of the confounding does not interfere too much with inference here (although clearly the same robustness is not seen for MR). For BN with all 12 risk factors (B12), there is very high power to detect causal relationships when they are present, even higher than with B1, most probably due to the complementary manner in which all of the data is used together to better resolve the direction of edges. The type I errors are also much lower than B1 for the same reason. The powers are higher than for MR-BMA, probably due to the fact that the SNPs that affect Y are modelled in BN but are not accounted for in the MR-BMA analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scenario Frequency of Q = 1 Parameters influencing Y Parameters influencing H</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Parameters influencing W</head><formula xml:id="formula_0">β 0 β q (Q to Y) β W (W to Y) β H (H to Y) α 0 α q (Q to H) α W (W to H) δ 0 δ q (Q to W) A 0.</formula><p>MR-BMA shows very high power when there is an effect and very low type I error when there is no effect or a reverse effect. Although MR-BMA is powerful (with low type I error) at successfully selecting only those metabolites that affect Y, its power is slightly lower than that of BN, and, unlike BN, it cannot detect a reverse effect from Y to the metabolites.</p><p>We also analysed these data using the recently-developed latent causal variable (LCV) method <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref>, which uses all 10,000 SNPs to test whether the "genetic causality proportion" (GCP) (the extent to which part or all of the genetic component of one trait is causal for another) differs from 0. However, in comparison to the other methods considered, the results (S15 Fig) were rather poor, with a very low rejection rate for the LCV test of GCP = 0 when there is a causal relationship between the metabolite and Y in either direction. The LCV tests of GCP = -1 and GCP = 1 did, however, show good power to (correctly) reject the hypotheses that one variable was fully causal of another.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>There is a growing interest in the use of causal inference methods in genetic epidemiology. With "omics" data becoming increasingly available in large cohort studies, we now have potential to uncover novel predictive and prognostic markers at the molecular level, variation in which may correlate with disease status even in its early stages. To make use of such markers, it is crucial to evaluate the extent to which any observed associations are due to causal relationships between the variables. For more than a decade, MR has been a popular approach used to strengthen or undermine a hypothesized causal relationship identified from epidemiological studies. However, conventional MR may not be readily applicable to infer simultaneous causal relationships in large-scale "omics" data because it generally deals with only one potential cause and one potential effect at a time. A naive application of MR, such as testing a causal effect of each "omics" variable on the disease outcome one at a time, may violate the no-pleiotropy assumption. Thus, recent developments in MR <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[24]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">56]</ref> have focussed on considering several instruments and/or mediators simultaneously, in principle better accounting for horizontal pleiotropy. However, in most of these approaches, an underlying hypothesized graphical structure representing the relationships between variables must be assumed (rather than being learned from the data).</p><p>Here we propose Bayesian network analysis with the inclusion of genetic anchors to help orient relationships as a complementary approach for performing exploratory analysis of causal relationships in complex data. BN has many conceptual (and practical) similarities to MR, indeed BN in the context used here could be considered as an implementation of the basic logic of MR <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Both MR implemented through IV analysis and BN rely on assuming a specific graphical model (as well as making certain other assumptions) to carry out inference regarding the relationships between two or more variables of interest, and the inference obtained will be affected by any violation of the assumed relationships. In particular, unmeasured confounding is a problem for both methods, although MR does have the advantage of being robust to unmeasured confounding that only operates between the mediator and the outcome (i.e. non-genetic confounding), while the same is not necessarily the case for BN. However, there are also differences between the approaches, in particular the algorithmic details (and required calculations) for the two methods as performed in practice are quite different. BN naturally offers some additional flexibility in terms of exploring a (potentially large) number of different graphical models, a goal that could be considered to have motivated the development of MR extensions such as bi-directional MR and MR Steiger. BN also allows an appealing quantification of the strength of evidence provided by the data for different relationships (and indeed for entire graphical models) via calculation of network scores and bootstrap estimates of posterior probabilities for specific relationships. This contrasts with the inference provided from MR which is generally presented in frequentist terms and is based on p-values (or effect estimates and their standard errors). Despite recent debate about the utility and potential for misinterpretation of p-values in scientific research <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[54]</ref>, we note that p-values can still be considered as useful summaries of the compatibility between a data set and an underlying hypothesized model <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[54,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">57]</ref>. While this interpretation is only strictly correct if the entire assumed data generating model (not just the lack of existence of the targeted effect) holds, genetic associations identified using this paradigm have generally proved highly reproducible and, in the human genetics literature, p-values remain the most commonly-used summary measures indicating the extent of evidence for potential associations <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[58]</ref>. Indeed, it is this very fact that underpins their potential utility for use in MR. Thus, while we concur with the opinion <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[54]</ref> that the use of absolute significance thresholds should be avoided (and we do not propose that any particular threshold should be considered as "correct"), we still consider p-values to be useful summary measures that may be used, as in our illustrative example, to inform the comparison of competing hypotheses, or, as in our simulation studies, as a heurstic to examine the relative performance of different methods (in terms of true and false detections of relationships) as the thresholds are varied.</p><p>Our motivating example involved a situation where two correlated risk factors were associated with the same genetic variant, and showed how BN could help to resolve their simultaneous potential causal effects. Our example illustrated that BN could infer causal relationships even in the absence of a genetic anchor for the risk factor, as long as a genetic anchor for the outcome is available. In principle, BN can be applied to more complicated data with much larger numbers of variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[46]</ref>, as long as the conditional dependencies of the variables are graphically representable as DAGs. Thus BN complements MR in terms of allowing a deeper exploration of possible underlying causal structures, and in providing a natural way of including multiple instruments and/or mediators in the analysis, similar to the goal of a number of recent MR extensions <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[24]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">56]</ref>.</p><p>We conducted a series of simulation studies and showed that BN with two directional anchors outperformed bi-directional MR based on ROC curves of the true positive rate (i.e. power) for a fixed false positive rate (i.e. type I error). The behaviour of both approaches will depend on the sample size and the absolute value of the causal effect as well as on the presence of confounding; both BN and MR perform better as the true causal effect (or the sample size) increases. BN performs better with more directional anchors available, since they remove uncertainty in the model search and help orient the true causal directions between other variables. However, even when only a single directional anchor is available, BN performs as well as or better than MR, at least under the scenarios and parameter values considered here. In our study, the performance of both BN and MR was affected by genetic confounding but barely affected by non-genetic confounding. (However, note that non-genetic confounding can, in some circumstances, create serious bias, and MR has begun addressing this by carrying out between-sibling analyses which are protected from the common sources of this bias <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[59]</ref>). In models involving pleiotropic relationships, BN outperformed both MR and the recently-proposed MR-BMA method, as well as outperforming SMUT.</p><p>We also considered a recently-developed latent causal variable (LCV) method <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref> which infers, for pairs of measured traits, the extent to which part or all of the genetic component of one trait is causal for the other. This method analyses one mediator variable and one outcome variable at any given time, making use of genetic data across the whole genome, rather than following the usual MR approach of selecting specific genetic variants to be used as instruments. However, the approach is conceptually rather different from the other methods considered here, and unlike the other methods, does not formally test whether the mediator is causally related to the outcome (or vice versa). Exploratory analysis (S15 Fig) using data from Simulation Study 3 suggested that the LCV test of GCP = 0 was not well-powered in this scenario, possibly because the concept of a genetic causality proportion (GCP) was not directly encapsulated by our simulation model.</p><p>We are not the first to propose the utility of genetic anchors to help orient relationships between variables in the context of network analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[43]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[44]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[45]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">47]</ref>. However, to our knowledge, this is the first study to directly compare the performance of MR and BN in both real and simulated data. Previously, Ainsworth et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[60]</ref> applied MR, BN and structural equation modelling to simple simulated data scenarios and noted that BN and structural equation modelling could offer potentially attractive alternative (or at least complementary) approaches to MR. Given that structural equation modelling and BN overlap in many situations (for example, if the graphical model is a DAG and the local distribution follows a normal distribution), this current study corroborates that suggestion. We show here that BN with both directional anchors has greater power than bi-directional MR when applied to the same data, and further report on scenarios where BN could be more easily applied than MR. These include data with multiple risk factors and/or data with no genetic variant for one of the risk factors available.</p><p>Like any analytical approach, BN has limitations. Its assumptions (required for valid causal inference) are easily violated. For example, modelling all possible causes and confounding factors of all variables in the data is usually impossible (although this limitation is shared with most other methods for causal inference). BN cannot explain a cyclic or feedback relationship among variables, whereas bi-directional MR can test this to some extent. The performance of BN is affected by the sample size and true causal effect sizes, and the posterior probability threshold that corresponds to any particular type 1 error rate is therefore hard to define. In addition, although not explored in our current study, BN is also more likely than MR to be adversely affected by measurement error <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>. Arguably the most serious limitation of BN is the fact that analysis is performed on individual level data, and the method is not readily extended to summary data (although this represents an interesting topic for future investigation). In contrast, MR approaches such as two-sample MR can utilize previously generated results, including those based on summary statistics, to make robust causal inference. Indeed, this is the predominant mode of MR analysis at present (although there may well be a move back to single sample individual participant data analysis in the future, given the availability of large-scale studies such as UK Biobank <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[61]</ref>). These latter two limitations (the sensitivity to measurement error and the requirement for individual level data) mean that BN will not replace MR, but instead offers a complementary approach, offering some advantages and some disadvantages. Both BN and MR rely on some fairly strong assumptions (such as the known graph for MR and the lack of latent confounders for BN) that should ideally be assessed in real data analysis. But, as BN and MR depend on different sets of assumptions, and ones that would not necessarily lead to distortion of the results to the same degree (or even in the same direction), findings from the two approaches could contribute to the triangulation of evidence regarding a particular causal question <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[62]</ref>. This would preferably be a pre-planned exercise, and where possible would include estimates from other approaches utilizing methods aimed at strengthened causal inference, all of which could be biased, but with orthogonal sources of bias affecting each <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[63]</ref>.</p><p>There are some limitations to our current study. First, in our simulations, we consider only fairly simple scenarios with relatively small numbers of variables where both BN and MR can easily be applied (although we note that BN can readily be extended to utilize larger numbers of variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[43]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[44]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[45]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[46]</ref>). It is possible that BN may perform differently or worse in larger, more complex data sets. Thus, further studies on more complex real and simulated data (for example involving known biological or metabolic pathways) are required. In spite of these limitations, our study highlights the utility of BN as an appealing approach for performing causal inference in complex biological data sets that thus warrants further investigation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials and methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mendelian randomization</head><p>Mendelian randomization was performed using two-stage least squares linear regression <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[64]</ref>. The first linear regression used one or more genetic variables (either a single SNP, two SNPs or an allele score) as the explanatory variable(s) and the hypothesized risk factor as the response variable. The second linear regression used the predicted values of the risk factor for each individual from the first regression as the explanatory variable, and the outcome as response variable. We used instrumental variable regression using the function ivreg() from the R statistical software package AER <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[65]</ref>, which takes into account the uncertainty of the predicted values in the first-stage regression to calculate the MR p-values. These p-values were used as a measure of evidence of a causal relationship. We also performed two-stage least squares regression using the lm() function in R, but without accounting for the uncertainty of the predicted values in the first-stage regression (denoted by MR'). We note that this method provides equivalent inference (identical p-values) to that obtained by simply regressing the outcome variable on the genetic variable(s).</p><p>We note that MR was originally <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> introduced as a general approach that uses the directionality from genetic variable to phenotype as the basic principle, but not with any particular analytical strategy (such as that suggested by its use here) in mind. In practice, the large majority of MR studies have attempted effect estimation and have used either two-stage least squares linear regression for analysis carried out within a single study sample, or two-sample MR based on summary statistics when utilizing data from two separate studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">17]</ref> (which provides equivalent inference). This motivates our choice of two-stage least squares linear regression as reflecting the most commonly used analysis strategy, while also having the advantage of allowing direct comparison with BN (which, at least in its current implementations, requires access to individual level-rather than summary statistic level-data).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bayesian networks</head><p>A variety of algorithms have been proposed for learning the structure and parameters of a Bayesian network. We considered two different algorithms, one motivated by the default algorithm implemented in the R package deal <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[53]</ref> and the other motivated by an option available in the R package bnlearn <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[39]</ref>, which were implemented in C++ in our own software package, BayesNetty <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[66]</ref>. The bnlearn algorithm that we used corresponded to the Hill-Climbing score-based algorithm with Bayesian information criterion (BIC) score described on pages 52 and 106 of <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[39]</ref>. The BIC used to construct the network score has the structure of a penalized negative log-likelihood, meaning that models with lower BIC scores are considered to be a better fit, with the score for any hypothesized network inversely related to its posterior probability (calculated under specific distributional assumptions, namely that discrete nodes follow a multinomial distribution and continuous nodes a normal distribution, with distributional parameters determined by the values of the incoming parent nodes). The deal algorithm that we used involved specifying a prior network structure which is used, along with training data and default distributional assumptions, to generate an overall network score. For full details see <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[53]</ref>. For exploring the graph space, we used the same Hill-Climbing algorithm as was used with bnlearn. The bnlearn approach (as we demonstrate) was found to be more powerful and robust than deal. The bnlearn method is therefore the primary method used to generate the BN results presented in this article.</p><p>Networks were drawn using the igraph <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[67]</ref> R package. Average networks were calculated by bootstrapping the data with replacement 1000 times, and selecting the best-fit network for each replicate. The probability of an edge existing, and the probability of the edge being in a particular direction (given that it exists) were estimated by counting the proportion of times that such events occurred amongst the 1000 resulting best-fit bootstrap networks. For plotting the resulting average network, only edges that were considered sufficiently strong in the context of the current average network <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[39]</ref> were plotted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MR Steiger</head><p>In addition to MR and BN, we also considered a recently-proposed extension of MR known as MR Steiger <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>. This approach involves applying two tests which must both pass a p-value threshold in order to conclude a causal relationship between variables X and Y: firstly a test to decide if a genetic variable G is most suitable as an IV for variable X or Y, then a standard MR test using G as an instrument to test either the relationship X to Y, or the relationship Y to X.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Multivariable MR based on Bayesian model averaging</head><p>We also considered a recently-developed extension to multivariable MR <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b68">68]</ref> termed "multivariable MR based on Bayesian model averaging" (MR-BMA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref>. MR-BMA, like original multivariable MR, is basically an extension of standard MR to model not one, but multiple, risk factors on an outcome, thus accounting for measured pleiotropy. MR-BMA aims to address the problem of selecting, from many potential causal risk factors, those that are most useful for one outcome variable, using Mendelian randomization principles. The method is based on inverse-variance weighted (IVW) linear regression in a two-sample framework, where the associations between genetic factors and the outcome (tested in sample 1) are regressed on the genetic associations with all the risk factors (tested in sample 2) in a multivariable regression approach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Latent causal variable method</head><p>We also considered the recently-developed latent causal variable (LCV) method <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref> which infers, for pairs of measured traits, the extent to which part or all of the genetic component of one trait is causal for the other. This method makes use of genetic data across the whole genome, rather than following the usual MR approach of selecting specific genetic variants to be used as instruments. The method tests a newly-defined quantity between two traits, the "genetic causality proportion" (GCP), where large (positive or negative) values of GCP imply that interventions on one trait are likely to affect the other, suggesting (without specifically testing) that one trait may itself be causal on the other. Formally, the GCP test performs a twosided test of the null hypothesis that the GCP = 0. The software also produces p-values for "full causality" between the two traits in either direction, testing the null hypothesis that GPC = 1 (implying trait 1 causes trait 2) or that GPC = -1 (implying trait 2 causes trait 1), respectively. The underlying graphical model used to motivate the LCV method actually corresponds to a model in which an (unmeasured) latent variable is the causal variable for both measured traits. One could therefore argue that demonstration of such an effect suggests that it is actually the latent variable that should be intervened upon, rather than one of the traits, if one wishes to bring about a corresponding change in the value of the other trait.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Multi-SNP mediation intersection-union test</head><p>We also applied a recently-proposed multi-SNP mediation intersection-union test known as SMUT <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[48]</ref>. SMUT tests the joint mediation effects of multiple (potentially correlated) genetic variants on a trait through a single mediator, effectively generating a hypothesis test for mediation but with a multivariate genetic exposure. SMUT adopts the classical mediation framework, takes a frequentist approach, and relies on individual level data, treating the mediator effect as fixed and the effects of multiple SNPs upon the mediator as random.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Illustrative example: Fatty acids and BMI</head><p>The data analysed here consisted of 5654 twins with measurements of BMI, the two metabolites EPA and DGLA, and 42 SNPs. For the purposes of the current analysis we used all twins and treated them as independent (i.e. ignoring pairwise clustering due to twin relationships; this will overestimate the statistical significance (nominal p-value) of any observed associations, but we anticipate that this phenomenon should affect all the methods evaluated equally). Three SNPs were used directly as IVs: rs174556 for EPA, and rs968567 and rs6498540 for DGLA. The other 39 SNPs known <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">52]</ref> to be associated with BMI were combined into a weighted allele score variable (i.e. the number of effect alleles for each individual were counted for each the 39 SNPs, and these were summed, weighting by their previously estimated <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">52]</ref> regression coefficient). The EPA and DGLA data were pre-processed using the same approach used by Shin et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[50]</ref>. Specifically, the metabolite values were log transformed, the resulting transformed variables were adjusted for study day using linear regression, and the residuals from the regression were then transformed to the quantiles of a standard normal distribution to produce the final metabolite variables used for analysis. The genetic variables (rs174556, rs968567, rs6498540 and the weighted allele score) were used as instruments in MR to explore causal relationships between the metabolites and BMI. Relationships between all variables were also explored via BN, with the directional constraint that arrows were constrained to come out from (rather than go into) any nodes corresponding to genetic variables.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Simulation study 1</head><p>We also investigated the performance of BN and MR via computer simulations of a quantitative trait. Data were simulated for two continuous variables (X and Y), together with a genetic instrument G (coded as 0, 1, 2, mimicking a SNP) and a continuous instrumental variable Z (mimicking a SNP allele count). Data were simulated for 2500 individuals under three different generating models (shown in Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>), using a variety of values for the regression coefficients (the βs). These models cover a variety of plausible scenarios in terms of potential confounders (C and S). In each case, the direction of causality goes from X to Y.</p><p>For all three simulation models, the following analyses were implemented:</p><p>1. MR(G): Test the relationship X to Y using MR with G used as an IV for X.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">MR(Z):</head><p>Test the relationship Y to X using MR with Z used as an IV for Y. We also performed MR and MR Steiger without accounting for the uncertainty of the predicted values from the first-stage regression (denoted as MR' and St' respectively). As noted above, this provides equivalent inference (identical p-values) to that obtained by simply regressing the outcome variable on the chosen IV.</p><p>For BN, G and Z were constrained to operate as instruments i.e. the direction of the arrows was constrained to come out from (rather than go into) these nodes. For the purpose of network fitting, all variables were treated as continuous, regardless of whether they actually followed a continuous or discrete distribution.</p><p>For MR and MR Steiger, powers and type I errors (based on 1000 simulation replicates) were calculated for different values of β XY (ranging from 0 to 0.5), with α thresholds of 0.01, 0.05 and 0.1 used to define detection of a relationship. For BN, powers and type I errors (based on 1000 simulation replicates) for testing X to Y and Y to X were calculated with β XY equal to either 0 or 0.5, with probability thresholds 0.7, 0.8 and 0.9 used to define detection of a relationship. As a further visualization of the performance of BN for different values of β XY ranging from 0 to 0.5, the estimated probabilities (based on the average bootstrap network) of an edge existing from X to Y and from Y to X were calculated for each of the 1000 simulation replicates, and the distributions plotted as box plots.</p><p>Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves (based on 1000 simulation replicates) for the detection of an edge existing from X to Y were generated by imposing either different α thresholds (for MR and MR Steiger) or different probability thresholds (for BN). As the relevant threshold is relaxed, the chance of a true positive detection of a relationship increases, but so does the chance of a false detection of a relationship. Evaluation of power (a true positive effect from X to Y) was performed by simulating data under models with β XY equal to 0.1, 0.3 and 0.5. Evaluation of type 1 error (a false positive effect from X to Y) was performed by simulating data (a) under a model with no effect (i.e. with β XY equal to 0), and (b) under a model with an effect in the 'wrong' direction (i.e. from Y to X, with β YX equal to 0.1, 0.3 or 0.5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Simulation study 2</head><p>We also investigated the utility of BNs for performing causal inference in a binary trait setting. Discrete binary data was simulated for 5000 individuals using four models considered in recent work by Shih et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[55]</ref>, in the context of quantifying the effects of alcohol consumption and high alanine transaminase levels on hepatocellular carcinoma. We used the same graph (Fig 7 ) and parameter settings (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>) used by Shih et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[55]</ref>. The data simulated consisted of four binary variables: Q, a gene; W, high alcohol; H, high alanine transaminase; and the outcome variable, Y, representing hepatocellular carcinoma. The data were analysed using BN with the constraint that Q has no parent nodes, and then again with the extra constraint that Y has no child nodes. For the purpose of network fitting, all variables were treated as multimomial (binomial), reflecting the fact that they followed a discrete distribution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Simulation study 3</head><p>We also carried out a simulation study involving more complex networks of variables, as considered by Zuber et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref> in their development of the "multivariable MR based on Bayesian model averaging" (MR-BMA) method. We simulated data in a very similar manner to Zuber et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref> and then applied MR-BMA, along with BN, MR, and SMUT. Data was simulated for 1000 individuals, using 1000 replicates (allowing us to determine powers and type I errors using p-value thresholds of 0.1, 0.05 and 0.01, or posterior probability thresholds of 0.7, 0.8 and 0.9, respectively).</p><p>To inform our simulation model, we used the same publicly available summarized data on genetic associations with risk factors derived from a recent metabolite GWAS <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[69]</ref> as used by Zuber et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref>. To avoid selection bias we took the same subset of 150 independent SNPs as Zuber et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref>, that had been found to be associated with any of the three main lipid measurements (LDL-cholesterol, triglycerides or HDL-cholesterol) at a genome-wide level of significance (p-value &lt;5 × 10 -8 ) in an external data set, namely a large meta-analysis by the Global Lipids Genetics Consortium <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[70]</ref>.</p><p>Beta-coefficients and standard errors of genetic associations between the 150 SNPs and the 118 metabolites with available data were extracted from the metabolite GWAS <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[69]</ref>, in order to allow us to retain the empirically observed relationships between SNPs and metabolites. The set of metabolites was reduced by excluding at random one from each pair of metabolites that had a genetic correlation (calculated using the beta-coefficients of the 150 SNPs) stronger than |r| &gt; 0.99. From the resulting 92 metabolites, 12 were chosen at random to be used in our simulation study. Four of the metabolites were chosen to be used in the simulation model as null variables (with no effects on the outcome variable, Y), four were chosen to be used in the simulation model with a direct effect on Y, and the other four were chosen to be used in the simulation model with a reverse effect (from Y to the metabolites).</p><p>The data for the 150 SNPs were simulated using the allele frequencies given in by the Global Lipids Genetics Consortium <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[70]</ref>, assuming Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE). The four metabolites with direct effects on Y were simulated conditional on the simulated data for the 150 SNPs (based on their corresponding beta-coefficients for association with metabolites). Y was then simulated based on these four metabolites and 75 randomly-chosen SNPs (with betacoefficients derived from their relationship with a randomly discarded metabolite, Ile). The metabolites not directly affecting Y were simulated based on the 150 SNPs and (for the 4 metabolites where a reverse effect was present) on Y. Any causal effects between the metabolites and Y, or vice versa, were simulated using a beta-coefficient of value 0.3, and the standard error was set to 1. A further 9775 SNPs with no effects on any other variables were simulated assuming HWE using a minor allele frequency simulated from a uniform distribution between 0.01 and 0.5. This gave a final simulated data set consisting of 10,000 SNPs, 12 metabolites and one outcome variable, Y.</p><p>We performed MR between every individual metabolite and Y, as well as MR in the reverse direction to test if Y has a causal effect on each metabolite. Weighted allele score variables were used as instrumental variables and were re-constructed within each simulation replicate using SNPs passing a p-value threshold of p &lt; 5 × 10 -6 of association with the appropriate metabolite or with Y, using the estimated regression coefficients as weights. The same SNPs were also used as the genetic variants in SMUT (using the R package SMUT <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[48]</ref>), which was also performed between every individual metabolite and Y (or vice versa for reverse causal effects).</p><p>The MR-BMA test was performed using R code written by the MR-BMA authors and was designed to detect which risk factors for an outcome are causal. The test outputs marginal probabilities for each metabolite being causal on the outcome variable; these are the probabilities presented in the results. The SNPs were chosen for the MR-BMA test using a pvalue threshold of p &lt; 5 × 10 -6 for association with any of the metabolites.</p><p>Average Bayesian networks were used to estimate the probabilities of causal effects between the metabolites and Y using the same instrumental variables as used by the MR tests. Bayesian network analyses were initially performed using only 4 variables for every metabolite: the metabolite itself, the outcome Y, and the 2 corresponding allele scores (one for the metabolite and one for Y). Subsequently we considered Bayesian network analyses that used all 12 metabolites, Y, and the 13 relevant allele score variables (for the 12 metabolites and Y) simultaneously. In all analyses, the allele score variables were constrained to operate as individual genetic instruments i.e. to have one and only one edge going from itself to the corresponding instrumented variable (either a metabolite or Y).</p><p>We also applied the LCV method proposed by O'Connor and Price <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref>. The test was evaluated using the R code written by the LCV authors and uses only one metabolite and the outcome variable at any one time, together with all 10,000 SNPs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Quantification of data underlying plots and graphs</head><p>We quantified the data underlying the various plots and graphs resulting from our analyses in S1-S20 Spreadsheets.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig 1. Average Bayesian networks for the TwinsUK data using either (A) all available variables or (B, C, D) a subset of variables, as shown. The red numbers indicate the probability of existence of the edge, and the numbers in brackets indicate the probability of the edge operating in direction shown, given that it exists. The thickness of an edge indicates its strength (probability of existence).</figDesc><graphic coords="7,95.98,78.01,479.96,479.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig 1A) is -33500.99. The average network score when all variables are included and SNPs can have children but the BMI allele score is constrained to have no children (conceptually similar to the model in Fig 1B) is -33528.85. The average network score when all variables are included and the BMI allele score can have children but the SNPs are constrained to have no children (conceptually similar to the model in Fig 1C) is -33546.05. The average network score when all variables are included and SNPs and the BMI allele score are both constrained to have no children (conceptually similar to the model in Fig 1D) is -33573.91. These average BICs illustrate the considerably better fit obtained when all anchor variables are allowed to influence the values of the other variables in the model.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Simulation study 1 MR</head><label>1</label><figDesc>and BN powers and type I errors. We initially used three relatively simple simulation models (Fig 2) to investigate the powers and type I errors of MR, MR Steiger and BN for testing the relationship X to Y (or Y to X), with assumed effect size β XY or β YX = 0.5 (or 0). By definition, MR with G used as an IV for X tests the relationship X to Y (and MR with Z used as an IV for Y tests the relationship Y to X), while MR Steiger chooses the most appropriate instrument (G or Z) to use as an instrument when testing the relationship X to Y (or Y to X). We</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig 2. Simulation models used in simulation study 1 of quantitative trait data. Data were simulated for two continuous variables (X and Y), together with a genetic instrument G (coded as 0, 1, 2) and a continuous instrumental variable Z. Parameter values for models involving weak confounding were chosen as β GX = 0.1, β ZY = 0.075 and β CX = β CY = β GS = β SY = 0.25. For models involving strong confounding, the parameter values were the same except that β CX = β CY = β GS = β SY = 0.5 i.e. the parameters controlling the confounding effects were doubled. The parameter β XY was varied using values of 0.0, 0.1, 0.2, 0.3, 0.4 and 0.5. For the calculations where false positives were counted as detections of an arrow between X and Y in the wrong direction, the direction of causality was reversed between X and Y, such that for model 1 the equations become X � N ðb YX Y þ b GX G; 1Þ and Y � N ðb ZY Z; 1Þ, with β YX varied using values of 0.1, 0.3 and 0.5 (and similarly for models 2 and 3).https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008198.g002</figDesc><graphic coords="9,95.98,398.84,479.96,220.54" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig 3. Performance (power and type I error) of different methods for detecting an edge from X to Y, under different generating scenarios that include weak confounding. MR and St denote MR and MR Steiger respectively, performed using instrumental variable regression which takes into account the uncertainty of the predicted values in the first-stage regression to calculate the MR p-values. MR' and St' denote MR and MR Steiger respectively, performed using two-stage least squares regression without accounting for the uncertainty of the predicted values in the first-stage regression. Left hand plots (A, D, G) are generated under model 1 (no confounding), middle plots (B, E, H) are generated under model 2 (non-genetic confounding), and right hand plots (C, F, I) are generated under model 3 (genetic confounding). https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008198.g003</figDesc><graphic coords="10,95.98,277.23,479.96,351.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig 4. Performance (power and type I error) of different methods for detecting an edge from X to Y, under different generating scenarios that include strong confounding. MR and St denote MR and MR Steiger respectively, performed using instrumental variable regression which takes into account the uncertainty of the predicted values in the first-stage regression to calculate the MR p-values. MR' and St' denote MR and MR Steiger respectively, performed using two-stage least squares regression without accounting for the uncertainty of the predicted values in the first-stage regression. Left hand plots (A, D, G) are generated under model 1 (no confounding), middle plots (B, E, H) are generated under model 2 (non-genetic confounding), and right hand plots (C, F, I) are generated under model 3 (genetic confounding). https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008198.g004</figDesc><graphic coords="11,95.98,78.01,479.96,351.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, panel I), or vice versa (S6 Fig, panel B), when there is weak confounding and G is included as a possible explanatory variable. Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves. Figs 5 and 6 show receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves for MR/MR Steiger and BN for testing the relationship X to Y under simulation models 1-3, with assumed effect size β XY or β YX = 0.5. The results in the middle and right hand plots (models 2 and 3) in Fig 5 involve weak confounding, while those in Fig 6 involve strong confounding.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig 5. ROC curves for different methods for detecting an edge from X to Y, under different generating scenarios that include weak confounding. MR and St denote MR and MR Steiger respectively, performed using instrumental variable regression which takes into account the uncertainty of the predicted values in the first-stage regression to calculate the MR p-values. Left hand plots (A, D) are generated under model 1 (no confounding), middle plots (B, E) are generated under model 2 (non-genetic confounding), and right hand plots (C, F) are generated under model 3 (genetic confounding).For the top plots (panels A-C), false positives on the x-axis are counted using simulations when there is no effect (β XY = 0), while for the bottom plots (panels D-F), the false positive rate is calculated by simulating from a model where there is a causal effect from Y to X.</figDesc><graphic coords="13,95.98,78.01,479.96,356.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig 6. ROC curves for different methods for detecting an edge from X to Y, under different generating scenarios that include strong confounding. MR and St denote MR and MR Steiger respectively, performed using instrumental variable regression which takes into account the uncertainty of the predicted values in the first-stage regression to calculate the MR p-values. Left hand plots (A, D) are generated under model 1 (no confounding), middle plots (B, E) are generated under model 2 (non-genetic confounding), and right hand plots (C, F) are generated under model 3 (genetic confounding).For the top plots (panels A-C), false positives on the x-axis are counted using simulations when there is no effect (β XY = 0), while for the bottom plots (panels D-F), the false positive rate is calculated by simulating from a model where there is a causal effect from Y to X. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008198.g006</figDesc><graphic coords="14,95.98,78.01,479.96,356.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig 9</head><label>9</label><figDesc>shows the average BN for scenarios A-D when the model is fitted with the extra constraint that Y (representing the outcome, hepatocellular carcinoma) has no child nodes. The results are similar to Fig 8 except that panel C now has the edge from W to Y in the correct direction (as implied by the extra constraint)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig 10 ,Fig 7 .</head><label>107</label><figDesc>Fig 7. Graph of the simulation model used for simulation study 2 for four different parameter scenarios as described by Shih et al. [55]. The data simulated consisted of four binary variables: Q, representing a gene; W, representing high alcohol; H, representing high alanine transaminase; and the outcome variable, Y, representing hepatocellular carcinoma. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008198.g007</figDesc><graphic coords="16,134.87,72.00,441.07,390.78" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>simulated to have no effects, 4 metabolites (Fig 10, middle panels) simulated to have a causal effect on the outcome Y, and 4 metabolites (Fig 10, right hand panels) with a reverse effect (so that Y influenced the metabolite). We applied the recently proposed SMUT [48] method, along with BN, MR and a recent MR extension (MR-BMA) [25]. Fig 10 shows the powers and type I errors of MR, SMUT, BN using one metabolite risk factor (B1), BN using all 12 metabolite risk factors (B12) and MR-BMA, for testing the relationship between each metabolite and Y. MR, SMUT and B1 tested the relationship between each metabolite and Y separately (ignoring any information from other metabolites), whereas</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig 8. Average Bayesian networks for each of the four scenarios (A-D) used for the simulated binary data. The red numbers indicate the probability of existence of an edge, and the numbers in brackets indicate the probability of the edge operating in direction shown, given that it exists. The thickness of the edges indicates their strength (probability of existence). G is constrained to have no parents. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008198.g008</figDesc><graphic coords="17,95.98,74.55,479.96,469.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig 9. Average Bayesian networks for each of the four scenarios (A-D) used for the simulated binary data. The red numbers indicate the probability of existence of an edge, and the numbers in brackets indicate the probability of the edge operating in direction shown, given that it exists. The thickness of the edges indicates their strength (probability of existence). G is constrained to have no parents and Y is constrained to have no children. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008198.g009</figDesc><graphic coords="18,95.98,78.01,479.96,469.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Fig 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig 10. Performance (power and type I error) of different methods under a simulation model with 12 metabolites, an outcome Y, 150 SNPs affecting the metabolites, 75 other SNPs affecting Y, and 9775 SNPs with no effect. Four metabolites (middle panels) have a causal effect on Y, four metabolites (right hand panels) have a reverse causal effect from Y to the metabolite, and four metabolites (left hand panels) have no effects to Y in any direction. The left-to-right arrows show tests for a causal effect from the metabolite to Y, and right-to-left arrows show tests from Y to one of the metabolites. MR: Mendelian randomization using an allele score as an instrumental variable for one of the metabolites or Y. S: SMUT, using SNPs as random effect variables for one of the metabolites or Y. B1: Bayesian network consisting of one metabolite, Y and the two corresponding allele score variables. B12: Bayesian network consisting of all 12 metabolites, Y and all corresponding allele score variables. BMA: multivariable MR based on Bayesian model averaging (MR-BMA). https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008198.g010</figDesc><graphic coords="19,95.98,73.99,479.96,356.26" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>St(G): Test the relationship X to Y (or Y to X) using MR Steiger with G used as an IV for X (or Y).4. St(Z):Test the relationship X to Y (or Y to X) using MR Steiger with Z used as an IV for X (or Y).5. BN(G,Z): Perform BN with variables X, Y, G and Z.6. BN(G): Perform BN with variables X, Y, G only.7. BN(Z): Perform BN with variables X, Y, Z only.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>factor Outcome Instrument-risk factor p-value(s) MR p-value</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>rs174556</cell><cell>EPA</cell><cell>BMI</cell><cell>3.18 × 10 -16</cell><cell>0.0498</cell></row><row><cell>BMI Allele Score</cell><cell>BMI</cell><cell>EPA</cell><cell>1.74 × 10 -15</cell><cell>0.6668</cell></row><row><cell>rs968567, rs6498540</cell><cell>DGLA</cell><cell>BMI</cell><cell>0.00127, 0.00337</cell><cell>0.0327</cell></row><row><cell>BMI Allele Score</cell><cell>BMI</cell><cell>DGLA</cell><cell>1.74 × 10 -15</cell><cell>0.7082</cell></row><row><cell>rs174556</cell><cell>EPA</cell><cell>DGLA</cell><cell>6.93 × 10 -20</cell><cell>0.0425</cell></row><row><cell>rs968567, rs6498540</cell><cell>DGLA</cell><cell>EPA</cell><cell>0.0120, 0.0263</cell><cell>0.0320</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008198.t001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>). .94 × 0.80 and 0.76 = 0.99 × 0.77. However, when all instruments are removed (i.e. only variables DGLA, EPA and BMI are included in the analysis)(Fig 1D)</figDesc><table><row><cell>and the BMI score variables could only go in one direction (outwards from the variable</cell></row><row><cell>towards a child node), consistent with the notion of these variables acting as genetic instru-</cell></row><row><cell>ments or anchor variables. The average network shows strong evidence (overall probabilities</cell></row><row><cell>of 0.89 = 0.96 × 0.93, and 0.86 = 0.99 × 0.87, respectively) of DGLA and EPA being causal on</cell></row><row><cell>BMI. With the removal of the BMI score variable (Fig 1B), the probabilities are slightly</cell></row><row><cell>decreased to 0.82 = 0.93 × 0.88 and 0.76 = 0.98 × 0.78, still supporting the direction of relation-</cell></row><row><cell>ships between the metabolites and BMI when one instrument (the BMI score) is removed.</cell></row><row><cell>Similarly, when only the BMI score anchor variable is present (Fig 1C), the relationships</cell></row><row><cell>between the metabolites and BMI are still supported, although with reduced probabilities of</cell></row><row><cell>0.75 = 0</cell></row><row><cell>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008198.g001</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 . Performance of MR, MR Steiger and BN on the simulated quantitative trait data. Underlying true scenario</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Method</cell><cell>Assumptions Met</cell><cell>Non-Genetic-Confounding</cell><cell>Genetic-Confounding</cell></row><row><cell>MR</cell><cell>OK</cell><cell>OK</cell><cell>Very poor, huge type I error</cell></row><row><cell>MR Steiger</cell><cell>Low power</cell><cell>Low power</cell><cell>Poor, bad ROC curves</cell></row><row><cell>BN</cell><cell>Excellent ROC curves</cell><cell>OK, but possible inflated type I error for no effect</cell><cell>Possible inflated type I error for reverse effect</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008198.t002</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>PLOS Genetics | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008198 March 2, 2020</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>PLOS Genetics | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1008198 2, 2020</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>We thank <rs type="person">Chin Yang Shapland</rs> for pointing out some errors in, and <rs type="person">Vanessa Didelez</rs> for providing useful comments on, previous versions of this paper. We thank <rs type="institution">TwinsUK</rs> for granting us access to their data.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><p>RH and HJC are supported by the <rs type="funder">Wellcome Trust</rs> (grant number <rs type="grantNumber">102858/Z/13/Z</rs>). SYS was supported by a <rs type="grantName">Post-Doctoral Research Fellowship</rs> from the <rs type="funder">Oak Foundation</rs>. CR and GDS work in the <rs type="projectName">Medical Research Council Integrative causal relationships in complex data sets such as those generated from modern</rs> "omics" technologies.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_9QTJxVN">
					<idno type="grant-number">102858/Z/13/Z</idno>
					<orgName type="grant-name">Post-Doctoral Research Fellowship</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_7hVMNWC">
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Medical Research Council Integrative causal relationships in complex data sets such as those generated from modern</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The data underlying the results presented in the study are available from TwinsUK <ref type="url" target="http://twinsuk.ac.uk/resources-forresearchers/access-our-data/">http://twinsuk.ac.uk/resources-forresearchers/access-our-data/</ref>.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supporting information</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epidemiology-is it time to call it a day?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ebrahim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ije/30.1.1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/30.1.1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new approach to causal inference in mortality studies with a sustained exposure periodapplication to control of the healthy worker survivor effect</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0270-0255(86)90088-6</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/0270-0255(86)90088-6" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mathematical Modelling</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1393" to="1512" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation of the causal effects of time-varying exposures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Herna ´n Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Longitudinal Data Analysis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Chapman &amp; Hall/CRC Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="553" to="599" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mendelian randomization&apos;: can genetic epidemiology contribute to understanding environmental determinants of disease?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ebrahim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ije/dyg070</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyg070" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Randomization: New Applications in the Coming Age of Hypothesis-Free Causality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mendelian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev-genom-090314-050016</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-genom-090314-050016PMID" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu Rev Genomics Hum Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25939054</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is Mendelian randomization &apos;lost in translation?&apos;: Comments on &apos;Mendelian randomization equals instrumental variable analysis with genetic instruments&apos; by Wehby et al</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lawlor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Windmeijer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/sim.3308</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">18509868</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/sim.3308" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistics in Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2750" to="2755" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mendelian randomization as an instrumental variable approach to causal inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Didelez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sheehan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0962280206077743</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">17715159</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0962280206077743" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat Methods Med Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="330" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reading Mendelian randomisation studies: a guide, glossary, and checklist for clinicians</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Holmes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">362</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Plasma HDL cholesterol and risk of myocardial infarction: a mendelian randomisation study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Voight</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Peloso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Orho-Melander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Frikke-</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barbalic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60312-2</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">22607825</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60312-2" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">380</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="572" to="580" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of the relationship between plasma lipids and abdominal aortic aneurysm: A Mendelian randomization study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Weng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Roetker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lutsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alonso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Pankow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0195719</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">29649275</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0195719" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">195719</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA Methylation and BMI: Investigating Identified Methylation Sites at HIF3A in a Causal Framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Richmond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sharp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fraser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Lyttleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mcardle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2337/db15-0996</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">26861784</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2337/db15-0996" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabetes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1231" to="1244" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic Mendelian randomization framework elucidates hundreds of CpG sites which may mediate the influence of genetic variants on disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Haycock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Timpson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Gaunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/hmg/ddy210</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">29893838</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/hmg/ddy" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum Molec Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3293" to="3304" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide mapping of plasma protein QTLs identifies putatively causal genes and pathways for cardiovascular disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Keefe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mendelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Huan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41467-018-05512-x</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">30111768</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-018-05512-x" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3268</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mendelian randomization analysis with multiple genetic variants using summarized data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Burgess</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Butterworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/gepi.21758</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">24114802</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/gepi.21758" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="658" to="665" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mendelian randomization: genetic anchors for causal inference in epidemiological studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hemani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/hmg/ddu328</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">25064373</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/hmg/ddu328" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum Molec Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="R89" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">EPIC-InterAct Consortium. Using published data in Mendelian randomization: a blueprint for efficient identification of causal risk factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Burgess</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Timpson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10654-015-0011-z</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">25773750</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10654-015-0011-z" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="543" to="552" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two-sample Mendelian randomization: avoiding the downsides of a powerful, widely applicable but potentially fallible technique</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hartwig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hemani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ije/dyx028</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">28338968</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyx028" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1717" to="1726" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two-step epigenetic Mendelian randomization: a strategy for establishing the causal role of epigenetic processes in pathways to disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Relton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ije/dyr233</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">22422451</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyr233" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="176" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mendelian randomization with invalid instruments: effect estimation and bias detection through Egger regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bowden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ije/dyv080</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">26050253</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyv080" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="512" to="525" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multivariable Mendelian randomization: the use of pleiotropic genetic variants to estimate causal effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Burgess</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/aje/kwu283</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">25632051</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/aje/kwu283" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">181</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="260" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EPIC-InterAct Consortium. Network Mendelian randomization: using genetic variants as instrumental variables to investigate mediation in causal pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Burgess</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Daniel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Butterworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ije/dyu176</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">25150977</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyu176" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="484" to="495" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A framework for the investigation of pleiotropy in two-sample summary data Mendelian randomization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bowden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Del</forename><surname>Greco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Minelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sheehan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/sim.7221</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">28114746</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/sim.7221" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistics in Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1783" to="1802" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting individual and global horizontal pleiotropy in Mendelian randomization: a job for the humble heterogeneity statistic?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bowden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hemani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/aje/kwy185</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">30188969</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/aje/kwy185" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">187</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2681" to="2685" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of widespread horizontal pleiotropy in causal relationships inferred from Mendelian randomization between complex traits and diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Verbanck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Neale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Do</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41588-018-0099-7</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">29686387</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-018-0099-7" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="693" to="698" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selecting causal risk factors from high-throughput experiments using multivariable Mendelian randomization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Zuber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Colijn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Klaver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Burgess</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1101/396333</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1101/396333" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">bioRxiv</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mendelian randomization integrating GWAS and eQTL data reveals genetic determinants of complex and clinical traits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Porcu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ru ¨eger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lepik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Consortium</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bios Consortium</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Santoni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41467-019-10936-0</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-019-10936-0PMID" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31341166</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">C-reactive protein levels and body mass index: elucidating direction of causation through reciprocal Mendelian randomization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Timpson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Nordestgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Harbord</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zacho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Frayling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tybjaerg-Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/ijo.2010.137</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/ijo.2010.137" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Obes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="300" to="308" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Orienting the causal relationship between imprecisely measured traits using GWAS summary data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hemani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tilling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pgen.1007081</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">29149188</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1007081" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLOS Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1007081</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distinguishing genetic correlation from causation across 52 diseases and complex traits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>O'connor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1726" to="1734" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian networks: A model of self-activated memory for evidential reasoning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings, Cognitive Science Society</title>
		<meeting>Cognitive Science Society<address><addrLine>Irvine, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="329" to="334" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Probabilistic Reasoning in Intelligent Systems: Networks of Plausible Inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduction to Causal Inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Spirtes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Machine Learning Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1643" to="1662" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Causation, prediction, and search</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Spirtes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Glymour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Scheines</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Causality: models, reasoning, and inference, 2nd Ed</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computation and causation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Scheines</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1467-9973.00223</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/1467-9973.00223" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Metaphilosophy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="158" to="180" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabilistic Computational Causal Discovery for Systems Biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Lagani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Triantafillou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ball</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tegne ´r</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Tsamardinos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Uncertainty in Biology: A Computational Modeling Approach. Studies in Mechanobiology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Geris</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gomez-Cabrero</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Switzerland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer International Publishing</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="73" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Bayesian Networks in R</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nagarajan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Scutari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Le ´bre S</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating the potential role of pleiotropy in Mendelian randomization studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hemani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bowden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/hmg/ddy163</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">29771313</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/hmg/ddy163" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum Molec Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="R208" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian Networks with Examples in R</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Scutari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Denis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Texts in Statistical Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Chapman &amp; Hall/CRC ( US</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-Sample Learning of Bayesian Networks is NP-Hard</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chickering</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Heckerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Meek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Machine Learning Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1287" to="1330" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting the potential cancer association or metastasis by multiomics data analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Xia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4238/gmr.15038987</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4238/gmr.15038987" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetic Molecular Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Untangling the role of one-carbon metabolism in colorectal cancer risk: a comprehensive Bayesian network analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Myte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gylling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ha ¨ggstro ¨m</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schneede</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Magne</forename><surname>Ueland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hallmans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/srep43434</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">28233834</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/srep43434" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">43434</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrative genomics approach to the reconstruction of gene networks in segregating populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Lum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lamb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Guhathakurta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Thieringer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1159/000078209</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">15237224</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1159/000078209" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cytogenetic and Genome Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2-4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="363" to="374" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stitching together multiple data dimensions reveals interacting metabolomic and transcriptomic networks that modulate cell regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dombek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Vu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001301</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">22509135</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001301" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1001301</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generating a robust statistical causal structure over 13 cardiovascular disease risk factors using genomics data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Yazdani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Yazdani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Samiei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Boerwinkle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jbi.2016.01.012</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">26827624</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbi.2016.01.012" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Biomedical Informatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="114" to="119" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mixed Graphical Models for Integrative Causal Analysis with Application to Chronic Lung Disease Diagnosis and Prognosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sedgewick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Buschur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ramsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Raghu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Manatakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bty769</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">30192904</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bty769" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1204" to="1212" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning Causal Biological Networks With the Principle of Mendelian Randomization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Badsha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fgene.2019.00460</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">31164902</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3389/fgene.2019.00460" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">460</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-SNP mediation intersection-union test</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Spracklen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mohlke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btz285</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">31099385</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btz285" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4724" to="4729" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cohort Profile: TwinsUK and healthy ageing twin study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Moayyeri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hammond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Valdes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Spector</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ije/dyr207</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">22253318</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyr207" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An atlas of genetic influences on human blood metabolites</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Fauman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Krumsiek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/ng.2982</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/ng.2982" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="543" to="550" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Association analyses of 249,796 individuals reveal eighteen new loci associated with body mass index</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Speliotes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/ng.686</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">20935630</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/ng.686" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="937" to="948" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A meta-analysis identifies new loci associated with body mass index in individuals of African ancestry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Monda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/ng.2608</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">23583978</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/ng.2608" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="690" to="696" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">deal: A Package for Learning Bayesian Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Boettcher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dethlefsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Statistical Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">20</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The ASA&apos;s Statement on p-Values: Context, Process, and Purpose</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Wasserstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lazar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/00031305.2016.1154108</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/00031305.2016.1154108" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American Statistician</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A multiple mediator analysis approach to quantify the effects of the ADH1B and ALDH2 genes on hepatocellular carcinoma risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shih</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/gepi.22120</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">29600553</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/gepi.22120" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetic Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="394" to="404" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">MR-TRYX: A Mendelian randomization framework that exploits horizontal pleiotropy to infer novel causal pathways. bioRxiv</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Haycock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sanderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Gaunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Apmg</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1101/476085</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1101/476085" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical tests, P values, confidence intervals, and power: a guide to misinterpretations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Greenland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Senn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rothman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Carlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Poole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Goodman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10654-016-0149-3</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">27209009</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10654-016-0149-3" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="350" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Five years of GWAS discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Visscher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Mccarthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ajhg.2011.11.029</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">22243964</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajhg.2011.11.029" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Hum Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Within-family studies for Mendelian randomization: avoiding dynastic, assortative mating, and population stratification biases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Brumpton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sanderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pires</forename><surname>Hartwig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Åberge</forename><surname>Vie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1101/602516</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/602516" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">bioRxiv</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison of methods for inferring causal relationships between genotype and phenotype using additional biological measurements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Ainsworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cordell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/gepi.22061</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">28691305</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/gepi.22061" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="577" to="586" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The UK Biobank resource with deep phenotyping and genomic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bycroft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Freeman</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Petkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Band</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Elliott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L T</forename><surname>Sharp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Motyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vukcevic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Delaneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O'</forename><surname>Connell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cortes</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Welsh</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Young</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Effingham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mcvean</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Leslie</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Allen</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Donnelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Marchini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41586-018-0579-z</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">30305743</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-018-0579" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">562</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="209" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Triangulation in aetiological epidemiology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lawlor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tilling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ije/dyw314</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">28108528</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyw314" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1866" to="1886" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust research needs many lines of evidence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Munafò</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/d41586-018-01023-3</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-018-01023-3" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">553</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="399" to="401" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A review of instrumental variable estimators for Mendelian randomization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Burgess</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Small</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0962280215597579</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">26282889</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0962280215597579" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat Methods Med Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2333" to="2355" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Applied Econometrics with R</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kleiber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zeileis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=AER" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Howey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bayesnetty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.staff.ncl.ac.uk/richard.howey/bayesnetty/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The igraph software package for complex network research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Csardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nepusz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">InterJournal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">1695</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<pubPlace>Complex Systems</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An examination of multivariable Mendelian randomization in the single-sample and two-sample summary data settings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sanderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Davey</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Windmeijer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bowden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ije/dyy262</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyy262" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide study for circulating metabolites identifies 62 loci and reveals novel systemic effects of LPA</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kettunen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Demirkan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wu ¨rtz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Draisma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Haller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rawal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/ncomms11122</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">27005778</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms11122" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11122</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Common variants associated with plasma triglycerides and risk for coronary artery disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Do</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Willer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sengupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Peloso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/ng.2795</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">24097064</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/ng.2795" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1345" to="1352" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
