<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The author have declared that no financial relationships with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work; nor any other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Aldo</forename><surname>Alvarez-Risco</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Modelo de Ecua- ciones Estructurales usando de Mínimos Cuadrados Parciales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Barreras para la implementación de la Cosmetovigilancia en Perú</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Modelo de Ecua- ciones Estructurales usando de Mínimos Cuadrados Parciales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Barreras para la implementación de la Cosmetovigilancia en Perú</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Modelo de Ecua- ciones Estructurales usando de Mínimos Cuadrados Parciales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Barreras para la implementación de la Cosmetovigilancia en Perú</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Av</forename><surname>Las Calandrias</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Modelo de Ecua- ciones Estructurales usando de Mínimos Cuadrados Parciales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Barreras para la implementación de la Cosmetovigilancia en Perú</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Perú</roleName><forename type="first">Santa</forename><forename type="middle">Anita</forename><surname>Lima</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Modelo de Ecua- ciones Estructurales usando de Mínimos Cuadrados Parciales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Barreras para la implementación de la Cosmetovigilancia en Perú</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Shyla</forename><surname>Del-Aguila-Arcentales</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Modelo de Ecua- ciones Estructurales usando de Mínimos Cuadrados Parciales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Barreras para la implementación de la Cosmetovigilancia en Perú</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Modelo de Ecua- ciones Estructurales usando de Mínimos Cuadrados Parciales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Barreras para la implementación de la Cosmetovigilancia en Perú</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Santiago</forename><surname>Diaz-Risco</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Modelo de Ecua- ciones Estructurales usando de Mínimos Cuadrados Parciales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Barreras para la implementación de la Cosmetovigilancia en Perú</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Modelo de Ecua- ciones Estructurales usando de Mínimos Cuadrados Parciales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Barreras para la implementación de la Cosmetovigilancia en Perú</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The author have declared that no financial relationships with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work; nor any other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.30827/ars.v59i1.7275</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 08.01.2018 Accepted: 05.03.2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T19:52+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Cosmetovigilance</term>
					<term>Peru</term>
					<term>adverse cosmetic events RESUMEN Cosmetovigilancia</term>
					<term>Perú</term>
					<term>eventos adversos por cosméticos</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Aim: This paper examines the barriers in Peruvian community pharmacies for cosmetovigilance practice.</p><p>Methods: It was obtained information from the pharmacists of 81 community pharmacies in 2 districts in Lima, Peru. For reliability´s evaluation, it was used SPSS software V.24. The validity of construct, discriminant validity and, internal consistency by the composite reliability was analyzed with structural equation modelling using partial least square using SmartPLS 3 software.</p><p>Results: 81 questionnaires self-administered anonymous were completed (response rate = 51.9%). Average of years of working in community pharmacies was more than 6.36 years (SD: 4.63). More than 70% of the participating pharmacists chose the «strongly agree» and «agree» alternative for items about barriers that included: Lack of time, National health system structure in general and My interest to report adverse reaction by cosmetics. About daily activities, more than 70% of the participants chose the «strongly agree» and «agree» alternative for items that included «Rarely I explain to users about adverse reaction with cosmetics use» and «Rarely I have material to inform to users about adverse reaction with cosmetics use».</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>The need for regulation of the safety of cosmetic products should be the primary goal. The possibility that these safety issues are recognized makes it a global problem; although these cases are not as common as other types of products such as food, pharmaceuticals or medical devices, there is a need to investigate the mechanisms of implementation of cosmetovigilance system in order to ensure that the cosmetics used by consumers are safe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>What is the Peruvian legislation on cosmetics?</head><p>The Law N° 26842 -Health General Law 1 states that in Titles I, II and II as follows: Also, the certifications of Good Pharmacy Practice for community pharmacies express as mandatory the dispensing process for pharmaceuticals products, medical devices and health products (cosmetics are included). Also, it is mandatory as well comply with Good Pharmacovigilance Practice, which implies the reporting of adverse reactions.</p><p>On an international level, there are Andean regulations that facilitate the entry of cosmetic products among its member countries (Bolivia, Colombia, Ecuador, Peru and Venezuela). These rules are governed by the following basic namics, expecting that cosmetic category one of the more impact <ref type="bibr">3</ref> expected, even for the attempt to negotiate as a block with Asian countries <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">4</ref> . In this way, Peru needs to ensure safety of new cosmetics which will arrive to Peruvian market.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Aim of the study</head><p>Determinate what the barriers in Peruvian community pharmacies for cosmetovigilance practice are?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research model</head><p>For the current study, it was designed a research model to be evaluated. Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> shows the research model. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>According the research model, it is proposed the following set</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Questionnaire development</head><p>For the current study, it was built a questionnaire ad hoc.</p><p>The instrument comprised two sections. The first section captured demographic information as sex, age, education level, year of experience and their position in the pharmacy. The second part included a 5-point Likert scale, where 1=strongly agree and 5=strongly disagree. It was tested 16 items, distributed in 4 dimensions: resources, interest, regulation and pharmacist practice. The evaluation the reliability, it was used SPSS software V.24, and it was calculated the Cronbach's of 20 completed questionnaires because for internal consistency reliability, the composite reliability is considered adequate when an item o dimension has a factor loading greater than 0.707 as expressed by Carmines &amp; Zeller <ref type="bibr">5.</ref> Cronbach's values of each dimension were 0.711, 0.800, 0.709 and 0.865, so it did not need changes in items of questionnaire.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Validation with SEM PLS</head><p>Using Partial Least Squares Structural Equation Modeling (PLS-SEM) was analyzed the validity of construct and discriminant and, internal consistency by the composite reliability. SmartPLS statistical package <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">6</ref>  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head><p>Out of 81 questionnaires of distributed in 2 districts in Lima were fulfilled (response rate = 51.9%). Regarding the pharmacists who answered the survey, 72.83% were women.</p><p>The average age was 35.72 years (SD: 5.68). Average of years of working in community pharmacies was more than 6.36 years (SD: 4.63). Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> presents the analysis of factor including the Cronbach's for each variable. Cronbach's values were more than 0.707, which is considered statistically acceptable.</p><p>More than 70% of the participants chose the «strongly agree» and «agree» alternative for items about barriers that included:  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Evaluation of hypotheses</head><p>Considering the relation showed in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">2</ref>, we evaluated the hypotheses proposed.   </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>I.</head><label></label><figDesc>Health is a prerequisite for human development and critical to achieving individual and collective welfare environment. II. The protection of health is of public interest. It is therefore the responsibility of the State to regulate, monitor it and promote it. III. Everyone has the right to health protection under the terms and conditions established by law. Additionally, the Law N° 29459 -Law of Pharmaceutical Products, Medical Devices and Health Products establishes the requirements to apply for the Health Authorization. For pharmaceutical products in Peru there is a national pharmacovigilance system that allows health professionals to report adverse reactions. Also, Peruvian Regulatory Agency (DIGEMID) receives reports of adverse reactions by use of medical devices. The Law N° 29459 has two specific regulations: Regulation of Pharmaceutical Facilities (Norm N° 014) and Regulation for registration, control and surveillance of Pharmaceutical Products, Medical Devices and Health Products (Norm N° 016). Although these documents have been approved, the specific guidelines to regulate and support in detail the access and use of pharmaceutical products, medical devices and health products are approved yet, which should have been approved in 2012.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>platform among Member Countries of the Andean Community, to ensure that the right to trade in the products falling within its scope is exercised in a fair and transparent manner; b. Balance between safeguarding public health and the free movement of products in the Andean sub region; c. Compulsory Sanitary Notification and recognition as market access mechanism, instead of Sanitary Registration; d. subsequent control, which allows effectively verify the sanitary quality of the products on the market; and simplification of administrative procedures to facilitate free trade in products between Member Countries of the Andean Community, without undermining the health quality of them. These actions are part of different documents like the Declaration of Cartagena 2014 Business Council 2 . It is expected that the Pacific Alliance generates more commercial dy-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 1. Research model</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>was used to calculate the factorial structure of the indicators, using Partial Least Squares. SEM-PLS aims to predict the latent variables by estimating Partial Least Squares (PLS) and Principal Component Analysis (PCA). The main advantage of PLS is the greatest strength calculations to smaller samples and breach of statistical assumptions of the variables (non-normal distribution, different levels of measurement, multicollinearity, among others). In a PLS model, the individual reliability of the indicators is assessed by examining the load between each indicator and dimension, accepting as reliable those above 0.40 loads for exploratory studies 7 . Informed consent was obtained from each participant of current study, following in accordance with The Code of Ethics of the World Medical Association.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>a. Lack of time b. National health system structure in general c. My interest to report adverse by cosmetics Also, about daily activities, more than 70% of the participants chose the «strongly agree» and «agree» alternative for items that included: a. Rarely I explain to patients/customers about adverse reaction with cosmetics use b. Rarely I have material to inform to customers about adverse reaction with cosmetics use Ars Pharm. 2018; 59(1): 21-26 Shyla Del-Aguila-Arcentales, Aldo Alvarez-Risco, Santiago Diaz-Risco</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Research model tested</figDesc><graphic coords="4,71.24,570.05,204.77,143.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Finally, pharmacists reported</head><label></label><figDesc>that they rarely develop activities focus in cosmetovigilance practice to get information from customers about adverse cosmetic reaction. Daily activities of community pharmacists show the impact of current barriers to not allow the implementation of cosmetovigilance.CONCLUSIONCosmetics legislation does not include any element which is required cosmetovigilance since trade agreements with other economic blocks will Peruvian citizens at greater risk in using different products. The absence of specific legislation is a major constraint but also it is the lack of professionals with experience in this kind of specific regulation for cosmetics. The virtualized start notifications will ensure a systematization of notifications, having to take into account different means according to the ages and behavioral preferences of citizens. The pharmacist's views expressed barriers as resources, interests and regulation. Also, they expressed that their daily activities are not focus in reports of customers of adverse cosmetic events. The need the cosmetovigilance is issue of public health to take responsibility for care customers against cosmetic. The implementation of cosmetovigilance, regardless of the institution responsible for the regulation of cosmetics, is an urgent task. Consumers need it.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 . Analysis of factors</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Items</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Barriers for implementation of cosmetovigilance in Peru: Structural Equation Modeling Using Partial Least Square Resource barriers have a positive influence over Cosmetovigilance Practice observing that the path coefficient is 0.421 for the Resources endogenous latent variable. Also, data shows that the Resources barriers explain 17.7% of the variance in Cosmetovigilance Practice.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>guidelines can be developed to be used in daily activities</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>in community pharmacies but again, this kind of docu-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ment is not available yet. Cosmetics Europe Guidelines on</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>the Management of Undesirable Effects and Reporting of</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Serious Undesirable Effects from Cosmetics in the Euro-</cell></row><row><cell>The composite reliability for each latent variable was:</cell><cell>pean Union 9 can be used as a guide for implementation of cosmetovigilance in practice as previously have described</cell></row><row><cell>Resources: 0.707 Interest: 0.862</cell><cell>by Zakaria 10 about Malaysia health system. Also, other au-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>thors have reported need of cosmetovigilance as Udupa y</cell></row><row><cell>Regulation: 0.815 Cosmetovigilance Practice: 0.909</cell><cell>Ligade 11 in India.</cell></row><row><cell>DISCUSSION</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>About resources, lack of time is usually a problem for care</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>patients in community pharmacies which perform activi-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ties focus basically in sells products instead of care patients.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Also, many customers arrive to community pharmacies so</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>it is not feasible can take time with one of them and have</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>the rest of customers waiting while pharmacists explain</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>about use or safety issue.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Specific space in pharmacies is an expected barrier because</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>customers need a private area to talk about their personal</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>problems with use of cosmetics which can be light prob-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>lems until serious events. Knowledge about cosmetic is es-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>sential to recognize adverse events with use of cosmetics</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>by consumers but there are not available specific education</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>in universities undergraduate programs for detect adverse</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>events by cosmetics which explain low level of training in</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>community pharmacists about this issue.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>An important item reported was «my interest to report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>adverse events by cosmetics». This item can show a deep</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>problem because the pharmacists express their lack of in-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>terest about report adverse events. It is can be explained by</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>lack of previous models, lack of training previous and lack</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>of safety goals in community pharmacies.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Managers and owners of community pharmacies, mostly</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>no pharmacists, cannot find any benefits of get and report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>adverse events by cosmetics to regulatory agency. Com-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>mercial focus of this group explain lack of interest; also,</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>pharmacists express that the customers are not interest;</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>however, Di Giovanni et al. 8 showed that consumers re-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ported adverse cosmetic events whereby future studies are</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>need to know perspectives of customers. Both regulators</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>and third parties don't have cosmetovigilance as a tool to</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>improve safety in patients and even reduce costs of health</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>due to damage of patients.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Regulation is the main gap of lack of cosmetovigilance</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>practice. As it was explained above, the elaboration and</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>publication of norms that promote the cosmetovigilance in</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Peru are pending. Also, independent of national regulation,</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Facultad de Ciencias Administrativas y Recursos Humanos</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Lima, Perú</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint/>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Universidad de San Martin de Porres</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">REFERENCES 1. Ministry of Health. General Law in Health</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.30827/ars.v59i1.7275</idno>
		<idno>22/11/2017</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.digemid.minsa.gob.pe/UpLoad/UpLoaded/PDF/LEYN26842" />
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Centro de Fertilidad de Cajamarca</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Lima, Perú</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Declaración del Consejo Empresarial Cartagena</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alianza</forename><surname>Pacífico</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://alianzapacifico.net/docu-ments/2014/DECLARACION_V_SESION_CEAP_100214.pdf12/02/2014Accessed22/12/2017" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Cartagena Declaration of the Business Council</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Opportunities trade agreement the Pacific Alliance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gestion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Pe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://gestion.pe/economia/oportunidades-acuerdo-comercial-alianza-pacifico-2088582Accessed30/12/2017" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Las oportunidades del acuerdo comercial de la Alianza del Pacífico</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ars Pharm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shyla</forename><surname>Del-Aguila-Arcentales</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aldo</forename><surname>Alvarez-Risco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>Santiago Diaz-Risco</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pacific Alliance: to conquer Asia</title>
		<idno>18/12/2017</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.americaeconomia.com/economia-mer-cados/comercio/alianza-del-pacifico-la-conquista-de-asia?utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+america-economia+" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Alianza del Pacífico: a la conquista de Asia</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Am%C3%A9rica+ Econom%C3%ADa</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Reliability and Validity Assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Carmines</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Zeller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
			<publisher>SAGE Publications</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Beverly Hills, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ringle Cm Wende</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Smartpls</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Boenningstedt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Germany</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>SmartPLS GmbH</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use of partial least squares (PLS) in strategic management research: a review of four recent studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hulland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Strategic Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="204" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cosmetovigilance survey: are cosmetics considered safe by consumers?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Di</forename><surname>Giovanni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Arcoraci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Gambardella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmac Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cosmetics Europe Guidelines on the Management of Undesirable Effects and Reporting of Serious Undesirable Effects from Cosmetics in the European Union</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Renner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cosmetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulation of Cosmetics: What has Malaysia Learnt from the European System?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zakaria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10603-014-9271-3</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10603-014-9271-3" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Consumer Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Need of Cosmetovigilance in India. Value in Health</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Udupa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ligade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">836</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
