<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Environment and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance in State Elementary Schools in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru City</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Amir</forename><surname>Syarifudin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master in Educational Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ahmad</forename><surname>Suriansyah</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master in Educational Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Ngadimun</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master in Educational Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Environment and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance in State Elementary Schools in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru City</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-34</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T21:27+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>instructional leadership</term>
					<term>work environment</term>
					<term>satisfaction</term>
					<term>teacher performance</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The objective of this study is to describe and analyze the direct and indirect relationship between the variables of the principal's instructional ability, work environment, job satisfaction, teacher performance. This research study employed a quantitative with correlational technique that is revealing causality among variables. The research population was 147 teachers from 15 state elementary schools in Cempaka District. The research sample was 108 people who were selected by proportional random sampling. Data collection using instrument were consisted of instructional ability (35 items), work environment (35 items), job satisfaction (35 items) and teacher performance (48 items). The research instrument has been tested for validity and reliability by using path analysis. The results showed that instructional ability had a direct influence on teacher performance, work environment had a direct influence on teacher performance, job satisfaction had a direct influence on teacher performance, instructional ability had a direct influence on the work environment, job satisfaction had a direct influence on the work environment, instructional ability has an indirect effect on teacher performance through the work environment and job satisfaction has an indirect effect on teacher performance through job satisfaction.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Teachers are the most influential component in the quality of educational processes and outcomes. Therefore, any improvement efforts made to improve the quality of education will not make a significant contribution without the support of professional and qualified teachers. Teachers who have high performance are highly needed. With high performance, the level of human resources in Indonesia will begin to gradually improve, especially the younger generation of Indonesia. As a result, a nation that is intelligent and capable of facing future challenges is created. The teachers have hard task and responsibility. In addition, they must make students smarter by honing Intelligence Quetion. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Andhika &amp; Kartomo (2016)</ref> stated that teacher performance is everything that affects how much they contribute to the organization. This opinion reveals that the more teachers contribute to education, the better the performance of the teacher. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Supardi (2013)</ref> suggests that the teacher's performance is said to be successful if it has an effect on the development of students' potential in a psychological and physical context, which is positive for what they learned, both in terms of purpose and benefits; as a result, cognitive, affective and psychomotor intelligence develop. The point is whether there is a change in behavior, systematically thinking and skillfully about what is happening. The reality on the ground, especially what happened to schools in the Cempaka District, Banjarmasin Regency is that there are still many teachers who have performance problems such as teachers who still have not made learning preparations before teaching, teachers who have not been able to condition the class situation to be calm when students are noisy in class, teachers who have not used varied learning strategies that is considered boring learning for students, not to mention the case of teachers falling asleep in class during the teaching and learning process. Improvement efforts that can be made to improve teacher performance in schools must also continue to be carried out by examining various factors that may affect teacher performance in schools. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Supardi, 2013)</ref> many factors affect teacher performance, both internal and external factors. Internal factors are factors from within the teachers, including work motivation and teacher satisfaction. Meanwhile, external factors include the environment and the principal's leadership. The work environment includes, among others, the relationship between teachers, principals, school committees, and all school stakeholders. One of the factors that influence performance is the leadership of the principal. A research study conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Pratiwi et al., 2018)</ref> showed that the principal has a significant influence on teacher performance because the principal is a motivator and supervisor in fostering and improving teacher performance. It is also supported by a research study conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Suriansyah et al., 2020)</ref> showing that good principal leadership is able to have a significant positive influence on teacher performance. The impact of principal leadership on teacher performance is positive which means every increase in principal leadership will improve teacher performance. A principal plays an important role in determining the success of a school. Thus, the notion of the principal can be defined as a functional teacher who is given the task of leading a school where the teaching and learning process is held, or a place where there is interaction between teachers who deliver the lessons and students who receive the lessons <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Wahjosumidjo, 2015)</ref>. The principal's roles are as an educator, manager, administrator, supervisor, leader, innovator, motivator which is abbreviated as EMASLIM <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Mulyasa, 2014)</ref>. The principal's instructional leadership is in a strategic position in fostering teacher work commitment and teacher work discipline so that teachers can work more optimally. With good principal leadership, it will have an impact on teacher commitment and work discipline and in the end the performance of teachers in the school achieves maximum results. Instructional leadership according to Bush is "Instructional leadership focuses on teaching and learning and on the behavior of teachers in working with students. Leader's influences are targeted at students learning via teachers <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Suriansyah et al., 2020)</ref>. Work environment factors also have an influence on teacher performance because the thing that must be sought to improve teacher performance is to ensure that teachers can carry out their duties in a condition that meets the requirements. Thus, teachers can carry out their duties without experiencing tensions, or in other words schools must provide a good work environment for teachers (Sofyan, 2013:122). The work environment is all things or elements that can affect directly or indirectly the organization that will have a good or bad impact on performance and job satisfaction as stated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Nitisemito, 2014)</ref>. A pleasant work environment is very important in improving performance. The work environment is said to be good if the teacher can provide the results of his work that is able to achieve school goals to the fullest. Work environment greatly affects the performance produced by the teacher because the state of the work environment can affect the emotions and behavior of the teacher. When teachers like the work environment where they work, they will feel like at home or their office is a second home. They also do activities conveniently and effectively. If these environmental factors are not considered properly, it is feared that the teacher's performance will also not work as it should. Most likely teachers will feel lazy to work, even they will not carry out their duties as educators to the fullest. The results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Ajayi, 2017)</ref> explained that an unpleasant work environment will make teachers have decreased performance and the time for achieving the tasks that have been given can run not according to the given targets so that the work results applied become ineffective and efficient, on the contrary. A pleasant work environment will have a good impact on themselves and the school so that teachers get satisfaction in achieving their performance and schools also get the educational goals they want to achieve. The next factor that can affect teacher performance is job satisfaction. Job satisfaction is the general attitude of an individual towards his job, a person with a high level of job satisfaction shows a positive attitude towards the job, a person who is dissatisfied with his job shows a negative attitude towards the job <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Robbins &amp; Judge, 2016)</ref>. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Siagian (2014)</ref>, the scope of human resource management generally discusses matters relating to human beings, including job satisfaction. Job satisfaction is a factor that is considered important as it can affect the running of the organization as a whole. The satisfaction felt by employees at work is an indication that employees have feelings of pleasure in carrying out work duties. Job satisfaction for a teacher is a crucial factor because the satisfaction they got will also determine a positive attitude towards work. Feeling satisfied at work can have a positive impact on behavior. Job satisfaction is also related to outcomes such as performance, so that if job satisfaction is higher, it will lead to enthusiasm at work. Thus, it will be easier for someone to achieve high performance. The results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Arbaine (2018)</ref> state that the satisfaction obtained by teachers in their work can lead teachers to optimal ways of working or performance. Teacher job satisfaction is determined by school conditions, salary, communication relations between colleagues, job demands and responsibilities. Job satisfaction can indicate the success of an organization in managing schools well so that the expectations of teachers with the rewards obtained are appropriate. Based on the description above, many factors that influence teacher performance (including instructional leadership, work environment and job satisfaction) have an important role to produce the best teacher performance in achieving organizational goals and dealing with everything that happens in the organizational environment. This is the background of the problem to conduct research on the influence of principal instructional leadership, work environment and job satisfaction on teacher performance in state elementary schools in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHOD</head><p>This study aims to describe and analyze direct and indirect relationships between the variables of instructional ability on teacher performance, work environment on teacher performance, job satisfaction on teacher performance, environment on performance, satisfaction on performance through the environment and job satisfaction on performance through the environment. The population of the study were all public elementary school teachers in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru City as many as 147 people. The sampling technique used was proportional random sampling. The number of samples was determined based on the Cronbach Alpha formula, 108 people were found as the research sample. Descriptive-quantitative data collection, aims to describe and </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 3. 1 Research design RESULTS</head><p>The results of the respondents' descriptive statistical analysis of the research variables, namely the principal's instructional leadership, work environment, job satisfaction, and teacher performance measured in 5 groups are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> which includes the ideal mean and ideal standard deviation. The descriptive data in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> means that the respondents gave the highest emphasis in answering research questionnaires on managerial activities and the lowest emphasis was on teacher performance. The results of the normality test using the One-Sample Kolmogorov-Smirnov test showed that the data of all variables in this study could be said to be normally distributed. In addition, the results of the linearity test of the principal managerial activity variables, academic supervision and organizational climate with the teacher performance variable resulted in data deviations from the linear line, it can be concluded that the data is in the form of a linear function and the regression model does not occur multicollinearity, it can be concluded that non-multicollinearity data in the model regression. Through the results of simple regression test, partial test (T test), coefficient of determination test and path analysis. The summary of the calculation of the direct and indirect relationship of the principal managerial activity variables, academic supervision and organizational climate with the teacher performance variable can be seen in table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref> summary of the path coefficients as follows: The results of the path analysis as can be seen in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref> are used to answer the seven research hypotheses that have been formulated whose decisions are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">3</ref> and Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">4</ref>. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">3</ref> is a summary of the decisions H1, H2, H3, H4, and H5 with the criteria of less significance value. of 0.05, then the hypothesis is accepted. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">4</ref> is a summary of the decisions for testing the H6 and H7 hypotheses provided that if the direct correlation coefficient is smaller than the indirect correlation coefficient, then the hypothesis is considered accepted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. The Direct Effect of Principal's Instructional Leadership on Teacher Performance at SDN Cempaka District, Banjarbaru</head><p>Based on the results of the hypothesis test, there is a relationship that is seen from the analysis results. Based on the results of the path regression hypothesis test, it can be seen that the regression coefficient value of the principal's instructional leadership variable is 0.625, which means that if the principal's instructional leadership variable increases by 1 point, the teacher's performance variable will increase by 0.625 points. Therefore, the higher the principal's instructional leadership, it will increase the teacher's performance variable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Influence of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Environment and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance in State Elementary Schools in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru City</head><p>The influence of instructional leadership on performance is also relevant to previous research, namely <ref type="bibr">Southworth</ref>   <ref type="formula">2018</ref>), the conclusions of the research have similarities, namely stating that there is an influence of instructional leadership on performance. The results of this study are also in line with the results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Pratiwi et al., 2018)</ref> concluding that there is a positive and significant influence between instructional leadership and teacher performance at SDN Banjarmasin Timur District. The influence of the principal's instructional leadership on teacher performance at SDN Cempaka District, Banjarbaru was obtained based on a significance value of 0.001 &lt;0.05 and seen from the T-Count value of 3.519 &gt; 1.660 (Ttable), meaning that there was a significant influence of the principal's instructional leadership variable on teacher performance. The results of this study are supported by research by (HZ, 2019) which concludes that the higher the implementation of the principal's instructional leadership, the higher the teacher's performance. On the other hand, the lower the quality of the principal's learning leadership, the lower the teacher's performance and the (Yasa &amp; Utama, 2019) research results show a coefficient of determination of 79.7%, meaning that the increase in teacher performance can be influenced by the principal's instructional leadership. The relationship between the influence of instructional leadership and teacher performance at SDN Cempaka District can be seen from the effective contribution of 22.74%, meaning that the instructional leadership variable has an influence of 22.74% on teacher performance compared to the work environment and job satisfaction variables. Empirical facts of the principal of SDN Cempaka District in carrying out the role as a learning leader for the principal in an effort to run programs that support improving teacher performance. Based on the respondents' answers, it shows that the principal as the principal as instructional leadership in the development of the teaching curriculum in schools always adjusts to the school's vision (school renewal priorities), also directs by motivating teachers on an ongoing basis professional development and ultimately improves teacher performance as well as student achievement as the ultimate goal. Overall, the results of the study show that there is an influence of instructional leadership on the performance of SDN teachers in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru. The principal makes clear, measurable school goals, has a time target, communicates school goals to all school communities so that they know and support them, principals develop teacher professionalism by supervising and monitoring the implementation of the curriculum whether it is in accordance with the school curriculum objectives and participating actively active in checking curriculum materials, monitoring teaching and learning activities at school. This is in accordance with the instructional leadership theory by <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Sedarmayanti &amp; Dakhi, 2017)</ref> who states that the instructional leadership model is suitable to be applied to school principals who have high attention to academic or learning quality. Instructional school principals allocate more time to improve the quality of learning through activities related to improving teacher performance. The results of this study strengthen the research conducted by (HZ, 2019) entitled "The influence of the principal's instructional leadership on teacher performance and high school student achievement in Manggarai NTT". , which means Sig t &lt; (0.05). This means that there is a significant influence of instructional leadership on the performance of high school teachers in Manggarai, NTT. Budiman's further research (2020) with the research title "The influence of instructional leadership, motivation and work discipline on the level of teacher performance at SDN Kwayuhan, Minggir District, Sleman". The results of testing the influence of instructional leadership on teacher performance can be proven by a significance value (p-value) of 0.002 &lt; = 0.05. The test results prove that instructional leadership has a positive and significant effect on teacher performance and can be accepted or supported by the reality that occurs in the object of this study. Other studies such as Karyono (2019), Suriansyah et al (2020) and Gunawan (2019) who presented the results of the same study regarding the influence of principal's instructional leadership on teacher performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. The Direct Effect of Principal's Instructional Leadership on the Work Environment at SDN Cempaka District, Banjarbaru</head><p>The research hypothesis states that there is an influence of the principal's instructional leadership on the work environment at SDN Cempaka District, Banjarbaru, as evidenced by the t-test results yielding a significance value of 0.000 &lt; 0.05 and a T count of 10.900 &gt; 1.660 (Ttable). This research study corroborates previous research conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Sumaryanto, 2021)</ref> in which based on the results of data analysis there is a significant influence of instructional leadership on the work environment of teachers, in addition to the results of Arianto (2020) entitled "The Influence of Instructional Leadership, Work Environment and Work Culture on Teacher Performance." The results of the study indicate that instructional leadership has an effect on improving the conditions of the work environment so that a good and pleasant work environment makes it easier to work optimally. The results of the research on respondents' responses to the physical work environment variable the average score is 3.16 including high categories, such as the physical work environment is sufficient lighting, good air circulation, the size of the work space including comfort in the space, the ease and availability of office equipment and teachers feel safe. All physical conditions that exist around the workplace that can affect teachers either directly or indirectly. The physical work environment is more focused on the physical state of the workplace because in the absence of disturbances in the work environment, the teacher will be able to work well.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Influence of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Environment and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance in State Elementary Schools in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru City</head><p>Based on the results of the termination, the R Square coefficient value of 0.528 means that 52.8% changes in the work environment variable are influenced by the instructional leadership variable. The close influence of school principals' instructional leadership on the work environment can be seen in the way school principals build non-physical work environments such as managing relationships with school leaders regarding work structures and work responsibilities, leadership attention and support, collaboration between groups in this case teachers and smooth communication. If these environmental factors are not considered properly, it is feared that the teacher's performance will also not work as it should. Most likely the teacher will feel lazy to enter his room, even the teacher will not carry out his duties as an educator to the fullest. Some of the results of previous studies are in line with the results of this study such as the results of this study. The results of this study are also in line with the results of research by <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Suwandono et al., 2021)</ref> who conducted research on the influence of instructional leadership, work environment, and compensation on job satisfaction and teacher performance on teacher performance in high school in Karangdowo District State. This study concludes that there is an influence of principal's instructional leadership on the work environment by creating pleasant working conditions and ease of use of school facilities. This is also in line with the results of (Sumaryanto, 2021) research which concluded that instructional leadership abilities affect the work environment by 0.551 or 55%. In line with research study conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Arianto, 2020)</ref>, it shows that the results of instructional leadership have an effect on good physical and non-physical environmental conditions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Direct Effect of Work Environment on Teacher Performance</head><p>Based on the results of the regression test hypothesis, it can be seen that there is an influence of work environment variables on the performance of SDN teachers in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru. The significance value of the environmental variable on teacher performance is 0.001 &lt; 0.05, and the T-count value is 3.467 &gt; 1.660 (Ttable). Therefore, there is a direct influence of work environment variables on teacher performance. These results are in accordance with research by Takassenser &amp; Christoffel (2019)and Hairina (2020)concluding that the work environment is a predictor of performance, because the work environment has a moderate correlation with performance. Thus, it can be concluded that the level of the teacher's work environment will affect performance. The results of this study are in accordance with the opinion of (Widiawati &amp; Sofyan, 2013)which states that the work environment is all things or elements that can affect directly or indirectly an organization or company that will have a good or bad impact on performance. The work environment that is directly related is the ease of using school facilities, setting the space for movement such as setting the table layout for the size of the room and others. While the work environment that is not directly related or requires an intermediary is good air circulation so as to make comfort while in the workspace, the smell of the room and others. The results of Ajayi (2017) stated that an uncomfortable work environment will affect a person's emotions because an uncomfortable environment will make them uncomfortable and interfere with comfort in completing work so that performance will be disrupted and people will get angry quickly. Thus, it can be concluded that the physical environment is everything around the teacher that can be seen and felt and then has both negative and positive side effects on the results of the work. The creation of a comfortable, safe and pleasant work environment is one way to improve employee performance. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Supardi, 2013)</ref>, what is meant by performance is the quality and quantity of work achieved by a person in carrying out his duties in accordance with the responsibilities given to him/her. Employees can improve their performance to the maximum with the support of an appropriate work environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. The Direct Effect of Principal's Instructional Leadership on Teacher Job Satisfaction</head><p>Based on the hypothesis test, it can be seen from the regression path that there is a direct influence of the principal's instructional leadership variable on the job satisfaction of SDN teachers in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru. This can be seen from the regression structure equation which shows that the value of the principal's instructional leadership coefficient is 0.720. This means that each principal's instructional leadership increases by 1 point, the teacher's job satisfaction will increase by 0.720 points. This study is in line with the results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Takassenser &amp; Christoffel, 2019)</ref>The Effect of Instructional Leadership, Work Environment and Job Satisfaction on the Performance of Islamic Religious Education Teachers in Bengkulu First Schools. The results showed that 27.49% of the teacher's performance was influenced by the principal's instructional leadership ability. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Pratiwi et al (2018)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Margaritas, 2019)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Gunawan (2019)</ref>, each concluded that there is an effect of principal's instructional leadership on job satisfaction. According to Schemerhorn <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Akdol &amp; Arikboga, 2015)</ref>, the level of job satisfaction is also caused by several aspects, such as the work itself, supervisor (supervision), coworkers, promotions, and wages or salaries. Job satisfaction can also be influenced by several factors, such as compensation policies, job security, working conditions, relationships with superiors, promotion and career development, leadership styles, working in teams, and the employees themselves <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Darmawan, 2018)</ref>. Based on the results of the questionnaire, it can be seen from the respondents' answers that the level of job satisfaction of the teachers at SDN Cempaka District is in the high category with a percentage of 51.85%, while for respondents who have job satisfaction in the medium category it is 48.15%. Instructional leadership in influencing teacher satisfaction can be seen from the The Influence of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Environment and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance in State Elementary Schools in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru City behavior of principals taking a strategic approach, namely formulating and communicating school goals, always involving teacher involvement in making school decisions, teacher perceived recognition, teacher expectations, interpersonal relationships that occur in the work environment and authority received by the teacher. In addition, instructional leadership related to teachers recognizes and recognizes the status of each teacher's achievement, provides available resources, provides school principals the freedom to manage teaching, and builds harmony in the aspect of cooperation both between teachers and with school principals. The effect of the principal's instructional leadership on job satisfaction for SDN Cempaka District teachers is that the significance value of the principal's instructional leadership variable on teacher performance is 0.000 &lt;0.05 and the Tcount is 10.688&gt; 1.660 (Ttable). Then, there is a direct influence of the principal's instructional leadership variable on job satisfaction. Instructional leadership will think about how to achieve the expected goals, and also think about the welfare of teachers and have a strong influence that is able to change awareness, and can inspire enthusiasm to encourage teachers to achieve vision and mission of the school. Huber (2013) explains that instructional leadership plays a very important role in creating teacher job satisfaction, which includes the ability to fulfill needs. A person's work is driven in order to meet certain needs. The relationship with teacher job satisfaction is very close to the performance of the teacher itself. With a good principal's leadership, of course, it can create conditions that allow for the birth of job satisfaction which is reflected in a positive attitude towards his work. The results of data analysis can be seen that the R Square coefficient of 0.519 means that 51.9% changes in the job satisfaction variable are influenced by the instructional leadership variable. Job satisfaction is very necessary for teachers because teachers who have job satisfaction will love and have positive feelings towards their work and tend to be more effective and productive. The role of instructional leadership in increasing teacher job satisfaction at SDN Cempaka District can be seen from the role of leadership in providing opportunities. The findings of this study provide empirical confirmation that one of the predictors of job satisfaction is influenced by the transformational leadership factor of the principal. This is in agreement with the opinion of Colquit, LePine, and Wesson <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Sunyoto &amp; Danang, 2015)</ref> who states that one of the factors that increase job satisfaction is the instructional leadership factor because with leaders who are able to encourage, motivate, emphasize performance development for teachers, it makes teachers feel comfortable. and satisfied at work or in other words supervision satisfaction, which means workers' feelings about their superiors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. The Direct Effect of Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance</head><p>Based on the interpretation of the hypothesis test, there is a significant influence of the satisfaction variable on the performance of SDN teachers in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru. This can be seen from the regression coefficient value of the job satisfaction variable of 0.302, which means that if the teacher's job satisfaction variable increases by 1 point, the teacher's performance will increase by 0.302 points. So the better the teacher's work motivation, the better the teacher performance. Stoner and Freeman's research study <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Dewanto, 2019)</ref> on job satisfaction shows the compatibility between the expectations that arise with the rewards provided by the job so that job satisfaction is also related to performance. Newstrom <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Djaali &amp; Muljono, 2018)</ref> discussed the factors that influence teacher performance. The fundamental factor that is closely related to the professional performance of teachers is job satisfaction which is closely related to teacher welfare. This satisfaction is motivated by the following factors: (1) remuneration, (2) a sense of security, (3) interpersonal relationships, (4) working environment conditions, (5) opportunities for self-development and self-improvement.From this opinion, it can be seen that in addition to the principal's instructional leadership, other factors that can affect teacher performance is the teacher's job satisfaction itself. A person's job satisfaction is closely related to the fulfillment of needs. A person's work is encouraged in order to meet certain needs. The relationship with teacher job satisfaction is very closely related to the teacher's performance itself. The majority of teachers' job satisfaction at SDN Cempaka District, Banjarbaru is in the high category with a percentage of 51.85%, while for respondents who have job satisfaction in the medium category it is 48.15%. Job satisfaction is shaped by indicators, namely the positive attitude of the teachers towards their work, the adequacy of needs through the salary and benefits obtained, the opportunity to improve their career or position, support from a good principal and harmonious relations with coworkers. Based on the data analysis of the data statistically proves that teacher job satisfaction has a significant positive effect on teacher performance. This indicates that the higher the job satisfaction of teachers, the teachers will show their best performance. If the company always implements the career and compensation system properly, the existence of good relationships between coworkers, the attitude of leaders who always motivates, and a conducive physical work environment will make teachers feel safe and comfortable working. The impact is that the teachers will work as well as possible and always try to provide the best service to their students. This shows that the teacher's performance is high. Judging from the results of the t-test, it can be seen that the significance value of the job satisfaction variable on teacher performance is 0.001 &lt; 0.05 and the T count is 3.393 &gt; 1.660 (Ttable). There is a direct effect of job satisfaction on teacher performance. Job satisfaction is one of the most important factors to get optimal work results. A person with a high level of job satisfaction has a positive attitude towards his job, and someone who is dissatisfied with his job will have a negative attitude towards the job. Job satisfaction reflects a person's feelings towards his job. This can be seen through the teacher's positive attitude towards work and everything that is faced in the school environment. Therefore, job satisfaction will make teachers try</p><p>The Influence of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Environment and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance in State Elementary Schools in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru City their best with all their abilities to complete their work assignments, so that they can improve their performance at school. Teachers who feel job satisfaction will always improve their performance. Job satisfaction can have an impact on achieving the target time for completing work, and optimizing quality. Meanwhile, teachers who feel dissatisfied will tend not to have the drive to achieve maximum performance. So that the teacher feels unmotivated in carrying out his work.</p><p>Based on what has been described above, it is clear that job satisfaction is very influential on teacher performance that job satisfaction is an attitude of pleasure or positive emotion resulting from work measurements about how well the work they do and what results they get from the good work. A person with a high level of job satisfaction shows a positive attitude towards the job, and someone who is dissatisfied with his job shows a negative attitude towards his job. Various studies show that job satisfaction has a positive and significant effect on performance. Some of them are <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Sumaryanto, 2021)</ref> who found that job satisfaction significantly affects teacher performance. The results of his research show that job satisfaction has a positive correlation on performance, that increasing satisfaction encourages an increase in teacher performance. The results of research that prove the same thing are also reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Akdol &amp; Arikboga, 2015)</ref> which emphasizes the importance of job satisfaction which has an impact on teacher performance in the field of education. In addition, research conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Arbaine, 2018)</ref> found that school policies, supervision, wages, interpersonal relations, opportunities for promotion, working conditions, the work itself, achievement, recognition, and responsibility are factors that affect the performance of the teachers. Sunardi (2020) says that when teachers are satisfied with their work, they will develop and maintain a high level of performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F. Indirect Effect of Principal's Instructional Leadership through the Work Environment on Teacher Performance</head><p>The results of the calculation of the value of the indirect influence of the leadership variable on teacher performance through the work environment variable is to look at the results of the multiplication of H2 with H3 which is 0.727 x 0.311 = 0.226. This value indicates that the value is positive, meaning that there is an indirect influence of the leadership variable on teacher performance through the work environment variable at SDN Se Cempaka District. Instructional leaders not only guide and develop teacher performance through improving teaching and learning systems but also things that are able to support teachers to carry out their performance, one of which is a good work environment. Good leadership will be able to create a comfortable environment for teachers to work which has an impact on the performance of the teachers they lead. According to Fiedler <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Heystek &amp; Emekako, 2020)</ref>, performance can be achieved effectively if the instructional leader develops an approach that best contributes to the achievement of organizational goals may vary in different situations or environments. The results of the Sobel test calculation show that 5,023 (Tcount) &gt; 1,660 (Ttable). The results of the Sobel test show that the tcount value is greater than the t-table (5%), so it can be concluded that the work environment mediation variable is significant, meaning that there is an indirect influence on the leadership variable on teacher performance through the work environment variable at SDN in Cempaka District. The work environment is also a factor that can increase teacher performance or even decrease it. When teachers work in a good work environment, their ideas, productivity, and performance can increase. Conversely, if the work environment is not good and does not support performance and productivity, then the ability of employees to produce good work will decrease. The principal should be obliged to create a work environment that supports cooperation between all elements in the school. The work environment must at least support the performance of teachers so that teachers feel helped and make it easier to comfortably complete their work. If the work environment is not good, the performance will be disrupted.</p><p>Research that shows a significant influence of school principals' instructional leadership through the work environment on teacher performance is (Arbaine, 2018)that there is a positive and significant influence of school principals' leadership through the work environment on teacher performance with the results of the Sobel test test t value greater than t table 7,084 &gt; 1,600 and <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Manik &amp; Bustomi, 2011)</ref> research also shows that there is a significant influence between instructional leadership on teacher performance through the work environment because the test results for the t-count value are greater than the t-table.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G. Indirect Effect of Principal's Instructional Leadership through Job Satisfaction with Teacher Performance</head><p>The calculation of the value of the indirect influence of the instructional leadership variable on teacher performance through the job satisfaction variable is the calculation of the value of the indirect influence of the leadership variable on the teacher's performance through the job satisfaction variable by looking at the results of the multiplication of H4 with H5, which is 0.720 x 0.302 = 0.217. This value indicates that the value is positive, meaning that there is an indirect influence of the leadership variable on teacher performance through the job satisfaction variable at SDN in Cempaka District. The results of this study are in accordance with Bass's theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Pratiwi et al., 2018)</ref>which states that good instructional leadership is able to create comfortable working conditions and be able to fulfill the desires of their subordinates so that subordinates will feel satisfaction at work and feel satisfaction with the applied leadership so that they strive to achieve good work performance. higher quality and in return for perceived job satisfaction. Furthermore, Bass said that creating job satisfaction by aligning the wishes of The Influence of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Environment and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance in State Elementary Schools in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru City the leader with the wishes and needs of the teacher in achieving learning objectives, namely student achievement and this can only be done with instructional leadership. The results of this study are also in accordance with the opinion of Tarter, Hoy &amp; Kottkamp <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Pratiwi et al., 2018)</ref> who stated that given the importance of the principal's instructional leadership on teacher performance, a principal must be able to encourage and create a conducive atmosphere, which allows teachers to work comfortably and comfortably. calm, full of intimacy and mutual respect so that job satisfaction and high commitment to the organization grow, which will then affect performance. The same thing was also stated by Miner <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Mulyasa, 2014</ref>) that the interaction between quality superiors and subordinates will have an impact such as job satisfaction, productivity and employee performance. Job satisfaction as an intervening or mediator in increasing the influence of instructional leadership on teacher performance obtained a regression significance value of 0.217, while the coefficient value of the direct influence of instructional leadership on teacher performance was 0.304 so that even though there was an indirect influence on instructional leadership through job satisfaction with teacher performance at SDN Cempaka District. However, the intervening variable job satisfaction was not able to strengthen the direct influence of instructional leadership on teacher performance. This means that teacher job satisfaction is not always obtained from external factors, but satisfaction can also come from within, such as satisfaction with the work itself. Several studies that support this research are such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Suwandono et al., 2021)</ref> entitled "The Influence of Instructional Leadership, Work Environment, and Compensation on Job Satisfaction and Teacher Performance on teacher performance in SMA Negeri Karangdowo District." The results of his research that the value of the indirect effect was obtained from the path coefficient value y1x1 multiplied by the path coefficient value y2y1 to (0.308 x 0.447) = 0.138. The multiplication result shows that the indirect effect coefficient value {(ρy2x1) x (ρy2y1)} is smaller than the direct effect coefficient value y1x1, (0.209). This shows that the principal's instructional leadership variable can be through an intervening variable, namely job satisfaction in influencing the level of teacher performance. The intervening variable with r value is 0.383 and t count (2.0834) &gt; t table <ref type="bibr">(1.667)</ref>. Furthermore, the results of this study are strengthened by Sumaryanto (2020) to which the results of his research as a job satisfaction intervening show that instructional leadership has a significant effect on performance with a significant value of t (tsig) of 0.000 which means it is smaller than = 0.05 (tsig 0.000 &lt;0.05). Based on the path analysis, the coefficient value through interneving of 0.234 and 0.249 is greater than directly that is 0.221 and 0.217. Yasa &amp; Utama (2019) research results state that there is a significant relationship between instructional leadership on performance and job satisfaction as an intervening because the R2 value is 0.14 it means that the variation of the dependent variable can be explained by the independent variable simultaneously by 14% greater than the direct effect.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head><p>To conclude, the principal's instructional leadership variable is included in the high category, the level of the work environment variable is included in the high category with job satisfaction variables included in the high category and teacher performance is included in the medium category with the percentage being in the medium category. There is a direct influence of the principal's instructional leadership on teacher performance. Then, there is a direct influence of the principal's instructional leadership on the teacher's work environment, and there is a direct influence of the work environment on teacher performance. Further, there is a direct influence of the principal's instructional leadership on teacher job satisfaction, a direct influence of job satisfaction on teacher performance, an indirect effect of principal's instructional leadership on teacher performance through the work environment, and an indirect influence of principal's instructional leadership on teacher performance through job satisfaction. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>The Influence of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Environment and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance in State Elementary Schools in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru City</head><label></label><figDesc>of the principal's instructional leadership variable work environment, job satisfaction on the performance of State Elementary School teachers in Cempaka District, the validity of the instrument was analyzed by correlation technique. The data collected was analyzed by path analysis to see the direct and indirect relationships between variables by first testing the requirements analysis. This study tries to reveal causality in the form of the influence of the independent variables, namely the principal's instructional leadership (X), work environment (Z1) and job satisfaction (Z2) as intermediate variables (intervening) on teacher performance (Y). as the dependent variable, so State Elementary Schools in Cempaka District. The relationship among variables formulated into the path analysis model is either direct or indirect.</figDesc><table><row><cell>analyze the influence</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Z1 = Work</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H6</cell><cell>Environment</cell><cell>H6</cell></row><row><cell>H2</cell><cell></cell><cell>H3</cell></row><row><cell>X = Instructional</cell><cell></cell><cell>Y =</cell></row><row><cell>Leadership</cell><cell>H1</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Teacher Performance</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Z2 = Job</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H4</cell><cell>Satisfaction</cell><cell>H5</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>H7</cell></row><row><cell>H7</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 . Mean, Standard Deviation and Stage of Research Variables</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell></cell><cell>mean</cell><cell cols="2">Standard Deviation Stage</cell></row><row><cell>Principal</cell><cell>Instructional</cell><cell>107,1111</cell><cell>10.26502</cell><cell>Tall</cell></row><row><cell>Leadership</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Work environment</cell><cell>93.2222</cell><cell>12,49174</cell><cell>Tall</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Job satisfaction</cell><cell>91.9630</cell><cell>10.93560</cell><cell>Tall</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Teacher Performance</cell><cell>39.8056</cell><cell>7.08883</cell><cell>Tall</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 . Summary of Path Analysis Regression Analysis Test Results</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Variable Effect</cell><cell>Regression Test Direct Indirect</cell><cell>Partial Test (T-Test)</cell><cell>Determinati on Test</cell><cell>Information</cell></row><row><cell>Principal's Instructional Leadership (X 1 ) -Teacher Performance (Y)</cell><cell>0. 304</cell><cell>3,519</cell><cell>22.74%</cell><cell>Significant</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>The Influence of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Environment and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance in State Elementary Schools in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru City</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Variable Effect</cell><cell cols="2">Regression Test Direct Indirect</cell><cell>Partial Test (T-Test)</cell><cell>Determinati on Test</cell><cell>Information</cell></row><row><cell>Principal's instructional leadership (X 1 ) -Work environment ( Z )</cell><cell>0.727</cell><cell></cell><cell>10,900</cell><cell>23.54%</cell><cell>Significant</cell></row><row><cell>Work environment (X 2 ) -Teacher Performance (Y)</cell><cell>0.3 11</cell><cell></cell><cell>3,393</cell><cell>22.74%</cell><cell>Significant</cell></row><row><cell>Job satisfaction (X 2 ) -Work environment ( Z )</cell><cell>0.452 _</cell><cell></cell><cell>6,340</cell><cell>27.71%</cell><cell>Significant</cell></row><row><cell>Work Environment ( Z )-Teacher Performance (Y)</cell><cell>0.311 _</cell><cell></cell><cell>3,467</cell><cell>22.72%</cell><cell>Significant</cell></row><row><cell>Principal's instructional leadership</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(X 1 ) -Work environment ( Z ) -</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.226</cell><cell>2,945</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>Significant</cell></row><row><cell>Teacher Performance (Y)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Job satisfaction (X 2 ) -Work</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>environment ( Z ) -Teacher</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.217</cell><cell>3,525</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>Significant</cell></row><row><cell>Performance (Y)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 3 . Summary of Hypothesis Testing Decisions H 1 H 2 H 3 H 4 and H 5</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Hypothesis</cell></row></table><note><p>2 : There is a direct relationship between the principal's instructional leadership and the work environment 0.727 Accept H 3 : There is a direct relationship between job satisfaction and teacher performance 0.311 Accept H 4 : There is a direct relationship between job satisfaction and work environment 0.720 Accept H 5 : There is a direct relationship between the work environment and teacher performance 0.302 Accept</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 4 . Summary of Hypothesis Testing Decisions H 6 and H 7</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Coefficient Connection</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Hypothesis</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Decision</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Direct</cell><cell>Not direct</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H 6 : Job satisfaction is an intermediary relationship between</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>the principal's managerial activities and teacher</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.266 _</cell><cell>Accept</cell></row><row><cell>performance</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H 7 : Job satisfaction is the intermediary of the relationship between the work environment and teacher performance</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.217 _</cell><cell>Accept</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>&amp; Geoff, (2016), Mielcarek &amp; Michelle, (2016), Takassenser &amp; Christoffel, (2019) and Cunningham &amp; Cordeiro (</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>The Influence of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Environment and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance in State Elementary Schools in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru City</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Work Environment As Corellate Of Academic Staff Job Performance In South West Nigerian Universities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ajayi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Euroopian Journal of Educational Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">16674</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of Leader Behavior on Job Satisfaction A Research on Technology Fast Turkey Companies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Akdol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Arikboga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal on Technology, Innovation and Entrepreneurship</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance Evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Andhika</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kartomo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Effect of Principal Leadership, Work Environment and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance at SDN Batu Sopang District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Arbaine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1945">2018. August 17, 1945</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Paser Regency. University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Instructional Leadership, Work Environment and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Arianto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Instructional Leadership and the School Principal: The Passing Fancy that rfuses to Fade Away</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">&amp;</forename><surname>Cunningham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Cordeiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<pubPlace>Bangkok, Thailand</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>College of Management,. Mahidol University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principles of Organizational Behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Darmawan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<pubPlace>Universal Pen</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Relationship between Principal Instructional Leadership and Motivation on Teacher Performance through Job Satisfaction on State Elementary School Teachers in Banjarmasin City</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dewanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Measurement in the Field of Education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">&amp;</forename><surname>Djaali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Muljono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>PT. Grasindo</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Relationship between Principal Leadership Roles and Work Motivation with Teacher Performance at SDN in Astambul District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gunawan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relationship of Instructional Leadership and Job&apos;s Satisfactionb through work Achievment on the performance of state vocational high school teachers in Banjarmasin city</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hairina</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of K6 Education and Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leadership and motivation for improved academic performance in schools in low socio-economic contexts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heystek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Emekako</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Educational Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">School Leadership International Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Principal Instructional Leadership on Teacher Performance and High School Student Achievement in Manggarai NTT</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Business Strategy, and Entrepreneurship</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Journal of Management</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Effect of Instructional Leadership and Teacher Performance on Increasing Student Achievement at SMPN Tabanan District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Karyono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University Bali</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pengaruh Kepemimpinan Kepala Sekolah, Budaya Organisasi dan Motivasi Kerja Terhadap Kinerja Guru Pada SMP Negeri 3 Rancaekek</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Manik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bustomi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Ekonomi, Bisnis &amp; Entrepreneurship</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="107" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Influence of Principal Instructional Leadership, Organizational Climate and Teacher Job Satisfaction on Teaching Performance of State Elementary School Teachers in Sukabumi City</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Margaritas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michelle</forename><surname>Mielcarek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">A Model of School Success: Instructional Leadership, academic Press, and student achievement</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principal Leadership Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mulyasa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<pubPlace>Rosdakarya Youth</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Work environment. Grasindo</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Nitisemito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efforts to Develop Religious and Moral Value Ability (Identify Know Salah Times) Using a Combination of Rhyming Method and Make A Match Model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pratiwi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aslamiah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Miliyawati</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of K6 Education and Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Organizational Behavior: Organizational Behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Robbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Judge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Salemba Four</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Persepsi mengenai Promosi Jabatan Struktural PNS Perempuan di Pemerintah Kota Gunungsitoli</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sedarmayanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">N R</forename><surname>Dakhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Ilmu Administrasi: Media Pengembangan Ilmu Dan Praktek Administrasi</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="184" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Tips to Increase Work Productivity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Siagian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>PT. Rineka Cipta</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leadership Instructional Leadership In Schools: Reflections and Emperical Evidence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">&amp;</forename><surname>Southworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Geoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Science Education -Routledge Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">XXXIII</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">150</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Instructional Leadership, Work Environment, Job Satisfaction, and Motivation on Junior High School Teacher Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sumaryanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economics and Entrepreneurship</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Relationship of Principal Instructional Leadership and Teacher Work Environment with Job Satisfaction of State Vocational High School Teachers in Samarinda City</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sunardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Human Resource Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">&amp;</forename><surname>Sunyoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Danang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Human Resources Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Fun Books</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Teacher Performance. PT. RajaGrafindo Persada</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Supardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship of instructional leadership, organizational climate and teacher&apos;s commitment to job satisfaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ahmad</forename><surname>Suriansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Suhaimi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of K6 Education and Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="260" to="270" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Peningkatan Produktivitas Usaha Sambal Kemasan Bagi Usaha Kecil Menengah. JURNAL APLIKASI DAN INOVASI IPTEKS&quot; SOLIDITAS</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Suwandono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hermawan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wicaksono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="100" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Instructional Leadership, Work Environment and Job Satisfaction on the Performance of Islamic Religious Education Teachers in Bengkulu City First Public Schools</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">&amp;</forename><surname>Takassenser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Christoffel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBA Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1726" to="1736" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principal Leadership: A Theoretical Review and Its Problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wahjosumidjo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>King Grafindo Persada</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perbandingan Prestasi Belajar Matematika Siswa antara yang Mendapatkan Metode Kumon dan Metode Konvensional</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Widiawati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sofyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mosharafa Jurnal Pendidikan Matematika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of Instructional Leadership and work environment on job satisfaction and performance of SMAN teachers in Karma Jimbaran District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yasa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Utama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Udayana University Management E-Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="609" to="620" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>There is an Open Access article, distributed under the term of the Creative Commons Attribution -Non Commercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0. which permits remixing, adapting and building upon the work for non-commercial use, provided the original work is properly cited</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
