<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Essentials of Structural Equation Modeling</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Mustafa</forename><forename type="middle">Emre</forename><surname>Civelek</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Zea Books Lincoln</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2018</postCode>
									<settlement>Nebraska</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Zea Books Lincoln</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2018</postCode>
									<settlement>Nebraska</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Essentials of Structural Equation Modeling</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.13014/K2SJ1HR5</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T17:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Structural Equation Modeling is a statistical method increasingly used in scientific studies in the fields of Social Sciences. It is currently a preferred analysis method, especially in doctoral dissertations and academic researches. However, since many universities do not include this method in the curriculum of undergraduate and graduate courses, students and scholars try to solve the problems they encounter by using various books and internet resources.</p><p>This book aims to guide the researcher who wants to use this method in a way that is free from math expressions. It teaches the steps of a research program using structured equality modeling practically. For students writing theses and scholars preparing academic articles, this book aims to analyze systematically the methodology of scientific studies conducted using structural equation modeling methods in the social sciences. This book is prepared in as simple language as possible so as to convey basic information. It consists of two parts: the first gives basic concepts of structural equation modeling, and the second gives examples of applications.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PREFACE</head><p>Structural Equation Modeling is a statistical method increasingly used in scientific studies in the field of Social Sciences. Nowadays, it is a preferred analysis method especially in doctoral dissertations and academic researches. However, since most of the universities do not include this method in the curriculum of undergraduate and graduate courses, students and scholars try to solve the problems they encounter by using various books and internet resources. The aim of this book is to guide the researcher who wants to use this method in a way that is free from math expressions and to teach the steps of a research using structured equality modeling practically. For the students who write thesis and the scholars who prepare academic articles, this book aims to systematically analyze the methodology of the scientific studies which is conducted by using structural equation modeling method in social sciences. This book is prepared in a simple language as possible so as to convey basic information. This book consists of two parts. In the first part, basic concepts of structural equation modeling are given. In the second part, examples of applications are given.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>There are various computer programs that are used when the structural equation modeling method is applied. The most common ones are LISREL (Linear Structural Relations), AMOS (Analysis of Moment Structures), MPlus, EQS (Equation Modeling Software) <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(Taşkın &amp; Akat, 2010)</ref>. The samples and illustrations in this book were made according to the AMOS program. The AMOS program is a visual program that is easier to use than other programs. This is why it is preferred in this book. There will also be plenty of videos related to AMOS on YouTube and similar sites. That will make the learning process easier for readers. There are different versions of the AMOS program. AMOS 22 version was used for the analysis examples in the book. All the narrations in the book have been tried to be supported by visuals. In this book, it is assumed that the readers have basic statistical information. The main aim is to provide a guide to the readers on structural equation modeling.</p><p>Although the structural equation modeling method is similar to linear regression analysis, it has many advantages. Some of the features that outperform the structural equation modeling are summarized below. These superior features distinguish structural equation modeling from other classical linear modeling approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Çelik &amp; Yılmaz, 2013)</ref>.</p><p>1. It reveals the relationship among hidden structures that are not directly measured.</p><p>2. Possible mistakes in the measurements of the observed variables are taken into consideration. The classic regression approach assumes no measurement error.</p><p>3. It is a very useful method to analyze highly complex multiple variable models and to reveal direct and indirect relationships between variables.</p><p>In this book, firstly the basic concepts related to structural equation modeling are discussed. Basic concepts such as measurement model versus structural model, latent versus observed variables, and endogeneous versus exogeneous variables are explained. Once the goodness of fit indices have been defined, all the processes of a research have been dealt with up to hypothesis testing, from determining the validity and reliability of the scale. The first chapter of the book consists of a description of the topics related to the structural equation modeling. In the second chapter, there are sample applications. Samples consist of summaries of actual research done on the field. This is intended to give readers a template that they can follow in their own research. It is recommended that the readers who will be using AMOS for the first time have started this book after looking at the tutorial videos on YouTube and similar sites. Also, to use AMOS, it is absolutely necessary to be able to use SPSS and to have basic statistical information. Assuming that the readers have this information, the subject explanations have been prepared.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. CHAPTER CONCEPTS AND METHODOLOGY</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">BASIC CONCEPTS OF STRUCTURAL EQUATION MODELING</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Definitions and Features</head><p>Structural equation modeling is a statistical method increasingly used in scientific studies in the field of social sciences in recent years. The most important reason of the spread of this statistical technique is that the direct and indirect relationships among causal variables can be measured with a single model <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">(Meydan &amp; Şen, 2011)</ref>. Structural equation modeling is a statistical method used to test the relationships between observed and latent variables. Observed variables are the measured variables in the data collection process and latent variables are the variables measured by connecting to the observed variables because they can not be directly measured. Structural Equation Modeling consists of two basic components as structural model and measurement model.</p><p>Another reason for the widespread adoption of this method is the ability of taking in to the account of the measurement errors and the relationships between errors in the observed variables. In this way measurement errors can be minimized.</p><p>In traditional regression analysis, potential measurement errors are neglected. Another difference from the regression models of structural equality models is that they are based on the covariance matrix. For this reason, in some sources, it is named as covariance structure modeling or analysis of covariance structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Bayram, 2013)</ref>. On the other hand, , the correlation matrix is the basis of the regression. Covariance is a nonstandardized measure of the relationship between two variables, so it can take values between -∞ and + ∞. Correlation, however, can take values between -1 and +1, since it is standardized <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(Gujarati, 1999)</ref>. The covariance which is the basic statistic of the structural equation model can be shown for two observed and continuous variables as follows: Cov xy = r xy SD x SD y</p><p>In the formula shown above, r xy indicates the Pearson correlation coefficient, and also, SDx and SDy indicate the standard deviation of each variable <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Kline, 2011)</ref>. Structural equation modeling differs from some other multivariate statistical methods in that it is a confirmatory approach. In Table <ref type="table">1</ref>, it can be seen that the explanatory and confirmatory ones of the multivariate methods are <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Hair, Hult, Ringle, &amp; Sarstedt, 2017)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tablo 1. Explanatory and Confirmatory Multivariate Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Explanatory Confirmatory</head><p>x CulusterAnalysis</p><p>x Explanatory Factor Analysis</p><p>x Multidimensional Scaling</p><p>x Partial Least Squares Structural Equation Modeling (PLS-SEM)</p><p>x Analysis of Variance</p><p>x Logistic Regression</p><p>x Multiple Regression</p><p>x Confirmatory Factor</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis</head><p>x Covariance Based Structural Equation Modeling (CB-SEM)</p><p>Source: <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Hair, J., Hult, G., Ringle, C., &amp; Sarstedt, M. (2017)</ref>. A primer on partial least squares structural equation modeling PLS-SEM. Los Angeles: SAGE.</p><p>Most of the statistical methods other than structural equation modeling try to discover relationships through the data set.</p><p>However, structural equation modeling confirms the correspondence of the data of the relations in the theoretical model. For this reason, it can be said that structural equation modeling is more suitable for testing the hypothesis than other methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Karagöz, 2016)</ref>. Structural equation modeling consists of a system of linear equations. The key in the regression analysis is to determine how much of the change in the dependent variable is explained by the independent variable or variables. Although multiple regression analysis can only be applied to observed variables, the basic principles can be applied to structural equation modeling <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Kline, 2011)</ref>. Differently from the regression, structural equation modeling, as a new statistical analysis technique, allows to test research hypotheses in a single process by modeling complex relationships among many observed and latent variables. In traditional regression analysis, only direct effects can be detected. However, in the method of structural equation modeling, direct and indirect effects are put together.</p><p>In order to test the accuracy of the conceptual model, the most common method encountered in the literature on structural equation modeling is a two-stage method consisting of measurement model and structural model. In the first stage, the measurement model is tested; in the second stage the structural model is tested. The measurement model measures how well hidden variables are represented by the observed variables. It is mainly confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) and indicates the contruct validity of scales. Therefore, if the measurement model fit indices are low, it will not make sense to test the structural model <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Dursun &amp; Kocagöz, 2010)</ref>. As seen in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, structural equation modeling is a compound of factor analysis and regression analysis. The measurement model and the structural model are interwoven. But the structural equation modeling is based on the confirmatory approach. It is based on the statistical confirmation of the theoretical model. For this reason, the measurement model is confirmatory factor analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Latent and Observed Variables</head><p>The obseved variable (manifest variable) is the measured variable in the data collection process; latent variables are variables that are measured by connecting to observed variables because they can not be directly measured. Latent variables must be represented by more than one observed variable since they represent abstract concepts. It is recommended that the number of observed variables connected to a latent variable in structural equality models be at least three. Latent variables represent hypothetical constructs in a research model <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Raykov &amp; Marcoulides, 2006)</ref>.</p><p>Observed variables in the structural equation modeling can be categorical, discrete or continuous variable, but latent variables must always be continuous variable. There are other statistical techniques that allow analysis with categorical latent variables, but in structural equation modeling only continuous variables can be analysed <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Kline, 2011)</ref>. Continuous variable is a variable that takes any random value from the set of real numbers. However discrete variable can only take value from the set of even number. Research questionnaires used to collect data in social sciences are generally prepared by using the Likert type ordinal scale. Values in this scale type take integer values ordered by importance. Therefore, the indicators used to describe a concept are discrete variables.</p><p>Latent variables are always continuous variables due to they are linked to more than one indicator.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 2. Endogeneous and Exogeneous Variables</head><p>As shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, the first latent variable (Latent Variable 1) is linked to the observed variables (Question 1, Question 2, and Question 3) which are composed of the questions answered in the research questionnaire. As seen in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, the observed variables and latent variables are connected to each other in a reflective way.</p><p>In the same way, the observed variables of the second dimension (Question 4, Question 5 ve Question 6) in the conceptual model of the research are connected to another latent variable (Latent Variable 2). The direction of the arrows connecting the observed variables and the hidden variables is important.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 3. Symbols in Structural Equation Models</head><p>Again referring to the examples in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, the quadrangular symbols indicate the observed variables, while the elliptical symbols represent the predicted latent variables (this book is based on the notation used in the AMOS program). Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> shows the meanings of the most commonly used symbols in structural equation models.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Endogeneous and Exogeneous Variables</head><p>Variables in the structural equation modeling, except for the distinction between latent and observed, are dealt with in two groups: endogeneous and exogeneous. In structural equation modeling, the Endogeneous Exogeneous distinction is used as a more accurate distinction because a variable can assume the role of both the dependent variable and the independent variable at the same time. Endogeneous variables are dependent variables explained by other variables. In Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, the variables Z, W and T are endogeneous variables. Exogeneous variables are independent variables that are not explained by any variables. In Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, the variables X and Y are external variables. If there are more than one exogeneous variable, covariance between these variables is required. As shown in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, a bi-directional arrow is placed between the X and Y latent variables. It should not be forgotten to add an error term to the endogeneous variables. The terms Res1, Res2 and Res3, which appear in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, represent the residuals of each endogeneous variable. These residuals are also called as error terms of the structural model. The error terms in the measurement model are shown in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> by the notation 'e'. The error terms in both groups are usually marked with a separate notation in this way. Unlike regression models, structural equality models are based on the covariance matrix. But it mainly consists of the system of linear equations. Therefore, the linear equations of the model in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> can be written as:</p><p>( As shown in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, there are 3 endogeneous (dependent) variables, and the above three equations are written. The residual term of the first equation named as Res1, the residual term of the second and third equation named as Res2 and Res3 respectively. The coefficients of residual terms are fixed as '1'. β coefficients are free parameters. The variables to the left of the above equations are dependent variables, while the ones to the right are independent variables. There is another point of interest in equations. W and Z variables are dependent variables in the first and second equations while they play an independent role in the third equation. In the group of these equations only the variables X and Y are always independent. This is because X and Y variables are exogeneous variables as seen in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>. And the variables T, W and Z are endogeneous variables. Again as seen in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>., residual error of each latent variable correspond to the residual term of each regression equation in which the latent variable has the dependent variable role. Residual terms mainly represent variance that can not be explained by factor <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Kline, 2011)</ref>. The square root of the variance equals to the standard deviation. This value represents how far or near the distribution of the values in a serial from the mean. If the standard deviation is small, the values are scattered close to the serial average.</p><p>Measurement errors of the observed variables that form the latent variable are symbolized by "e" notation. Once again, the superiorities of structural equation modelling are that more than one regression analysis can be conducted at the same time and take into account the measurement errors in the observed variables when doing so. For this reason, it can also be regarded as a simultaneous equation system. The three regression equations described above are equations for the structural model. However, as already mentioned, the structural equation model consists of two parts, the measurement model and the structural model. In the example in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, there are 15 more regression equations in the measurement model as seen below:</p><p>( In these above equations, each observed variable is a dependent variable. Latent variables are independent variables. This is due to the fact that the observed variables and the latent variables are connected in a reflective way in the measurement model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Parameters</head><p>There are three kinds of parameters in structural equation models. These are called free, fixed and constrained parameters. Free parameters are parameters for which no value is assigned and whose value is to be estimated. Fixed parameters are parameters with a specific value, such as 0 or 1. Constrained parameters are estimated parameters depending on value of other parameters <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Raykov &amp; Marcoulides, 2006)</ref>.</p><p>In Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, the estimated total number of parameters in equations in both the structural model and the measurement model is 21. Of these, 6 are the regression coefficients forming the structural model and indicated by the β symbol, 15 are the factor loads of the measurement model and are indicated by the λ symbol. In order to estimate the parameters included in the structural equation model given in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, it is seen that a total of 21 regression models are working together at the same time. The assumption of regression, which is a prerequisite for each regression, needs to be provided. Therefore, the assumptions that apply to the regression models apply within the structural equation models.</p><p>These are the assumptions of linearity, normal distribution of error terms (normality), lack of multicollinearity, constant variance of error terms (homoscedasticity), and no relation among error terms (authocorrelation). The assumptions about structural equation modeling will be explained in section 2.6.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.">Fit Indices</head><p>In the method of structural equation modeling, the measures that assess the compliance of the models with the data are called fit indices or fit statistics. There are many fit indices in the literature. Below there are definitions of the most commonly used of these fit indices. The size of the sample should be considered in the analyzes to be done by the structural equation modeling. Because many of the fit indices are affected by sample size. The minimum sample size that must be used in the structural equation modeling method is at least 10 times the number of parameters that can be estimated in the model <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Jayaram, Kannan, &amp; Tan, 2004)</ref>. In addition, the minimum sample size for structural equation modeling is suggested as 150 <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Bentler &amp; Chou, 1987)</ref>. Some researchers suggest that the sample size for Structural Equation Models should be 200-500, at least 200 <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Çelik &amp; Yılmaz, 2013)</ref>.</p><p>CMIN is the likelihood ratio chi-square test. This test shows the correspondence between the proposed model and the actual model and it is most commonly used fit indice. As a result of this test, it is evaluated whether the covariance matrix of the sample with which the model is tested is equal to the population covariance matrix. Furthermore, since this test is a difference test, it is not desirable that chi-square value is significant. The fact that the CMIN / DF ratio is less than 3 and the chi-square value is insignificant indicates that the model's overall fit is within acceptable limits <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">(Meydan &amp; Şen, 2011)</ref>. The DF, ie the degree of freedom, is calculated from the number of observations in a model and number of the parameters needed estimation. Assumed that the number of observed variable in a models equals p. In this model, the estimated number of parameters can not be more than p(p+1)/2. In this case, the degree of freedom is found as follows <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Raykov &amp; Marcoulides, 2006)</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Bayram, 2013)</ref>.  <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Bayram, 2013)</ref>.</p><p>RMSEA is a measure of fit that compares the mean differences of each expected degree of freedom that can occur in the population with each other. This scale is adversely affected by sample size. A value of 0.05 or less for the RMSEA fit indice indicates good fit <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Bayram, 2013)</ref>. Values between 0.05 and 0.08 indicate acceptable fit <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Byrne, 2010)</ref>.</p><p>NFI <ref type="bibr">(Normed Fit Index)</ref>  The CMIN (chi-square likelihood ratio) value appears to be significant when the P value is 0,000 in the example below. However, this test is required to be insignificant since it is a difference test. However, in most cases this value is significant. This may be due to the neglect of some of the assumptions of structural equation modeling described in the next section as general practice during analyzes. In addition to the fit indices described above, there are also indices used for model comparison. These are called model comparison adaptation indices. AIC (Akaike Information Criterion) is one of them. In the compared models the one which has lowest AIC value is considered as the closest model to reality <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Karagöz, 2016)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.">Assumptions of Structural Equation Modeling</head><p>Similar to regression analysis, structural equation modeling has its assumptions. But in structural equality models, many regression equations work together, whether in the structural model part or in the measurement model part. Therefore, the assumptions that apply to the regression models are valid for the structural equation models. As these assumptions are known, linearity, that is, the relationship between dependent and independent variables is linear, normal distribution of error terms (normality), no multicollinearity which means independent variables are not related to each other, the variance of error terms is fixed (homoscedasticity) or in other words there is no relationship between independent variables and error terms ve no authocorrelation that means that there is no relationship between error terms <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">(Wooldridge, 2003)</ref>. If these assumptions are met, it should be considered whether the assumptions required for the structural equation models are also met. These assumptions can be summarized as follows <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Bayram, 2013)</ref>.</p><p>x Observed variables have multivariate normality:</p><p>The multivariate normal distribution is the most important assumption of the maximum likelihood estimation method used in structural equation modeling. This rule is often violated when ordinal and discrete scales are used. Neglecting the assumption of multivariate normal distribution of observed variables leads to a high CMIN / DF value and a significant test outcome. In case of violation of this assumption, it is recommended to use the estimation methods such as weighted least squares (WLS) instead of the maximum likelihood estimation method. This method can be used if the data is continuous but does not meet the normal distribution requirement. Other prediction methods that may be preferred in this case are ADF (asymptotically distribution free), MLM (Robust Maximum Likelihood) and GLS (generalized least squares) <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">(Tabachnick &amp; Fidell, 2001)</ref>. As the complexity level of the model tested in the structural equation modeling method increases, the number of sample observations must also be increased. However, as the distribution of the data becomes farther away from the normal distribution, it is necessary to increase the number of data <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Kline, 2011)</ref>.</p><p>The skewness and kurtosis values are examined to determine whether the variables in the data set are normally distributed. These values are calculated on the basis of moments. In general, the packaged softwares calculate these values to be 0 as base value. In this case values between -2 and +2 are considered normal. In addition, Kolmogorov-Smirnov and Shapiro-Wilk tests can be conducted to test whether the data set is normally distributed <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">(Sarstedt &amp; Mooi, 2014)</ref>.</p><p>In cases where the data set does not fit the normal distribution, the outliers (extreme values) should be cleared first. In AMOS program in analysis properties window in output tab, normality and outliers can be tested. It is sufficient to mark the "test for normality" and "outliers" options so that these test values can be obtained in a tabular form.</p><p>Additionally in SPSS, outliers can be determined by examining the Mahalonobis distance value. If the dataset is not normally distributed, what can be done is covered in the last section of this book.</p><p>x Latent variables have multivariate normal distribution:</p><p>It refers to the endogeneous latent variables have normal distribution. In practice, it is a violated assuption.</p><p>x Linearity:</p><p>As stated at the beginning of the book, structural equation modeling is a component of factor and regression analysis. Therefore, linearity, which is the most important assumption of regression analysis, also applies to structural equation modeling. In the structural equation model, it is assumed that there are linear relationships between latent variables and also between observed and latent variables.</p><p>x Absence of outliers:</p><p>The outlier affects the significance of the existence model negatively.</p><p>x Multiple measurements:</p><p>In the structural equation model, three or more observed variables must be used to measure each latent variable.</p><p>x No multicollinearity:</p><p>It is assumed that there is no relation between the independent variables in the structural equation model.</p><p>x Sample size:</p><p>In the structural equation modeling, many of the fit indices are influenced by sample size. In some sources, a minimum sample size of 150 is recommended for structural equation models <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Bentler &amp; Chou, 1987)</ref>. The minimum sample size that should be used in the structural equation modeling method is at least 10 times the number of parameters that can be estimated in the model. <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Jayaram, Kannan, &amp; Tan, 2004)</ref>.</p><p>According to some researchers, the sample size required for structural equation modeling should be at least 200 and 200-500 <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Çelik &amp; Yılmaz, 2013)</ref>.</p><p>x No correlation between error terms:</p><p>It is assumed that there is no correlation between error terms in the structural equation modeling method. However, if it is explicitly stated by the researcher in the conceptual model, a correlation can be made between the error terms <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Doğan, 2015)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7.">Types of Structural Equation Models</head><p>There are four basic types of structural equation models.</p><p>These are explained below:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7.1.">Path Analysis Models</head><p>In the method of structural equation modeling, the models established with only observed variables are called path analysis models. The basis of the structural equation modeling depends upon path analysis. Path analyzes first started to be implemented in the 1920s. Developed by biologist Sewall Wright <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(Taşkın &amp; Akat, 2010)</ref>. The path analysis is similar to multiple regression as it is done with observed variables. But it is superior than multiple regression. Because there is one dependent variable in the multiple regression. However, there may be more than one dependent variable in the path analysis, and a variable can be both a dependent variable and an independent variable. In path analyzes, more than one regression model can be analyzed at the same time, and indirect and direct effects can be measured at the same time.</p><p>Direct effect is the effect of one variable on another variable without any mediation. However, the indirect effect arises from the intervention of a variable which is playing mediator role between independent and dependent variables. This variable is named as the mediator variable. The sum of the direct effect and the indirect effect of a variable on another variable is called the total effect <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Raykov &amp; Marcoulides, 2006)</ref>. Since path analyzes do not contain latent variables, they can not be saved from measurement errors <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">(Meydan &amp; Şen, 2011)</ref>. For this reason, structural regression models generated by latent variables give more accurate results. Because structural regression models include measurement model. Path analysis models and examples will be discussed in more detail in chapter 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7.2.">Confirmatory Factor Analysis Models</head><p>Factor analysis is divided into two types as exploratory and confirmatory. In explanatory factor analysis, factors are revealed from relations among variables. In explanatory factor analysis, the observed variables can be loaded on any factor or on multiple factors. However, in the confirmatory factor analysis, the theoretically predetermined factor structure is confirmed by the current data. In other words, in the confirmatory factor analysis, which factor will be loaded on an observed variable is predetermined. By means of the explanatory factor analysis, the latent variables are revealed from the observed variables. However, in the confirmatory factor analysis, previously discovered scales are confirmed again with the collected data. In Section 3, examples of firstlevel one-factor, first-level multi-factor and second-level multifactor confirmatory factor analysis are included.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7.3.">Structural Regression Models</head><p>It is regression models formed between latent variables in structural equation models. It consists of a combination of measurement model and structural model. Incorporating the measurement model and the structural model allows the inclusion of measurement errors so that more accurate results can be obtained. In other words, confirmatory factor analysis and multiple regression analysis coexist. Structural regression models will be discussed in more detail in Section 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7.4.">Latent Change Models</head><p>They are also named as "latent change models", "latent growth curve models" or "latent curve analysis". Models that describe longitudinal variation in time series <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Raykov &amp; Marcoulides, 2006)</ref>. These models are the models used to explain the growth and decay of an event over time, similarities or differences within and between units. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Doğan, 2015)</ref>. In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">4</ref>, two factorial growth models are observed for two time points (T1, T2  (1) Describe observed and unobserved vertical section data.</p><p>(2) Characterize the development of individuals and groups.</p><p>(3) To predict individual and group differences in developmental forms.</p><p>(4) To examine the dynamic determinants among variables in time.</p><p>(5) To reveal the group differences of the dynamic determinants between variables in time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">VALIDITY AND RELIABILITY ANALYSIS</head><p>Scale is the method used to find the numerical values of the dimensions that constitute a concept. Since concepts can not be directly measured in social sciences, questionnaires are formed to define these concepts. Reliability means that a scale is always measure the same value under the same conditions consistently. For example, a questionnaire form is reliable if the same group is given the same result when applied two different times. So if we ask the same questions about the same people, if the conditions are not changed, they are expected to give the same answers. Otherwise, this means that the persons in the sample either they did not understand the questions on the questionnaire or they did not read them.</p><p>Validity is a measure of what we really want to measure. For example, if a questionnaire actually measures a different concept than the dimension we want to measure, it is not valid. If the questions we ask about the concept A are confused with the questions about the concept B, then it means that the concepts we consider to measure are not perceived or perceived as different from those in the sample.</p><p>In this case, the scale we use is not a valid measurement tool for this sample. For this reason, it is necessary to test the validity and reliability of the scale before any analysis is started.</p><p>As a result of these tests, verification of unidimensionality is generally provided. Unidimensionality means that the observed variables used to measure each dimension must measure only one dimension <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Avcılar &amp; Varinli, 2013)</ref>. Construct validity and reliability must be determined in order to confirm unidimensionality. In a theoretically determined model, construct validity refers to convergence of observed variables that are connected to the same latent variable (convergent validity) and dissociation of observed variables from other observed variables that are connected to other latent variables (discriminant validity). The construct validity indicates that the observed variables do not measure any latent variable other than they connected in the conceptual model. But in this case it would not be correct to say that the validity of the construct is fully realized without confirming the reliability of the scale <ref type="bibr">(Gerbing &amp; Anderson, 1988)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Determination of Convergent Validity</head><p>Convergent validity indicates that the correlations between questions constituting a construct are high. In structural equation modeling method, it is necessary to look at the results of confirmatory factor analysis to determine the convergent validity of the scales used to measure the dimensions constituting the conceptual model of the research. The standard value of each coefficient in the measurement model is the factor loadings of the confirmatory factor analysis. Each factor load should be higher than 0.50. Otherwise, the fit indices of the general model will be adversely affected. The fact that the factor loads are above 0,5 is evidence of convergent validity. If the critical rate value of a question in CFA results is greater than 2 as an absolute value this means that this item is loaded to the factor it is connected.</p><p>In structural equation modeling method, while the CFA model is set, some parameters are freed while some are fixed. As shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5</ref>, Parameter of question 1 and parameters of error terms are fixed by assigning 1 value. Others are fixed.</p><p>The freed parameters will be estimated by the program.</p><p>Before applying confirmatory factor analysis (CFA), it is first necessary to look at the results of explanatory factor analysis (EFA) in practice. Even though scales generally accepted in the literature are used, to see if the survey fillers correctly perceive the questions principle component analysis should be conducted in SPSS before set up CFA model in AMOS. And how many different dimensions the questions are perceived by those who solve the questionnaire should be clarified.</p><p>At this stage, the necessary questions should be eliminated. This step is also called the purification stage. Principle component analysis is a type of analysis that assigns the variables in the data set into groups so that the relationship between the variables in the group is maximized. Main purpose of this analysis is to obtain the least number of factors to represent the relationship among items at the highest level. In this way, it tests whether the sample size is sufficient to perform principle component analysis. Values above 0.7 are considered good. If it is below 0.5, factor analysis can not be continued <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Karagöz, 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Essentially, principle component analysis is done to determine scale validity, but it also fulfills the purpose of making the data set analyzable. It fulfills the following functions for this (Aksu, Eser, &amp; Güzeller, 2017):</p><p>-To remove the dependency between variables.</p><p>-To obtain fewer new variables those are not related to each other. After conducting explanatory factor analysis and purification by principle component analysis, the remaining indicators (questions) are linked under the structures they belong to and the CFA model is created in the AMOS program as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5</ref> (The principle component analysis performed in the SPSS program is not explained because it is out of scope of this book). The number of factors is freed in EFA. In CFA, the number of factors and which indicators are connected is determined in advance.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">4</ref> shows the way in which confirmatory factor analysis results are given. What is important here is that the standard factor loads of the questions under each conceptual variable are over 0.50. By looking at this table, questions with a standard factor load of less than 0.50 are discarded.</p><p>In this case factor analysis is done again. Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref> shows a second-order CFA model. It is important to note here that residual terms are to be placed in the first-level latent variables (Res1, Res2 and Res3). Figure <ref type="figure">9</ref> shows another second-level multi-factor CFA model. The difference of this model is that there are more than one factor in the second level. Since there are more than one exogeneous variables, covariance is placed between the second level latent variables (between A and B).</p><p>The fit indices of the CFA model are then tabulated. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">6</ref> shows the analysis features that must be marked in the Analysis Properties window before running the CFA model in the AMOS program. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7</ref> shows the first-order multifactor CFA model. In this case it must be considered to place covariance between the latent variables. The rule of placing covariance between exogeneous variables is also valid here. In Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>, covariance is not placed when there is only one exogeneous variable. However Figure <ref type="figure">9</ref> shows covariance between two exogeneous variables.  Another indicator of convergent validity is the Average Variance Extracted (AVE) value. To be able to confirm the convergent validity, it must be more than 0.50 or 0.50. <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Fornell &amp; Larcker, 1981)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Determination of Discriminant Validity</head><p>Discriminant validity is the measure of the level at which a structure in a measurement model differs from other structures. It is an indicator of a low correlation between the questions that form a construct and other questions that form other construct. To find the discriminant validity for each dimension, we first need to calculate the Average Variance Extracted (AVE) value for each dimension. The acceptable AVE value must be greater than 0.50 or 0.50. However, as noted in the previous section, this value confirms convergent validity when examined alone <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Fornell &amp; Larcker, 1981)</ref>. In order to determine discriminant validity, it is also desirable that the values of the AVE for each construct in the data set are larger than the correlation coefficients of that construct with the other constructs. In this case, it can be determined that the scales used have discriminant validity for each dimension. AVE value alone does not indicate discriminant validity but the square root of the AVE value of each construct is larger than the inter-dimensional correlation value it can be said that there is discriminant validity <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Fornell &amp; Larcker, 1981)</ref>. In Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">5</ref>, the values shown in parentheses as crosswise is the square root of the AVE values. For the 9 dimensions in the table, the square root of the AVE values in each column is higher than the correlation coefficients in that column. In addition, the AVE values are above the 0.50 threshold. In this case, it can be said that the scales used for this example have discriminant validity. The AVE value is not calculated by the AMOS package program. However, it is easy to find ready-made excel files that provide this value calculation on the internet.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Determination of Reliability</head><p>After determination of the validity of the scales by means of CFA reliability analysis must be conducted for each construct. First of all, Cronbach's α value is calculated for each dimension separately. Values greater than 0.7 threshold indicate that the internal reliability of the scale used is sufficient. Cronbach's α is a measure based on correlations between items in a consruct. It is obtained by dividing the sum of the variances of the items constituting a scale by the general variance. It takes a value between 0 and 1. Values beyond 0.7 threshold indicate that the scale is reliable. If it is below 0.6, the reliability of the scale is low. <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Karagöz, 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Another value that is used to calculate the reliability of the scale for each dimension is the composite reliability value. The composite reliability value is calculated from the factor loads found in the confirmatory factor analysis. After CR values beyond 0.7 threshold or equals to 0.7 it can be said that there is composite reliability <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Raykov, 1997)</ref>.  There are statistically significant relationships among the constructs in the sample in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">5</ref>. Correlation is the coefficient that indicates the power of linear relationship between variables. This coefficient must be statistically significant in order to be able to say that there is a relationship between variables. The correlation coefficient takes a value between -1 and +1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">(Sipahi, Yurtkoru, &amp; Çinko, 2010)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">STRUCTURAL REGRESSION MODEL</head><p>As a result of the processes described above, convergence validity and discriminant validity are determined. Then the phase for forming the structural model begins.  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">10</ref> shows the properties to be marked in the analysis properties menu in the AMOS program when starting the path analysis. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_13">6</ref>     These examples are called structural regression models.</p><p>Although the models in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">11</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">12</ref> are based on the same measurement model, the path analysis created is different. In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">11</ref>, there are more than one exogenous variable and therefore covariance is placed between them. In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">12</ref> there is only one exogeneous variable. In both models residual terms are linked to the endogeneous variables.</p><p>Careful attention should be paid to these rules when constructing structural models. Otherwise the model will not work. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">PATH ANALYSIS</head><p>Structural model can be established by directly observed variables in cases factor analysis is done before and the average of the questions that make up the constructs or when working with the secondary data. Such models are called as path analysis. Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">13</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">14</ref> show the models constructed in Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">11</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">12</ref>, respectively, with the observed variables.</p><p>As seen in the figures, covariance and residuals remained the same in the models. This is because the rules are the same in the path analyzes made with the observed variables. But the measurement models are gone. Therefore, it is assumed that there are no measurement errors in the path analysis.</p><p>Predictive error terms are included in dependent variables. Before running the path analysis in the AMOS program, the options in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">10</ref> should be checked in the analysis properties window. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">MODEL MODIFICATION</head><p>If the fit indices of the structural model do not come to an adequate level, the AMOS program suggests modifications to the user. These modifications improve fit indices. For example, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">15</ref> shows the modifications suggested under the Modification Indices menu in the AMOS program. In the case of placing covariance among those with the highest value among the proposed changes in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">13</ref>, the model's fit indices will improve. Because the modification index value corresponds to the decrease in the chi-square value of the model. However, these covariances are not to be considered as unrelated concepts in the literature that should be taken into account when setting. Because each modification changes the conceptual model which is first introduced. It should be noted that the changes made by this reason do not contradict the purpose of the research and the relations in the literature.</p><p>To reach the modification indices, the modification indices box in the analysis properties window in the AMOS program must be marked as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">10</ref>. In the example shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">15</ref>, first the model is run again by adding covariance between the error terms e24 and e22 and compared with the previous situation. Because the highest modification value in the table is 17.457, which is between e24 and e22. After the modifications are made, the model is retested, and if sufficient compliance values can not be obtained, the proposed modifications can be repeated. Again, modifications made should be consistent with the literature. Unrepeatable and inappropriate modifications made are scientifically unacceptable and result in inconsistent situations with the population. For this reason, it is necessary to apply it very carefully. Just in order to raise the fit indices, covariance should not be placed between concepts that are not related to each other.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 15. AMOS Modification Indices</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">MEDIATOR VARIABLE ANALYSIS METHODOLOGY</head><p>The variable starting the causality relation between the independent and the dependent variable is called as mediator variable <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">(Wu &amp; Zumbo , 2008)</ref>. It is also called as intervening variable <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">(MacKinnon, Lockwood, Hoffman, West, &amp; Sheets, 2002)</ref>. It can also be defined as the variable that transfers the indirect effect of an independent variable to the dependent variable. Analysis of mediator variable is based on the hierarchical regression method introduced by <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Baron and Kenny in 1986.</ref> In order to apply this method, the following conditions must first be met <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Baron &amp; Kenny, 1986</ref>) : a. The changes that occur in the independent variable cause a change in the mediator variable, b. Changes in the mediator variable cause changes in the dependent, c. If the mediator and independent variables are together included in the regression analysis, the effect of the independent variable on the dependent variable either falls or completely ceases.</p><p>In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">16</ref>, there is a sample mediator variable model. After this model is created, it is first checked whether there is a correlation between all variables. It is thus tested whether the model meets the first two preconditions put forward by Baron and Kenny. Table <ref type="table">7</ref> shows an example of correlation table. Once the three regression models given above are run separately, the results found are compared as seen in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_15">8</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 16. Mediator Variable Model and Hypotheses Table 7. Example of Correlation Coefficient</head><p>As shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_15">8</ref>, when the B variable is added in model 3, the coefficient of the relationship between A and C is lowered and turns to be insignificant. This indicates that the variable B has mediator role in the relationship between variable A and variable C. As a result, hypotheses H 1 , H 2 , H 3 and H 4 are accepted. In this way, the Baron and Kenny method can be easily applied in the SPSS program in the presence of a third variable that plays a role of mediator variable between the two variables. Structural equation modeling can be used in mediator variable analysis when testing multiple mediator variables or multiple independent or dependent variables. For example, in the conceptual model shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">17</ref>, there are two mediator variables.</p><p>In the same way, The Baron and Kenny method is applied while the analysis of the mediator variables is done in the structural equality models. For this reason, once the model is constructed, first, it is checked whether there is a correlation among all variables. It is thus tested whether the model meets the first two preconditions put forward by Baron and Kenny. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_17">9</ref> shows an example of correlation table. When an mediator analysis is performed, the three different models shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">18</ref>, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">19</ref>, and Figure <ref type="figure">20</ref> below are run in AMOS and the coefficients of the models are compared against each other. Table <ref type="table">10</ref> shows an example of a table comparing the β coefficients found after running models in AMOS.</p><p>As shown in Table <ref type="table">10</ref>, the coefficient β for the relationship between A and D, which is significant and high in Model 1, has fallen and become insignificant with the inclusion of the variables B and C in Model 3. In this case, the mediator role of B and C are found statistically significant.</p><p>In addition, fit indices of each model tested should be given. Therefore Table <ref type="table">10</ref> shows the fit indices of each model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 17. Two Mediator Conceptual Model and Its Hypotheses</head><p>For scientific validation of mediator variable roles, these fit indices must also be within acceptable limits. This method can be applied to more variables. The basic logic of this analysis is the comparison of the coefficients of the model to which the mediator variables are not included and the coefficients of the next model to which the mediator variables are included.  If the statistically significant coefficients become insignificant, the role of intermediate variable is confirmed. If the p value of the coefficient remains significant but there is a serious decrease in the coefficient, it can be said that there is semimediator effect. In the conceptual model in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">17</ref>, the mediator roles of B and C can be tested together. But if needed, these variables can be included to analyses one by one.   The AMOS program is a program that works together with the SPSS program. For this reason, it is first necessary to contact the SPSS file containing the data to be worked on before starting the model drawing. For this, File → Data Files menus are followed and the window that appears in Figure <ref type="figure">23</ref> opens. In this screen, click the File Name menu to select the relevant file and click OK to close the window. In this way, the AMOS file is linked to the data to be run.</p><p>When starting to draw the model after this step, firstly the indicator symbol is pressed to draw the hidden variable and the three observed variables (indicator) which are shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">24</ref>.  The data set icon is pressed and the observed variables in the data set are listed. The variables found in this list can be linked to the indicators by means of drag and drop method. Select each latent variable and click on the right mouse button and select the object property from the pop-up menu and write the names of the F1, F2 and F3 factors appearing in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">25</ref>.</p><p>After that, by pressing error symbol to add residual to endogeneous variable. Finally, the plugins → Name Unobserved Variables menus are followed and the variable name is assigned to the error term of each indicator and the residue term of the endogeneous variable. Therefore, in the model shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">25</ref>, error names from e1 to e10 are automatically assigned by the program. Right click on the variables on the screen, and when the object properties is selected in the drop-down menu, the window shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">26</ref> opens. In this window in text tab, variable names can be assigned.</p><p>In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">25</ref>, F1, F2, F3 and R1 variable names are assigned in this way. In this tab, the font size can be adjusted. In this window in the parameters tab, it is possible to assign the values of parameters which is desired to be kept constant in the model. F1 and F2 are exogeneous variables. Due to the fact that between them covariance is inserted by using the symbol . F3 is endogeneous variable. Therefore residual term (R1) is added by using the symbol . After the model is drawn, the Analysis Properties menu opens in order to select the analysis that you want to perform.</p><p>Click on the icon to open this menu. When this icon is clicked, the window shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">27</ref> opens. The options marked on the Output tab in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">27</ref> must be noted. On the Estimation tab, the Maximum likelihood option is usually selected. After the selections are made, the program is run by clicking on the icon. The special cases in which other estimation methods can be used are mentioned in previous chapters.</p><p>The items to be marked on the Output tab vary according to the properties of the analysis to be performed. For example, when performing confirmatory factor analysis, the factor score weights option should be marked. After running the analyzes, click the icon to view the results on the model. Click on the view text icon to view the results in tabular form.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 26. Object Properties Window Text Tab</head><p>When this icon is clicked, the screen shown in Figure <ref type="figure">28</ref> opens. For this window to be opened separately, the results can be viewed both in text format and on the model at the same time as shown in  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.">SAMPLE OF MEDIATOR VARIABLE ANALYSIS</head><p>In Section 7, we focused on the methodology of mediator variable analysis. Mediator analysis methodology is based on the hierarchical regression method introduced by Baron and Kenny in 1986 <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Baron &amp; Kenny, 1986)</ref>. The structural equation modeling method allows analysis of direct and indirect relations together, so the application of the Baron and Kenny method in the structural equation model provides an advantage especially when there are more than one mediator variable in the conceptual model.</p><p>In Section 7, how the mediator analysis methodology is applied is described both by regression analysis method and by structural equation modeling method. In the case of mediator variable analysis in the structural equation modeling, a real research example is summarized below in order that the reader can better understand the way the tables are given <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Civelek, İnce, &amp; Karabulut, 2016)</ref>. The literature section of the research is not given and only the parts enough to understand the method are given.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.1.">Title of the Research</head><p>Mediator role of attitude towards site in the relationship between system quality and net benefit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.2.">Purpose</head><p>The aim of this research is to determine the role of users' attitudes towards the site and satisfaction levels in system quality which was found to have a positive impact on net benefit in previous research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.3.">Conceptual Model and Scales</head><p>While constructing the conceptual model, the models developed in previous researches measuring the success of information systems were used.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 30. Conceptual Model</head><p>The scale developed by Wu and Wang in 2006 was used to measure the net benefit dimension <ref type="bibr" target="#b74">(Wu &amp; Wang, 2006)</ref>. Scales developed by Chen et al. In 2013 were used to measure other dimensions <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Chen, Rungruengsamrit, Rajkumar, &amp; Yen, 2013</ref>). The scales were measured according to the five-point Likert scale. The conceptual model of the research is shown in Figure <ref type="figure">30</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.4.">Determination of Validity and Reliability</head><p>Confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) was performed to determine the construct validity of the scales used. The fit indice values of the CFA model were found satisfactory: χ2/DF =3.790, CFI=0.920, IFI=0.921, RMSEA= 0.083. Table <ref type="table">10</ref> shows the standard factor loadings of the confirmatory factor model. The standard factor loads are above 0,50 and the fit indices are close to the threshold values. Therefore the convergent validity of the scales is determined.</p><p>The AVE (Avarage Variance Extracted) values given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_20">12</ref> are above the 0.50 threshold and the square root of the AVE values is greater than the correlation values in that column for each dimension. Therefore the discriminant validity of the scales is determined.</p><p>In addition, Cronbach α and Composite Reliability values are above the threshold value of 0.70, indicating the reliability of the scales used. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.5.">Analysis Results</head><p>Three separate models have been analyzed as described in Chapter 7. The analysis results of three different models are compared in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_21">13</ref>. In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">31</ref>, the results of the analysis of model 3 are given as an image.  As shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_21">13</ref>, in the first model, the regression coefficient of the relationship between system quality and net benefit is statistically significant and quite high. However, in the third model, when the relationship includes user satisfaction and attitude toward site dimension, the coefficient of the relationship decreases and it turns out to be statistically insignificant. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.6.">Conclusion</head><p>As a result, this research shows that the quality of the system has no direct effect on the net benefit perceptions of the users. The system quality indirectly affects the net benefit perception. In other words, the relation between the system quality and the net benefit perception user satisfaction and attitudes of the users towards the site play mediator role. This means: Increasing the quality of the system primarily increases the satisfaction of users and improves their attitude towards the site. In the end, user satisfaction and attitude, which turned into positive, increase the net benefit perception.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.">MULTITRAIT-MULTIMETHOD MODEL</head><p>In some cases, nested structures can be found. In other words, some scale questions can be designed to measure nested concepts at the same time. As an example, assume that a scale to measure teachers' competence in a school has been developed. On this scale, there are questions that measure the social, academic and English competence of the teachers. The questions were asked to the same number of groups of students and colleagues. In this example, there is a structure consisting of three features and two separate methods as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">32</ref>, the best method that can be used to determine the construct validity of such models is Multitrait-Multimethod Model. As shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">32</ref>, there are two separate questions asked to two different groups. In the model shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">32</ref>, social, academic and English competences are the traits and students and peers are the methods.</p><p>In the model there are as many questions as the multiplication of the numbers of traits and methods. Multitrait-Multimethod Model was first proposed by Campbell and Fiske in a paper published in 1959.</p><p>Although different alternatives have been proposed over time models based on covariance structure became important <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Byrne, 2010)</ref>. Construct validity, according to Campbell and Fiske, focused on the determination of the convergent validity, which expresses the correlation of the components that make up, the discriminant validity, which expresses low degree of correlation with the components constituting other constructs and method effect, which is an extension of discriminant validity <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Campbell &amp; Fiske, 1959)</ref>. The method effect can be defined as the bias that results from using the same method to evaluate different properties <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Byrne, 2010)</ref>.</p><p>In Figure <ref type="figure">33</ref>, there is a larger example that will provide a better understanding of Multitrait-Multimethod Model. In the figure, there is an assumption model of this example. In Figure <ref type="figure">33</ref>, there are 7 traits as X, Y, V, W, Z, T, U and methods as A, B, C, D, E. Therefore, a scale consisting of questions was used. The notation of ",1" on the latent variables forming traits and methods indicates that the factor variance is fixed at 1 (The another notation "1," indicates that the factor averages are fixed at 1). This is a symbolic notation, and comma notation does not appear in the AMOS program, it looks as seen in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">35</ref>. To fix the variance of a hidden variable in the AMOS program, enter the value in the variance box under the "Parameter" tab in the "Object Properties" dialog box which opened by right mouse button on selected variable. When we look at the parameter summaries in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">14</ref>, it is seen that the variances of 12 variables are kept constant.</p><p>It is also seen that the variance of 35 error terms obtained as a result of estimation is released. 70 regression coefficients were estimated and 35 regression coefficients belongs to the error terms were fixed. Therefore, there are a total of 105 regression weights. In this case, when the fixed regression weights and latent variable variances are evaluated together, it is seen that 47 parameters are kept constant. There are totally parameters in the whole model.   <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">36</ref> appears. The reason for this warning is that there are no covariances among all the exogeneous variables. In this case, "proceed with the analysis" should be selected and continued. In some cases, the error terms get negative values when the model is run. In this case, a post hoc model is created as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">37</ref>.</p><p>In this model, Var (a) value is assigned in order to fix the negative error term. The assignment of value Var(a) is also made in alternative models created for comparison with Model 1. Note that the same value assignment is shown in Figure <ref type="figure">38</ref>.-39.-40. For this reason this model is called as perfectly correlated traits; freely correlated methods. In Model 4, there is no covariance between methods. In Model 1, which is the model where the correlations between traits and methods are free, calculated correlation values are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_24">18</ref>. In the Multitrait-Multimethod models approach, analyzes are performed at the matrix level and the parameter level to test the construct validity (both convergent and discriminant validity).</p><p>In matrix level analysis, comparison of fit indices of alternative models with model 1 is made. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_22">15</ref> shows the values of fit indices of each model. Factor loads are expected to be significant. the Multitrait-Multimethod models, four models are formed as described above. There is a need for a model that is free from bias in these models. In this case, correlated uniqueness model can be established. In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">41</ref>, correlated uniqueness model is shown.</p><p>First, it is checked whether the fit indices of the model are within the acceptable range. In this model, the factor loads must be significant in order to confirm the construct validity.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="11.">METHODS TO BE APPLIED IN CASE OF DATA INADEQUACY</head><p>Sometimes, there may be cases where the assumptions of the estimation methods used are not met by the existing data set. In this case, there are methods that can be applied if it is necessary to be satisfied with the dataset available. Leading methods among them are bootstrap partial least sequare.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="11.1.">Bootstrap Method</head><p>The bootstrap technique is applied when one of the assuptions of normal distribution or being continuous variable is not met. This method was developed by B. <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Efron in 1979</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Efron, 1979)</ref>. In many studies in the literature the condition of normal distribution obligation is neglected. It is also seen in many studies in the literature that X 2 value is derived by maximum likelihood and generalized least squares methods. Estimation methods which are frequently used in the structural equation model are these two methods. In particular, with the non-normal distribution, the number of observations is also low cause X 2 value to increase. At the same time, irreversible and inadequate modifications made during the analysis of such data are not scientifically acceptable and result in inconsistent estimations about the population. In the bootstrap method, a different data set is obtained from the existing observations <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">(Sacchi, 1998)</ref>. This method is basically the derivation of the sample from the sample.</p><p>There are advantages and limitations of the bootstrap process.</p><p>The main advantage of the bootstrap technique is the ability to evaluate the accuracy of the predicted parameters. The idea underlying the bootstrap technique is to create sub-samples of the current data and look at the distribution of the parameters computed from each sub-sample.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 42. Bootstrap Properties Window</head><p>There are various criticisms in the literature about the correctness of the results obtained with this technique. <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Kline, 2011)</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(Ichikawa, 1995)</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b75">(Yung &amp; Bentler, 1994</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Hancock &amp; Nevitt, 1999</ref>). It's wrong to see this technique as a magical method. This method should not be used especially in small samples with low representation ability and in extreme nonnormal distribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Kline, 2011)</ref>. Because especially in small samples, there is the posibility to further enhance its properties that do not match the population <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(Rodgers, 1999)</ref>.</p><p>The AMOS program includes bootstrap analysis. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">42</ref> shows the bootstrap tab under the analysis properties window.</p><p>In this window it is initially marked that how much the bootstrap technique can be applied in the sample. The window is closed after the confidence interval and prediction method are selected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="11.2.">Partial Least Square Structural Equation Modeling ( PLS-SEM)</head><p>It is also called covariance-based structural equation modeling since the structural equation model that has been examined in the previous sections is based on the covariance matrix. However partial least square structural equation modeling is based on variance. For this reason, it is also called as the variance-based structural equation modeling. Partial least square structural equation modeling (PLS-SEM) is an advantageous method when the assumptions of least squares are not met. It is an alternative of covariance-based structural equation modeling (CB-SEM). It is a second generation multivariate analysis method that enables measurement model and structural model to be analyzed together like covariancebased structural equation modeling.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 20. Classification of Multivariate Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exploratory Confirmatory</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>First Generation Techniques</head><p>x Cluster Analysis</p><p>x Exploratory Factor Analysis</p><p>x Multidimensional Scaling</p><p>x Analysis of Variance</p><p>x Logistic Regression</p><p>x Multiple Regression</p><p>x Confirmatory Factor Analysis</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Second Generation Techniques</head><p>x Partial Least Square Structural Equation Modeling (PLS-SEM)</p><p>x Covariance-Based Structural Equation Modeling (CB-SEM)</p><p>Source: <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Hair, J., Hult, G., Ringle, C., &amp; Sarstedt, M. (2017)</ref>. A primer on partial least squares structural equation modeling PLS-SEM. Los Angeles: SAGE.</p><p>But it is not a confirmatory analysis technique like Covariance-Based Structural Equation Modeling. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">20</ref> shows the classification of multivariate methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Hair, Hult, Ringle, &amp; Sarstedt, 2017)</ref>. As shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">20</ref>, it is an exploratory analysis technic.</p><p>According to some sources in the literature, covariance-based structural equation modeling is a more powerful and reliable method. For this reason, the partial least square structural equation modeling method is generally preferred in cases where the conditions listed below are found:</p><p>• If the sample is small.</p><p>• If the data do not distribute normally.</p><p>• If the number of indicators connected to the latent variable is less than three.</p><p>• If there is a multicollinearity.</p><p>• There is missing value.</p><p>• If the number of observations is less than the number of explanatory variables.</p><p>If the above listed conditions are found, method PLS-SEM method is far superior to method CB-SEM. Because, in these cases, it reduces the unexplained variance to the lowest level.</p><p>As the model is complex, such as in the CB-SEM method, no larger sampling is required in PLS-SEM. However, some researchers who have done research on the sampling sensitivity of the PLS-SEM method have raised the ten-fold rule. According to this rule, there is a necessity to have 10 times observation of the number of indicators used to measure a construct in the measurement model and 10 times observation the number of the path in a structural model <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Barclay, Higgins, &amp; Thompson, 1995)</ref>.</p><p>However, the PLS-SEM method is a non-parametric method because it does not have any distributional assumption <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Hair, Hult, Ringle, &amp; Sarstedt, 2017)</ref>. It is also an explanatory approach, which is why it is preferred in exploratory research.</p><p>In other words, when the theory is underdeveloped, it can be said that researchers prefer to use partial least squares structural equation modeling. This judgment is partially correct in cases where the structure need to be predicted and relations need to be explained <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Rigdon, 2012)</ref>.</p><p>When the theory needs to be tested and verified, in case of there is cycles in the structural model and if the model needs to be verified in general with fit indices it is more accurate to use CB-SEM method. Because the PLS-SEM method can not explain loop-related relations. In addition, it does not give general fit indices of the model.</p><p>Partial least squares method can be easily implemented by means of a packet program called SmartPLS. SmartPLS is a packet program that allows the creation of partial least squares based structural equation models. Structural equation modeling programs outside of SmartPLS makes the maximum likelihood estimation method the default choice. Because covariance based structural equation modeling is defined by this estimation method in the literature. However, as explained in previous chapters, different estimation methods can be used in case of necessity. Therefore, the method that is most likely to be used in the covariance-based structural equation modeling should be based on a valid reason <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Kline, 2011)</ref>. This is the most important reason for criticism of PLS-SEM method. For this reason, it is necessary to make sure that all solution alternatives are exhausted if the partial least squares method is used in a research according to some sources. But there are also resources that assess them as blind and misleading criticisms, and that reveal the advantages of the partial least squares method <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Henseler, Dijkstra, Sarstedt, Ringle, Diamantopoulos, &amp; Straub, 2014)</ref>. Despite all this criticism and hesitation, the PLS-SEM method has become an increasingly used method in scientific studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Hair, Hult, Ringle, &amp; Sarstedt, 2017)</ref>.</p><p>As mentioned above, a packet program called SmartPLS is used to construct the least squares based structural equation models. The following steps describe how to build a structural equation model with SmartPLS. These descriptions are based on SmartPLS 3 version. When SmartPLS is first turned on, the screen shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">43</ref> 'opens. In order to create a new project, in the top menu "File" is selected, and after that "Create New Project" command is clicked on.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 43. SmartPLS Start Screen</head><p>When the command is clicked, the "Create Project" window shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_21">44</ref> opens. Enter the project name in the Name field of this window and press the OK button to close the window. As a result, the project name is displayed in the Project Explorer section of the main screen. Double click on "Double-click to import data" on the project name and the data set to be worked on is connected to the project. The SmartPLS program is not a SPSS-compatible program like AMOS, so it only accepts Excel files. If the data set to be used is in the SPSS program, data can be easily transferred from the SPSS to the Excel file.  The hidden variable plotted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_22">45</ref> can be easily dragged with the mouse and the variable can be renamed by right clicking on it. After all the variables are drawn in this way, paths are drawn between the hidden variables using the Connect button at the top of the screen. After the model drawing process is completed, the Calculate → PLS Algorithm command, which is located at the top of the screen, is executed. The predicted values of the path coefficients in the opened window can be obtained in matrix form or graphically.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_23">46</ref> shows the estimated values in a matrix form.  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Demarcation between Measurement Model and Structural Model Source: Byrne, B. M. (2010). Structural Equation Modeling with AMOS. New York: Routledge Taylor &amp; Francis Group.</figDesc><graphic coords="12,77.21,292.40,286.69,172.21" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Latent Change Model Example Source: Raykov, T., &amp; Marcoulides, G. (2006). A First Course in Structural Equation Modeling. Mahwah: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates.</figDesc><graphic coords="34,77.15,112.04,286.27,350.11" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Single Factor CFA Model</figDesc><graphic coords="39,77.15,50.24,286.39,158.53" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. Analysis Properties Window for CFA Models in AMOS program.</figDesc><graphic coords="42,77.51,127.28,285.79,322.09" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. Multi-Factor First-Order CFA Model</figDesc><graphic coords="43,76.91,286.82,286.81,215.65" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 11 and</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11  and Figure12show examples of structural models based on the first-level multi-factor DFA model given in Figure7.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10. Analysis Properties Window for the Structural Model in the AMOS program.</figDesc><graphic coords="51,77.51,50.66,285.61,321.37" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 11</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11. Structural Regression Model Example</figDesc><graphic coords="52,77.21,127.10,286.81,144.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 13. Example of Path Analysis</figDesc><graphic coords="53,77.21,379.64,286.50,130.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 18. Model 1</figDesc><graphic coords="62,77.21,360.44,287.29,114.31" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 19. Model 2</figDesc><graphic coords="63,77.21,248.90,287.29,266.29" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 20. Model 3</figDesc><graphic coords="65,77.21,50.36,286.69,214.63" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 21 .</head><label>21</label><figDesc>Figure 21. AMOS Startup Screen</figDesc><graphic coords="67,77.51,298.40,286.26,170.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 22. Drawing Tools in the AMOS Program</figDesc><graphic coords="69,76.91,372.50,286.93,117.79" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure 29 .</head><label>29</label><figDesc>If you click on the Model Fit tab in the menu on the left side of this screen, the values of the fit indices of the model are reached. Regression weights are reached from the Estimate tab. Modification suggestions can be obtained from the modification indices tab.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 27. Analysis Properties Window Estimation Tab</figDesc><graphic coords="75,77.51,50.60,286.20,333.01" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 31. Model 3</figDesc><graphic coords="84,77.57,50.66,286.05,172.51" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Figure 32 .</head><label>32</label><figDesc>Figure 32. Multitrait-Multimethod Model Source: Byrne, B. M. (2010). Structural Equation Modeling with AMOS. New York: Routledge Taylor &amp; Francis Group.</figDesc><graphic coords="86,77.21,50.36,286.38,274.69" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 33. Hypothesized Multitrait-Multimethod Model</figDesc><graphic coords="88,86.09,402.20,265.66,117.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 37. Post Hoc Model 1</figDesc><graphic coords="93,86.09,402.74,265.66,118.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>Figure 41 .</head><label>41</label><figDesc>Figure 41. Model 5 (Correlated Uniqueness Model)</figDesc><graphic coords="102,86.09,400.34,265.66,117.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>Figure 44 .</head><label>44</label><figDesc>Figure 44. Project Creation Screen</figDesc><graphic coords="112,77.93,248.12,285.43,181.09" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head>Figure 45 .</head><label>45</label><figDesc>Figure 45. Drawing Latent Variable</figDesc><graphic coords="113,77.93,112.70,286.82,178.57" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23"><head>Figure 46 .</head><label>46</label><figDesc>Figure 46. Coefficient Estimation Results</figDesc><graphic coords="114,77.93,50.96,286.39,145.27" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_24"><head>Figure 47 .</head><label>47</label><figDesc>Figure 47. Estimation Results</figDesc><graphic coords="115,77.93,51.08,286.11,190.09" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="16,77.21,112.04,286.50,193.39" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="17,77.21,111.92,286.38,284.53" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="54,77.21,73.70,286.32,198.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="56,114.59,104.06,208.33,433.51" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="58,77.21,112.04,286.32,194.89" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="61,77.21,249.02,287.29,212.17" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="76,77.51,50.66,285.55,319.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="77,78.11,51.26,286.38,208.45" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="79,77.21,265.46,286.32,182.29" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="89,77.21,239.60,287.29,213.91" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="91,77.93,74.36,285.61,313.81" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="106,77.51,172.46,285.79,322.09" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 . Good Fit Values Fit Indices Goodness of Fit Values</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>:</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">DF= p(p+1)/2-(number of parameters in the model)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Models with zero degree of freedom in the structural equation</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">model are called saturated models. Saturated model shows</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">perfect fit with data. Negative degree of freedom indicates that</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">the model can not be defined. The model can be defined if the</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">degree of freedom is not negative, ie zero or positive.</cell></row><row><cell>CMIN/DF</cell><cell>0 &lt;CMIN/DF&lt; 2</cell></row><row><cell>CFI</cell><cell>0,97 &lt; CFI &lt; 1</cell></row><row><cell>AGFI</cell><cell>0,90 &lt; AGFI &lt; 1</cell></row><row><cell>GFI</cell><cell>0,95 &lt; GFI &lt; 1</cell></row><row><cell>NFI</cell><cell>0,95 &lt;NFI&lt; 1</cell></row><row><cell>RMSEA</cell><cell>0 &lt; RMSEA &lt; 0,05</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Source: Bayram, N. (2013). Yapısal Eşitlik Modellemesine Giriş. Bursa: Ezgi</cell></row><row><cell>Kitapevi.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">CFI (Comparative Fit Index) is a fit indice that compares the</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">saturated model with the independent model. In the</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">independent model, there is no relationship among the</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3 . Acceptable Fit Values Fit Indices Goodness of Fit Values</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>CMIN/DF</cell><cell>2 &lt;CMIN/DF&lt; 3</cell></row><row><cell>CFI</cell><cell>0,95 &lt; CFI &lt; 0,97</cell></row><row><cell>AGFI</cell><cell>0,85 &lt; AGFI &lt; 0,90</cell></row><row><cell>GFI</cell><cell>0,90 &lt; GFI &lt; 0,95</cell></row><row><cell>NFI</cell><cell>0,90 &lt;NFI&lt; 0,95</cell></row><row><cell>RMSEA</cell><cell>0,05 &lt; RMSEA &lt; 0,08</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Source: Bayram, N. (2013). Yapısal Eşitlik Modellemesine Giriş. Bursa: Ezgi</cell></row><row><cell>Kitapevi.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">The GFI fit indice is a measure of the degree of variance and</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">covariance that is explained by the model. The value of the</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">GFI fit indice rises as the sample size increases. This feature</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">can prevent accurate results when sample size is low. The GFI</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Saturated model is the mode where the degree of freedom is zero and the data is perfectly matched to the model. For this reason, the indice values of the best model are in this line. On the bottom line there is independence model. It's the worst possible model. This line contains the worst possible indice values.</figDesc><table><row><cell>takes values between 0 and 1. Higher</cell></row><row><cell>values show better fit. Values greater than 0.90 are acceptable,</cell></row><row><cell>while values greater than 0.95 are good fit. It is in the group of</cell></row><row><cell>the fit indices based on independent model.</cell></row></table><note><p>In the "output model fit" section of the AMOS program, the model's fit indices are displayed as follows. In the following example, the values of CMIN/DF and RMSEA are acceptable. However other fit indices show a problem. In this case, indices may come up to normal values after model modifications. Fit indice values should be read from the "default model" line. Default model refers to the model being tested. On the bottom line there is the "saturated model".</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Because the scales used to measure the dimensions that make up the conceptual model will not be validated. Therefore, if the measurement model is insufficient, the fit indices of the structural model will be low. The t test results of all the coefficients in the measurement model should indicate that the coefficient values are different from zero.</figDesc><table /><note><p><p><p>The measurement model part of structural equation models correspond to confirmatory factor analysis (Confirmatory Factor Analysis -CFA). Therefore, if the measurement model fit indices are low, there is no need to test the structural model (See also</p>Figure 1. Demarcation between Measurement Model  and Structural Model)</p>.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table 4 . Results of Confirmatory Factor Analysis</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>t-Value</cell></row><row><cell>Items</cell><cell>Conceptual Variable</cell><cell>Standardized Factor Loads</cell><cell>Unstandar Factor dized</cell><cell>Standard Error</cell><cell>(Critical Ratio)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Loads</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Qestion1</cell><cell></cell><cell>0,818</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Qestion2</cell><cell>X</cell><cell>0,906</cell><cell>1,104</cell><cell>0,049</cell><cell>22,523</cell></row><row><cell>Qestion3</cell><cell></cell><cell>0,907</cell><cell>1,111</cell><cell>0,049</cell><cell>22,570</cell></row><row><cell>Qestion4</cell><cell></cell><cell>0,825</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Qestion5</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>0,732</cell><cell>0,882</cell><cell>0,057</cell><cell>15,549</cell></row><row><cell>Qestion6</cell><cell></cell><cell>0,718</cell><cell>0,885</cell><cell>0,058</cell><cell>15,187</cell></row><row><cell>Qestion7</cell><cell></cell><cell>0,757</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Qestion8</cell><cell>Z</cell><cell>0,835</cell><cell>1,102</cell><cell>0,062</cell><cell>17,785</cell></row><row><cell>Qestion9</cell><cell></cell><cell>0,939</cell><cell>1,255</cell><cell>0,062</cell><cell>20,176</cell></row><row><cell>Qestion10</cell><cell></cell><cell>0,676</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Qestion11</cell><cell>W</cell><cell>0,799</cell><cell>1,131</cell><cell>0,083</cell><cell>13,555</cell></row><row><cell>Qestion12</cell><cell></cell><cell>0,785</cell><cell>1,158</cell><cell>0,087</cell><cell>13,379</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Note: For all values P&lt;0.01</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>shows a sample table showing Cronbach's α, AVE and</cell></row><row><cell>CR values calculated for each construct and the correlation</cell></row><row><cell>values between constructs. Cronbach's α value can be</cell></row><row><cell>calculated from the scale reliability menu in the SPSS program.</cell></row><row><cell>The AVE and CR values are found by placing the results of</cell></row><row><cell>the CFA factor loadings in to the formulas. There are ready-</cell></row><row><cell>made calculation tools on the Internet.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Table 5 . Descriptive Statistics, Correlation Coefficient, Reliability Results and Discriminant Validity</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Std.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Avr.</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Dev.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1. Construct</cell><cell>3,25</cell><cell>0,81</cell><cell>(0,842)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2. Construct</cell><cell>3,28</cell><cell>0,71</cell><cell>,216 *</cell><cell>(0,711)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>3. Construct</cell><cell>3,63</cell><cell>0,72</cell><cell>,427 *</cell><cell>,383 *</cell><cell>(0,840)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>4. Construct</cell><cell>3,72</cell><cell>0,68</cell><cell>,228 *</cell><cell>,533 *</cell><cell>,457 *</cell><cell>(0,718)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>5. Construct</cell><cell>3,62</cell><cell>0,70</cell><cell>,449 *</cell><cell>,192 *</cell><cell>,378 *</cell><cell>,298 *</cell><cell>(0,769)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>6. Construct</cell><cell>3,76</cell><cell>0,68</cell><cell>,430 *</cell><cell>,394 *</cell><cell>,551 *</cell><cell>,450 *</cell><cell>,499 *</cell><cell>(0,734)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>7. Construct</cell><cell>3,23</cell><cell>0,87</cell><cell>,585 *</cell><cell>,166 *</cell><cell>,452 *</cell><cell>,174 *</cell><cell>,449 *</cell><cell>,479 *</cell><cell>(0,800)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>8. Construct</cell><cell>3,68</cell><cell>0,67</cell><cell>,394 *</cell><cell>,496 *</cell><cell>,672 *</cell><cell>,508 *</cell><cell>,350 *</cell><cell>,508 *</cell><cell>,358 *</cell><cell>(0,722)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>9. Construct</cell><cell>3,02</cell><cell>0,77</cell><cell>,340 *</cell><cell>,374 *</cell><cell>,353 *</cell><cell>,335 *</cell><cell>,209 *</cell><cell>,302 *</cell><cell>,219 *</cell><cell>,410 *</cell><cell>(0,754)</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Cronbach Alfa Reliability Coefficient</cell><cell>0,927</cell><cell>0,861</cell><cell>0,901</cell><cell>0,851</cell><cell>0,781</cell><cell>0,771</cell><cell>0,828</cell><cell>0,808</cell><cell>0,721</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Composite Reliability Coefficient (CR)</cell><cell>0,924</cell><cell>0,854</cell><cell>0,905</cell><cell>0,841</cell><cell>0,791</cell><cell>0,777</cell><cell>0,840</cell><cell>0,813</cell><cell>0,725</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Average Variance Extracted (AVE)</cell><cell>0,710</cell><cell>0,506</cell><cell>0,706</cell><cell>0,516</cell><cell>0,592</cell><cell>0,539</cell><cell>0,640</cell><cell>0,522</cell><cell>0,570</cell></row></table><note><p>* P&lt;0,05, Note: the values written in brackets indicate the square root of the AVE values.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The structural model is based on measurement model. In this phase it should be noted that the structure and order of CFA model is preserved in the model that will be established with latent variables. Depending on the causal relationships between latent variables, the directions of the arrows are determined in accordance with the developed hypotheses and a structural model is constructed. Two-way arrows indicate the covariance between two variables without specifying the direction of causality. While constructing the structural model, the conceptual model leads the way. The conceptual model is mainly based on the relations found in the literature. Finally, the conceptual model is tested using real data. Before the hypothesis tests, the fit indices of the model are examined.If the fit indices of the model are not within the limits recommended in the literature, the modifications are made and the fit indices are improved provided that they are compatible with the literature. If the fit indices are at an adequate level, the predicted values of the model parameters are checked first. Then the hypothesis test results of the research are given in a table. Figure</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>shows an example of the hypothesis test results. The values in this table are in the estimates section of the output screen of the AMOS program. The notation *** in AMOS output means that P is equal to zero.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>Table 6 . Hypothesis Test Results Table Example</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Unstandar</cell></row><row><cell>Relations</cell><cell>Standard Coefficients</cell><cell>d Coefficien</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>ts</cell></row><row><cell>X → Z</cell><cell>0.533 *</cell><cell>0.594 *</cell></row><row><cell>Y → Z</cell><cell>0.437 *</cell><cell>0.638 *</cell></row><row><cell>Z → W</cell><cell>0.493 *</cell><cell>0.377 *</cell></row><row><cell>*p &lt; 0.05</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head>Table Constructs</head><label>Constructs</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="4">When an mediator analysis is performed, three different</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">models are run and the coefficients of the models are</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">compared with one another. Models and hypotheses tested are</cell></row><row><cell>as follows:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">H 1 : Variable A affects variable B in the positive direction.</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">H 2 : Variable B affects variable C in the positive direction.</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">H 3 : Variable A affects variable C in the positive direction.</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">H 4 : Variable B plays mediator role in the relationship</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">between Variable A and Variable C.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model 1:</cell><cell></cell><cell>(H 3 )</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model 2:</cell><cell></cell><cell>(H 1 )</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model 3:</cell><cell></cell><cell>(H 2 ve H 4 )</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>A</cell><cell>B</cell><cell>C</cell></row><row><cell>A</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>B</cell><cell>0,492 *</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>C</cell><cell>0,575 *</cell><cell>0,672 *</cell><cell>-</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head>Table 8 . Example of Regression Coefficients Table</head><label>8</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note><p>* P&lt;0.001</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_17"><head>Table 9 . Correlation Coefficients Sample Table</head><label>9</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Variables</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>A</cell><cell>-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>B</cell><cell>0.883*</cell><cell>-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>C</cell><cell cols="2">0.861* 0.928*</cell><cell>-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>D</cell><cell cols="2">0.430* 0.653*</cell><cell>0.703*</cell><cell>-</cell></row></table><note><p>*p &lt; 0.01.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_18"><head>Table Relations</head><label>Relations</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Model 1</cell><cell>Model 2</cell><cell>Model 3</cell></row><row><cell>A → D (H 1 )</cell><cell>0.414*</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.035</cell></row><row><cell>A → B (H 2 )</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.863*</cell><cell>0.865*</cell></row><row><cell>A → C (H 3 )</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.279*</cell><cell>0.870*</cell></row><row><cell>C → D (H 4 )</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.532*</cell></row><row><cell>B → D (H 5 )</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.935*</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>χ2/df=2.554</cell><cell>χ2/df=2.921</cell><cell>χ2/df=2.856</cell></row><row><cell>Model Fit</cell><cell>CFI=0.985</cell><cell>CFI=0.954</cell><cell>CFI=0.947</cell></row><row><cell>Indices</cell><cell>IFI=0.985 RMSEA=0.14</cell><cell>IFI=0.954 RMSEA=0.14</cell><cell>IFI=0.947 RMSEA=0.14</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Note: Path analysis coefficients are standardized.</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>*p&lt;0.01</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_19"><head>Table 11 . Confirmatory Factor Analysis Results</head><label>11</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Constructs</cell><cell>Items</cell><cell>Standardized Factor Loads</cell><cell>Unstandardize d Factor Loads</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Use1</cell><cell>0.760</cell><cell>1.00</cell></row><row><cell>Usability</cell><cell>Use2</cell><cell>0.786</cell><cell>1.10</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Use3</cell><cell>0.647</cell><cell>0.80</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Sa1</cell><cell>0.912</cell><cell>1.00</cell></row><row><cell>System Quality</cell><cell>Sa2</cell><cell>0.807</cell><cell>0.91</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Sa3</cell><cell>0.663</cell><cell>0.62</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Ats1</cell><cell>0.717</cell><cell>1.00</cell></row><row><cell>Attitude</cell><cell>Ats2</cell><cell>0.747</cell><cell>1.13</cell></row><row><cell>Toward the</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Site</cell><cell>Ats3</cell><cell>0.847</cell><cell>1.11</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Ats4</cell><cell>0.763</cell><cell>1.10</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Us1</cell><cell>0.761</cell><cell>1.00</cell></row><row><cell>User</cell><cell>Us2</cell><cell>0.831</cell><cell>1.09</cell></row><row><cell>Satisfaction</cell><cell>Us2</cell><cell>0.941</cell><cell>1.25</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Us4</cell><cell>0.818</cell><cell>1.06</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Nf1</cell><cell>0.772</cell><cell>1.00</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Nf2</cell><cell>0.630</cell><cell>0.99</cell></row><row><cell>Net Benefit</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Nf3</cell><cell>0.818</cell><cell>1.15</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Nf4</cell><cell>0.646</cell><cell>0.95</cell></row><row><cell>Note: For all p&lt;0.01</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_20"><head>Table 12 . Correlation, AVE and Reliability Values</head><label>12</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Variables</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.767)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1. System Quality</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2. User Satisfaction</cell><cell>0.575*</cell><cell>(0.840)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>3. Attitude Toward Site</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.566* 0.677*</cell><cell>(0.770)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>4. Net Benefit</cell><cell cols="2">0.492* 0.672*</cell><cell cols="2">0.709* (0.721)</cell></row><row><cell>Cronbach α</cell><cell>0.821</cell><cell>0.901</cell><cell>0.848</cell><cell>0.808</cell></row><row><cell>Composite Reliability</cell><cell>0.895</cell><cell>0.905</cell><cell>0.853</cell><cell>0.810</cell></row><row><cell>(CR)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Avarage Variance</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Extracted (AVE)</cell><cell>0.589</cell><cell>0.706</cell><cell>0.593</cell><cell>0.520</cell></row><row><cell>*p &lt; 0.01</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Note: The values in brackets indicate the square root of the AVE</cell></row><row><cell>values.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_21"><head>Table 13 . Test Results</head><label>13</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Relations</cell><cell>Model 1</cell><cell>Model 2</cell><cell>Model 3</cell></row><row><cell>System Quality →Net Benefit</cell><cell>0.701*</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.03**</cell></row><row><cell>System Quality → User Satisfaction</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.733*</cell><cell>0.839*</cell></row><row><cell>System Quality → Attitude Toward Site</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.487*</cell><cell>0.880*</cell></row><row><cell>User Satisfaction →Net Benefit</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.331*</cell></row><row><cell>Attitude Toward Site → Net Benefit</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.651*</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>χ2/df=4.039</cell><cell>χ2/df=3.678</cell><cell>χ2/df=3.750</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>CFI=0.944</cell></row><row><cell>Model Fit Indices</cell><cell>CFI=0.974 IFI=0.974,RMS</cell><cell>CFI=0.967</cell><cell>IFI=0.944</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>EA=0.08</cell><cell>IFI=0.967</cell><cell>RMSEA=0.08</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>RMSEA=0.08</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Note: Regression coefficients are standard values.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>*p&lt;0.01</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>**Insignificant</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_22"><head>Table 15 . Summary of Fit Indices</head><label>15</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Fit Indices</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Models</cell><cell>x 2</cell><cell>df</cell><cell>CFI</cell><cell>RMSEA</cell><cell>90% C.I.</cell><cell>PCLOSE</cell></row><row><cell>1. Freely</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>correlated</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>traits; freely</cell><cell cols="2">86.62 78</cell><cell>.897</cell><cell>.015</cell><cell>.000 .048</cell><cell>.897</cell></row><row><cell>correlated</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>methods</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2. No traits;</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>freely correlated</cell><cell>459.1 2</cell><cell>98</cell><cell>.693</cell><cell>.204</cell><cell>.122 .157</cell><cell>.000</cell></row><row><cell>methods</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>3. Perfectly</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>correlated traits; freely correlated</cell><cell>317.1 2</cell><cell>85</cell><cell>.795</cell><cell>.086</cell><cell>.081 .110</cell><cell>.000</cell></row><row><cell>methods</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>4. Freely</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>correlated traits; uncorrelated</cell><cell>123.3 9</cell><cell>81</cell><cell>.964</cell><cell>.058</cell><cell>.037 .065</cell><cell>.000</cell></row><row><cell>methods</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="7">In figurel 34, Heterotrait-Heteromethod Triangles,</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">Heterotrait-Monomethod Triangles, Heterometdod Blocks</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">and Monomethod Blocks in Multitrait-Multimethod Matrix</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">are shown. When the Multitrait-Multimethod models are run,</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">the warning shown in Figure</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_23"><head>Table 16 . Comparisons of Nested Models</head><label>16</label><figDesc>The parameters of the covariances between the methods are released. In Model 3, the features and methods are included in the same model but this time the covariance parameters between the latent variables forming the traits are fixed to 1.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Difference</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Models</cell><cell>x 2</cell><cell>df</cell><cell>CFI</cell></row><row><cell>Test of Convergent</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Validity</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model 1 and Model 2 (traits)</cell><cell>372.506</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>.204</cell></row><row><cell>Test Discriminant Validity</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model 1 and Model 3 (traits)</cell><cell>230.502</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>.102</cell></row><row><cell>Model 1 and Model 4 (methods)</cell><cell>74.230</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>.067</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Then, 3 alternative models are created. These models are as</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">seen in Figures 38-39-40. Model 2 consists only of methods.</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">The latent variables that make up the traits are not included in</cell></row><row><cell>the model.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_24"><head>Table 18 . Traits and Methods Correlations in Model 1</head><label>18</label><figDesc>Table 16 compares each alternative model with model 1. The comparison between Model 1 and Model 2 shows convergent validity, comparisons between Model 1 and Model 3 and Model 4 show the discriminant validity. The significance of difference between X 2 values of Model 1 and Model 2 indicating the convergent validity is sufficient.</figDesc><table><row><cell>As shown in Table 16, ΔX 2 (372.506, p&lt;0.01) and ΔCFI</cell></row><row><cell>(0.204, p&lt;0.01) are significant. In addition, the difference</cell></row><row><cell>between X 2 values of Model 1 and Model 3 and Model 4 are</cell></row><row><cell>the basis for confirming the discriminant validity. As shown in</cell></row><row><cell>Table 16, between Model 1 and Model 3, ΔX 2 (230.502,</cell></row><row><cell>p&lt;0.01) and ΔCFI (0.102, p&lt;0.01) are significant, between</cell></row><row><cell>Model 1 and Model 4, ΔX 2 (74.230, p&lt;0.01) and ΔCFI (0.067,</cell></row><row><cell>p&lt;0.01) are significant. Another indicator of construct validity</cell></row><row><cell>is parameter level analysis. For comparison at the parameter</cell></row><row><cell>level, the factor loadings and factor correlations in Table 17</cell></row><row><cell>are compared.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_25"><head>Table 19 . Factor Loading in Model 5</head><label>19</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>X</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>V</cell><cell>W</cell><cell>Z</cell><cell>T</cell><cell>U</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>A</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>X</cell><cell>.810</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Y</cell><cell></cell><cell>.801</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>V</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.797</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>W</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.644</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Z</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.751</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>T</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.800</cell></row><row><cell>U</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.721</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>B</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>X</cell><cell>.501</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Y</cell><cell></cell><cell>.416</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>V</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.353</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>W</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.489</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Z</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.518</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>T</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.468</cell></row><row><cell>U</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.499</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>C</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>X</cell><cell>.741</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Y</cell><cell></cell><cell>.428</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>V</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.555</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>W</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.721</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>* P&lt; 0.01</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div><p><rs type="person">Zea Books</rs> are published by the <rs type="funder">University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 36. AMOS Warnings Window</head><p>The matrix structure in the background of the example model in Figure <ref type="figure">33</ref> is as seen in Figure34. Due to the difficulty in displaying the figure, only a limited drawing including methods A, B and C was made.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">CONTENT PREFACE .........................................................................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">CONTENT .......................................................................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">INTRODUCTION ......................................................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">I. CHAPTER...................................................................................................... 6 CONCEPTS AND METHODOLOGY ...................................................... 6 2. BASIC CONCEPTS OF STRUCTURAL EQUATION MODELING ....................................................................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">1. Definitions and Features ................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">2. Latent and Observed Variables ...................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Endogeneous and Exogeneous Variables</title>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">13</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">4. Parameters ........................................................................................ 16 2.5. Fit Indices ......................................................................................... 17 2.6. Assumptions of Structural Equation Modeling ........................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">22</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Types of Structural Equation Models</title>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">.......................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">26</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">1. Path Analysis Models ...........................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">26</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">2. Confirmatory Factor Analysis Models ................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">27</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">3. Structural Regression Models ................................................ 28 2.7.4. Latent Change Models ..........................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">28</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">VALIDITY AND RELIABILITY ANALYSIS ....................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Determination of Convergent Validity .....................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">32</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">2. Determination of Discriminant Validity ...................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">41</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Determination of Reliability ........................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">42</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">STRUCTURAL REGRESSION MODEL ............................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">PATH ANALYSIS .....................................................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">MODEL MODIFICATION ...................................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">MEDIATOR VARIABLE ANALYSIS METHODOLOGY ............................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">II. CHAPTER .................................................................................................. 61 APPLICATIONS ..........................................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">61</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">USE OF AMOS Program ........................................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">61</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">SAMPLE OF MEDIATOR VARIABLE ANALYSIS .......................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">73</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Title of the Research ......................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">2. Purpose ............................................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">3. Conceptual Model and Scales .......................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Determination of Validity and Reliability ...................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">5. Analysis Results ..............................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">6. Conclusion ......................................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">MULTITRAIT-MULTIMETHOD MODEL ....................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">80</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">METHODS TO BE APPLIED IN CASE OF DATA INADEQUACY ............................................................................................................ 100 11.1. Bootstrap Method .....................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">PLS-SEM) ....................................................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Least Square Structural Equation Modeling</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Bibliography .................................................................................................................... 111 BIBLIOGRAPHY Aksu</orgName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Açımlayıcı ve Doğrulayıcı Faktör Analizi ile Yapısal Eşitlik Modeli Uygulamaları</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Eser</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Güzeller</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ankara</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Detay Yayıncılık</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural Equation Modelling in Practice: A Review and Recommended Two-Step Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gerbing</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Perakende Marka Değerinin Ölçümü ve Yapısal Eşitlik Modeli Uygulaması (1 b.)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Avcılar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">İ</forename><surname>Varinli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Detay Yayıncılık</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Ankara</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing Method Variance in Multitrait-Multimethod Matrices: The Case of Selfreported Affect and Perceptions at Work</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Bagozzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="547" to="560" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">History and rationale of longitudinal research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Baltes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nesselroade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The partial least sequares approach to causal modeling: Personal computer adoption and use as illustration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Barclay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Higgins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technology Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Moderator-Mediator Variable Distinction in Social Phychological Research: Conceptual, Strategic and Statistical Considerations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Baron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kenny</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Phychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1173" to="1182" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Yapısal Eşitlik Modellemesine Giriş</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Bayram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Ezgi Kitapevi</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Bursa</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Practical Issues in Structural Modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bentler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-P</forename><surname>Chou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Methods Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="117" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Byrne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Structural Equation Modeling with AMOS</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge Taylor &amp; Francis Group</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Covergent and Discriminant Validation by the Multitrait-Multimethod Matrix</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fiske</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="105" />
			<date type="published" when="1959">1959</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rungruengsamrit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Rajkumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Yen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Success of Electronic Web Sites: A Comparative Study in Two Countries</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="344" to="355" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Civelek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>İnce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Karabulut</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Mediator Roles Of Attitude Toward The Web Site And User Satisfaction On The Effect Of System Quality On Net Benefit: A Structural Equation Model On Web Site Success</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="73" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Çelik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Yılmaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Lısrel 9.1 ile Yapısal Eşitlik Modellemesi</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ankara</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Anı Yayıncılık</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Farkli Veri Yapisi ve Örneklem Büyüklüklerinde Yapisal Eşitlik Modellerinin Geçerliği ve Güvenirliğinin Değerlendirilmesi</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">İ</forename><surname>Doğan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>Eskİşehİr Osmangazİ Ünİversİtesİ Doktora Tezi</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Eskişehir</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Yapısal Eşitlik Modellemesi ve Regresyon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dursun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kocagöz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Karşılaştırmalı Bir Analiz. Erciyes Üniversitesi İ.İ.B.F. Dergisi</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bootstrap method: Another look at the jackknife</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Efron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating Structural Equation Models with Unobservable Variables and Measurement Error</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Larcker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Updated Paradigm for Scale Development Incorporating Unidimensionality and Its</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gerbing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Joournal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="192" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Essentials of Econometrics (2 b.)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gujarati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<publisher>McGRAW-HILL</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Singapore</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A primer on partial least squares structural equation modeling PLS-SEM</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hult</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ringle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sarstedt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>SAGE</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Los Angeles</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bootstrapping and the identifcation of exogenous latent variables within structural equation models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hancock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nevitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Structural Equation Modeling</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="394" to="399" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Henseler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dijkstra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sarstedt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ringle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Diamantopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Straub</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Common beliefs and reality about partial least squares: Comments on Rönkkö &amp; Evermann</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2014. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="182" to="209" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application of the bootstrap methods in factor analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ichikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influence of initiators on supply chain value creation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jayaram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Kannan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Production Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4377" to="4399" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Karagöz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">SPSS ve AMOS 23 Uygulamalı İstatistiksel Analizler</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ankara</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Nobel</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principles and practice of structural equation modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Guilford</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison of methods to test mediation and other intervening variable effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mackinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lockwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Sheets</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Meydan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Şen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Yapısal Eşitlik Modellemesi AMOS Uygulamaları</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ankara</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Detay Yayıncılık</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation of composite reliability for congeneric measures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Raykov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Psychological Measurement</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="184" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A First Course in Structural Equation Modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Raykov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Marcoulides</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Mahwah</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rethinking partial least squares path modelling: In praise of simple methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rigdon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Long Range Planning</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The bootstrap, the jackknife, and the randomization test: A sampling taxonomy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rodgers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Multivariate Behavioral Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="441" to="456" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A bootstrap procedure for high-resolution velocity analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sacchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sarstedt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mooi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">A concise guide to market research: The process, data, and methods using IBM SPSS statistics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>nd b; Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating the Fit of Structural Equation Models: Tests of Significance and Descriptive Goodness-of-Fit Measures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Schermelleh-Engel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Moosbrugger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods of Psychological Research Online</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sosyal bilimlerde SPSS&apos;le Veri Analizi</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sipahi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Yurtkoru</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Çinko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Beta Basım A</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<pubPlace>İstanbul</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Using multivariate statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Tabachnick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fidell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<publisher>Ally and Bacon</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Araştırma Yöntemlerinde Yapısal Eşitlik Modelleme</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ç</forename><surname>Taşkın</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ö</forename><surname>Akat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Ekin Basım Yayın</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Bursa</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Widaman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Hierarchically Tested Covariance Structure Models for Multitrait-Multimethod Data</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="26" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introductory Econometrics: A Modern Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wooldridge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<publisher>Thomson</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Mason</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding and Using Mediators and Moderators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zumbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Indicators Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="367" to="392" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring KMS Success: A Respecification of the DeLone and McLean&apos;s Model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-H</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-M</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information &amp; Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="728" to="739" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bootstrap-corrected ADF test statistics in covariance structure analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bentler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British Journal of Mathematical and Statistical Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
