<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">DEBATE, CRITICAL THINKING DISPOSITION, AND SELF-CONFIDENCE: DO THEY CONTRIBUTE TO SPEAKING PROFICIENCY? by</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Miftaqur</forename><surname>Rochmah</surname></persName>
							<email>miftaqurrochmah1@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">ISLAM NEGERI KEDIRI</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">ISLAM NEGERI KEDIRI</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">INSTITUT AGAMA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">UNIVERSITAS ISLAM</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">NEGERI MAULANA MALIK IBRAHIM MALANG</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">INSTITUT AGAMA</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ayu</forename><surname>Saputri</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">ISLAM NEGERI KEDIRI</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">ISLAM NEGERI KEDIRI</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">INSTITUT AGAMA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">UNIVERSITAS ISLAM</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">NEGERI MAULANA MALIK IBRAHIM MALANG</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">INSTITUT AGAMA</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Rohmani</forename><forename type="middle">Nur</forename><surname>Indah</surname></persName>
							<email>indah@bsi.uin-malang.ac.id</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">ISLAM NEGERI KEDIRI</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">ISLAM NEGERI KEDIRI</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">INSTITUT AGAMA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">UNIVERSITAS ISLAM</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">NEGERI MAULANA MALIK IBRAHIM MALANG</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">INSTITUT AGAMA</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Fathor</forename><surname>Rasyid</surname></persName>
							<email>frasyid@yahoo.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">ISLAM NEGERI KEDIRI</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">ISLAM NEGERI KEDIRI</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">INSTITUT AGAMA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">UNIVERSITAS ISLAM</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">NEGERI MAULANA MALIK IBRAHIM MALANG</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">INSTITUT AGAMA</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">DEBATE, CRITICAL THINKING DISPOSITION, AND SELF-CONFIDENCE: DO THEY CONTRIBUTE TO SPEAKING PROFICIENCY? by</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T00:37+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Debate</term>
					<term>Critical thinking disposition</term>
					<term>Self-confidence</term>
					<term>Speaking proficiency</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Critical thinking, self-confidence, and speaking skills are fundamental skills, and debate is one method that enhances these skills. This study investigates the direct and indirect contributions of debate, critical thinking dis'12position, and self-confidence to improve speaking skills. The design of this research is path analysis and uses AMOS 24 in the data analysis. 67 out of 72 students who participated in the debate competition at East-Java English Club 4 became the sample of this research. Questionnaires were used to determine students' perceptions of debate, critical thinking disposition, and self-confidence. In addition to the questionnaire, a speaking test using the Student Oral Language Observation Matrix (SOLOM) was used to measure speaking proficiency. The findings show a significant direct debate contribution to students' critical thinking, self-confidence, and speaking skills. For indirect contribution, there is a significant contribution from debate to speaking skills through critical thinking and a significant contribution from debate to speaking skills through self-confidence. From these results, recommendations for future researchers are about how to implement the in-class debate method in the realm of experimental research to develop the three variables previously mentioned.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Integrating cognitive aspects and communication skills in English learning is a challenge and demands in language classes. Due to an increasingly competitive workforce and technological developments requiring superior negotiation, analysis, problem-solving, and communication skills <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Aclan &amp; Aziz, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Zare &amp; Othman, 2015)</ref>. A study conducted by the People Management Association of the Philippines (PMAP) shows an astonishing fact. Four out of ten PJEE <ref type="figure">------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref> thinking <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Aclan &amp; Aziz, 2014)</ref>. Therefore, the ability to speak and think critically is a buzzword in today's life.</p><p>Combining speaking skills and critical thinking in English learning is not impossible because critical thinking is correlated with language skills such as speaking and writing <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Indah, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Riwayatiningsih, 2019)</ref>. In developing students' speaking skills, critical thinking must be present to support speaking skills (Glaser in <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Sovianti, 2021)</ref>. Speaking skill reflects success in EFL learning because students can practice and use the target language in absolute terms <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Amiri et al., 2017)</ref>. Ironically, most students in EFL are passive (Marcelino in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Iman, 2017)</ref>.</p><p>Meanwhile, the ability to think critically is considered an ability that millennials must possess <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Tiasadi, 2020)</ref>. It is proven by the findings showing that 99% of university faculties consider the importance of developing critical thinking skills as a fundamental goal of undergraduate education (Arum and Roska in <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Ramezani et al., 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Speaking is a productive ability that can be observed directly and empirically, which involves a combination of lexicon, structure, and discourse from the speaker <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Brown, 2004)</ref>.</p><p>Five aspects must be considered to be a good speaker, including pronunciation, grammar, vocabulary, fluency, and understanding <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Brown, 2001)</ref>. However, in Indonesia, many external and internal factors hinder the development of students' speaking skills. The external factors include the monotony of the topics presented inappropriateness of methods in speaking classes, such as reading dialogues in front of the class. The internal factors include students' difficulties composing words or sentences, fear of conveying ideas, lack of motivation, and lack of selfconfidence <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Firmansyah &amp; Valatansa, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Sovianti, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Suhendra, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Critical thinking is one aspect of the 6Cs in education introduced by Miller <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Indriani, 2017)</ref>. According to him, critical thinking is the process of filtering, analyzing, and questioning information/content contained in various media, then synthesizing it in a form that has value for an individual. It allows students to understand the content presented and apply it in their daily lives. There are six crucial aspects in critical thinking: interpretation, analysis, conclusion, evaluation, explanation, and self-regulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Facione, 2015)</ref>. The results of other studies also reveal that an essential factor that affects the ease of expressing critical thinking is language skills. A critical thinker can express his thoughts well through good language, both verbal and written <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Indah &amp; Kusuma, 2016)</ref>.</p><p>- <ref type="figure">-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref> Besides critical thinking that supports students in language classes to convey their ideas and analysis, another factor that seems to be closely related to speaking ability is the students' self-confidence. This ability involves thoughts, feelings, and courage in carrying out tasks successfully without any doubt <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Moneva &amp; Tribunalo, 2020)</ref>. Four self-confidence variables focus on willingness to communicate, and these variables are situational beliefs, communication beliefs, language potential beliefs, and language skills beliefs <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Park &amp; Lee, 2005)</ref>. In addition, what is also important is the Personal Evaluation Inventory (PEI) which includes general self-confidence. The criteria consist of academic achievement, athletics, physical appearance, romantic relationships, social interactions, talking to others, general selfconfidence, and mood(Shraugerin <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Robinson et al., 1991)</ref>.</p><p>Self-confidence comes with the birth of an individual and, over time, changes its development since childhood. This ability is generally related to students' academic achievement and specifically to students' ability to express opinions verbally. It makes selfconfidence one of the twelve principles of language learning <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Brown, 2007)</ref>. Therefore, selfconfidence is vital because low self-confidence students tend to be shy to speak in public and find it difficult to make decisions and take responsibility <ref type="bibr">(Şar et al., 2010)</ref>.</p><p>In developing communication skills, critical thinking, and developing students' selfconfidence, a playful and interactive classroom atmosphere is needed to stimulate the development of these aspects. Many studies suggest and show that debate is a valuable approach for maintaining critical thinking, self-confidence, and speaking skills <ref type="bibr">(Sulaiman et al., in Aclan &amp; Aziz, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Jerome et al., Williams et al., Littlefield in Othman et al., 2015)</ref>.</p><p>Debates are known as two-sided arguments against each other, consisting of arguments for and against specific themes and helping students to defend their opinions and express their feelings <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Wulandari &amp; Ena, 2018)</ref>. In debate, students are encouraged to raise issues based on their team's position, either proposition or opposition. In the case building stage, they have to analyze their problem and communicate it with their friends. They use critical thinking in problem-solving and oral communication skills at this stage.</p><p>Many high schools in Indonesia facilitate extracurricular debates <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Wulandari &amp; Ena, 2018)</ref>. In addition, an annual debate competition is also held by Indonesia to increase student enthusiasm. In this pandemic era, debate competitions are still being held using a new system, <ref type="figure">------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref> Several previous studies discussed debate variables with students' critical thinking skills, self-confidence, and speaking skills. The researchers employed quantitative and qualitative methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Firmansyah &amp; Valatansa vegian, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Iman, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Lestari, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Suhendra, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Tiasadi, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wulandari &amp; Ena, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Zare &amp; Othman, 2015)</ref>. The research shows that the variables are related to one another. No recent research has focused on the contribution of debate to the disposition of critical thinking, self-confidence, and speaking ability of students analyzed through the path analysis method. Therefore, the researcher aims to investigate the direct and indirect contribution of debate, critical thinking disposition, and self-confidence to students' speaking ability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Design</head><p>This study utilized quantitative methods with a path analysis design. This technique allows researchers to estimate causal relationships between sets of variables depicted by path diagrams <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Abdurrahman &amp; Muhidin, 2007)</ref>. It allows collecting direct and indirect contributions between variables.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participants</head><p>This study involved 67 of 72 students in the English debate competition at the East Java English Competition (EJEC) 4 in 2020, held at SMK PGRI 2 Kediri. They took using simple random sampling. The 67 students consisted of 39 girls and 28 boys from 24 SMA and SMK in East Java. The researcher used the simple random sampling technique because this technique gives equal opportunities to members of the population to be a sample <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Latief, 2019)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Instruments and types of data</head><p>In terms of instruments and types of data, this study used two instruments, namely questionnaires and speaking tests. Researchers used two types of questionnaires: questionnaires <ref type="figure">------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref>  with a Likert scale to determine students' critical thinking disposition and self-confidence and closed-ended questionnaires with a yes/no question model to determine students' intensity in the debate. To measure students' speaking ability, the researcher used an interrater system from the English teacher to get objective results. In the critical thinking disposition questionnaire, the researcher adopted the questionnaire from Facione. The researcher adopted Park &amp; Lee's theory (2005) of self-confidence in communication willingness for the self-confidence questionnaire. As for the questionnaire, which aims to determine the intensity of students participating in debates.</p><p>Content validity was carried out by researchers first after completing the preparation of the questionnaire. The researcher involved a lecturer in educational psychology, an English debate coach, and the EJEC competition's vice-chairman. Lecturers of educational psychology were responsible for evaluating aspects of theory and content in the critical thinking disposition and self-confidence questionnaire. Meanwhile, the debate supervisor was responsible for evaluating the debate questionnaire.</p><p>Researchers carried out face validity after all content was by the directions of the two experts. In implementing face validity, the researcher tried out a questionnaire to 30 students who took part in extracurricular debates at SMK PGRI 2 Kediri and SMKN 1 Ngasem. The SPSS results show that the debate questionnaire has 25 items, critical thinking disposition has 45 items, and self-confidence has 37 items.</p><p>In addition to validity, reliability was also considered in the preparation of the questionnaire to measure its consistency. From the SPSS Cronbach's Alpha test results, it is known that the three questionnaires are reliable. With the following results; the debate questionnaire showed a reliability result of .784, the critical thinking disposition questionnaire showed a reliability result of .871, and the self-confidence questionnaire showed a reliability result of .946.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data collecting technique</head><p>After all the instruments were prepared, the researcher took the data directly to the EJEC 2020 debate competition. Questionnaires were distributed to all debate contest participants using a paper-based system. Meanwhile, to assess students' speaking, the researcher recorded the voices of each participant in all debate sessions. The recording results were then listened to again by the researcher and one inter-rater, namely the vice-chairman of the EJEC <ref type="figure">------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>-Premise Journal Volume 11 No 1, February 2022, e-ISSN: 2442-482x, p-ISSN: 2089-3345, page 189-207</head><p>Copyright@2022 194 competition, who is also an English teacher. Speaking scores were based on the Students' Oral Language Observation Matrix (SOLOM), which assesses five aspects: comprehension, fluency, vocabulary, pronunciation, and grammar <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Jose, 2013)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data analysis technique</head><p>The data collected was then inputted into Ms. Excel for further analysis. Researchers need to fulfill prerequisite tests in path analysis research before conducting path analysis.</p><p>Researchers conducted prerequisite tests, including tests of normality, linearity, heteroscedasticity, and linear regression. The prerequisite test was carried out using SPSS 21.</p><p>Meanwhile, to analyze the direct contribution of each variable, the researcher used the AMOS 24 application. This application was chosen to help researchers determine the contribution through the path diagram. Then to analyze the indirect contribution, the researcher inputs the data obtained from AMOS into the Sobel test. The path analysis diagram in this study is described as follows: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULT AND DISCUSSION</head><p>This section describes the research findings and discussion on the contribution between debate and independent variables, critical thinking and self-confidence as the intervening  <ref type="figure">------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref>  The results above show whether the direct contribution is significant or not. The higher the C.R value, the more significant the contribution. In AMOS, the significance can be seen <ref type="figure">------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref> from the multiplication between the estimate value Y1 &lt;---X with Z &lt;---Y1.</p><p>In the second indirect contribution, it is known that the Sobel test result is 2.385, which is greater than 1.96. These results indicate that debate contributes significantly to speaking skills through self-confidence. Meanwhile, these variables' direct and indirect total is 0.064, obtained by multiplying the estimated value Y2 &lt;---X with Z &lt;---Y2.</p><p>From all the results, debate significantly contributes to students' critical thinking, selfconfidence, and speaking skills. In addition, debate contributes significantly to students' speaking skills through critical thinking and self-confidence. In short, the debate has a significant contribution to speaking skills directly and indirectly through critical thinking and self-confidence.</p><p>- <ref type="figure">-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The direct contribution of debate toward critical thinking disposition</head><p>This study shows a significant direct contribution between debate and critical thinking disposition (see table <ref type="table">2</ref>). This finding is in line with Tawil's research that regardless of the topic, debate encourages students' curiosity, open mind, systematic, analytical, and confidence level in reasoning <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Tawil, 2016)</ref>. The participation of students in the EJEC 4 debate competition has been proven to make a positive contribution to the development of critical thinking disposition in students. By participating in an English debate competition, students can learn and practice to see the situation from various perspectives and points of view and find justification for what they stand for. They must not choose which side they will defend in the debate, but they must be prepared to be either an affirmative or an opposing team. It forces them to look for pointpoint arguments that might strengthen their team and weaken the opposing team.</p><p>The pre and while-debate sessions are crucial for students in this study to develop a critical thinking disposition. It is because they are required to build and present arguments. In the post-debate session, they were only required to listen to the verbal adjudication from the jury and the announcement of the winner of the debate.</p><p>In the pre-debate process, the participants of the debate competition did case building for thirty minutes after the debate topic, and team positions were launched. In the pre-debate process, the EFL class requires students to think consciously and critically as members of the debate team. The students need to find the context in which the debate will be brought and how they will bring it <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Iman, 2017)</ref>. In this session, students must build arguments according to the team's position and their position as the first, second, or third speaker. In this process, students' <ref type="figure">------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref> in-depth analysis of the topics discussed is fundamental, especially in the Impromptu topic debate system as it is currently being studied. Brainstorming activities, combining information or data from prior knowledge, and integrating facts with the arguments they build are a fundamental part of case-building and involve good analysis.</p><p>In the pre-debate, the process involving critical thinking disposition in this study also appears in the while-debate process. Problem-solving, in the context of recognizing problems, interpreting ideas, finding essential points of view, seeking elaboration, and showing logical evidence can also be found in the debate process. It can be seen from the process of delivering POI, refuting the opponent's opinion with other perspectives and evidence, and completing or adding information that his team may have forgotten. Students must measure and predict whether the arguments and defenses they convey are strong enough to defend their team and weaken the opposing team. It is in line with Othman et al. that several factors that make debates encourage critical thinking. These factors occurred in the brainstorming session before the debate and discussion between team members and the application of group strategies as they usually do in POI. Furthermore, the scaffolding or continuity of complex thinking activities made them find mixed patterns and characteristics <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Othman et al., 2015)</ref>. In conclusion, critical thinking skills can be improved through debate with the process of reasoning, argumentation, explanation, and interruption/question.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The direct contribution of debate toward speaking proficiency</head><p>The findings show that debate contributes directly to students' speaking development (see table <ref type="table">2</ref>). In this study, students can gain much experience related to speaking skills such as analyzing, delivering, and arranging speech quickly and correctly. The students must express their ideas and only bring notes of what they have to explain in 7 minutes, and this note is prepared thirty minutes before the debate (Case building). A speaker must have an outline to generate their ideas before speaking <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Kennedy, 2007)</ref>. Explaining ideas in a debate trains them to be confident in public speaking. This is because spontaneity in the debate must convince the audience regardless of the conditions. In addition, debate activities increase students' vocabulary, affecting students' speaking ability. The activity of speaking with their teammates, judges, or coaches in English can enrich their vocabulary, reduce pauses, and improve their pronunciation. The feedback also given by the teacher and their teammates is also valuable to develop further their speaking skills <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Wulandari &amp; Ena, 2018)</ref>.</p><p>- <ref type="figure">-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref> All sessions in the EJEC 4 debate competition are considered to improve students' speaking skills. In the pre-debate stage, speaking skills can be improved through interaction and collaboration to achieve coherence and complete idea generation. New vocabulary acquired through reading activities provides opportunities for students to gain information and discover new vocabulary that can be used in their debates. In while-debate, students' speaking skills are closely related to their critical thinking because they have to express arguments and convince the audience using credible analysis. With debate, students can improve their speaking skills by convincing the jury with a comprehensive explanation, speaking effectively and fluently, giving and receiving POI, and Rebuttal. Furthermore, in post-debate, speaking skills can be improved through learning from listening and interacting with others and from corrective feedback from verbal adjudication <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Aclan &amp; Aziz, 2014)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The indirect contribution of debate toward speaking proficiency through critical thinking disposition</head><p>The researcher stated that debate contributed to students' critical thinking disposition and speaking proficiency in the previous discussion. At the same time, critical thinking disposition also contributes to students' speaking skills. Participating in this debate competition also faces many challenges in constructing cases and ideas, adjusting each speaker's argument, overcoming opposing arguments, and refuting the opponent's ideas. In addition, they need to discuss and communicate with their team to strengthen their argument and argue with their opponent. The students who took part in the EJEC 4 debate competition had good critical thinking disposition and speaking skills. In other words, students who have good critical thinking disposition will show better performance in speaking <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Ramezani et al., 2016)</ref>.</p><p>On the other hand, those not included in this category have poor performance in speaking proficiency. Similarly, that critical thinking disposition increases students' thinking levels and helps them improve speaking skills simultaneously. It can be proven that the students who take critical thinking English conversation classes have a higher level of satisfaction in speaking because they have more willingness and challenges to solve problems or answer questions through communication and discussion. Therefore they participate more intensively(Wand in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bagheri, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr">Worrel and Grath in Ramezani et al., 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Apart from the researcher's findings regarding the contribution of debate to critical thinking disposition and speaking proficiency, the researcher also found an astonishing phenomenon. The success or good achievement of students participating in the EJEC 4 <ref type="figure">------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref> competition could not be separated from the school culture and the competence of their supervising teachers. The winning team in the competition was a team from a leading school in East Java. It makes it possible that these schools have a school culture oriented towards student achievement. School culture is essential as a system that produces values in school culture to create positive attitudes and behaviors that align with these values <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Hede, 2021)</ref>. Schools oriented towards student achievement will provide more support or provide infrastructure for their students as a forum for developing student potential. In addition, the competence of teachers in the context of critical thinking also affects students. Teachers' critical thinking can be in the form of providing a challenging atmosphere during the learning process. It can be done using learning methods such as discussion, problem-based learning, project-based learning, and other innovative learning methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Nuraida, 2019)</ref>. In the debate competition, the accompanying teacher usually also plays the role of a coach. They are tasked with training and correcting students' speaking skills and providing input or analysis of the cases or phenomena they discussed during practice. In addition, they also provide feedback after the debate session is over to provide an analysis of the course of the debate so that they can learn from the experience and perform better in the future.</p><p>The results of the study, which show the contribution of debate to critical thinking disposition and speaking skills, may be related to phenomena in the education of the 21st century. English learning in Indonesia shows attention to the 4Cs, namely collaboration, critical thinking and problem solving, creative thinking and innovation, and communication <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Septikasari &amp; Frasandy, 2018)</ref>. This aspect can be applied by implementing debate methods in language classes or developing school debate extracurriculars. The participation of students in preparing and discussing their opinions on a topic with their teammates can illustrate the collaboration process between students. The application of the debate method has at least fulfilled three of the four elements of C in the 2013 curriculum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The direct and indirect contributions among debate, self-confidence, and speaking proficiency</head><p>Based on the statistical tests that researchers have carried out, this study shows direct and indirect contributions between variables. In this part, the researcher discusses the direct contribution of debate toward self-confidence. Besides that, the researcher also made an indirect contribution between the debate variables on speaking proficiency through self-confidence.</p><p>- <ref type="figure">-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The direct contribution of debate toward self-confidence</head><p>Based on the researcher's findings, it can be concluded that debate contributes significantly to students' self-confidence (see table <ref type="table">2</ref>). The researcher found that the debate process followed by the participants in this competition affected their confidence and reduced their speaking anxiety. It can be achieved because students must have the courage to express their ideas during training sessions and debate competitions continuously. This process is also stimulated by verbal adjudication after the debate. According to Quinn, verbal adjudication is an evaluation, suggestion, and feedback carried out by the adjudicator, which is carried out after the debate activity. The motivation and feedback given by the trainers and judges increase students' selfconfidence because they want to try to be better. This motivation will influence them to express their arguments confidently and stimulate them to practice their spoken language <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Quinn, 2005)</ref>.</p><p>Students can show their standpoints even though they have opposing opinions by participating in debate training and debate competitions such as EJEC 4. Participating in the debate can reduce stage fright and increase students' self-confidence. Comments and statements given after the debate, students gain the confidence to speak freely without anxiety in front of others. This is because the input given by the supervising teacher makes them believe that what they convey is correct <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Zare &amp; Othman, 2015)</ref>. Furthermore, there are several advantages to joining the debate. First, students become more active in group discussions. The reason is that discussion activities appear in every debate in the case-building session. Second, it will increase students' confidence when giving an academic presentation (Luckett in <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Yonsisno, 2015)</ref>. It also means that debate gives students active discussion, confidence in giving oral presentations and builds students' intellect.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The indirect contribution of debate to speaking proficiency through self-confidence</head><p>This study found that debate contributed indirectly to students' speaking ability through self-confidence. The researcher found that students who took part in the EJEC 4 debate competition were stimulated to be confident and show their different points of view. In this way, confidence and speaking skills cannot be separated because when they have good selfconfidence, they will easily express their opinion. They must dare express their ideas before their opponents and judges in a debate. Motivation also encourages them to be better at debating and present their arguments with confidence.</p><p>- <ref type="figure">-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref> opinions and receiving verbal feedback can build students' self-confidence <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Brown, 2014)</ref>. In the EJEC 4, students are trained to have good self-confidence, which is the key to speaking and convincing the adjudicator and audience. In a debate session, they have to speak in front of other people and their opponents to convey their arguments and ideas. In addition, the motivation and feedback given by the teacher or even the jury in verbal adjudication can also boost self-confidence.</p><p>The higher the students' self-confidence, the lower their anxiety and the better their speaking ability. Speaking skills are a complex process that affects affective and cognitive factors, the primary sources of individual differences in foreign language learning. Therefore, self-confidence plays a significant role in students' speaking activities. Affective factors are the emotional side of human behavior and involve many aspects of personality such as motivation, emotion, attitude, personality, anxiety, and self-confidence. Students who have good selfconfidence tend to overcome negative thoughts and fears to communicate and speak in front of others quickly <ref type="bibr">(Brown and Skehan in Al-Hebaish, 2012)</ref>.</p><p>Some facts show that students can develop interpersonal competence and increase their competitiveness by participating in this debate competition. Students can meet and exchange experiences with students from other schools and their teammates in the debate competition.</p><p>Teamwork helps students build self-esteem, self-confidence, interpersonal and conflict management skills, and leadership skills <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Akindele, 2012)</ref>. In addition, by participating in competitions, students are stimulated to accept defeat and victory as part of their sportsmanship and competitive spirit. In debate competitions, students will be scored based on observations from the adjudicator. This scoring is not based on numbers but rather on how an argument is presented persuasively and convincingly. Moreover, the debate provides a more significant opportunity for them to meet new friends and socialize with new people as in sparring and competition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitation</head><p>There are several limitations to this research. The first is that researchers distribute Indonesian-language questionnaires to make it easier for students to understand the context of the questionnaire so that the answers they choose represent them. The researcher does not guarantee whether the questionnaire in English form will give similar results. In addition, this study involved students who took part in an English debate competition at the East Java level.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------Premise Journal</head><p>They represent the school and have basic English language skills, critical thinking skills, and good self-confidence. Researchers do not guarantee that debates with more heterogeneous participants will give the same results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSION AND SUGGESTION</head><p>This study aims to determine how students' participation in debate contributes directly or indirectly to critical thinking disposition, self-confidence, and speaking ability. The researcher argued at the outset that critical thinking disposition and self-confidence are essential skills in this century and can be integrated with language learning, especially speaking.</p><p>Therefore, a method is needed to facilitate these needs, one of which is the debate method discussed in this study. The literature discusses the debate variables with critical thinking skills, self-confidence, and students' speaking skills using both quantitative and qualitative methods.</p><p>However, the present study investigates the contribution of debate to students' critical thinking disposition, self-confidence, and speaking ability through the path analysis method. The research results found significant direct and indirect contributions between the variables of debate, critical thinking disposition, and self-confidence on students' speaking skills. The findings can be the basis for teachers to develop debate methods in teaching and learning activities in integrative and active learning.</p><p>This research involves developing a questionnaire as an instrument to achieve the desired results. Therefore, these results raise questions about whether the debate method is applied as part of the classroom learning method. On this basis, it will be helpful to continue research on implementing the debate method into the realm of experimental research to find out how effective it is for developing critical thinking, self-confidence, and speaking skills when applied to heterogeneous classes.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>-Premise Journal Volume 11 No 1, February 2022, e-ISSN: 2442-482x, p-ISSN: 2089-3345, page 189-207 Copyright@2022 190 new graduates are not accepted for work because of effective communication and critical</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>-Premise Journal Volume 11 No 1, February 2022, e-ISSN: 2442-482x, p-ISSN: 2089-3345, page 189-207 Copyright@2022 191</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>-Premise Journal Volume 11 No 1, February 2022, e-ISSN: 2442-482x, p-ISSN: 2089-3345, page 189-207 Copyright@2022 192 namely through digital platforms such as the zoom application, google meet, or the mix idea site. It is evidenced by several debate competitions held by various campuses and those officially held by the education office. One example is the 2021 NSDC (National School Debating Championship) held online. It also indicates that schools that provide extracurricular English debates also continue to practice to face these competitions.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>-Premise Journal Volume 11 No 1, February 2022, e-ISSN: 2442-482x, p-ISSN: 2089-3345, page 189-207 Copyright@2022</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>193</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Path analysis</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>-Premise Journal Volume 11 No 1, February 2022, e-ISSN: 2442-482x, p-ISSN: 2089-3345, page 189-207 Copyright@2022 195 variables, and speaking proficiency as the dependent variable. To calculate the result of path analysis, the researcher utilized the AMOS 24 application. The results are shown in diagram 2. Diagram 1 The numbers contained in the flow diagram show the contribution of one variable to another. Researchers then use these results to calculate the indirect contribution between variables. Furthermore, the data obtained from the diagram can be interpreted in more detail through the regression weights in table 1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>-Premise Journal Volume 11 No 1, February 2022, e-ISSN: 2442-482x, p-ISSN: 2089-3345, page 189the interpretation of the research findings. Several highlighted points are discussed in this part. This section includes direct and indirect contributions from the debate, critical thinking disposition, self-confidence, and speaking proficiency. The direct and indirect contributions among debate, critical thinking disposition, and speaking proficiency Based on the statistical tests that researchers have carried out, this study shows direct and indirect contributions between variables. Direct contributions include how debate contributes to critical thinking disposition and speaking proficiency. In addition, there is also an indirect contribution between the debate variables on speaking proficiency through critical thinking disposition.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>-Premise Journal Volume 11 No 1, February 2022, e-ISSN: 2442-482x, p-ISSN: 2089-3345, page 189-207 Copyright@2022 198</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>-Premise Journal Volume 11 No 1, February 2022, e-ISSN: 2442-482x, p-ISSN: 2089-3345, page 189-207Copyright@2022 199</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>-Premise Journal Volume 11 No 1, February 2022, e-ISSN: 2442-482x, p-ISSN: 2089-3345, page 189-207 Copyright@2022 200</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>-Premise Journal Volume 11 No 1, February 2022, e-ISSN: 2442-482x, p-ISSN: 2089-3345, page 189-207 Copyright@2022 201</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>2022 202</head><label>2022</label><figDesc>-Premise Journal Volume 11 No 1, February 2022, e-ISSN: 2442-482x, p-ISSN: 2089-3345, page 189-207 Copyright@Debate increases students' confidence through training, speaking and expressing their ideas, conveying if they have different ideas, and motivation in verbal adjudication. Showing</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Volume 11 No 1, February 2022, e-ISSN: 2442-482x, p-ISSN: 2089-3345, page 189-207 Copyright@2022 203</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 Regression Weights: (Group number 1 -Default model)</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Estimate S.E. C.R. P Label</cell></row><row><cell>Y1 &lt;---X</cell><cell>1,070 ,222 4,826 ***</cell></row><row><cell>Y2 &lt;---X</cell><cell>,621 ,183 3,386 ***</cell></row><row><cell>Z &lt;---X</cell><cell>,104 ,031 3,366 *** a</cell></row><row><cell>Z &lt;---Y2</cell><cell>,104 ,031 3,366 *** a</cell></row><row><cell>Z &lt;---Y1</cell><cell>,104 ,031 3,366 *** a</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Researchers can use the Sobel calculation to determine the significance of the indirect contribution by inputting data on the Sobel test. The inputted data comes from the data on the regression weights (table 1). To determine the significance of the indirect contribution, the researcher input data from the Estimate and Standard Error (S.E) X values to Y1 or Y2 and from Y1 or Y2 to Z in the provided Sobel column. Meanwhile, to estimate the total indirect contribution value, researchers need to multiply the estimated value from X to Y1 or Y2 and from Y1 or Y2 to Z.</figDesc><table><row><cell>results above show that all paths connecting variables have a *** sign indicating a significant</cell></row><row><cell>direct contribution. It means there is a significant contribution of debate with critical thinking</cell></row><row><cell>disposition, debate with self-confidence, debate with speaking skills, critical thinking with</cell></row><row><cell>speaking skills, and self-confidence with speaking skills.</cell></row></table><note><p><p>-Premise Journal Volume 11 No 1, February 2022, e-ISSN: 2442-482x, p-ISSN: 2089-3345, page 189-207</p>Copyright@2022 196 from Column P. This method is provided by AMOS by displaying *** if the contribution is significant. The symbol X refers to the debate variable, Y1 refers to the critical thinking disposition variable, Y2 refers to self-confidence, while Z refers to speaking proficiency. In addition, the arrows in the table indicate the contribution path from one variable to another. The After tabulating the Sobel test, it can be seen that there is a significant indirect contribution between the debate on speaking skills through critical thinking disposition. Sobel's Z value shows 2.753, greater than 1.96, with a significance level of 5%. It indicates that the indirect contribution of debate to speaking skills through critical thinking disposition is significant. Meanwhile, these variables' total direct and indirect contribution is 0.215, obtained</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The author acknowledges the support received from her beloved partner Moh. <rs type="person">Ana Usuludin</rs> for helping to analyze the data. Thank you to <rs type="person">Piranti Astri Pertiwi</rs> and <rs type="person">Mega Sanja Imelda</rs> for their support and encouragement.</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <ref type="figure">------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref><p>Rohmani Nur Indah is an associate professor on English Language Teaching of Faculty of Humanities, Universitas Islam Negeri Maulana Malik Ibrahim Malang. Her research area covers Psycholinguistics, critical thinking, and language disorder. She is the editor in chief of El Harakah Jurnal Budaya Islam. Email: indah@bsi.uin-malang.ac.id.</p><p>Fathor Rasyid is a senior lecturer on English Language Teaching at the Magister Program of English Language Teaching Institut Agama Islam Negeri Kediri. His current research deals with language teaching methodology and learning strategies. Email: frasyid@yahoo.com. <ref type="figure">------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref> </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Analisis Korelasi, Regresi Dan Jalur Dalam Penelitian Dengan Aplikasi Program SPS</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Abdurrahman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Muhidin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Pustaka Setia</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring Parliamentary Debate as a Pedagogical Tool to Develop English Communication Skills in EFL/ESL Classrooms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Aclan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">H A</forename><surname>Aziz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7575/aiac.ijalel.v.4n.2p.1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.7575/aiac.ijalel.v.4n.2p.1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Applied Linguistics &amp; English Literature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhancing Teamwork and Communication Skills Among First-Year Students at the University of Botswana</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Akindele</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">TESOL Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Correlation between General Self-Confidence and Academic Achievement in the Oral Presentation Course</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Al-Hebaish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4304/tpls.2.1.60-65</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4304/tpls.2.1.60-65" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theory and Practice in Language Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A case study of the development of an ESL learner&apos;s speaking skills through instructional debate</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Amiri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Othman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jahedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Humanities and Social Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="126" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Critical thinking and autonomy in speaking ability: A case study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Bagheri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal on Studies in English Language and Literature (IJSELL)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probing on the Relationship between Students&apos; Self-Confidence and Self-Efficacy while engaging in Online Learning amidst COVID-19</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Blanco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Carlota</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Nasibog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rodriguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Saldaña</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Vasquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gagani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.37899/journallaedusci.v1i4.220</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.37899/journallaedusci.v1i4.220" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal La Edusci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Teaching by Principles: An Interactive Approach to Language Pedagogy</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Pearson Education</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Language Assessment: Principles and Classroom Practices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">Pearson Education. Brown, D.</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Teaching by principles: An interactive approach to language pedagogy</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Pearson</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>rd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Language Assessment Principle and Classroom Practices</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>th Edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Critical Thinking: What It Is and Why It Counts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Longman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Facione</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>Pearson Education</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving the Students&apos; Speaking Skills through Debate Technique</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Firmansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Valatansa Vegian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.22460/project.v2i6.p891-895</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.22460/project.v2i6.p891-895" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PROJECT (Professional Journal of English Education)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pengaruh Budaya Sekolah dan Sarana Pendukung Terhadap Motivasi Belajar Siswa Dampaknya pada Mutu Pendidikan di Lingkungan SMK Triguna 1956</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hede</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">HUMANIS (Humanities,Management and Science Proceedings)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="687" to="695" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Debate Instruction in EFL Classroom: Impacts on the Critical Thinking and Speaking Skill</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Iman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.12973/iji.2017.1046a</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.12973/iji.2017.1046a" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Instruction</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="108" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Critical Thinking, Writing Performance and Topic Familiarity of Indonesian EFL Learners</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Indah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.17507/jltr.0802.04</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.17507/jltr.0802.04" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Language Teaching and Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="236" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factors Affecting The Development of Critical Thinking of Indonesian Learners of English Language</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Indah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kusuma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.9790/0837</idno>
		<idno>ISSN: 2089-3345</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IOSR Journal Of Humanities And Social Science (IOSR-JHSS)</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</forename></persName>
		</editor>
		<idno type="ISSN">2442-482x</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="207" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-02">2016. February 2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">@</forename><surname>Copyright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">206</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developing Pre-Service English Teachers&apos; Critical Thinking by Using</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Indriani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.31002/metathesis.v3i2.1859</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.31002/metathesis.v3i2.1859" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academic Journal Writing. Metathesis: Journal of English Language, Literature, and Teaching</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Student Oral Language Observation Matrix</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Bilingual Education Office of the California Department of Education</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">In-Class Debates: Fertile Ground for Active Learning and the Cultivation of Critical Thinking and Oral Communication Skills</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Latief</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research Methods on Language Learning: An Introduction</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Universitas Negeri Malang</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>th Edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Teaching Pragmatics to Indonesian Learners of English</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lestari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.31002/metathesis.v1i2.465</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.31002/metathesis.v1i2.465" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Metathesis: Journal of English Language, Literature, and Teaching</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Students&apos; Level of Self-confidence and Performance Tasks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Moneva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Tribunalo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Asia Pacific Journal of Academic Research in Social Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="42" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Peran Guru Dalam Mengembangkan Keterampilan Berpikir Kritis Siswa Dalam Proses Pembelajaran</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nuraida</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Teladan: Jurnal Ilmu Pendidikan Dan Pembelajaran</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effects of Debate Competition on Critical Thinking among Malaysian Second Language Learners</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Othman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sahamid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Zulkefli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hashim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mohamad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5829/idosi.mejsr.2015.23.04.22001</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5829/idosi.mejsr.2015.23.04.22001" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Middle-East Journal of Scientific Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Step by Step Guide to Data Analysis Using the SPSS Program</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pallant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Mc-Graw-Hill</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">L2 learners&apos; Anxiety, Self-Confidence, and Oral performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="208" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Kunsan National University, Concordia University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Debating</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Quinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<pubPlace>Brisbane</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving Writing Skill with Questioning: A Path on Critical Thinking Skill</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ramezani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Larsari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kiasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.31002/metathesis.v3i2.1665</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.31002/metathesis.v3i2.1665" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Metathesis: Journal of English Language, Literature, and Teaching</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="213" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Speaking Ability. English Language Teaching</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Measures of Personality and Social Psychological Attitudes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Shaver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wrightsman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>Academic Press, Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing undergraduate students&apos; self-confidence levels in terms of some variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Şar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Avcu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Işıklar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.sbspro.2010.07.262</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sbspro.2010.07.262" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Procedia -Social and Behavioral Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1205" to="1209" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Keterampilan 4C Abad 21 Dalam Pembelajaran Pendidikan Dasar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Septikasari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Frasandy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Tarbiyah Al-Awlad</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="112" to="122" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Correlation Between Critical Thinking Ability and Self-Confidence toward Speaking Skill Among The Third Level Students at Language Center Pare-Kedir</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A R</forename><surname>Sovianti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.32503/proficiency.v2i2.1406</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.32503/proficiency.v2i2.1406" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Pendidikan Bahasa Inggris Proficiency</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parliamentary English Debate within Communicative Language Teaching Context: A Personal Reflection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Suhendra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.20414/edulangue.v3i1.2033</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.20414/edulangue.v3i1.2033" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of English Language Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="102" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<idno>ISSN: 2089-3345</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022-02">February 2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="207" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">@</forename><surname>Copyright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">207</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Validity and Reliability of the Research Instrument; How to Test the Validation of a Questionnaire/Survey in a Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Taherdoost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2139/ssrn.3205040</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.3205040" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SSRN Electronic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Classroom debates: A tool to enhance critical thinking in science</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tawil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="48" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Debating practice to support critical thinking skills: Debaters&apos; perception. AKSARA: Jurnal Bahasa Dan Sastra</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tiasadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.23960/aksara/v21i1.pp1-16</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.23960/aksara/v21i1.pp1-16" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using Debate Activities to Develop Indonesian High School Students</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wulandari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Ena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.24071/llt.2018.Suppl2102</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.24071/llt.2018.Suppl2102" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Speaking Skills. Language and Language Teaching Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Supplement</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Using Debate Technique Toward Students&apos; Speaking Skill at The Eleventh Grade Students of SMA Negeri 2 Kota Sungai Penuh</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Yonsisno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Penelitian Universitas Jambi Seri Humaniora</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="40" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Students&apos; Perceptions toward Using Classroom Debate to Develop Critical Thinking and Oral Communication Ability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zare</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Othman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5539/ass.v11n9p158</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5539/ass.v11n9p158" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Asian Social Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="158" to="170" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
