<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Journal of Economics, Finance and Management Studies</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2023-09-09">09 September 2023</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Iskandar</forename><surname>Hardiyansyah</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Krisnadwipayana Jakarta</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ismail</forename><surname>Razak</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Krisnadwipayana Jakarta</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Eddy</forename><forename type="middle">Sanusi</forename><surname>Silitonga</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Krisnadwipayana Jakarta</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Journal of Economics, Finance and Management Studies</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">(print): 2644-0490</idno>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2023-09-09">09 September 2023</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.47191/jefms/v6-i9-19</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T00:32+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Motivation</term>
					<term>Compensation</term>
					<term>Job Satisfaction</term>
					<term>Employee Performance</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This study aims to 1) determine the effect of motivation on employee performance, 2) determine the effect of compensation on employee performance, 3) determine the effect of motivation on employee job satisfaction, 4) determine the effect of compensation on employee job satisfaction, 5) determine the effect of job satisfaction on performance employees, 6) determine the effect of motivation, through job satisfaction on employee performance, 7) determine the effect of motivation, through job satisfaction on employee performance. The research was conducted by PT Unisadhuguna with a sample of 94 respondents. The sampling technique uses a saturated sample technique. Methods of data analysis using descriptive analysis and path analysis. The results showed that 1) motivation has an effect on increasing employee performance, 2) compensation has an effect on increasing employee performance, 3) motivation has an effect on increasing job satisfaction, 4) compensation has an effect on increasing job satisfaction, 5) job satisfaction has an effect on increasing employee performance, 6) motivation influences employee performance through job satisfaction, 7) compensation influences employee performance through job satisfaction.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>PT. Unisadhuguna is a world-class international education provider in Indonesia, Unisadhuguna offers a variety of international standard and career-focused programs through new learning approaches and has helped more than 3,500 students to enter prestigious universities around the world.</p><p>PT. Unisadhuguna was founded in 1994 and gives students access to top universities around the world. Organizing simplified education and global exposure becomes very important in building human resources in this day and age. With a new learning approach, Unisadhuguna provides just that: a series of international standard programs with an emphasis on career-focused lessons.</p><p>Along with the development of superior human resources which is carried out through education, the development of superior human beings has also been implemented in developed countries, one of which is based on the Danish Lesson Learned Scandinavian Welfare State Model scheme to increase Gross National Happiness (GNH), which in terms of the level of community needs, companies and governments have been met with high levels, starting with creating superior resources contained in figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> stated that they must have strong roots, which are based on honesty by developing integrity, mutual respect, discipline, honesty, self-confidence, fairness, concern for driven by high enthusiasm and passion, producing competence, namely skills, knowledge and good behavior.</p><p>In maintaining the quality of providing quality education, of course, Unisadhuguna must have quality human resources, because human resources are a very important element in determining the success of a company. After all, humans are creatures that have thoughts, feelings, needs, and certain expectations. This requires special attention because these factors will affect work performance, dedication, loyalty, and love for work and company. So the company must be able to create conditions that can encourage or enable employees to develop and improve their abilities and skills optimally.</p><p>Based on data that since 2019, the target number of students has not been met, it can be stated that performance needs to be improved. To win market competition, every company is required to always improve the performance of its employees, to compete and win the competition. Improving employee performance is very important because it is closely related to company profitability. Efforts that can be taken by the company include motivating employees through the implementation of compensation according to their abilities so that job satisfaction is achieved, employees who feel satisfied will be more loyal and their performance will increase within the company. Job satisfaction is an important condition that every employee must have employees who work, where humans can interact with the work environment and they will work with passion as well seriously so that their contribution to achieving company goals will increase (Kunartinah, 2012). Dermawan, et al <ref type="bibr">(2015)</ref> prove that compensation has a significant effect on job satisfaction. Employee motivation and expectations to get appropriate compensation make employees work optimally to achieve high performance for employees. Murty and Hudiwinarsih (2012) state that a motivated employee will be energetic and enthusiastic, and conversely, an employee with low motivation will often display discomfort and displeasure with their work which results in their performance being poor and company goals not being achieved. Sulistyani et al. <ref type="bibr">(2003)</ref> state that subjective employee satisfaction comes from conclusions based on comparisons between what employees receive compared to what is expected and desired.</p><p>Motivation is a potential force that exists in a human being that can be developed by himself, or developed by some outside forces which are essentially about monetary rewards and non-monetary rewards, which can affect the results of his performance positively or negatively, which depends on the situation and conditions. faced by the person concerned <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Winardi, 2001)</ref>.</p><p>Dermawan, et al <ref type="bibr">(2015)</ref> proved that compensation has a significant effect on job satisfaction. Motivation and expectations of employees to get appropriate compensation to make employees work optimally to achieve high performance for employees. Murty and Hudiwinarsih (2012) state that a motivated employee will be energetic and enthusiastic, and conversely, an employee with low motivation will often display discomfort and displeasure with their work which results in their performance being poor and company goals not being achieved.</p><p>As explained above, motivation, compensation, and increasing job satisfaction are ways that companies can improve the performance of their employees in achieving targets that are currently not being met so that they can also empower and explore the potential of PT. Unisadhuguna needs to increase attention to the performance of its employees, through motivation, providing appropriate compensation, and increasing the job satisfaction of its employees. The hope of this is that employees can work more productively so that it is useful for the company at this time and in the future.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>LITERATURE REVIEW Employee Performance</head><p>According to Mangkunegara (2008), performance is the result of work in quality and quantity achieved by an employee or an employee in carrying out his duties following the responsibilities given to him. Based on the opinion above, it can be concluded that performance is the appearance of work results that can be achieved by employees based on the skills, experience, sincerity, and time needed to do the work that is their job and all these results will be assessed by the company or their superiors and also work performance is the result of work that achieved by an employee or workforce in a certain period compared to the criteria or standards, targets or goals that have been determined. This is feedback to employees about the implementation of their work.</p><p>Employee performance indicators according to Mathis (2002) are as follows: a. Quantity. Quantity is the amount of work that can be done by someone in one working day. b. Quality. Quality is adherence to procedures, discipline, and dedication. c. Employee reliability. Employee reliability is the ability to do the job required with minimum supervision. Employee reliability includes performance consistency and reliability in service, accuracy, truth, and precision. d. Presence. Attendance is the belief that you will come to work every day and according to working hours. Feelings of satisfaction (in the sense of being satisfied with the product and service), namely the expression of feelings of satisfaction or dissatisfaction from customers when receiving good service and quality products from the company.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Compensation</head><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kadarisman (2012)</ref>, compensation is an award to employees fairly and properly for work achievements and for services that have been issued towards organizational goals to achieve organizational goals. With this positive impact, it will certainly provide benefits for the organization/company which will attract employees with a high level of competence to work for the organization or company.</p><p>According to Simamora (2015), compensation indicators are: a. Wages and Salaries. Wages are the most frequently used payment for production and maintenance workers. Wages are generally linked to hourly wage rates and wages are usually applied to annual, monthly, or weekly pay rates. b. Incentive. Incentives are additional compensation above or beyond the salary or wages provided by the company.</p><p>The Influence of Motivation and Compensation on Employee Performance at Pt Unisadhuguna with Job Satisfaction Mediation c. Allowances. Allowances are health and life insurance, pension plans, vacations paid by the company, and other benefits related to employment. d. Facility. Amenities are generally associated with amenities such as company cars or access to company aircraft that employees obtain</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Job Satisfaction</head><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Handoko (2021)</ref>, job satisfaction is an employee's opinion that is pleasant or not about his work, This feeling can be seen from the employee's good behavior towards work and all the things that are experienced in the work environment. Thus job satisfaction is also related to the sense of belonging and loyalty of employees because it is a view of their affection or feelings for the organization or company Job satisfaction is an employee's attitude towards work related to work situations, cooperation between employees, rewards received at work, and matters relating to physical and psychological factors <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Sutrisno, 2019)</ref>. This attitude can be in the form of a positive attitude, which means employees or members of the organization are satisfied, or even negative, which means they are dissatisfied with all aspects of the job, be it from the work situation, task load, rewards, risks, and so on. Meanwhile, Vecchino <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Wibowo, 2016)</ref> argues that job satisfaction is a person's thoughts, feelings, and action tendencies which are a person's attitude towards work. This means that job satisfaction is also very related to the overall mental processes and actions that will be carried out by employees or personnel. In other words, this attitude will affect their performance and psychological processes towards the work they will do.</p><p>Measurement of job satisfaction must be carried out objectively through analysis and identification of concrete symptoms which are indications of satisfaction itself. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Afandi (2018)</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Motivation</head><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hasibuan (2005)</ref>, motivation is the provision of a driving force that creates excitement in one's work so that they want to work together, work effectively, and integrate with all their resources and efforts to achieve satisfaction.</p><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Robbins (2016)</ref>, motivation is the willingness to make high efforts to achieve organizational goals conditioned by the ability to meet certain individual needs. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Wibowo (2016)</ref>, Motivation is the encouragement of a series of processes of human behavior in achieving goals. Meanwhile, motivation according to Sutrisno (2019) is as follows: "Motivation is a factor that encourages someone to carry out a certain activity, therefore motivation is often interpreted as a driving factor for one's behavior According to Maslow in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hosnawati (2016)</ref>, the indicators used to measure work motivation are as follows a. Physiological needs b. Safety needs c. Social needs d. The need for appreciation e. Self-actualization</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESEARCH METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Design</head><p>Based on the research objectives, this research is explanatory through hypothesis testing to test the causal relationship between the variables of motivation, compensation, training, and employee performance. The data used in this study is primary data by surveying by distributing questionnaires to employees of PT. Unisadhuguna. The data analysis method used is the descriptive analysis method and path analysis. Descriptive analysis is used to analyze data by describing or describing the data that has been collected as it is without intending to make general conclusions or generalizations and knowing the description of each respondent's statement based on each indicator on each variable studied, while path analysis is used to test the hypothesis to obtain a direct or indirect causal relationship between motivation, compensation, job satisfaction, and employee performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Population and Sample</head><p>Population is a collection of data that has the same characteristics and becomes an object of inference. Inference statistics bases itself on two basic concepts, the population as all data, both real and imaginary, and the sample, as part of the population used to make inferences (approach/description) to the population from which it originates.</p><p>The population according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Sugiyono (2013)</ref>, is a generalization area consisting of objects or subjects that have certain qualities and characteristics determined by researchers to be studied and then draw conclusions. In this study, the population is all employees of PT. Non-director UNISADHUGUNA, totaling 94 people According to Arikunto (2012) if the population is less than 100 people, then the total sample is taken as a whole, but if the population is greater than 100 people, then 10-15% or 20-25% of the total population can be taken. Based on this research, because the total population is not greater than 100 respondents, the authors take 100% of the population at PT. Unisadhuguna, namely as many as 94 respondents. Thus the use of the entire population without having to draw a research sample as a unit of observation is referred to as a census technique.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis Models</head><p>An analysis model is a method or way of processing data into information so that the characteristics of the data are easy to understand and also useful for finding solutions to problems, especially in research. The goal is to describe the data so that it can be understood, and then to make inferences or draw conclusions about the characteristics of the population based on the data obtained from the sample, usually based on guessing or testing hypotheses. According to Ferdinand (2006), descriptive analysis is used to provide an empirical description or description of the data collected in the study. The data that has been collected is then edited, coded, and tabulated to explain the characteristics of the variables studied in the descriptive analysis in the form of a frequency table.</p><p>The path analysis model is a tool used to analyze the pattern of relationships between variables to know the direct and indirect effects of a set of independent variables on the dependent variable. Path analysis is also an analytical technique used to analyze the inherent causal relationships between variables arranged according to a temporary order by using the path coefficient as a magnitude value in determining the magnitude of the influence of exogenous independent variables on endogenous dependent variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Sarwono, 2012)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESEARCH RESULT Model Test</head><p>Step I The structural equation model used as a whole consists of two exogenous variables, one mediating variable, and one endogenous variable. The picture above shows that the variable is affected by the estimation of direct effect, indirect effect, and total effect. The results showed that the effect value of the regression coefficient, both direct, indirect, and total effect has a significance value (p-value).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Coefficients</head><p>a. Hypothesis 1 Based on the hypothesis test, hypothesis 1 shows that employee motivation and performance have a positive and significant value on job satisfaction. With a coefficient value of 0.226, the effect is greater than 0.05 (p-value &gt; 0.05), it can be said that empirically and theoretically, motivation has a positive and significant effect on employee performance. b. Hypothesis 2 Based on the hypothesis test, hypothesis 2 shows that compensation has a positive and significant value on employee performance. With a compensation value of 0.264 which is greater than 0.05 (p-value &lt; 0.05), it can be said that empirically and theoretically, compensation has a positive and significant effect on employee performance. c. <ref type="bibr">Hypothesis</ref>  Based on the hypothesis test, hypothesis 4 shows that compensation has a positive and significant value on job satisfaction. With a compensation coefficient value of 0.376 which is greater than 0.05 (p-value &gt; 0.05), it can be said that empirically and theoretically, compensation has a positive and significant effect on job satisfaction. e. Hypothesis 5 Based on the hypothesis test, hypothesis 5 shows that job satisfaction has a positive and significant value on employee performance. With a job satisfaction coefficient value of 0.241 which is greater than 0.05 (p-value &gt; 0.05), it can be said that empirically and theoretically, job satisfaction has a positive and significant effect on employee performance. f. Hypothesis 6 Based on the results of hypothesis testing through job satisfaction. The effect of the coefficient value on the exogenous variable motivation on job satisfaction and the influence of the job satisfaction variable on employee performance can be seen based on the coefficients of direct and indirect influence, with a coefficient value greater than 0.05 (p-value &lt;0.05), it can be said that empirically and theoretically, motivation has a positive and significant effect on employee performance through job satisfaction.</p><p>When referring to the hypothesis table, it can be seen that the magnitude of the total indirect effect of 0.289 is greater than the direct effect of 0.226. It can be said that the intervening variable or job satisfaction functions on the variable motivation on employee performance. g. Hypothesis 7</p><p>Based on the results of hypothesis testing through job satisfaction. The effect of the coefficient value on the exogenous variable competence on job satisfaction and the influence of the job satisfaction variable on employee performance can be seen based on the indirect coefficient, with a coefficient value greater than 0.05 (p-value &gt; 0.05), it can be said that empirically and theoretically, compensation has a positive and significant effect on employee performance through job satisfaction. Referring to the hypothesis table, it can be seen that the magnitude of the indirect total effect of 0.466 is greater than the direct effect of 0.376. It can be said that the intervening variable job satisfaction functions on the competency variable on employee performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">The Effect of Motivation on Employee Performance</head><p>Motivation is an encouragement that comes both from within (intrinsic) and from outside (extrinsic) to fulfill all needs and desires. The company strives with its strategy to accommodate the motivation of its employees. PT Unisadhuguna tends to agree that motivation is shaped by indicators of physiological needs, safety needs, social needs, and needs for esteem and actualization. Indicators of physiological needs and the need for appreciation provide the greatest support in shaping motivation. This proves that PT. Unisadhuguna tries to meet the needs of its employees, for example by increasing periodic salaries, providing health insurance, conducting gathering activities, and providing opportunities for its employees to take part in self-development programs with overseas university partners and support and appreciate scientific work. published by its employees. Indicators of physiological needs and the need for appreciation as a measure of motivational variables provide the greatest contribution and are followed by other indicators. This means indicators of physiological needs and the need for appreciation dominate more as a measure of motivational variables compared to other indicators. The results showed that the indicators of physiological needs and the need for appreciation were the best reflections of motivational variables. If related to the concept of motivation, PT. Unisadhuguna tries to run to improve the performance of its employees.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">The Effect of Compensation on Employee Performance</head><p>Compensation is the overall remuneration received by employees as a result of carrying out work in the organization. Every company is obliged to provide compensation to its employees, which is also regulated by law. Analysis of the description of the compensation variable shows that PT Unisadhuguna employees tend to agree that compensation is formed by indicators of wages and salaries, incentives, benefits, and facilities. Employment indicators provide the greatest support in compensation. This shows that the compensation provided by the company tends to be good so the employee turnover rate is very small. The estimation model shows the factor loading value of the Compensation variable indicating that the allowance indicator as a measure of the Compensation variable gives the largest contribution and is followed by other indicators. This means that the allowance indicator dominates as a measure of the compensation variable compared to other indicators. The results of the study show that the allowance indicator is the best reflection of the Compensation variable. The compensation provided is also to achieve good employee performance. However, based on research conducted at PT. Unisadhuguna shows that compensation has no significant effect on employee performance. Appropriate compensation allows employees to focus on the work they are doing.</p><p>Compensation is closely related to the position and effort that employees make in achieving company targets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Influence of Motivation and Compensation on Employee Performance at Pt Unisadhuguna with Job Satisfaction Mediation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">The Effect of Motivation on Job Satisfaction</head><p>Descriptive analysis of job satisfaction variables is formed by job indicators, quality, quantity, supervisors, and co-workers. Job indicators provide the greatest support in shaping job satisfaction, namely if the targets are given by the company and employees feel that the things they are doing are quite challenging because they need ideas -innovative ideas in the solution. By being a pioneer of international education programs affiliated with universities abroad, this program has proven to be one of the advantages or competitiveness possessed by PT. Unisadhuguna when compared to other competitors. In the Job Satisfaction variable, the job value indicator as a measure of the Job Satisfaction variable gives the largest contribution and is followed by other indicators. This means the indicator of job value dominates as a measure of Job Satisfaction compared to other indicators. The results showed that the job value indicator is the best reflection of the Job Satisfaction variable. PT. Unisadhuguna tries to accommodate the motivation of its employees in the hope of increasing job satisfaction. Although based on research conducted, motivation does not affect the job satisfaction of PT. Unisadhuguna.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Effect of Compensation on Job Satisfaction.</head><p>Compensation is the total remuneration received by employees as a result of carrying out work in the organization. Every company is obliged to provide compensation to its employees, which is regulated by law. Analysis of the description of the compensation variable shows that PT Unisadhuguna employees tend to agree that compensation is formed by indicators of wages and salaries, incentives, allowances, and facilities. Employment indicators provide the greatest support in compensation. This shows that the compensation provided by the company tends to be good so the employee turnover rate is very small. The estimation model shows the factor loading value of the Compensation variable showing that the benefits indicator as a measure of the Compensation variable makes the largest contribution and is then followed by other indicators. This means that the benefits indicator dominates as a measure of the compensation variable compared to other indicators. The results of the research show that the benefits indicator is the best reflection of the Compensation variable, by providing good compensation to its employees, it has a positive and significant influence on the Job Satisfaction of PT. Unisadhuguna employees.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">The Effect of Job Satisfaction on Employee Performance</head><p>The descriptive analysis of the job satisfaction variable is formed by job indicators, wages/salaries, promotions, supervisors, and co-workers. Job indicators provide the greatest support in forming Job Satisfaction. To achieve Employee Performance which will demonstrate the existence of a company, the company with the strategy or policy it issues will make efforts to achieve Employee Performance. Through job indicators, quality, promotions, supervisors, and co-workers, this can be seen from the small turnover rate, employees who work until retirement, which in the end, will achieve Employee Performance.</p><p>The research results state that job satisfaction has a positive effect on employee performance, this is in line with the results of research conducted by Nurcahyani, and Adnyani (2016) Research results show that Job Satisfaction has a positive effect on Employee Performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">The Effect of Motivation on Employee Performance, through Job Satisfaction as an Intermediate Variable.</head><p>Motivation is formed by indicators of physiological needs, safety needs, social needs, esteem needs, and self-actualization. This can be seen from the employees of PT. Unisadhuguna strongly agrees that basic needs, housing, and rewards are met by working for the company PT employees Unisadhuguna tends to agree that Job Satisfaction is shaped by indicators of work, quality, promotions, supervisors, and colleagues. It can be seen that PT. Unisadhuguna employees agree that the job targets given by the company are appropriate. PT employees Unisadhuguna agree that Employee Performance is measured through indicators of quantity, quality, employee reliability, and always present. This is supported by the results of research that employees of PT. Unisadhuguna is satisfied with the good quality of its work, satisfied with its reliability in doing the job. From the research results, Job Satisfaction does not act as a mediating variable that increases Employee Performance. From the results of path analysis, it is known that the influence of motivation through Job Satisfaction on Employee Performance has a smaller value when compared to the direct influence of motivation on Employee Performance. Theoretically, this would be unusual. This relates to indicators in the Job Satisfaction variable such as work, quality, promotion, supervisor, and co-workers which logically can be used as material for consideration and strategy for a motivation and compensation variable in achieving employee performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">The Effect of Compensation on Employee Performance, through Job Satisfaction as an Intermediate Variable.</head><p>From the results of the study, job satisfaction acts as a mediating variable that adds to employee performance. From the results of path analysis, it is known that the effect of compensation through job satisfaction on employee performance has a greater value when compared to the direct effect of compensation on employee performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONS Conclusion</head><p>Based on the results of research on the effect of motivation and compensation on employee performance with job satisfaction as an intermediate variable, the following conclusions can be drawn: 1. Based on the results of the descriptive analysis, it is found that: a. Motivational variables. Indicators of physiological needs, safety needs, social needs, needs for appreciation, and selfactualization contribute to the motivation variable. b. Compensation variables. Indicators of wages and salaries, incentives, benefits, and facilities contribute to the compensation variable. c. Job satisfaction variables. Job indicators wage/salary, promotions, as well as supervisors and co-workers contribute to the job satisfaction variable. d. Employee performance variables. Indicators of quantity, quality, employee reliability, and attendance contribute to the employee performance variable. 2. Motivation affects increasing employee performance 3. Compensation affects improving employee performance 4. Motivation affects the increase in job satisfaction. 5. Compensation affects increasing job satisfaction. 6. Job satisfaction affects increasing employee performance. 7. Motivation affects employee performance through job satisfaction 8. Compensation affects employee performance through job satisfaction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RECOMMENDATIONS 1. For the leadership of PT. Unisadhuguna</head><p>Through this research, it is hoped that it will be useful for other related parties, especially for PT leaders. Ultrasound, taking into account the following: a. As previously discussed, motivation influences employee performance. In the integrated motivation variable, especially the self-actualization indicator which has the lowest value in the formation of the integrated motivation variable. This can be done by developing employee potential. PT. Unisadhuguma can create a further study scholarship program or training program for its employees who have good performance, this is expected to increase employee motivation to create better performance b. In the compensation variable, especially the facility indicator which has the lowest value in the formation of the compensation variable. this can be overcome by providing health insurance facilities with better providers. providing transportation needs by purchasing operational vehicles at each branch. c. The job satisfaction variable, especially the promotion indicator, has the lowest value in forming the job satisfaction variable.</p><p>In connection with this, PT. Unisadhuguna can create guidelines for instructions and implementation of job promotions. Providing clear information regarding the promotion system implemented by activating the intranet within the company. Carrying out a more transparent appraisal system with previously simulated tools. Based on research conducted to increase employee job satisfaction at PT. Unisadhuguna has a positive influence on employee performance d. In the employee performance variable, especially the quantity indicator which has the lowest value in the formation of the employee performance variable. In this case, Unisadhuguna can improve the job description for each position holder, create clear indicators in the employee performance assessment system, and provide information via the company's intranet. e. Motivation influences employee performance through job satisfaction. This research has resulted in a program for sending employees for further studies with partner universities for high-achieving employees to increase employee motivation so that employees who have had the opportunity to actualize themselves feel satisfied working at PT. Unisadhuguna in this way. employee performance can be even better f. Compensation affects employee performance through job satisfaction which has been proven in this research. Programs that can be prepared apart from those above are vehicle ownership for high-achieving employees. With this compensation, employees feel that their level of job satisfaction can be accommodated, thereby of course increasing their employee performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">for Further Research</head><p>For further research, it is hoped that this research will be useful as reference material and can be developed further, namely relating to new theories related to motivation about generational differences, compensation for employee performance through job satisfaction as a mediating variable, with its relation to new developments by industry developments. 4.0 currently proposed by Clayton Christensen with the theory of disruptive innovation, and exponential growth by Peter Diamandis as previously mentioned in the new research.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, the indicators of job satisfaction include the following. a. Work. The content of the work done by a person does it have satisfying elements? b. Wages/Salary. The amount of payment received by someone as a result of carrying out work is following the needs that are felt to be fair. c. Promotion. A person can develop through promotion. d. Supervisor. Someone who always gives orders or instructions in the implementation of work. e. Work colleague. Colleagues who help each other in completing work.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>The Influence of Motivation and Compensation on Employee Performance at Pt Unisadhuguna with Job Satisfaction Mediation</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Motivation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(X1)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.226</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>0.376 0.233</cell><cell>Job Satisfaction (Y1)</cell><cell>0.241</cell><cell>Employee (Y2) Performance</cell></row><row><cell>Compensation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(X2)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.264</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><p><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> </p>Based on the hypothesis test, hypothesis 3 shows that motivation has a positive and significant value on job satisfaction. With a motivation coefficient value of 0.233 which is greater than 0.05 (p-value &gt; 0.05), it can be said that empirically and theoretically, motivation has a positive and significant effect on job satisfaction. d. Hypothesis 4</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia (Teori, Konsep dan Indikator)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Afandi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Zanafa Publishing</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Riau</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pengaruh Kompensasi danPengembangan Karier Terhadap Kepuasan Kerja dengan Mediasi Motivasi Kerja</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Agus</forename><surname>Dwi Nugroho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kunartinah</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Bisnis dan Ekonomi (JBE)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia. Cetakan Pertama. Penerbit Graha Ilmu</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ambar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sulistiyani Dan Rosidah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<pubPlace>Yogyakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manajemen Sumber Daya manusia Perusahaan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anwar</forename><surname>Prabu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mangkunegara</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Rosda</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Bandung</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Prosedur Penelitian Suatu Pendekatan Praktek</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Suharsimi</forename><surname>Arikunto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Rineka Cipta</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Metode Penelitian Manajemen: Pedoman Penelitian untuk skripsi</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ferdinand</forename><surname>Augusty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<pubPlace>Semarang</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Universitas Diponegoro</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Tesis dan Disertai Ilmu Manajemen</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Darmawan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Pengaruh Semangat Kerja, Komitmen Kerja dan Kompensasi terhadap Kepuasan Kerja Pegawai</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<pubPlace>Metromedia, Surabaya</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia. Cetak ke sebelas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Edy</forename><surname>Sutrisno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>Prananda Media Group</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manajemen Personalia dan Sumber Daya Manusia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Handoko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>BPFE</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Yogyakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hasibuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Malayu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Edisi Revisi</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Bumi Aksara</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pengaruh Motivasi Kerja dan Komitmen Organisasi Terhadap Kinerja Karyawan dengan Etos Kerja Sebagai Variabel Moderasi</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hosnawati</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Profita: Kajian Ilmu Akuntansi</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manajemen Pengembangan Sumber Daya Manusia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kadarisman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Raja Grafindo Persada</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mathis</forename><surname>Robert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jackson</forename><surname>John</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia. Jakarta : Salemba empat</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Pengaruh Kompensasi, Motivasi dan komitmen Organiasial Terhadap Kinerja Karyawan Bagian Akuntansi Studi Kasus Pada Perusahaan Manfukatur di Surabaya</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hudiwinarsih</forename><surname>Murti Dan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>STIE Perbanas Surabaya</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pengaruh Kompensasi Dan Motivasi Terhadap Kinerja Karyawan Dengan Kepuasan Kerja Sebagai Variabel Intervening</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ni</forename><surname>Nurcahyani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dewi</forename><surname>Made Dan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Adnyani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Manajemen</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Robbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Timothy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Judge</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Perilaku Organisasi Edisi</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Salemba Empat</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonathan</forename><surname>Sarwono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Path Analysis Untuk Riset Skripsi, Tesis dan Disertasi. Jakarta: Elex Media Komputindo Kompas Gramedia</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Simamora</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia. Yogyakarta : SIE YKPN</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Metode Penelitian Kuantitatif, Kualitatif dan R&amp;D</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sugiyono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Alfabeta.CV</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Bandung</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wibowo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Manajemen Kinerja, Edisi Kelima, PT. Rajagrafindo Persada Jakarta-14240</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Motivasi dan Pemotivasian dalam Manajemen. Jakarta: PT. Raja Grafindo Persada. There is an Open Access article, distributed under the term of the Creative Commons Attribution -Non</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Winardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>Commercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0</idno>
		<ptr target="https://creativecommons.or/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>), which permits remixing, adapting and building upon the work for non-commercial use. provided the original work is properly cited</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
