<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Analysis and control of vehicle steering wheel vibration based on acceleration transfer path analysis method Xiaoming Ye Dongfeng Motor Corporation</title>
				<funder ref="#_tcQNTYe">
					<orgName type="full">Scientific Research Projects of Dongfeng Motor Corporation Technical Center of China</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2023-09-27">September 27th, 2023</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yongliang</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Dongfeng Motor Corporation Technical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>430058</postCode>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Xiaoming</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wuhan University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>430070</postCode>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Dongfeng Motor Corporation Technical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>430058</postCode>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hao</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Dongfeng Motor Corporation Technical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>430058</postCode>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ting</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Dongfeng Motor Corporation Technical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>430058</postCode>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Menglei</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Dongfeng Motor Corporation Technical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>430058</postCode>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dongfeng Motor Corporation https://orcid.org</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Motor Corporation Ting Luo Dongfeng Motor Corporation Menglei Sun Dongfeng Motor Corporation</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>9534-8226 Hao Liu Dongfeng</addrLine>
									<postCode>0000-0001</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Analysis and control of vehicle steering wheel vibration based on acceleration transfer path analysis method Xiaoming Ye Dongfeng Motor Corporation</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2023-09-27">September 27th, 2023</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.21203/rs.3.rs-3298074/v1</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T21:39+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Acceleration transfer path method</term>
					<term>Steering wheel vibration</term>
					<term>Contribution analysis</term>
					<term>Structural modi cation</term>
					<term>Vibration control Acceleration transfer path method</term>
					<term>Steering wheel vibration</term>
					<term>Contribution analysis</term>
					<term>Structural modification</term>
					<term>Vibration control</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper is aimed to analyze and control the structure vibration of a vehicle steering wheel by using the acceleration transfer path analysis (TPA) method and vibration sensitivity method. A steering wheel vibration test is conducted to obtain the critical engine speed and corresponding to the frequency. The acceleration-acceleration transfer function from mounts body side to steering wheel is deducted and tested, in conjunction with the actual acceleration spectrums of mounts body side, the acceleration spectrum of steering wheel is synthesized and the accuracy of the synthetic results is evaluated high. Then the vibration transmitted by each path is investigated and the main vibration participation paths are picked out from numerous paths. The interaction mechanisms between the path transfer vibration, path vibration participation and the total vibration are further obtained. The critical parameters (mounting stiffnesses and vibration sensitivity) of the main vibration participation paths are matched, modified and the vibration control effect is experimental verified. The results indicate that, by pertinently matching the stiffness parameters of the mounts and reducing vibration sensitivity of structure, the dynamic force transmitted by the paths are decreased, the vibration transfer functions from mounts body side to steering wheel are decreased, and then the actual steering wheel vibration is controlled.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The trimbody (TB) structure are vulnerable to vibrate (especially the steering wheel of TB), when the exciting frequency of engine or road is close to the natural frequencies of powertrain rigid mode, steering wheel elastic mode or suspension elastic mode. If the steering wheel structure vibration perceived by passengers, it will affect the vehicle NVH performance seriously. Thus, it is an important and meaningful task for engineers to control the vibration of steering wheel structures to design high quality products.</p><p>The underlying physics governing of this dynamic behavior (steering wheel vibration) can be represented by the excitation characteristics (such as engine dynamic load or road dynamic load) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> and in conjunction with vibration transfer function (VTF) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> (also known as vibration sensitivity). In analyzing the VTFs for steering wheel structures, which is a low frequency vibration (frequency less than 60Hz) problem, the applications of numerical analytical method <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> (Multi-body Dynamics Model or Finite Element Model) or experimental test method (such as Hammer Transmission Experiment) are often employed <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> .</p><p>In order to control the vibration of structures, a transfer path analysis (TPA, also known as Classical TPA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> or a modified TPA (e.g. Operational TPA, Component-based TPA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> method are employed recently. TPA reveals the physical essence of the relationship between excitation source, transfer path and receiver. By using a TPA technology, the source excitations can be separated from the structural/acoustic transfer characteristics, allowing us to troubleshoot the dominant paths of vibration transmission. The engineer can then anticipate by making changes to either the source itself or the receiving structures that are connected to it <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> . Due to these advantages, TPA tends to be particularly associated with noise, vibration and harshness (NVH) engineering as commonly encountered in the automotive industry, although TPA having been developed mostly during the second half of the 20th century. The literatures on this aspect are voluminous, and we have compiled a selective to provide background information and useful cross-references on the subject. In the field of TPA, literatures <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> explained the general framework: history, theory and the classification of techniques, which was a useful asset to help understanding the countless possibilities and combinations within the TPA paradigm. The transfer matrix method (or modified transfer matrix method) in conjunction with experimental technique have been developed for analyzing and controlling the vibration and noise transmission of engineering structure, such as the study of the effect of structure-borne or air-borne paths induced interfering noise of a vehicle cab (e.g. braking noise <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> ,road noise <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref> , acceleration noise <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> , sound quality <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> ). With the two time-domain TPA models, Liu <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> found that the models can predict the transient vibration in the door slamming event and the contribution of each transfer path was obtained. Based on the transmissibility concept, Cervantes <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> investigated the design and implementation of a simplified method, which allows a rapid and accurate analysis. By using the power flow analysis and acoustic path participation method, literatures <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> obtained the high energy transfer paths and the dynamic parameters of these paths being modified to reduce noise radiation. Although the TPA or modified TPA have been investigated theoretically (e.g. Refs <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref> ) and applied to control the structure vibration (e.g. Refs <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref> ), the theoretical calculation process is complex which needs to voluminous formula derivation, matrix inversion and interface force calculation, or there is no independent intellectual property right by using the existing TPA commercial software (such as LMS Test.Lab or HEAD acoustics). The literatures about rapid TPA (with these characteristics: theory and application convenient, having independent intellectual property rights) and in conjunction with the dynamic parameter matching of identified path on the basis of vibration sensitivity analysis are handful.</p><p>Steering wheel vibration is caused by the excitation characteristics and vibration transfer characteristics of each system. To achieve significant vibration reduction at the steering wheel, the critical paths and critical structures need to be identified and matched. The current paper is partly motivated by these investigations and carries out related research. The direct acceleration TPA method is proposed, deducted, verified and applied to identify critical paths, and then the vibration sensitivity is investigated to modify critical structures. The remainder will be organized as follows. Section 2 will theoretically deduce the vibration sensitivity method and acceleration TPA method; Section 3 describes an engineering case application (steering wheel vibration); Acceleration TPA method will be applied to investigate steering wheel vibration and obtain the critical vibration participation paths in Section 4; The vibration sensitivity analysis will be conducted and structural parameters will be modified to control steering wheel vibration in Section 5; Section 6 draws some concluding remarks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Theoretical formulation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Vibration sensitivity method</head><p>A dynamic load F (ω) imposes at a node S on the structure (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>), the vibration responses of interest at node R on the structure (e.g. the steering wheel) can be numerical calculated, which can be written as [19,20]    </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">         - ( ) + ( ) ( ) ( ) i t i t i t i t M X e i C X e K X e F e           + = (1) () ( )= - + + F X M i C K    (1.1)</formula><p>where, x is the displacement response of the node R when dynamic load F(ω) imposed. M, C and K represent the mass matrix, damping matrix and stiffness matrix of structure respectively. ω and i is the angular frequency and plural unit, respectively. Taking the second derivatives of Eq. (1.1), the acceleration response of the node R is expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">2 2 - ( ) ( )=- ( ) - + + F a X M i C K      = (2)</formula><p>And then, the vibration transfer function (i.e. TF (ω)) that acceleration response of the node R with respect to the dynamic load F (ω) can be derived</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">2 ( ) - ( )= = ( ) - + + a TF F M i C K     <label>(3)</label></formula><p>It can be known from the Eq.( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">3</ref>) that the TF(ω) is only related to mass matrix, damping matrix and stiffness matrix of structure, which reveals the vibration transfer characteristics of the structure. The TF (ω) is also presented as the vibration sensitivity, revealing the sensitivity level of acceleration response of the node R caused by excitation at a node S. If the excitation node S and the receiver node R is a same node or the distance between the two nodes is very close, the TF(ω) is called input point inertance (i.e.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IPI(ω)).</head><p>A smaller value of the IPI(ω) in a certain frequency rang illustrates that the structure is not sensitive to external dynamic load at this frequency rang. If the excitation node S and the receiver node </p><formula xml:id="formula_3">R</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Acceleration transfer path method</head><p>Excitations, such as the engine load or road load, are transmitted into the vehicle body through the vibration isolation components or connecting nodes leading to steering wheel forced vibration (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</p><p>To investigate the relationship between excitation source, transfer path and receiver, the acceleration TPA method is derived in this section. The diagrammatic sketch of vibration transfer paths of a steering wheel is provided in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>. The engine mounts bushing and suspensions bushing are the interaction interfaces of the vibration transmission. These interaction interfaces are numbered from 1 to n (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>), and each interaction interface corresponds to a vibration transfer path. For the kth path, dynamic load Fk (ω) imposes at the passive side of bush and numerical calculate or test the vibration of steering wheel and imposing node. According to the Eq.( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">3</ref>), the vibration transfer function of the imposing node corresponding to steering wheel and IPI of the imposing node can be expressed respectively as</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">2 () - ( )= = () - + + r r k k r r r k k k k a TF F M i C K      (4) 2 () - ( ) = () - + + k k k k k k k k k k k a IPI F M i C K      = (<label>5</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">)</formula><p>in which, the M r k, C r k and K r k represent the mass matrix, damping matrix and stiffness matrix of structure corresponding to the path from imposing node to steering wheel. The M k k, C k k and K k k represent the mass matrix, damping matrix and stiffness matrix of structure at the imposing node. The Eqs.( <ref type="formula">4</ref>) and (5) can be rewritten in a dB form, which is more commonly used in the NVH field. where, the reference vibration sensitivity TFref(ω)=1m/s 2 /N.</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">() dB( ( ))=20 lg( ) () r r k k ref TF TF TF    (6) () dB( ( ))=20lg( ) () k k k k ref IPI IPI TF   <label>(7)</label></formula><p>By using the Eqs.( <ref type="formula">4</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">5</ref>), the accelerate-accelerate transfer function of the path from imposing node to steering wheel can be derived as</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) - + + ( ) = () ( ) ( ) ( ) - + + r r r k k k r k k k k k k k k k k k r r r k k k k k k k TF a F a M i C K ATF F IPI a a M i C K              = =  =<label>(8)</label></formula><p>Focusing on the Eq.( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">8</ref>), it is clear that ATF r k (ω) can be real or imaginary, or both, illustrating the acceleration spectrum transfer characteristics of the receiver with respect to the imposing node.</p><p>For the actual engine dynamic load excitation or road dynamic load excitation, the vibration acceleration transmitted to the passive side of bush denotes a s (ω)=(a s 1(ω), a s 2(ω),…,a s k(ω),…, a s n(ω)).</p><p>Thus，the vibration acceleration of steering wheel caused by the kth path transmitted can be obtained as</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">( ) - + + () ( ) - + + r k k k sr r s s s k k k k k k k k k k r r r k k k k TF M i C K a ATF a a a IPI M i C K        =  =  = <label>(9)</label></formula><p>The vibration acceleration of steering wheel caused by engine or road excitation is the superposition of the transmission vibration of each path, which can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">T 1 1 1 - + + ( ) ( ) ( ( ) )= ( ) - + + k k k n n n sr r sr r s s k k k k k k k r r r k k k k k k M i C K a a ATF a a M i C K      = = = =  = =     s ATF a (<label>10</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">)</formula><p>The superscript T denotes the complex conjugate of the a s .</p><p>If the calculated acceleration by using the Eq.( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">10</ref>) is in good agreement with the result of direct measurement acceleration at steering wheel, it indicates that the acceleration TPA method proposed in this paper has a high accuracy and can be applied to engineering problems. Thus, under such circumstances, the Eq.( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">9</ref>) can be used to further study the participation of path transmitted vibration to total vibration, which can be deduced as  According to the above theoretical derivation, the acceleration TPA method proposed in this paper is convenient, having independent intellectual property rights (no need to use commercial TPA software, such as LMS Test.Lab or HEAD acoustics) and no need to extract sub-structures from the whole vibration system. By using the acceleration TPA method, the critical paths of interest are identified from numerous paths. It is convenient for engineers to modify dynamic parameters of these critical paths to reduce the vibration of steering wheel pertinently and efficiently.</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">_ cos( , )<label>cos</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Engineering case study</head><p>During the slow acceleration of a four stroke four cylinder engine vehicle, the steering wheel vibration is serious within the 1000 rpm -1300rpm speed range, which is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>. The Y-labels in the Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref> is in a dB form, and the relationship between acceleration and dB is expressed as, in which the reference acceleration a0=1m/s 2 .</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">0 dB( )=20lg( ) a a a (<label>12</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">)</formula><p>1800 9001000 1100 1200 1300 1400 1500 1600 rpm 0 - It can be found from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref> that the vibration acceleration curve of steering wheel exists two large peaks, -2.7dB@1050rpm and -1.8dB@1250rpm respectively. The second-order vibration is the main contribution, which are -3.0dB@1050rpm and -2.3dB@1250rpm respectively. According to the formulation in literature [1] and in conjunction with the excitation characteristics of a four stroke four cylinder engine, the critical frequencies corresponding to the two peaks are 35Hz and 41.7Hz respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Application of acceleration TPA method</head><p>We choose the 35Hz (i.e. 1050rpm) as the critical frequency of interest to validate the acceleration TPA method proposed in this paper, and identify critical vibration paths. The application of acceleration TPA method in steering wheel vibration is conducted in the following steps (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>).</p><p>Notes: ① The power-assembly (engine, transmission and accessories) is a pendulum arrangement which has three mounts (i.e. left mount, right mount and lower rod mount); ②Vehicle runs at a constant speed (34km/h @ 2 nd gear and engine speed 1050rpm).</p><p>Thus, the vibration of road excitation transmitted to the steering wheel through the suspension path can be ignored, because the road excitation being less than 10Hz is lower than the critical frequency 35Hz. respectively, meaning that the vibration sensitivity of the path P3 is higher than that of path P7, i.e, the path P3 is sensitive at 33Hz. Focusing on these two amplitude curves of VTF(ω), further analysis knows that the up and down nodding mode of the steering wheel is 33Hz.</p><p>By using the tested VTF(ω), IPI(ω) of the 9 paths and in conjunction with the Eq.( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">8</ref>), the accelerateaccelerate transfer functions (ATF(ω)) of the paths from mounts body side to steering wheel can be calculated, in which the ATF(ω) of two paths are given in Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>. It can be seen from Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref> that the amplitude curves of ATF(ω) exist peak values at 33Hz, which are 19.9 and 41.7</p><p>respectively. This means that an unit acceleration vibration at the Z-direction of left mounts or at the Xdirection of lower rod will cause 19.9 times or 41.7 times of the Z-direction vibration at 12 o'clock of steering wheel, respectively. The amplitude of ATF(ω) at 33Hz of path P7 is bigger than that of path P3, although the VTF(ω) at 33Hz of path P3 is larger. The reason for this is that the IPI(ω) at 33Hz of path P7 is much smaller, which is 0.0068 m/s 2 /N (see Fig. , it is clear that there are obvious peak at 35Hz, which are -22.8dB, -28.0dB and -25.2dB for left mount Z direction, low rod X direction and Z direction, respectively. The peak accelerations at 35Hz is caused by the second-order excitation of the engine. Focusing on the tested acceleration spectrum (i.e. black line) in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">8</ref>, it is easy to know that the main peak is around 35 Hz (-5.5dB), i.e. the overall vibration of steering wheel will be significantly reduced if the vibration around 35Hz is controlled. According to the 9 tested acceleration spectrums (including amplitude and phase), 9 accelerateaccelerate transfer functions (ATF(ω)) spectrums and in conjunction with the Eq.( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">10</ref>), the acceleration spectrum at Z direction of steering wheel 12 o'clock can be calculated, which is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">8</ref> (red line: synthetic results by using the acceleration TPA method). It can be seen from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">8</ref> that the relative error between the synthetic value and the tested value is small around 35Hz, the synthetic value is -3.97dB (35Hz) and relative error is 1.53dB. Thus, the accuracy of acceleration TPA method proposed in this paper is high and the steering wheel vibration can be well predicted and investigated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Critical vibration paths identification</head><p>Because of the high accuracy of acceleration TPA method, the Eq.( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">9</ref>) can be used to further investigate the vibration transmitted by each path. The vibration accelerations transferred by the 9 paths are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref>. It can be known from Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref> that the paths P3, P6 and P7 (i.e. Z direction of left mount, Z direction of right mount and X direction of low rod) transfer vibration to the Z direction of steering wheel 12 o'clock significantly, which are -14.3dB(35Hz), -13.2dB(35Hz) and -9.5dB(35Hz) (i.e. 0.19m/s 2 , 0.22 m/s 2 , 0.34 m/s 2 ) respectively. And then, the major paths vibration transfer participation with respect to total synthetic vibration is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">10</ref> and Table .1. Focusing on the results in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">10</ref> and Table .1, it is easy to obtain that the participations of the vibration transferred of the major paths (P3, P6 and P7) to the synthetic vibration are positive, which are 0.07m/s 2 , 0.21m/s 2 and 0.33m/s 2 respectively.</p><p>According to the theoretical method in Section 2.2, for the positive participation paths, the acceleration at Z direction of steering wheel 12 o'clock will decrease pronounced by reducing the vibration transmission of these main paths</p><p>Compared with the Classical TPA, Operational TPA or Component-based TPA <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> , the acceleration TPA method proposed in this paper is high accuracy, convenient in theory and application. Thus this is a novelty of this paper. On the basis of the acceleration TPA method, the critical paths are picked out from numerous paths and the vibration participation of paths are obtained, which is an useful information for instructing the engineers to modify the structure pertinently.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Structural parameters matching to control vibration</head><p>For the identified main paths, the stiffness parameters of powertrain mounts and structural parameters of steering wheel system will be matched and improved to control the vibration of steering wheel.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Modification of mounts stiffness parameters</head><p>The paths P7, P6 and P3 are the main vibration participation paths, especially P7 and P6. Thus matching mounts parameters of these paths will reduce the force transmitted from the engine excitation to the body structure, and then the steering wheel vibration decreased. Reduce the stiffness parameters of the X direction of lower rod, Z direction of right mount and Z direction of left mount, calculate the rigid body mode of powertrain and force transfer functions (FTF(ω)) of the mounts when crankshaft axis is excited by an unit dynamic torque (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">11</ref>). This force transfer functions (FTF(ω)) is also called the sensitivity of the rotational movement of the powertrain body to the mounts. The matched mounts samples are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">12</ref>, in which the mounts stiffness of the left mount, right mount and lower rod are 426N/mm, 220N/mm and 230N/mm respectively. It can be seen from Table .2 that the frequency distributions and energy decoupling of the Case1 are obviously better than that of the Base. The frequency distributions of three rotational modes is lower, especially the pitch mode. The frequency and the energy decoupling rate of pitch mode are 10.2Hz and 96.2% respectively.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>f(Hz)</head><p>Base-FTF@P6 Base-FTF@P7 Case1-FTF@P6 Case1-FTF@P7 Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">13</ref>. The matched mounts samples</p><p>The force transfer functions (FTF(ω)) analysis (i.e. rotational sensitivity of powertrain) is adopted to evaluate the effect of stiffness matching on the force at the mounts, and the simulation results are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">13</ref>. The relationship between force and dB is expressed as Eq. ( <ref type="formula">13</ref>), in which the reference force F0=1N. Focusing on the results in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">13</ref>, it is clear that, after mounts stiffness matching, the force transmitted by the path P7 is from -4.6dB(35Hz) to -14.9dB(35Hz) (i.e. 10.3dB decreased) and that of the path P6 is from -29.0dB(35Hz) to -41.4dB(35Hz) (i.e. 12.4dB decreased). The reason for this is that the frequency distributions and energy decoupling rates of the Case1 are better, which leading to less force transferred by the critical paths.</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">0 dB( )=20 lg( ) F F F (13) Original Matched</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Improvement of steering wheel structures</head><p>There are two ways to control steering wheel vibration: (1) Reducing dynamic forces at the interaction interfaces of the main vibration participation paths; (2) Controlling vibration sensitivity (i.e.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VTF(ω) and IPI(ω)</head><p>) from the interaction interfaces to steering wheel. The dynamic forces of the paths P7, P6 and P3 have been decreased in Section 5.1, here the vibration sensitivity corresponding to the main vibration participation paths will be controlled.</p><p>The tested and simulated vibration sensitivity of the paths P7 and P6 are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">14</ref>. Focusing on the results in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">14</ref>, it is clear that the trends of simulated VTF(ω) and tested VTF(ω) are in good agreement, the amplitude error is small in the frequency band 25Hz to 40Hz. The peak values of tested VTF(ω) are -18.4dB(33Hz) and -22.9dB(33Hz), the peak values of simulated VTF(ω) are -20.7dB(35Hz) and -27.2dB(35Hz). Thus, the critical frequency of simulated and tested agrees well, and that of peak amplitude also agrees well. In view of this, the accuracy of this simulation model is high and the structural modification scheme made by this FEM model can predict the vibration sensitivity effectively. In order to reduce the vibration sensitivity of the main vibration participation paths around 35Hz, the IPI(ω) parameters of Node 10 are crucial (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">15</ref>).Thus, with the help of FEM(TB + Powertrain) model, the X direction, Z direction and Ry direction IPI simulation analysis of the node 10 are carried out, and the results are given in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">16</ref>. It can be seen from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">16</ref> that the X direction, Z direction and Ry direction IPI values are 124.2mm/s 2 /N(34Hz), 43.7mm/s 2 /N(34Hz) and 3.6°/(Nm)(35Hz), respectively. To decrease IPI(ω) in X direction, a triangular support is adopt to vertically connect the transverse pipe beam and the front wall structure (see modified position①in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">17</ref>). The thickness of transverse pipe beam is increased from 1.6mm to 2mm (see modified position②in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">17</ref>) to decrease IPI(ω) in Z direction. A support plate is added at the left end face of the transverse pipe beam and the distance between bolt holes (see modified position③ and partial enlarged view in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">17</ref>) is increased to decrease IPI(ω) in Ry direction. The results of IPI analysis of the modified steering wheel structure are given in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">16</ref>. It can be found from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">16</ref> that the X direction, Z direction and Ry direction IPI values are 85.5 mm/s 2 /N(34Hz), 26.7mm/s 2 /N(34Hz) and 1.3°/Nm(35Hz), respectively (i.e. decreased 31%, 39% and 64% ). The simulated and tested VTF(ω) results of the main vibration participation paths after structure modification are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">18</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">19</ref>. It can be known from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">18</ref> that, the vibration sensitivity (i.e. VTF(ω)) of path P6 and P7 are reduced by 6.2dB(35Hz) and 8.0dB(35Hz), respectively. Focusing on the tested results in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">19</ref>, the vibration sensitivity of path P6 and P7 are reduced by 9.2dB(33Hz) and 11.0dB(33Hz), respectively.  Based on the theory of Section 2.1 and engineering application of Sections 5.1 and 5.2, the vibration sensitivity analysis (VTF (translational motion sensitivity or rotational motion sensitivity) and IPI) used in this paper is effective, targeted and the control effect of the improved scheme on vehicle vibration is evaluated in an early phase. This is another novelty of this paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Experimental verification</head><p>The improved scheme for slow acceleration steering wheel vibration is verified on the whole vehicle, and the comprehensive experimental verification of Case 1 in Sections 5.1 and Case 2 in Sections 5.2 denotes Opt. The test results are provided in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">20</ref>. It is obvious to find from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">20</ref> that, during vehicle slow acceleration, the steering wheel vibration decreases seriously in the engine speed range 1000rpm-1250rpm. The overall vibration and 2 order vibration of steering wheel are reduced by 7.9dB@1050rpm (i.e. from -2.7dB to -10.6dB) and 9.0dB@1050rpm (i.e. from -3.0dB to -12.0dB) respectively. Thus, the effectiveness of acceleration TPA method, vibration sensitivity analysis method and targeted reduction of structure vibration are verified by experiments. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Conclusions</head><p>In this paper, the structural vibration analysis and control are conducted by employing the acceleration TPA method and vibration sensitivity method. The acceleration TPA analysis is adopted to achieve the vibration transmitted by each path, vibration participation of path and identify the critical vibration participation paths. Then, the force transfer sensitivity and vibration transfer sensitivity of these critical paths are investigated, the mounts stiffness parameters matching and structural improvement are further studied to reduce steering wheel vibration pertinently and effectively. Based on the above analysis, the following conclusions could be derived:</p><p>(1) The acceleration TPA method proposed in this paper is convenient in theory and application, having independent intellectual property right. On the basis of the acceleration TPA method, the steering wheel vibration can be well predicted and investigated.</p><p>(2) For different vibration transfer paths, the vibration participation of paths with respect to total vibration is different and the relationship between path transmitted vibration, path vibration participation and total vibration are derived. The value of vibration participation can be positive or negative which is determined by the angle between path transmitted vibration and total vibration.</p><p>(3) The vibration sensitivity analysis used in this paper is convenient, effective and targeted. By matching the mounts stiffness parameters corresponding to the critical path, the force transfer functions of these path decrease evidently. By modifying the steering wheel structure (triangular support, pipe thickness, support plate and bolt hole distance), the values of IPI(ω) decreased significantly, and the VTF(ω) results of the main vibration participation paths reduce by more than 6dB. The vehicle verification shows that the steering wheel vibration is reduced by more than 8dB.</p><p>The acceleration TPA method in conjunction with the vibration sensitivity method proposed in this paper can be used to analyze and control the vibration of complex engineering structure pertinently and effectively. The advantage is particularly obvious when engineering structure is imposed complex excitations and has many vibration transfer paths. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig.1. An excitation source-vibration transfer path-receiver model of steering wheel</figDesc><graphic coords="4,165.65,262.93,260.73,119.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Diagrammatic sketch of vibration transfer paths of steering wheel</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>βk is the angle between the kth path transfer vibration (i.e. a sr k(ω)) and total vibration (i.e. a sr (ω)). The unit of a sr k_p(ω) is m/s 2 and the value of a sr k_p(ω) can be positive, negative or zero. The physical meaning of a sr k_p(ω) is the projection of the acceleration transmitted by the kth path in the direction of the total vibration. The relationship between total vibration and a sr k_p(ω) is shown in Fig.3. If |𝛽 𝑘 | 90º, |𝛽 𝑘 | = 90ºor |𝛽 𝑘 | 90º, the vibration participation of the kth path transmitted are positive, neutral or negative to the total vibration. With increasing the vibration of this path, the total vibration increases, keeps unchanged or reduces, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Relationship between total vibration and path vibration transmission participation</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. The Z-direction vibration at 12 o'clock of steering wheel (red line: Overall; green line: 2-order)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Process steps of acceleration TPA method in analysis steering wheel vibration at 1050rpm</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 6 .Fig. 7 . 4 . 2</head><label>6742</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. ATF(ω) of Z direction of left mount body side to Z direction of steering wheel 12 o'clock</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Acceleration spectrum at Z direction of steering wheel 12 o'clock (black line: direct test result; red line: synthetic result)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 9 .Fig. 10 .</head><label>910</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Amplitudes of the vibration acceleration transferred of the 9 paths (Unit: dB)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. Schematic diagram of simulation model</figDesc><graphic coords="11,205.79,331.00,190.14,187.47" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. The matched mounts samples</figDesc><graphic coords="12,299.61,292.83,105.30,90.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 14 .Fig. 15 .</head><label>1415</label><figDesc>Fig. 14. Tested and simulated vibration sensitivity of the paths P7 and P6</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 16 .</head><label>16</label><figDesc>Fig. 16. IPI simulation analysis of the node 10 (Solid line: result of original structure; Dotted line: result of modified structure) Notes: ①The original steering wheel structure denotes Base; ②The steering wheel with modified structure denotes Case2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Fig. 17 .Fig. 18 .Fig. 19 .</head><label>171819</label><figDesc>Fig. 17. Structural modification sample of steering wheel system</figDesc><graphic coords="14,182.60,276.22,309.60,113.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Fig. 20 .</head><label>20</label><figDesc>Fig. 20. Z-direction vibration at 12 o'clock of steering wheel (black line: Base; red line: Improved scheme)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Fig. A. 1 .Fig. A. 2 .Fig. A. 3 .Fig. A. 5 .</head><label>1235</label><figDesc>Fig. A.1. VTF(ω) of Z direction of left mount body side to Z direction of steering wheel 12 o'clock</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Based on the vibration sensitivity analysis method, engineers can design, analyze and estimate the vibration characteristics of structures pertinently.</figDesc><table><row><cell>are not close, the TF(ω) is called path vibration sensitivity (i.e. VTF(ω)). A smaller value of the VTF(ω) in a certain frequency rang illustrates that the vibration response of the node R is not sensitive to external dynamic load at this frequency rang. Thus, by designing structure to obtain a small value VTF(ω) or IPI(ω) within a frequency range, the structure will be insensitive to vibration, i.e. insensitive to vibration response or insensitive to vibration Source input. Path Receiver F a</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table . 1</head><label>.</label><figDesc>. Relationship between major paths vibration transfer, vibration participation and total synthetic vibration</figDesc><table><row><cell>Im</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>O</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>a3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Re</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">a sr (35Hz)= 0.63m/s 2</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Path No.</cell><cell></cell><cell>P3</cell><cell>P6</cell><cell>P7</cell><cell>Total synthetic vibration</cell></row><row><cell>Amplitude</cell><cell>dB m/s 2</cell><cell cols="2">-14.3 -13.2 0.19 0.22</cell><cell>-9.5 0.34</cell><cell>-4.3 0.63</cell></row><row><cell>Phase</cell><cell>°</cell><cell>-11</cell><cell>264</cell><cell>-92</cell><cell>-79</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Participation m/s 2</cell><cell>0.07</cell><cell>0.21</cell><cell>0.33</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>sr (35Hz)= 0.19m/s 2 a6 sr (35Hz)= 0.22m/s 2 a 7 sr (35Hz)= 0.34m/s</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>/N)</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>The authors would like to thank the <rs type="funder">Scientific Research Projects of Dongfeng Motor Corporation Technical Center of China</rs> (No. <rs type="grantNumber">91224Y190059</rs>) for the support given to this research. The constructive comments from the anonymous reviewers are also acknowledged.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_tcQNTYe">
					<idno type="grant-number">91224Y190059</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Declaration of competing interest</head><p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix A. Results of VTF(ω), IPI(ω) and acceleration spectrums</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design and analysis of a multi-stage torsional stiffness dual mass flywheel based on vibration control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Qin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Acoustics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="172" to="181" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transfer path analysis and its application to diagnosis for low-frequency transient vibration in the automotive door slamming event</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Measurement</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">183</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">109896</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transfer path analysis and its application in low-frequency vibration reduction of steering wheel of a passenger vehicle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Acoustics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">157</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">107021</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A customized scheme of crosstalk cancellation for operational transfer path analysis and experimental validation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Sound and Vibration</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">515</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">116506</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Research on Airborne Noise of Battery Electric Vehicles Based on Transfer Path Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Shangguan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>SAE International</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">01</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">323</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Evaluation of Uncertainties in Classical and Component (Blocked Force) Transfer Path Analysis (TPA)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Moorhouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Meggitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Elliott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>SAE International</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1779" to="1789" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">General framework for transfer path analysis: History, theory and classification of techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vander Seijs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>De Klerk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rixen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Mechanical Systems and Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="244" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Operational transfer path analysis: Theory, guidelines and tire noise application</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Klerk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ossipov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Mechanical Systems and Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1950" to="1962" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experimental and numerical study of Advanced Transfer Path Analysis applied to a box prototype</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">À</forename><surname>Aragonès</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Poblet-Puig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Arcas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mechanical Systems and Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="448" to="466" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application of vibro-acoustic operational transfer path analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Vaitkus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tcherniak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Brunskog</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Acoustics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">154</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="212" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A framework for the propagation of uncertainty in Transfer Path Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Meggitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Moorhouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wienen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Sound and Vibration</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">483</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">115425</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Component replacement TPA: A transmissibility-based structural modification method for in-situ transfer path analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Meggitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Elliott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Moorhouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Sound and Vibration</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">499</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">115991</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Correlation-Based Transfer Path Analysis for Brake System-Induced Interfering Noise in the Vehicle Interior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Drichel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Jacobs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wegerhoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>SAE International</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">01</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5044</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Road noise input identification for vehicle interior noise by multi-reference Transfer Path Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tatlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ballatore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Procedia Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">199</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3296" to="3301" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Measurement Location Optimization of Component Transfer Path Analysis Method for Road Noise</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>De Boer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Iturbe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gagliardini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>SAE International</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">01</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1581</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Structure-Borne Path Identification of Rumbling Noise in a Passenger Car Based on In-Situ Blocked Force Transfer Path Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Jung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>SAE International</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">01</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1587</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research of transfer path analysis based on contribution factor of sound quality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Acoustics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">173</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">107693</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inverse transfer path analysis, a different approach to shorten time in NVH assessments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cervantes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Peral</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Campillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Acoustics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">181</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">108178</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Control of structure-borne noise for a vehicle body by using power flow analysis and acoustic path participation method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Qin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Acoustics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">157</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">106981</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Msc Nastran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Dynamic Analysis User&apos;s Guide</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Msc Nastran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Documentation</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
