<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Diagrammatics, Pentagon Equations, and Hexagon Equations of Topological Orders with Loop-and Membrane-like Excitations</title>
				<funder ref="#_dMXeS2E">
					<orgName type="full">Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Magnetoelectric Physics and Devices</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_bqbnYTX #_aTRGmgY">
					<orgName type="full">National Natural Science Foundation of China</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NSFC</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2025-02">th February, 2025</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yizhou</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sun Yat-sen University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>510275</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zhi-Feng</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for the Physics of Complex Ststems</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Nöthnitzer Straße 38</addrLine>
									<postCode>01187</postCode>
									<settlement>Dresden</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Peng</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
							<email>yepeng5@mail.sysu.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sun Yat-sen University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>510275</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">CONTENTS I. Introduction II</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Diagrammatics, Pentagon Equations, and Hexagon Equations of Topological Orders with Loop-and Membrane-like Excitations</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2025-02">th February, 2025</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2405.19077v3[hep-th]</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T18:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In spacetime dimensions of 4 (i.e., 3+1) and higher, topological orders exhibit spatially extended excitations like loops and membranes, which support diverse topological data characterizing braiding, fusion, and shrinking processes, despite the absence of anyons. Our understanding of these topological data remains less mature compared to 3D, where anyons have been extensively studied and can be fully described through diagrammatic representations. Inspired by recent advancements in field theory descriptions of higher-dimensional topological orders, this paper systematically constructs diagrammatic representations for 4D and 5D topological orders, generalizable to higher dimensions. We introduce elementary diagrams for fusion and shrinking processes, treating them as vectors in fusion and shrinking spaces, respectively, and build complex diagrams by combining these elementary diagrams. Within these vector spaces, we design unitary operations represented by F -, ∆-, and ∆ 2 -symbols to transform between different bases. We discover pentagon equations and (hierarchical) shrinking-fusion hexagon equations that impose constraints on the legitimate forms of these unitary operations. We conjecture that all anomaly-free higher-dimensional topological orders must satisfy these conditions and any violations indicate a quantum anomaly. This work opens promising avenues for future research, including the exploration of diagrammatic representations involving braiding and the study of non-invertible symmetries and symmetry topological field theories in higher spacetime dimensions.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>The concept of topological order was introduced in condensed matter physics to describe exotic phases of matter characterized by long-range entanglement <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[1]</ref>. Going beyond traditional symmetry-breaking theory, topological order has captured significant interest across various fields, including condensed matter physics, high-energy physics, mathematical physics, and quantum information <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2]</ref>. Literature has explored diverse properties of topological orders, encompassing the existence of topological excitations, fusion rules, braiding statistics, and chiral central charge, collectively constituting the "topological data" crucial for their characterization and classification.</p><p>One method of acquiring these data is through the path-integral formalism of topological quantum field theory (TQFT) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">4]</ref>. A notable example of TQFT is the 3D 1 Chern-Simons theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref>, which describes the low-energy, long-wavelength physics of 3D topological orders (known as anyon models) like fractional quantum Hall states. As a side note, the Chern-Simons theory is also applied to describe 3D symmetry-protected topological phases (SPT) and symmetry enriched topological phases (SET) by implementing global symmetry transformations, see, e.g., Refs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref>. Anyon properties, such as fusion rules and braiding statistics, can be systematically computed within the field-theoretical framework. Moreover, fusion and braiding can be depicted diagrammatically, with the corresponding diagrammatic algebra closely linked to TQFT and topological quantum computation <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref>. Within anyon diagrams, F -symbols and R-symbols can be defined to facilitate transformations between different diagrams, subject to consistency conditions like the pentagon and hexagon equations in anomaly-free topological orders 2 .</p><p>Topological orders in 3D have been extensively explored through the lenses of TQFT and category theory. How about higher-dimensional topological orders? In 4D, topological excitations include both point-like particles and one-dimensional loop excitations, hereafter referred to as "particles" and "loops" for brevity. While mutual braidings among particles are trivial in 4D and higher dimensions <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[24]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[27]</ref>, the presence of topological excitations with spatially extended shapes significantly expands the potential for braiding and fusion properties. Moreover, the existence of spatially extended shapes allows for the consideration of shrinking rules <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29]</ref>, which dictate how loops can be shrunk into particles across one or more channels. Notably, nontrivial shrinking 1 Unless otherwise specified, 3D, 4D, and 5D always represent dimensions of spacetime. That is, 3D=(2+1)D, 4D=(3+1)D, and 5D=(4+1)D. 2 For more details about anyon diagrams, we recommend the relevant section in the research article <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref> as well as the book <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref>. Appendix A is also supplemented for an introduction to pentagon equations and braiding-fusion hexagon equations in anyon models.</p><p>rules can only manifest in topological orders in 4D and higher, where topological excitations with spatially extended shapes exist. In 3D, a loop excitation is topologically indistinguishable from anyons since the braiding process is unable to detect the geometric hole of the loop excitation.</p><p>Analogous to the Chern-Simons field theory description of 3D topological orders, when particles and loops in 4D are respectively represented by charges and fluxes of an Abelian finite gauge group, the BF theory and its twisted variants <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[30]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[33]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[35]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[36]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[37]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[41]</ref> have been applied to describe 4D topological orders as well as gauged SPTs, which also attract a lot of investigations from non-invertible symmetry and symmetry topological field theory (SymTFT) <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[43]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[44]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[45]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[46]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[47]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[48]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[49]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[50]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[51]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[52]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[53]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[54]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[55]</ref>. The BF term (BdA in which B and A are respectively 2and 1-form gauge fields) equipped with various twisted terms (e.g., AAdA, AAAA, AAB, dAdA, and BB) enables systematic computation of topological data, such as particle-loop braiding <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[56]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[58]</ref>, multi-loop braiding <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[59]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[60]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[61]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[62]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[63]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[64]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[65]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[66]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[67]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b68">[68]</ref>, particle-loop-loop braiding (i.e., Borromean rings braiding) <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[38]</ref>, emergent fermionic statistics <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[35,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">69,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">70]</ref>, and topological response <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[71]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b72">[72]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b73">[73]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b74">[74]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b75">[75]</ref>. Refs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b76">[76]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b77">[77]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b78">[78]</ref> field-theoretically demonstrate how global symmetry is fractionalized on loop excitations. There, the concept of "mixed three-loop braiding" processes is introduced, leading to a classification scheme of SETs in higher dimensions. Importantly, braiding data discovered above are not always allowed to coexist. It has been shown that there exists important compatibility among these braiding processes <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[39]</ref>, ruling out gaugenon-invariant combinations of braiding processes. Furthermore, loop excitations in Borromean rings topological order <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[38]</ref> can exhibit non-Abelian fusion and shrinking rules <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>, despite the gauge charges carried by loops being Abelian. At the same time, all shrinking rules are consistent with fusion rules in the sense that fusion coefficients and shrinking coefficients together should satisfy consistency conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>. On the other hand, the emergence of fermions is also a fundamental issue. By studying correlation functions of Wilson operators equipped with the framing regularization, Ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[70]</ref> investigates how fermionic statistics of particle excitations can emerge in the low-energy gauge theory, successfully incorporating the data of self-statistics of particle excitations.</p><p>When considering topological orders in 5D, the topological data become even more exotic.</p><p>Topological excitations now include particles, loops, and two-dimensional membranes, highlighting unexplored features of topological orders. From a field-theoretical perspective, we can still employ BF field theory to investigate braiding statistics, fusion rules, and shrinking rules. The BF term can take the form of either CdA or BdB, where C represents 3-form gauge fields, B and B represent different 2-form gauge fields. These terms can be further enriched with various twisted terms, such as AAAAA, AAAdA, AdAdA, AAC, AAAB, BBA, AdAB, AAdB, and BC <ref type="bibr" target="#b79">[79]</ref>. Recently, several exotic braiding processes have been computed via these 5D topological terms <ref type="bibr" target="#b79">[79]</ref>, resulting in mathematically nontrivial links formed by closed spacetime trajectories of particles, loops, and membranes. Technically, braiding statistics can be systematically computed by evaluating correlation functions of Wilson operators, whose expectation values are related to intersections of sub-manifolds embedded in the 5D spacetime manifold. Additionally, exotic fusion and shrinking rules in 5D have been explored <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref>. Some membranes exhibit hierarchical shrinking rules, where a membrane shrinks into particles and loops, followed by the subsequent shrinking of loops into particles. Such nontrivial hierarchical shrinking structures can only exist in 5D and higher.</p><p>We have mentioned that the topological data of anyon models in 3D can be schematically represented by diagrams, with their corresponding algebraic structure related to TQFT and category theory. Using diagrammatic representations is beneficial for understanding the universal properties of topological orders and their underlying mathematical structures, which plays a critical role in unitary operations for realizing topological quantum computation <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref>. Important consistency conditions, such as the celebrated pentagon and hexagon equations can be efficiently handled via diagrams. However, there is still a lack of research on diagrammatic representations of higherdimensional topological orders, which hinders a systematic exploration of topologically ordered phases in higher dimensions. Especially, the presence of loop excitations and membrane excitations is expected to significantly enrich the potential constraints beyond 3D anyon theory. Inspired by the aforementioned progress in field theory in 4D and 5D, in this work, we aim to construct diagrammatic representations capable of describing the exotic properties of higher-dimensional topological orders in this paper.</p><p>In our diagrammatic representations, excitations are categorized into different sets, and we use different types of straight lines (e.g., single-line, double-line) to represent them. Given that fusion rules still satisfy the associativity condition, we can define fusion diagrams and F -symbols, similar to the case in 3D. Changing the order of fusion processes in a diagram is implemented by F -symbols, which can be understood as basis transformations. To describe (hierarchical) shrinking processes and the consistent relation between (hierarchical) shrinking and fusion, we define (hierarchical) shrinking diagrams and ∆-symbols (∆ 2 -symbols). Changing the order of fusion and (hierarchical) shrinking processes in a diagram is implemented by such ∆-symbols (∆ 2 -symbols), which can also be viewed as basis transformations. Having defined F -symbols and ∆-symbols (∆ 2 -symbols), we further discover a series of equations that must be implemented for these symbols. First, F -symbols still satisfy the "pentagon equation"; second, F -symbols and ∆-symbols (∆ 2 -symbols) jointly satisfy the so-called "(hierarchical) shrinking-fusion hexagon equations".</p><p>We conjecture that all anomaly-free topological orders in higher-dimensional spacetime should satisfy these equations. A quantum anomaly appears if one of these equations is not satisfied.</p><p>It should be noted that the diagrams we construct in this paper involve fusion and (hierarchical)</p><p>shrinking processes, thereby reflecting the algebraic structure of consistent fusion and (hierarchical) shrinking rules. As for braiding processes, since they may involve more than two excitations and thus form various kinds of exotic links, the diagrammatic representations may be considerably more complicated, and we leave them for future exploration.</p><p>This paper is organized as follows. In section II, we first review some basic concepts and properties of fusion and (hierarchical) shrinking rules, with a particular focus on their path-integral formalism established in our previous studies. We conclude that fusion rules respect (hierarchical) shrinking rules, which lays the foundation for our construction of diagrammatic representations of fusion and (hierarchical) shrinking rules. In section III, we study fusion and shrinking in 4D</p><p>and 5D as mappings between different sets of excitations. Since excitations from different sets play distinct roles in (hierarchical) shrinking processes, we need to treat them differently in our diagrams. In section IV, we focus on 4D topological orders. Based on what we have established in section III and IV, we define basic fusion and shrinking diagrams and combine them to generate more complex diagrams. By introducing F -and ∆-symbols, we can transform diagrams and ultimately obtain the pentagon equation and (hierarchical) shrinking-fusion hexagon equation, which are key equations in our diagrammatic representations. In section V, we extend our construction to 5D topological orders, introducing hierarchical shrinking diagrams and unitary operations denoted as ∆ 2 -symbols. Following a similar strategy, we derive a new consistency relation called the "hierarchical shrinking-fusion hexagon equation". A brief summary is provided in section VI, in which several promising future directions are discussed. Two appendices are supplemented.</p><p>In appendix A, we offer a short review of diagrammatic representations of 3D topological orders (anyon models). Appendix B discusses the completeness of pentagon equations and shrinkingfusion hexagon equations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. PATH-INTEGRAL FORMALISM OF TOPOLOGICAL DATA</head><p>In this section, we will review several field-theoretical results established before <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29]</ref>, where path-integral formalism is applied. We first present two typical twisted terms in BF theory, both of which can lead to non-Abelian fusion rules and nontrivial (hierarchical) shrinking rules. Then we give several examples of constructing gauge invariant Wilson operators for topological excitations. Meanwhile, we will explain the meaning of several useful notations that were introduced in our previous papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29]</ref>, which will be frequently used in establishing the notion of "set of excitations" in section III. Finally, we elaborate on how to calculate fusion and (hierarchical)</p><p>shrinking rules in path-integral formalism. By exhausting all possible fusion and (hierarchical)</p><p>shrinking processes, we conclude that in 4D BF theory, fusion rules respect shrinking rules, i.e. satisfy eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_31">20</ref>). While in 5D, there exist nontrivial hierarchical shrinking rules. Fusion rules no longer respect shrinking rules in 5D generally. Instead, fusion rules respect hierarchical shrinking rules, i.e., satisfy eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_32">21</ref>). The two relations <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(20)</ref> and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_32">21</ref>) are the key results in our previous works <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29]</ref>. Our construction of diagrammatic representations is essentially based on these two relations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. BF theory with twisted terms</head><p>We consider BF theory as the underlying TQFT for higher-dimensional topological orders.</p><p>The topological action consists of BF terms and twisted terms. The BF term BdA  <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">70]</ref>.</p><p>To better illustrate fusion and shrinking rules from TQFT, below we introduce two typical BF actions first <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29]</ref>. For simplicity, we only consider one twisted term and take the discrete Abelian gauge group as G = n i=1 Z N i = (Z 2 ) <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">3</ref> . In 4D, we choose the twisted term to be the AAB term and write the action as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">S = ˆN1 2π B 1 dA 1 + N 2 2π B 2 dA 2 + N 3 2π B 3 dA 3 + qA 1 A 2 B 3 ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where A i and B i are 1and 2-form gauge fields respectively. The coefficient q</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">= pN 1 N 2 N 3 (2π) 2 N 123</formula><p>, where p ∈ Z N 123 and N 123 is the greatest common divisor of N 1 , N 2 , and N 3 . A 1 , A 2 and B 3 satisfy the flat-connection conditions: dA 1 = 0, dA 2 = 0, and dB 3 = 0. The gauge transformations are:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">A 1 →A 1 + dχ 1 , A 2 → A 2 + dχ 2 , B 3 → B 3 + dV 3 , B 1 →B 1 + dV 1 - 2πq N 1 χ 2 B 3 -A 2 V 3 + χ 2 dV 3 , B 2 →B 2 + dV 2 + 2πq N 2 χ 1 B 3 -A 1 V 3 + χ 1 dV 3 , A 3 →A 3 + dχ 3 - 2πq N 3 χ 1 A 2 -χ 2 A 1 + 1 2 χ 1 dχ 2 - 1 2 χ 2 dχ 1 ,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where χ i and V i are 0-form and 1-form gauge parameters respectively. They satisfy the following compactness conditions: ´dχ i ∈ 2πZ and ´dV i ∈ 2πZ. Another example is the action that contains the BBA twisted term in 5D, we still consider G = n i=1 Z N i = (Z 2 ) 3 and write the action as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">S = ˆN1 2π B1 dB 1 + N 2 2π B2 dB 2 + N 3 2π C 3 dA 3 + qB 1 B 2 A 3 ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where A 3 , B i , Bi , and C 3 are 1-, 2-, 2-, and 3-form gauge fields respectively. The coefficient</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">q = pN 1 N 2 N 3 (2π) 2 N 123</formula><p>, where p ∈ Z N 123 and N 123 is the greatest common divisor of N 1 , N 2 and N 3 . The flat-connection conditions are dB 1 = 0, dB 2 = 0, and dA 3 = 0. The gauge transformations are given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">B 1 →B 1 + dV 1 , B 2 → B 2 + dV 2 , A 3 → A 3 + dχ 3 , B1 → B1 + d Ṽ 1 + 2πq N 1 V 2 A 3 + B 2 χ 3 + V 2 dχ 3 , B2 → B2 + d Ṽ 2 + 2πq N 2 V 1 A 3 + B 1 χ 3 + V 1 dχ 3 , C 3 →C 3 + dT 3 - 2πq N 3 V 1 B 2 + B 1 V 2 + 1 2 V 1 dV 2 + 1 2 V 2 dV 1 ,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where χ 3 , V i , Ṽ i and T 3 are 0-, 1-, 1and 2-form gauge parameters respectively. The compactness conditions are: </p><formula xml:id="formula_6">´dχ 3 ∈ 2πZ, ´dV i ∈ 2πZ, ´d Ṽ i ∈ 2πZ,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">O P 001 = exp i ˆγ A 3 ,<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where γ = S 1 is the closed world-line of the particle. Since the action (3) contains only one 1-form gauge field, i.e., A 3 , only n 3 can be nonzero. Since G = (Z 2 ) 3 , n 3 only takes 0 or 1 mod 2 here.</p><p>A loop in 5D can carry gauge charges minimally coupled to 2-form gauge fields and be decorated by particles, i.e., the loop can be decorated by gauge charges minimally coupled to 1-form gauge fields. We generally use</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">L m 1 m 2 •••m l n 1 n 2 •••n k ,ñ 1 ñ2 •••ñ k to represent a loop. Here n 1 , n 2 , • • • , n k in the subscript denote n 1 , n 2 , • • • , n k units of Z N 1 , Z N 2 , • • • , Z N k gauge charge minimally coupled to B 1 , B 2 , • • • , B k fields respectively. ñ1 , ñ2 , • • • , ñk in the subscript denote ñ1 , ñ2 , • • • , ñk units of Z N 1 , Z N 2 , • • • , Z N k gauge charge minimally coupled to B1 , B2 , • • • , Bk fields respectively. m 1 , m 2 , • • • , m l in the superscript denote m 1 , m 2 , • • • , m l units of Z N 1 , Z N 2 , • • • , Z N l gauge charge minimally coupled to A 1 , A 2 , • • • , A l</formula><p>fields respectively. In BBA twisted term, a loop simultaneously carrying gauge charges minimally coupled to B 1 and B 2 and decorated by gauge charge minimally coupled to A 3 is denoted as L 001 110,000 . The gauge invariant Wilson operator is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">O L 001 110,000 = exp i ˆσ B 1 + i ˆσ B 2 + i ˆγ A 3 ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where σ = S 1 × S 1 = T 2 is the closed world sheet of the loop excitation. γ is an arbitrary closed line on σ, i.e., γ ∈ σ. For the notational simplicity, we omit 000 in the superscript and subscript, thus L 001 110,000 can be rewritten as L 001 110, . Note that the comma in the subscript should not be omitted. The numbers on the left side of the comma correspond to the B fields while the numbers on the right side of the comma correspond to the B fields.</p><p>As for membranes, we consider two different shapes: the membrane denoted by M S is in the shape of S 2 and the membrane denoted by M T is in the shape of T 2 . Both of them can carry gauge charges minimally coupled to 3-form fields and they can be decorated by loops and particles. The loop and particle decorations on the membrane carry gauge charges minimally coupled to 2-form and 1-form fields respectively. We generally use</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">M S p 1 p 2 •••p k ;m 1 m 2 •••m l , m1 m2 ••• ml n 1 n 2 •••n k or M T p 1 p 2 •••p k ;m 1 m 2 •••m l , m1 m2 ••• ml n 1 n 2 •••n k to represent them. Here n 1 , n 2 , • • • , n k in the subscript denote n 1 , n 2 , • • • , n k units of Z N 1 , Z N 2 , • • • , Z N k gauge charge minimally coupled to C 1 , C 2 , • • • , C k fields respectively. p 1 , p 2 , • • • , p k in the superscript denote p 1 , p 2 , • • • , p k units of Z N 1 , Z N 2 , • • • , Z N k gauge charge minimally coupled to A 1 , A 2 , • • • , A k fields respectively. m 1 , m 2 , • • • , m l in the superscript denote m 1 , m 2 , • • • , m l units of Z N 1 , Z N 2 , • • • , Z N l gauge charge minimally coupled to B 1 , B 2 , • • • , B l fields respectively. m1 , m2 , • • • , ml in the superscript denote m1 , m2 , • • • , ml units of Z N 1 , Z N 2 , • • • , Z N l gauge charge minimally coupled to B1 , B2 , • • • , Bl</formula><p>fields respectively. For simplicity, we omit the whole superscript if there is no decoration. We also write "p 1 p 2 • • • ; 000, 000" as "p 1 p 2 • • • ;" and "000; 000, m1 m2 • • • " as ", m1 m2 • • • ", respectively.</p><p>In BBA twisted term, a torus-like membrane carrying unit gauge charge minimally coupled to 3-form field C 3 is denoted as M T 001 . The corresponding gauge invariant Wilson operator is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">O M T 001 = 4 exp i ˆω C 3 + 1 2 2πq N 3 d -1 B 1 B 2 + d -1 B 2 B 1 δ ˆσ B 1 δ ˆσ B 2 ,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where ω = T 2 × S 1 is the closed world volume of the membrane excitation. The nontrivial</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">terms 1 2 2πq N 3 (d -1 B 1 B 2 + d -1 B 2 B 1</formula><p>) are introduced to guarantee that the Wilson operator is gauge invariant. We define</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">d -1 B 1 and d -1 B 2 as d -1 B 1 = ´A∈ω B 1 and d -1 B 2 = ´A∈ω B 2 , where A is</formula><p>an open area on ω. As 1-form fields, d -1 B 1 and d -1 B 2 are well defined on ω if and only if B 1 and B 2 are exact on ω, i.e., B 1 and B 2 satisfy extra constraints: ´σ B 1 = 0 mod 2π, ´σ B 2 = 0 mod 2π, where σ is an arbitrary closed surface on ω. To enforce these constraints, we introduce two delta functionals in eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">7</ref>):</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">δ ˆσ B 1 =      1, ´σ B 1 = 0 mod 2π 0, else , δ ˆσ B 2 =      1, ´σ B 2 = 0 mod 2π 0, else .<label>(8)</label></formula><p>We can construct other Wilson operators for excitations by using the similar approach. In our previous papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29]</ref>, we have exhausted all topologically distinct Wilson operators in BF theory with AAB and BBA twisted terms respectively. We conclude that there are 19 topologically distinct excitations in BF theory with AAB twisted term and 29 topologically distinct excitations in BF theory with BBA twisted term.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Fusion and shrinking rules in path integral formalism</head><p>Fusion rules of topological excitations are important topological data in topological orders. If we adiabatically bring two topological excitations together spatially, the combination of the two excitations behaves like another topological excitation. Within the framework of path integral, fusing two topological excitations a and b is represented by</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">⟨a ⊗ b⟩ = 1 Z ˆD [ABC] exp (iS) × (O a × O b ) .<label>(9)</label></formula><p>where Z and S are partition function and action respectively. D [ABC] represents the integration over all field configurations. Refs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29]</ref> show that we can further calculate the fusion rules as</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">⟨a ⊗ b⟩ = 1 Z ˆD [ABC] exp (iS) × (O a × O b ) = 1 Z ˆD [ABC] exp (iS) × c N ab c O c = ⟨⊕ c N ab c c⟩ ,<label>(10)</label></formula><p>We can simply rewrite eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_16">10</ref>) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">a ⊗ b = ⊕ c N ab c c .<label>(11)</label></formula><p>a, b and c denote topological excitations and N ab c ∈ Z is fusion coefficient implying there are N ab c fusion channels to c. Summation ⊕ c exhausts all topological excitations in the system. If N ab c = 0, it means that such fusion channel does not exist and fusing a and b to c is prohibited. A fusion process that only has a single fusion channel is called an Abelian fusion process. In contrast, a non-Abelian fusion process contains multiple fusion channels, indicating different possible fusion outputs. For an excitation a, if fusing a and b is always Abelian for any b, we call a an Abelian excitation. Otherwise, we call a a non-Abelian excitation. Fusion rules satisfy commutativity and associativity, i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">a ⊗ b = a ⊗ b ,<label>(12)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_19">(a ⊗ b) ⊗ c = a ⊗ (b ⊗ c) .<label>(13)</label></formula><p>Following the notations in ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>, here we present an explicit example of fusing two loops.</p><p>A loop in the AAB twisted term carrying unit gauge charge minimally coupled to B 1 is denoted as L 100 , which can be represented by <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref> O L 100 = 2 exp i ˆσ</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">B 1 + 1 2 2πq N 1 d -1 A 2 B 3 + d -1 B 3 A 2 δ ˆγ A 2 δ ˆσ B 3 . (<label>14</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">)</formula><p>We define</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">d -1 A 2 and d -1 B 3 as d -1 A 2 = ´[a,b]∈c A 2 and d -1 B 3 = ´A∈σ B 3 respectively, where [a, b] is a segment of the closed curve c and</formula><p>A is an open area on σ. The delta functionals are:</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">δ ˆσ A 2 =      1, ´γ A 2 = 0 mod 2π 0, else , δ ˆσ B 3 =      1, ´σ B 3 = 0 mod 2π 0, else .<label>(15)</label></formula><p>Thus fusing two L 100 's is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">⟨L 100 ⊗ L 100 ⟩ = 1 Z ˆD [AB] exp (iS) × O L 100 × O L 100 = 1 Z ˆD [AB] exp (iS) × 2 exp i ˆσ B 1 + 1 2 2πq N 1 d -1 A 2 B 3 + d -1 B 3 A 2 × δ ˆγ A 2 δ ˆσ B 3 2 = 1 Z ˆD [AB] exp (iS) × 1 + exp i ˆγ A 2 + exp i ˆσ B 3 + exp i ˆσ A 2 + B 3 = 1 Z ˆD [AB] exp (iS) × O 1 + O P 010 + O L 001 + O L 010 001 =⟨1 ⊕ P 010 ⊕ L 001 ⊕ L 010 001 ⟩ , (<label>16</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_25">)</formula><p>where 1 is the vacuum, P 010 is a particle carrying a gauge charge minimally coupled to 1-form field A 2 , L 001 is a loop carrying a gauge charge minimally coupled to 2-form fields B 3 , L 010 001 FIG. <ref type="figure">1</ref>. A typical example of fusion rules in BF theory with AAB twisted term. Fusing two loops L 100 has four possible fusion channels: the vacuum, the particle P 010 , the pure loop L 001 , and the decorated loop</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">L 010 001 .</formula><p>is a decorated loop carrying both a gauge charge minimally coupled to A 2 and a gauge charge minimally coupled to B 3 . Their corresponding gauge invariant Wilson operators are <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28</ref>]</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">O 1 = 1 , O P 010 = exp i ˆγ A 2 , O L 001 = exp i ˆσ B 3 , O L 010 001 = exp i ˆγ A 2 + i ˆσ B 3 . (<label>17</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_28">)</formula><p>Here, γ is the world line of particles and σ is the world sheet of loops. Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_24">16</ref>) means that fusing two loops L 100 has four possible outputs: the vacuum, the particle P 010 , the loop L 001 , and the loop L 010 001 . This is a non-Abelian fusion process as shown in figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>. One fusion channel can be changed to another by braiding processes.</p><p>In 3D topological orders, topological excitations are point-like particles, i.e., anyons. However, in higher-dimensional topological orders, spatially extended topological excitations may occur.</p><p>For instance, in 4D, there exist loop excitations. By applying a series of local unitary operators, we can manipulate a particle to pass through the geometric hole of the loop, which forms a particleloop braiding process. However, such a process can only happen when the spatial size of the loop is larger than the correlation length of the TQFT. If we shrink the loop to a size that is smaller than the correlation length, no excitation can pass through the hole of the loop, causing the loop to behave like a particle when braiding with other excitations. This motivates us to consider the shrinking rules: when we shrink a spatially higher dimensional topological excitation to a sufficiently small size, it behaves like a spatially lower dimensional excitation. In 4D, there exist loop excitations and they can be shrunk to point-like particles. Keep lifting dimension to 5D, spatially extended topological excitations include both loops and membranes. Some membranes can be shrunk to loops first and then shrunk to particles, and such shrinking processes are called hierarchical shrinking rules. In the path integral representation, we define a shrinking operator S, then shrinking an excitation a is <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29]</ref> ⟨S (a)⟩ =⟨ lim</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">X 1 →X 2 a⟩ = lim X 1 →X 2 1 Z ˆD [ABC] exp (iS) O a = b 1 Z ˆD [ABC] exp (iS) S a b O b =⟨⊕ b S a b b⟩ ,<label>(18)</label></formula><p>where Z and S are partition function and action respectively. X 1 and X 2 (X 2 ⊂ X 1 ) are respectively spacetime trajectories (manifold) of excitation a (Wilson operator O a ) before and after shrinking. We can simply rewrite eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_29">18</ref>) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">S (a) = ⊕ b S a b b .<label>(19)</label></formula><p>S a b ∈ Z is the shrinking coefficient, and there are S a b shrinking channels to b. Summation ⊕ b exhausts all topological excitations in the system. If S a b = 0, then shrinking a to b is prohibited. A shrinking process is called Abelian if it has a single shrinking channel. Otherwise, it is deemed non-Abelian. Working in the TQFT paradigm, refs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29]</ref> show that (hierarchical) shrinking rules respect fusion rules; that is, in 4D, we have:</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">S (a) ⊗ S (b) = S (a ⊗ b) .<label>(20)</label></formula><p>Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_31">20</ref>) only holds for 4D because we only need one step to shrink loops to particles, which precludes the existence of non-trivial hierarchical shrinking structures. While in 5D, topological excitations can be particles, loops, and membranes. For a sphere-like membrane, we can directly shrink it to particles. However, for a torus-like membrane, we may first shrink it to a loop and then continue to shrink the loop to a particle. If we need at least two steps to shrink such a membrane to a particle, we say there exist hierarchical shrinking rules. Ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref> shows that for 5D topological order described by the BF field theory, the BBA and AAAB twisted terms can lead to nontrivial hierarchical shrinking rules. For the AAAAA, AAAdA, and AAC twisted terms, we find that they have non-Abelian shrinking rules, but their shrinking rules are not hierarchical, i.e., torus-like membranes are shrunk to nontrivial particles and the trivial loop in the first step. Since the trivial loop is equivalent to the vacuum and thus can be ignored, these torus-like membranes are directly shrunk to particles in the first shrinking process. For the AdAdA, AdAB, and AAdB twisted terms, they only admit Abelian shrinking rules and trivial hierarchical shrinking rules. Generally, in 5D, hierarchical shrinking rules respect fusion rules, that is,</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">S 2 (a) ⊗ S 2 (b) = S 2 (a ⊗ b) ,<label>(21)</label></formula><p>where S 2 (•) = S (S (•)) means shrinking twice.</p><p>Following the notations in ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref>, here we calculate an explicit example of shrinking a toruslike membrane M T 001 (whose Wilson operator is shown in eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">7</ref>)) in the BBA twisted term:</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">⟨S M T 001 ⟩ = ⟨ lim ω→σ M T 001 ⟩ = lim ω→σ 1 Z ˆD [ABC] exp (iS) × O M T 001 = lim ω→σ 1 Z ˆD [ABC] exp (iS) × 4 exp i ˆω C 3 + 1 2 2πq N 3 d -1 B 1 B 2 + d -1 B 2 B 1 × δ ˆσ B 1 δ ˆσ B 2 = 1 Z ˆD [ABC] exp (iS) 1 + exp i ˆσ B 1 + exp i ˆσ B 2 + exp i ˆσ B 1 + i ˆσ B 2 = 1 Z ˆD [ABC] exp (iS) O 1 + O L 100, + O L 010, + O L 110, =⟨1 ⊕ L 100, ⊕ L 010, ⊕ L 110, ⟩ .<label>(22)</label></formula><p>Here, M T 001 is a torus-like membrane carrying a gauge charge minimally coupled to 3-form field C 3 . 1 is the vacuum, L 100, and L 010, are loops carrying a gauge charge minimally coupled to 2form field B 1 and a gauge charge minimally coupled to 2-form field B 2 respectively, L 110, is a loop carrying both a gauge charge minimally coupled to B 1 and a gauge charge minimally coupled to B 2 . Their corresponding gauge invariant Wilson operators are <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_34">O 1 = 1 , O L 100, = exp i ˆσ B 1 , L 010, = exp i ˆσ B 2 O L 110, = exp i ˆσ B 1 + i ˆσ B 2 . (<label>23</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_35">)</formula><p>This result means that shrinking the membrane M T 001 has four shrinking channels: the vacuum, the loop L 100, , the loop L 010, , and the loop L 110, . These loops can be further shrunk to particles, i.e., the membrane M T 001 have hierarchical shrinking rules:</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">⟨S 2 M T 001 ⟩ = ⟨S (1 ⊕ L 100, ⊕ L 010, ⊕ L 110, )⟩ = ⟨lim σ→γ (1 ⊕ L 100, ⊕ L 010, ⊕ L 110, )⟩ =lim σ→γ 1 Z ˆD [ABC] exp (iS) 1 + exp i ˆσ B 1 + exp i ˆσ B 2 + exp i ˆσ B 1 + B 2 = 1 Z ˆD [ABC] exp (iS) [1 + exp (i0) + exp (i0) + exp (i0)] = 1 Z ˆD [ABC] exp (iS) × 4 • 1 = ⟨4 • 1⟩ .<label>(24)</label></formula><p>This result indicates that, by performing shrinking twice, M T 001 can be shrunk to the vacuum ultimately, as shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. FUSION AND SHRINKING RULES AS MAPPINGS</head><p>In this section, we will categorize excitations into different sets and investigate fusion and shrinking processes as mappings between these sets. Excitations from different sets need to be treated differently in our diagrammatic representations because they play distinct roles in (hierarchical) shrinking processes. Assuming only a finite number of topologically distinct excitations exist in a topological order, we can exhaust all excitations and put them in a set of excitations, denoted as Φ D 0 , where the superscript D denotes the spacetime dimension. In this paper, we mainly focus on D = 4, 5. In the following discussion, we interpret shrinking as a mapping from the set Φ D 0 to one of its subsets, denoted as Φ D 1 . If nontrivial hierarchical shrinking rules exist, we are allowed to map the subset</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">Φ D i to a smaller subset Φ D i+1 , where i = 0, 1, • • • , D -4.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. 4D topological orders</head><p>In a 4D topological order, we generally list all excitations in a set Φ 4 0 as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">Φ 4 0 = {1, P 1 , P 2 , • • • P n , L 1 , L 2 , • • • , L m } ,<label>(25)</label></formula><p>where 1 denotes the vacuum (both the trivial particle P 0 and trivial loop L 0 are equivalent to vacuum, i.e., 1 = P 0 = L 0 ). P i and L i denote particles and loops respectively. The possible outputs of fusing two excitations still form the set Φ 4 0 , thus we can regard fusion as a mapping:</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">⊗ : Φ 4 0 × Φ 4 0 → Φ 4 0 ,<label>(26)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">Φ 4 0 × Φ 4 0 = {(E i , E j ) | E i ∈ Φ 4 0 , E j ∈ Φ 4</formula><p>0 } and the symbol ⊗ means fusion. A shrinking operator can shrink loops into particles, but it will not alter particles (which means the shrinking operator acts on a particle will give the particle itself) as, evidently, there is no way to further shrink a point. Thus, shrinking can be considered as a mapping from the original set Φ 4 0 to a subset Φ 4  1 :</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">S : Φ 4 0 → Φ 4 1 .<label>(27)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_42">Φ 4 1 = {P 0 , P 1 , P 2 , • • • P n } .<label>(28)</label></formula><p>Ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref> shows that such a subset Φ 4 1 also has closed fusion rules, i.e., the possible outputs of fusing two excitations in Φ 4  1 still form the set Φ 4 1 . As a result, eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_39">26</ref>) can be generalized to encompass the following fusion processes:</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">⊗ : Φ 4 i × Φ 4 i → Φ 4 i , i = 0, 1 .<label>(29)</label></formula><p>Now consider two copies of the set Φ 4 0 , we have two ways to map Φ 4 0 × Φ 4 0 to the subset Φ 4 1 . The first approach involves mapping Φ 4 0 ×Φ 4 0 to Φ 4 0 by fusion, and then mapping Φ 4 0 to Φ 4 1 by shrinking. Alternatively, we can map Φ 4 0 × Φ 4 0 to Φ 4 1 × Φ 4 1 by shrinking, and subsequently map Φ 4 1 × Φ 4 1 to Φ 4 1 by fusion. These two procedures can be represented as</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">(a) ⊗ : Φ 4 0 × Φ 4 0 → Φ 4 0 , S : Φ 4 0 → Φ 4 1 ,<label>(30)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_45">(b) S : Φ 4 0 × Φ 4 0 → Φ 4 1 × Φ 4 1 , ⊗ : Φ 4 1 × Φ 4 1 → Φ 4 1 ,<label>(31)</label></formula><p>respectively. Recall eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_31">20</ref>) in 4D, shrinking rules respect fusion rules. We conclude that for In the following, we take the AAB twisted term in 4D as an example. We consider the gauge group as G = n i=1 Z N i = (Z 2 ) 3 and the action given by eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">1</ref>). Ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref> shows that there are 19 distinct excitations, which form the set Φ </p><p>Here, 1, P, and L denote the vacuum, particles, and loops respectively. Consider n i , m i = 0, 1, the subscript "n 1 n 2 n 3 " of a particle denotes that the particle carries n 1 , n 2 , and n 3 gauge charges minimally coupled to the 1-form gauge fields A 1 , A 2 , and A 3 , respectively. The subscript "n 1 n 2 n 3 " of a loop denotes that the loop carries n 1 , n 2 , and n 3 gauge charges minimally coupled to 2-form gauge fields B 1 , B 2 , and B 3 , respectively. The superscript "m 1 m 2 m 3 " of a loop denotes that the loop is decorated by m 1 , m 2 , and m 3 gauge charges minimally coupled to the 1-form gauge fields A 1 , A 2 , and A 3 , respectively. From ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>, we conclude that the subset Φ 4 1 is given by Φ 4 1 = {1, P 100 , P 010 , P 001 , P 110 } .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. 5D topological orders</head><p>We can generalize the above prescription to 5D, where excitations include particles, loops, and membranes. We can generally list the set Φ 5 0 as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">Φ 5 0 = {1, P 1 , P 2 , • • • P n , L 1 , L 2 , • • • , L m , M 1 , M 1 , • • • , M k } ,<label>(34)</label></formula><p>where 1 is the vacuum (trivial particle P 0 , trivial loop L 0 , and trivial membrane M 0 are equivalent to vacuum), P i , L i , and M i denote particles, loops, and membranes respectively. If we consider nontrivial hierarchical shrinking rules, loops and membranes are shrunk to particles and loops respectively in the first shrinking process, which can be considered as a mapping from the original set Φ 5 0 to a subset Φ 5 1 :</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">Φ 5 1 = {1, P 1 , P 2 , • • • P n , L 1 , L 2 , • • • , L p } ,<label>(35)</label></formula><p>where p ⩽ m because some loops may not appear as shrinking outputs. In fact, ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref> shows that we have p &lt; m for the BBA and AAAB twisted terms. (If the topological order does not have nontrivial hierarchical shrinking rules, then L 1 , L 2 , • • • , L p vanish, which means that the subset Φ 5 1 and the subset Φ 5 2 [to be defined below] contain the same excitations). Continue to shrink the excitations in subset Φ 5  1 , we get a smaller subset:</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">Φ 5 2 = {1, P 1 , P 2 , • • • P n } . (<label>36</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_51">)</formula><p>Given the result in ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref>, we can verify that the sets Φ 5 0 , Φ 5 1 , and Φ 5 2 all have closed fusion rules. Thus we can consider shrinking and fusion as mappings:</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">⊗ : Φ 5 i × Φ 5 i → Φ 5 i , i = 0, 1,<label>2</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_53">S : Φ 5 j → Φ 5 j+1 , j = 0, 1<label>(37)</label></formula><p>If we consider fusion and shrinking simultaneously, we will find that the original set Φ 5 0 only admits</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">S 2 (a) ⊗ S 2 (b) = S 2 (a ⊗ b) , a, b ∈ Φ 5 0 .<label>(38)</label></formula><p>While the subset Φ and Φ 5 2 admit</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">S (c) ⊗ S (d) = S (c ⊗ d) , c, d ∈ Φ 5 1,2 .<label>(39)</label></formula><p>Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_55">39</ref>) is not the most general relation in 5D because c and d can only be particles and loops.</p><p>Since the subset Φ 5 1 and Φ 5 2 can be obtained by acting a shrinking process on Φ 5 0 , i.e., we can always find a ∈ Φ and b ∈ Φ 5 0 such that S (a) and S (b) have shrinking channels to c ∈ Φ 5 1,2 and d ∈ Φ 5  1,2 respectively, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">S 2 (a) ⊗ S 2 (b) = S (S (a) ⊗ S (b))<label>(40)</label></formula><p>holds for the original set Φ 5 0 . Now consider two copies of the set Φ 5 0 , we have three ways to map Here, we take the BBA twisted term in 5D as an example. We consider the gauge group as G = n i=1 Z N i = (Z 2 ) 3 and the action given by eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">3</ref>). Ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref> shows that there are 29 distinct excitations, which form the set Φ 5 0 (pay attention to commas and semicolons in sub-and super-scripts): </p><formula xml:id="formula_57">Φ 5 0 × Φ 5 0 to Φ 5 2 : (a) S : Φ 5 0 × Φ 5 0 → Φ 5 1 × Φ 5 1 , S : Φ 5 1 × Φ 5 1 → Φ 5 2 × Φ 5 2 , ⊗ : Φ 5 2 × Φ 5 2 → Φ 5 2 ,<label>(41)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_58">(b) ⊗ : Φ 5 0 × Φ 5 0 → Φ 5 0 , S : Φ 5 0 → Φ 5 1 , S : Φ 5 1 → Φ 5 2 , (<label>42</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_59">) (c) S : Φ 5 0 × Φ 5 0 → Φ 5 1 × Φ 5 1 , ⊗ : Φ 5 1 × Φ 5 1 → Φ 5 1 , S : Φ 5 1 → Φ 5 2 . (<label>43</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_60">Φ 5 0 =</formula><p>Here, 1, P, L, M S , and M T denote the vacuum, particles, loops, sphere-like membranes, and toruslike membranes respectively. The superscripts and subscripts are defined as follows:</p><p>• For particles, the subscript "n 1 n 2 n 3 " denotes n 1 , n 2 , and n 3 gauge charges minimally coupled to A 1 , A 2 , and A 3 , respectively.</p><p>• For loops, the superscript "m 1 m 2 m 3 " denotes m 1 , m 2 , and m 3 gauge charges minimally coupled to A 1 , A 2 , and A 3 , respectively. The subscript "n 1 n 2 n 3 , ñ1 ñ2 ñ3 " of loops denotes (i) n 1 , n 2 , and n 3 gauge charges minimally coupled to B 1 , B 2 , and B 3 , respectively, and (ii) ñ1 , ñ2 , and ñ3 gauge charges minimally coupled to B1 , B2 , and B3 , respectively.</p><p>• For the sake of convenience, we simply write "n 1 n 2 n 3 , 000" and "000, n 1 n 2 n 3 " as "n 1 n 2 n 3 ,"</p><p>and ", n 1 n 2 n 3 " respectively.</p><p>• For sphere-like and torus-like membranes, the superscript "p 1 p 2 p 3 ; m 1 m 2 m 3 , m1 m2 m3 " denotes (i) p 1 , p 2 , and p 3 gauge charges minimally coupled to A 1 , A 2 , and A 3 , respectively, (ii) m 1 , m 2 , and m 3 gauge charges minimally coupled to B1 , B2 , and B3 , respectively, and (iii) m1 , m2 , and m3 gauge charges minimally coupled to B1 , B2 , and B3 , respectively. The subscript n 1 n 2 n 3 denotes n 1 , n 2 , and n 3 gauge charges minimally coupled to the 3-form gauge fields C 1 , C 2 , and C 3 , respectively.</p><p>• For the sake of convenience, we simply express "p 1 p 2 p 3 ; 000, 000" and "000; 000, m1 m2 m3 " as "p 1 p 2 p 3 ;" and ", m1 m2 m3 " respectively.</p><p>M ST n 1 n 2 n 3 ;m 1 m 2 m 3 ,p 1 p 2 p 3 can be generated by fusing a sphere-like M S 001 membrane and a toruslike membrane M T n 1 n 2 n 3 ;m 1 m 2 m 3 ,p 1 p 2 p 3 001 , i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">M ST n 1 n 2 n 3 ;m 1 m 2 m 3 ,p 1 p 2 p 3 = M S 001 ⊗ M T n 1 n 2 n 3 ;m 1 m 2 m 3 ,p 1 p 2 p 3 001 . (<label>45</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_63">)</formula><p>The subsets Φ 5 1 and Φ 5 2 are given by Φ </p><formula xml:id="formula_64">Φ 5 2 = {1, P 001 } . (<label>(46)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_65">)<label>47</label></formula><p>By means of these definitions of sets, we will construct diagrammatic representations of higherdimensional topological orders in section IV and section V.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. DIAGRAMMATICS OF 4D TOPOLOGICAL ORDERS</head><p>In this section, inspired by several results from TQFT, we construct diagrammatic representations of 4D topological orders that can consistently describe fusion and shrinking rules, especially focusing on unitary operators during the processes of fusion and shrinking. We obtain pentagon equations and shrinking-fusion hexagon equations for anomalous-free topological orders in 4D, which enforces constraints on legitimate unitary operators. We will generalize our construction to 5D in section V, in which the existence of membrane excitations makes hierarchical shrinking processes possible.</p><p>A. Fusion diagrams: fusion space, F -symbols, and pentagon relation First, we explore the construction of fusion diagrams in 4D. In the following discussion, Latin and Greek letters denote excitations and channels respectively. Suppose the fusion process a ⊗ b has fusion channels to c, we can represent these fusion channels diagrammatically in figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>.</p><p>The solid lines can be understood as the spacetime trajectories of excitations. As mentioned in section III A, we can either fuse two excitations in the set Φ 4 0 or two excitations in the subset Φ 4  1 . Hence, we use double-line and single-line to represent excitations from the sets Φ 4 given by figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>. We can express the equation in figure <ref type="figure">6</ref> as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">|(a, b) ; e, µ⟩ ⊗ |e, c; d, ν⟩ = f,λ,η F abc d eµν,fλη |a, f; d, η⟩ ⊗ |(b, c) ; f, λ⟩ .<label>(48)</label></formula><p>The summation over f exhausts all excitations in the system, λ = 1, 2,</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">• • • , N bc f and η = 1, 2, • • • , N af d . Since the F -symbol is unitary, we have f,λ,η F abc d eµν,fλη F abc d e ′ µ ′ ν ′ ,fλη * = δ ee ′ δ µµ ′ δ νν ′<label>(49)</label></formula><p>which implies figure <ref type="figure">7</ref>. We can also derive a constraint on fusion coefficients by comparing the dimension of V abc d calculated from figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">4</ref> and figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>, where the total space V abc d is constructed</p><p>by</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">⊕ e V ab e ⊗ V ec d and ⊕ f V af d ⊗ V bc f respectively. Thus dim(V abc d ) = e N ab e N ec d = f N af d N bc f .<label>(50)</label></formula><p>This formula can also be derived by directly using associativity and eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_17">11</ref>):</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">(a ⊗ b) ⊗ c = ⊕ e N ab e e ⊗ c = ⊕ ed N ab e N ec d d ,<label>(51)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_70">a ⊗ (b ⊗ c) = a ⊗ ⊕ f N bc f f = ⊕ fd N bc f N af d d . (<label>52</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_71">)</formula><p>Comparing the fusion coefficients, we have:</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">e N ab e N ec d = f N af d N bc f . (<label>53</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_73">)</formula><p>For other diagrams involving more excitations, we employ a similar tensor product approach to write down the corresponding vectors. Also, the F -symbols can be applied inside more complicated diagrams. For instance, consider fusing four excitations, we have different ways to transform Such pentagon equation also exists in diagrammatic representations of 3D anyons. It has been proven that no more identities beyond the pentagon equation can be derived by drawing more complicated fusion diagrams in 3D. Essentially, the pentagon equation in any dimension arises from the associativity of the fusion rules, leading to the conclusion that no more identities can be derived from fusion diagrams in any dimension. As a side note, if we draw all previous fusion diagrams in a single-line fashion, our fusion diagrams then reduce to 3D anyonic fusion diagrams.</p><p>A brief review of 3D anyon diagrams is shown in appendix A.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Shrinking diagrams: shrinking space and ∆-symbol</head><p>Suppose for a ∈ Φ 4 0 , S (a) has shrinking channels to b ∈ Φ 4 1 , then we define the corresponding shrinking diagram in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">9</ref>. We use a triangle to represent the shrinking process. Note that in a specific diagram, a double-line and a single-line may actually represent the same particle. However, they carry distinct meanings: the double-line means that this particle from Φ 4 0 is treated as the input of the shrinking process while the single-line means that this particle from Φ 4  1 is the output. Similar to the fusion diagram, the shrinking diagram in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">9</ref>  , which is</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">isomorphic to ⊕ f V f c ⊗ V ab f .</formula><p>The conclusion that shrinking rules respect fusion rules also implies that the space V</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">S(a)⊗S(b) c is isomorphic to V S(a⊗b) c</formula><p>, leading to:</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">dim V S(a)⊗S(b) c = dim V S(a⊗b) c = de N de c S b e S a d = f S f c N ab f .<label>(55)</label></formula><p>Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_76">55</ref>) can also be found in ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref> where all fusion and shrinking rules in the BF theory with the AAB twisted term are obtained. Also, eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_76">55</ref>) is numerically verified. This constraint on fusion coefficients and shrinking coefficients can be considered as a consistency condition for fusion rules and shrinking rules in anomaly-free 4D topological orders.</p><p>The two sets of vectors shown in figure <ref type="figure">10</ref>   </p><formula xml:id="formula_77">∼ = ⊕ de V de c ⊗ V b e ⊗ V a d and V S(a⊗b) c ∼ = ⊕ f V f c ⊗ V ab f .</formula><p>Unitarity of the ∆-symbol demands:</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">f,δ,γ ∆ ab c deµνλ,fδγ ∆ ab c d ′ e ′ µ ′ ν ′ λ ′ ,fδγ * = δ dd ′ δ ee ′ δ µµ ′ δ νν ′ δ λλ ′ ,<label>(58) d,e, µ,ν,λ</label></formula><p>∆ ab c deµνλ,fδγ</p><formula xml:id="formula_80">∆ ab c deµνλ,f ′ δ ′ γ ′ * = δ ff ′ δ δδ ′ δ γγ ′ . (<label>59</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_81">)</formula><p>The element of the ∆-symbol ∆ ab c deµνλ,fδγ is zero if the corresponding diagram is not allowed. Although we only use diagrams that involve shrinking and fusing two excitations to define the ∆-symbol, we are allowed to act a ∆-symbol on a part of a larger diagram, such as the diagram shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">12</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Shrinking-fusion hexagon equation</head><p>In 4D, fusion rules in both set Φ 4 0 and subset Φ 4 1 are closed and satisfy the associativity: </p><formula xml:id="formula_82">(a ⊗ b) ⊗ c = a ⊗ (b ⊗ c),</formula><formula xml:id="formula_83">far left = i,α,β,j, τ,ξ,k,θ,ϵ F efg d hδγ,iαβ ∆ bc i fgνλα,jτ ξ ∆ aj d eiµξβ,kθϵ far right ,<label>(60)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_84">far left = t,σ,ρ,k, ω,ϵ,j,τ,θ ∆ ab h efµνδ,tσρ [∆ tc d ] hgρλγ,kωϵ F abc k tσω,jτ θ far right ,<label>(61)</label></formula><p>respectively. Notice that the far right diagram is labeled by j, k, τ, θ, and ϵ. By comparing the coefficients of the far right diagrams in eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_83">60</ref>) and eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_84">61</ref>), we obtain a constraint on both the F -symbols and ∆-symbols:</p><p>i  <ref type="formula" target="#formula_76">55</ref>) holds), we conclude that the shrinking-fusion hexagon equation actually implies eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_76">55</ref>). Therefore, the shrinking-fusion hexagon equation is a stronger constraint on consistent fusion and shrinking rules, describing not only the behavior of fusion and shrinking coefficients but also the transformations of bases. We conjecture that such a shrinking-fusion hexagon is universal. All anomaly-free 4D topological orders should have consistent fusion and shrinking rules, thus satisfying this equation.</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">N fg i α=1 N ei d β=1 S j i ξ=1 F efg d hδγ,iαβ ∆ bc i fgνλα,jτ ξ ∆ aj d eiµξβ,kθϵ = t N ab t σ=1 S t h ρ=1 N tc k ω=1 ∆ ab h efµνδ,tσρ [∆ tc d ] hgρλγ,kωϵ F abc k tσω,jτ θ .<label>(62)</label></formula><p>We can further consider applying the F -symbols and ∆-symbols inside of diagrams involving more excitations, such as starting from the diagram for S (a) ⊗ S (b) ⊗ S (c) ⊗ S (d) and then implementing basis transformations. However, we can verify that no more independent equations can be obtained from the diagram involving four excitations. Details can be found in appendix B. We further conjecture that no more independent equations can be obtained from diagrams involving more excitations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Hierarchical shrinking diagrams and ∆ 2 -symbols</head><p>Suppose a has nontrivial hierarchical shrinking rules and S 2 (a) gives c finally. We can define the corresponding hierarchical shrinking diagram in figure <ref type="figure">13</ref>. Here, the triangle denotes the shrinking process. The triple-line, double-line, and single-line represent excitations in the sets Φ 5 0 , Φ 5  1 , and Φ 5 2 respectively. Similar to the case in 4D, although these three kinds of lines may represent the same excitation in a specific diagram, they carry different meanings, implying different roles (input or output) in a hierarchical shrinking process. The diagram in figure <ref type="figure">13</ref> can be understood as a vector |b; c, ν⟩ ⊗ |a; b, µ⟩. Generally, there are various legitimate choices for b, µ, and ν that can finally give the desired output c. Thus, different b, µ, and ν label different orthogonal vectors.</p><p>The orthogonal set {|b; c, ν⟩ ⊗ |a; b, µ⟩} spans the total shrinking space V total . This total shrinking space is isomorphic to</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">⊕ b V b c ⊗ V a b</formula><p>. Therefore, we can calculate its dimension as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_87">dim V total = dim ⊕ b V b c ⊗ V a b = b S b c S a b .<label>(63)</label></formula><p>Having defined the hierarchical shrinking diagram, we can further consider representing . We can calculate the dimension of V S 2 (a)⊗S 2 (b) c from these three diagrams as: </p><formula xml:id="formula_88">(a) dim V S 2 (a)⊗S 2 (b) c = dim ⊕ defg V fg c ⊗ V e g ⊗ V b e ⊗ V d f ⊗ V a d = defg N fg c S e g S b e S d f S a d ,<label>(64)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_89">(b) dim V S 2 (a)⊗S 2 (b) c = dim ⊕ hi V i c ⊗ V h i ⊗ V ab h = hi N ab h S i c S h i ,<label>(65)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_90">(c) dim V S 2 (a)⊗S 2 (b) c = dim ⊕ dej V j c ⊗ V de j ⊗ V b e ⊗ V a d = dej N de j S j c S b e S a d .<label>(66)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_91">⊕ dej V j c ⊗ V de j ⊗ V b e ⊗ V a d .</formula><p>Thus we have:</p><formula xml:id="formula_92">defg N fg c S e g S b e S d f S a d = hi N ab h S i c S h i = dej N de j S j c S b e S a d .<label>(67)</label></formula><p>Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_92">67</ref>) is the consistent condition for fusion and shrinking coefficients in 5D topological orders <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref>. gram for S D-3 (a ⊗ b) is denoted as the ∆ D-3 -symbol. In this convention, ∆ 1 -symbol is nothing but ∆-symbol. Unitarity of the ∆ 2 -symbol demands:</p><p>d,e,f,g, µ,ν,ρ,σ,η</p><formula xml:id="formula_93">∆ 2 ab c defgµνρση,hiλτ ω ∆ 2 ab c defgµνρση,h ′ i ′ λ ′ τ ′ ω ′ * = δ hh ′ δ ii ′ δ λλ ′ δ τ τ ′ δ ωω ′ ,<label>(68)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_94">h,i, λ,τ,ω ∆ 2 ab c defgµνρση,hiλτ ω ∆ 2 ab c d ′ e ′ f ′ g ′ µ ′ ν ′ ρ ′ σ ′ η ′ ,hiλτ ω * = δ dd ′ δ ee ′ δ ff ′ δ gg ′ δ µµ ′ δ νν ′ δ ρρ ′ δ σσ ′ δ ηη ′ . (69)</formula><p>As for changing bases from S 2 (a)⊗S Thus, as shown in figure <ref type="figure">16</ref> and 17, we establish the basis transformations between the three diagrams in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">14</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Diagrammatics of the hierarchical shrinking-fusion hexagon equation</head><p>Before investigating into diagrams where three excitations together undergo shrinking and fusion processes, we present a more compact version of figure <ref type="figure">13</ref>, as shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">18</ref>. We use a triangle decorated by a line inside the triangle, in order to represent the whole hierarchical shrinking process. If we only consider using the ∆ 2 -symbols and F -symbols, it is convenient to use such a compact fashion.</p><p>Recall the figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">12</ref>, where three excitations undergo shrinking and fusion processes to finally get a particle. By using the F -symbols and ∆-symbols, we transform diagrams from each other and finally derive the shrinking-fusion hexagon equation in 4D. Now, we generalize it to 5D by substituting the ∆-symbols with the ∆ 2 -symbols and employing the compact hierarchical shrinking diagrams shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">18</ref>. The resulting diagram shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">19</ref>  </p><p>Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_95">70</ref>) can be understood as the consistency relation between the F -symbols and ∆ 2 -symbols.</p><p>If we do not utilize the compact diagram in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">18</ref>, we can consider using the ∆-symbols in figure <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19</ref>. In this case, we will find that shrinking-fusion hexagon (62) still holds. However, it is noteworthy that now a, b and c in eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_85">62</ref>) can only belong to the subset Φ 5 1 . Such shrinking-fusion hexagon equation with a constraint on inputs is the consistency relation between the F -symbols and ∆-symbols in 5D.</p><p>Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_95">70</ref>) and eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_85">62</ref>) with constrained inputs are the key results in our 5D diagrammatic representations. They establish the consistency relation between the F -symbols, ∆-symbols, and ∆ 2 -symbols. They also imply constraints on fusion and shrinking coefficients, i.e., eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_92">67</ref>). We conjecture that all anomaly-free 5D topological orders should satisfy these two hexagon equations, ensuring consistent fusion, shrinking, and hierarchical shrinking rules.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. SUMMARY AND OUTLOOK</head><p>In this paper, with the help of our previous work on field-theoretical description of higher dimensional topological orders, we have successfully constructed diagrammatic representations for higher-dimensional topological orders in 4D and 5D spacetime, extending the framework known for topologically ordered phases in 3D spacetime. By introducing and manipulating basic fusion and shrinking diagrams as vectors within corresponding spaces, we have demonstrated the construction of complex diagrams through their stacking. Using the F -, ∆-, and ∆ 2 -symbols, we have established unitary transformations between different bases in these vector spaces and discovered key consistency conditions, including the pentagon equations and (hierarchical) shrinking-fusion hexagon equations. Our findings indicate that these consistency conditions are essential for ensuring the anomaly-free nature of higher-dimensional topological orders. Violations of these conditions suggest the presence of quantum anomalies, providing a diagnostic tool for identifying such anomalies in theoretical models.</p><p>Looking ahead, our work points towards several promising avenues for future research:</p><p>1. In the literature (see references cited in section I), braiding phases, fusion coefficients, shrinking coefficients, and quantum dimensions have been determined for a concrete topological order. It is also important to practically determine the unitary matrices (i.e., F -, ∆-, and ∆ 2 -symbols) introduced in this paper by solving pentagon equations and (hierarchical) shrinking-fusion hexagon equations. Solving these equations in the present work is expected to be very tedious (practical calculations in 3D can be found in references such as ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b80">[80]</ref>).</p><p>While it is beyond the scope of the current paper, solving these equations undoubtedly represents a key step toward a more complete description of higher-dimensional topological orders. Recently, Quantinuum's H2 trapped-ion quantum processor <ref type="bibr" target="#b81">[81]</ref> successfully realized a non-Abelian topological order in 3D spacetime and demonstrated control of its anyons. This topological order can be formally regarded as the lower-dimensional counterpart of the Borromean rings topological order proposed in ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[38]</ref>. Efforts toward the experimental realization of 4D topological orders and control of loop excitations through the platform of trapped-ion quantum processors will provide experimental evidence for theoretical predic-tions of the topological data of loop-like topological excitations.</p><p>2. In this paper, we solely focus on diagrams pertaining to fusion and shrinking rules, although it is worth noting that braiding statistics also hold significance in comprehending higherdimensional topological orders. More concretely, we have defined F -, ∆-, and ∆ 2 -symbols to perform unitary transformations associated with fusion and shrinking processes; however, we have not studied yet the higher-dimensional spacetime counterpart of R-symbol in 3D.</p><p>While diagrammatic representation of braiding processes is definitely intricate due to the involvement of spatially extended excitations, incorporating braiding processes into our diagrammatic representations presents an intriguing avenue for future exploration. Doing so may unveil new diagrammatic rules capable of encoding more complete algebraic structures relevant to braiding, fusion, and shrinking processes. Based on all data depicted by field theory and consistency conditions in diagrammatic representations, it is further interesting to study the connection between our field-theory-inspired diagrammatic representations and categorical approach in the future.</p><p>3. BF theory exhibits a close relationship with non-invertible symmetry and symmetry topological field theory (SymTFT). Various twisted terms, along with their fusion rules and braiding statistics, have been involved in the context of SymTFT, including notable examples such as BB, BBA, and AdAdA twisted terms, see, e.g., refs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">53,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">55]</ref>. These topological terms were previously a focus of investigation in the field-theoretical description of higher-dimensional topological orders <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">35,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">70,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b79">79]</ref>. It would be intriguing to explore the incorporation of shrinking and hierarchical shrinking rules <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29]</ref> into SymTFT and establish connections between SymTFT and our diagrammatic representations. Such investigations hold the potential to enrich our understanding of both SymTFT and the broader landscape of topological field theories. 4. In this paper, our focus is primarily on the diagrammatic representations of 4D and 5D topological orders. However, it is worth noting that the framework we have developed lends itself to potential generalization for arbitrarily higher-dimensional topological orders. Such generalization holds promise for providing deeper insights into the underlying structure and properties of higher-dimensional topological orders, warranting further exploration in future studies.</p><p>Since shrinking rules are trivial in 3D, we do not need to put excitations in different sets and treat them differently. Consequently, we can easily recover the diagrammatic representations for anyons by drawing all fusion diagrams in a single-line fashion.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Braiding statistics and diagrammatic representations</head><p>In section A 1, we only consider fusion processes, thus worldlines will not cross each other. In this section, we allow worldlines to cross over and under each other to form braiding processes.</p><p>For Abelian anyons, a braiding process only accumulates a phase e iθ , which can be regarded as a one-dimensional representation of the braid group. However, for non-Abelian anyons, a braiding process is equivalent to multiplying a unitary matrix to the initial wavefunction of the system. This unitary matrix can be regarded as a higher-dimensional representation of the braid group.</p><p>Suppose a and b fuse to c. This process can be viewed as a vector in the fusion space V ab c . Due to the principle of locality, if we (half) braid a and b first and then fuse them together, the fusion output remains c. Consequently, this whole process can also be viewed as a vector in the space V ab c . These two vectors are related to each other through the R-symbol, as shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">24</ref>. The upper and lower diagrams in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">24</ref> correspond to over-crossing and under-crossing respectively. From figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">27</ref> we can find 13 candidates for independent polygon equations as shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">28</ref>.</p><p>However, upon recovering the excitation and channel labels and attempting to write down the consistent equations, we find that only the pentagon and shrinking-fusion hexagon equations are independent, while the other equations are automatically satisfied and thus trivial.</p><p>To be more specific, we consider the quadrilateral equation given by diagrams 1, 3, 4, and </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIG. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>FIG. 2. A typical example of hierarchical shrinking rules in BF theory with BBA twisted term. The torus membrane M T 001 has four shrinking channels: the vacuum, the loop L 100, , the loop L 010, , and the loop L 110, . Subsequently, these loops are shrunk to vacua.</figDesc><graphic coords="16,171.84,71.99,266.58,159.84" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>a, b ∈ Φ 4 0</head><label>4</label><figDesc>, S (a ⊗ b) and S (a) ⊗ S (b) only differ by intermediate states and they give the same outputs.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>)</head><label></label><figDesc>For a, b ∈ Φ 5 0 , the condition S 2 (a) ⊗ S 2 (b) = S 2 (a ⊗ b) = S (S (a) ⊗ S (b)) indicates that the three processes above only differ by intermediate states and they should give the same outputs.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>0 and Φ 4 1 1 .FIG. 4 .</head><label>414</label><figDesc>FIG. 3. Elementary fusion diagrams. a, b and c denote excitations and we highlight them in blue. µ = 1, 2, • • • , N ab c</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>FIG. 6 .FIG. 7 .</head><label>67</label><figDesc>FIG. 6. Definition of the F -symbol. The left and right diagrams describe the same physics in different bases. We use the unitary F -symbol to change the basis. a, b, and c denote the inputs. d denotes the output.e, µ, ν, f, λ, and η denote different channels.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>FIG. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>FIG. 8. Diagrammatic representation of the pentagon equation (54). We highlight the excitations in blue. Starting from the far left diagram, we can go to the far right diagram through either the upper path or the lower path. Comparing these two different paths, we can derive the pentagon equation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>FIG. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>FIG. 9. Shrinking diagram. According to the definition at the beginning of section IV A, the double-line and single-line represent excitations from Φ 4 0 and Φ 4 1 respectively. Here, a ∈ Φ 4 0 is the input of the shrinking process and thus a can be a loop or a particle. b ∈ Φ 4 1 is the output of the shrinking process and thus b can only be a particle. We use a triangle to represent the shrinking process. This diagram describes shrinking a to b in the µ channel and we define it as a vector. The orthogonal set {|a; b, µ⟩ , µ = 1, 2, • • • , S a b } spans the shrinking space V a b with dim (V a b ) = S a b .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 10. Elementary diagrams that incorporate both fusion and shrinking processes. The upper diagram describes S (a) ⊗ S (b), while the lower diagram describes S (a ⊗ b). These diagrams can be constructed by tensoring smaller diagrams. Thus, we have V S(a)⊗S(b) c</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>FIG. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>FIG. 11. Definition of the ∆-symbol. The left diagram and the right diagram describe the same physics in different bases. Similar to the F -symbol, the ∆-symbol is also unitary and we can use it to change bases. a and b denote the inputs. c denotes the output. d, e, µ, ν, λ, f, δ, and γ denote different shrinking channels.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>which means we can use the F -symbols to change the bases when we consider diagrams involve fusing three excitations, regardless of which set do these excitations come from. We conclude that by applying the F -symbols and ∆-symbols inside of diagrams involving three excitations, we can obtain another consistency relation called the shrinking-fusion hexagon equation besides the pentagon equation. As shown in figure 12, both the upper and lower paths can transform the far left diagram (i.e., (S (a) ⊗ S (b)) ⊗ S (c)) to the far right diagram (i.e., S (a ⊗ (b ⊗ c))), these two paths correspond to:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>FIG. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>FIG. 12. Diagrammatic representations of the shrinking-fusion hexagon equation (62). Two different paths can be constructed to transform the far left diagram to the far right diagram. Comparing these two different paths, we obtain the shrinking-fusion hexagon equation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>S 2 (</head><label>2</label><figDesc>a) ⊗ S 2 (b), S 2 (a ⊗ b) and S (S (a) ⊗ S (b)) diagrammatically. As shown in figure 14, we stack the shrinking diagrams and fusion diagrams to describe the processes above. These diagrams are still understood as vectors and they can be constructed by tensor product. Since in 5D, hierarchical shrinking rules respect fusion rules: S 2 (a) ⊗ S 2 (b) = S 2 (a ⊗ b), we can expect that the diagrams for S 2 (a) ⊗ S 2 (b) and S 2 (a ⊗ b) describe the same physics. Also, as mentioned in section III B, for particles and loops, the relation S (c) ⊗ S (d) = S (c ⊗ d) still holds. In 5D, for any excitation c ∈ Φ 5 1 , we can always find an a ∈ Φ 5 0 such that S (a) has shrinking channels to c. Thus, we can replace c and d with S (a) and S (b) respectively and obtain S 2 (a) ⊗ S 2 (b) = S (S (a) ⊗ S (b)). Similarly, we expect that the diagrams for S (S (a) ⊗ S (b)) describe the same physics as S 2 (a) ⊗ S 2 (b). Now we can say that the three diagrams shown in figure 14 correspond to three different bases of the space V S 2 (a)⊗S 2 (b) c</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>FIG. 14 .</head><label>14</label><figDesc>FIG. 14. Diagrams for S 2 (a) ⊗ S 2 (b), S 2 (a ⊗ b) and S (S (a) ⊗ S (b)). These diagrams are understood as vectors. (a) Diagram for S 2 (a) ⊗ S 2 (b). Different d, e, f, g, µ, ν, ρ, σ, and η label different orthogonal vectors in the whole space V S 2 (a)⊗S 2 (b) c , which is isomorphic to ⊕ defg V fg c ⊗V e g ⊗V b e ⊗V d f ⊗V a d . (b) Diagram for S 2 (a ⊗ b). Different h, i, λ, τ , and ω label different orthogonal vectors. The tensor product construction in this diagram indicates that the whole space V S 2 (a)⊗S 2 (b) c is isomorphic to ⊕ hi V i c ⊗V h i ⊗V ab h . (c) Diagram for S (S (a) ⊗ S (b)). Different d, e, j, µ, ν, α, and β label different orthogonal vectors. The tensor product construction in this diagram indicates that the whole space is isomorphic to ⊕ dej V j c ⊗ V de j ⊗ V b e ⊗ V a d .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>FIG. 15 .FIG. 16 .</head><label>1516</label><figDesc>FIG. 15. Definition of ∆ 2 -symbols. The left and right diagrams describe the same physics in different bases. We can use a unitary ∆ 2 -symbol to change bases. "2" means that the diagrams involve hierarchical shrinking processes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>2 (b) to S (S (a) ⊗ S (b)), we can still use the ∆-symbols shown in figure 11 because even in 5D, loops and particles still obey S (c) ⊗ S (d) = S (c ⊗ d).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>FIG. 17 .</head><label>17</label><figDesc>FIG. 17. Basis transformation from S 2 (a ⊗ b) to S (S (a) ⊗ S (b)). We can derive this transformation by using the lower diagram in figure 15 and then use figure 16.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 19. Diagrammatic representations of the hierarchical shrinking-fusion hexagon equation. Here we use compact hierarchical shrinking diagrams shown in figure 18. Similar to figure 12, we have two different paths to transform the far left diagram to the far right diagram. Comparing these two different paths, we obtained the hierarchical shrinking-fusion hexagon equation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>FIG. 23 .FIG. 24 .</head><label>2324</label><figDesc>FIG. 20. Fusion diagram of two anyons. a, b and c denote anyons, µ = 1, 2, • • • , N ab c</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>FIG. 25 .</head><label>25</label><figDesc>FIG. 25. Hexagon equations. We highlight anyons in blue. Eq. (A3) and eq. (A4) correspond to the upper (over-crossing) and the lower (under-crossing) hexagon diagrams. Similar to figure 23, for each hexagon diagram, we have two paths to transform the far left to the far right. Comparing the upper and the lower paths directly leads to eq. (A3) and eq. (A4).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>- 1 FIG. 26 .FIG. 27 .</head><label>12627</label><figDesc>FIG.<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">26</ref>. All 21 diagrams that involve four topological excitations. We label them from 1 to 21 and their relations are given in figure27.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>FIG. 28 .</head><label>28</label><figDesc>FIG. 28. 13 polygons from figure 27. It turns out that all quadrilateral equations are trivial. Pentagons and hexagons essentially give the independent pentagon and shrinking-fusion hexagon equations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>8 1 → 4</head><label>814</label><figDesc>as an example. The transformations 1 → 3 → 8 and 1 → 3 → 4 give coefficients1 → 3 → 8 : m,γ,η n,δ,τ → 8 : n,δ,τ m,γ,η ∆ ab i efµνρ,nδτ F igh k jσλ,mγηrespectively. We can see that they equal to each other automatically and thus the quadrilateral equation is trivial. For a similar reason, other quadrilateral equations are also trivial.The two pentagons in figure28respectively give the pentagon equations for {a, b, c, d} and {S (a) , S (b) , S (c) , S (d)}, where a, b, c, d ∈ Φ 4 0 . Since S (a) , S (b) , S (c) , S (d) ∈ Φ 4 1 ⊆ Φ 4 0 , the later pentagon equation is automatically satisfied when we demand that the former pentagon equation holds. The five hexagons shown in figure 28 give the shrinking-fusion hexagon equations for {a, b, c}, {b, c, d}, {(a ⊗ b) , c, d}, {a, (b ⊗ c) , d} and {a, b, (c ⊗ d)} respectively and essentially they are the same equation. Thus we conclude that there are only two independent equations</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>BF terms include CdA and BdB terms, where C is 3-form, B and B are two different 2-form, A</figDesc><table><row><cell>is 1-form. Twisted terms now include AAAAA, AAAdA, AdAdA, AAC, AAAB, BBA, AdAB,</cell></row><row><cell>AAdB and BC terms. A BF action can contain several different twisted terms as long as the</cell></row><row><cell>action is gauge invariant</cell></row></table><note><p><p>3 </p>in 4D is written as a wedge product of B and dA, where B and A are respectively 2and 1-form gauge fields. Twisted terms in 4D consist of AAdA, AAAA, AAB, dAdA and BB terms. While in 5D,</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>and ´dT 3 ∈ 2πZ. The two examples above both have non-Abelian fusion and shrinking rules. Besides, the BBA twisted term also admits hierarchical shrinking rules.n 1 n 2 •••n k to represent a particle simultaneously carrying n 1 , n 2 , • • • , n k units of Z N 1 , Z N 2 , • • • , Z N k gauge charge.The Wilson operator for such excitation should be constructed by using k gauge fields A 1 , A 2 , • • • , A k . Consider BBA twisted terms as an example, a particle carrying unit gauge charge minimally coupled to 1-form gauge field A 3 is denoted as P 001 , which can be represented by the following gauge invariant Wilson operator O P 001 :</figDesc><table><row><cell>B. Wilson operators for topological excitations</cell></row><row><cell>In TQFT, topological excitations carry gauge charges minimally coupled to gauge fields. Thus,</cell></row><row><cell>by respectively using gauge fields of 1-, 2-, and 3-form, we can construct Wilson loop operators for</cell></row><row><cell>particle excitations, Wilson surface operators for loop excitations, and Wilson volume operators</cell></row><row><cell>for membrane excitations. We use the Wilson operator O a to represent the topological excitation a</cell></row><row><cell>in the path integral formalism. Following the notations in refs. [28, 29], we present some examples</cell></row><row><cell>of these Wilson operators.</cell></row><row><cell>A particle can only carry gauge charges minimally coupled to 1-form gauge fields A and we</cell></row><row><cell>generally use P</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1, P 001 , L 100, , L 010, , L 110, , L 001 100, , L 001 010, , L 001 110, , L ,100 , L ,010 , L ,110 , L 100,100 , L 010,010 , L 100,110 , M S 001 , M S 001; 001 , M S ,100 001 , M S ,010 001 , M S ,110 001 , M T 001 , M T 001; 001 , M T ,100 001 , M T ,010 001 , M T ,110 001 , M ST , M ST 001; , M ST ,100 , M ST ,010 , M ST ,110 .</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_0"><p>The wedge product "∧" is omitted for the notational convenience.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Acknowledgments <rs type="person">A. Review</rs> of anyon diagrams 1. Fusion rules and diagrammatic representations 2. Braiding statistics and diagrammatic representations B. Diagrams involving four excitations References ACKNOWLEDGMENTS P.Y. thanks <rs type="person">Z.-C. Gu</rs> for the warm hospitality during the visit to the <rs type="affiliation">Chinese University of Hong Kong</rs>, where part of this work was conducted. This work was partially supported by the <rs type="funder">National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC)</rs> under Grant Nos. <rs type="grantNumber">12474149</rs> and <rs type="grantNumber">12074438</rs>. The calculations reported were performed on resources provided by the <rs type="funder">Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Magnetoelectric Physics and Devices</rs> (No. <rs type="grantNumber">2022B1212010008</rs>).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_bqbnYTX">
					<idno type="grant-number">12474149</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_aTRGmgY">
					<idno type="grant-number">12074438</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_dMXeS2E">
					<idno type="grant-number">2022B1212010008</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. DIAGRAMMATICS OF 5D TOPOLOGICAL ORDERS</head><p>The idea of constructing the diagrammatic representations of 4D topological orders can be generalized to 5D, where nontrivial hierarchical shrinking rules may appear. An anomaly-free 5D topological order should have consistent fusion and shrinking rules. If there exist nontrivial hierarchical shrinking rules, we further demand that such hierarchical shrinking rules are also consistent with fusion and shrinking rules, which leads to the hierarchical shrinking-fusion hexagon.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Fusion diagrams</head><p>The construction of fusion diagrams in section IV A can be easily generalized to 5D. We can simply replace double-lines with triple-lines in the previous fusion diagrams to represent fusing two excitations in the set Φ 5 0 (see eq. ( <ref type="formula">34</ref>)). Double-lines and single-lines in 5D represent excitations from the subset Φ 5 1 and Φ 5 2 respectively. The definitions of the F -symbols and the pentagon equation in section IV A remain valid. Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>, 7, and 8 can be drawn in triple-, double-and single-line fashions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix A: Review of anyon diagrams</head><p>In this appendix, we will briefly review the basic concepts in the diagrammatic representations of anyons. The diagrammatic rules and algebra set up the structure of anyon theories and they are closely related to TQFT descriptions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Fusion rules and diagrammatic representations Appendix B: Diagrams involving four excitations</head><p>In this appendix, we consider diagrams that involve four excitations and show that we cannot obtain new consistency relations besides the pentagon and shrinking-fusion hexagon equations from these diagrams.</p><p>Starting with [[S (a) ⊗ S (b)] ⊗ S (c)] ⊗ S (d), we can finally generate a total of 21 distinct diagrams by utilizing the F -and ∆-symbols. We list all these diagrams in figure <ref type="figure">26</ref> and omit all</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">figure 28, which are the pentagon and shrinking-fusion hexagon equations</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quantum information meets quantum matter -from quantum entanglement to topological phase in many-body systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D.-L</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1508.02595</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>condmat.str-el</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Colloquium: Zoo of quantum-topological phases of matter</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/RevModPhys.89.041004</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rev. Mod. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">41004</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum field theory and the jones polynomial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Witten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/BF01217730</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commun. Math. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">351</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Turaev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1515/9783110435221</idno>
		<title level="m">Quantum Invariants of Knots and 3-Manifolds</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin, Boston</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>De Gruyter</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effective theories of the fractional quantum hall effect at generic filling fractions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Blok</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.42.8133</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8133</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nayak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/RevModPhys.80.1083</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Non-abelian anyons and topological quantum computation</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1083</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quantum field theory of many-body systems: from the origin of sound to an origin of light and electrons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theory and classification of interacting integer topological phases in two dimensions: A chern-simons approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-M</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vishwanath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.86.125119</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">125119</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Projective construction of two-dimensional symmetry-protected topological phases with u(1), so(3), or su(2) symmetries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.87.195128</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">195128</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multikink topological terms and charge-binding domain-wall condensation induced symmetry-protected topological states: Beyond chern-simons/bf field theories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-C</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.93.115136</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">115136</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">k matrix construction of symmetry-enriched phases of matter</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L.-Y</forename><surname>Hung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.87.195103</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">195103</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anyons in an exactly solved model and beyond</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kitaev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.aop.2005.10.005</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">321</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>january Special Issue</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">String-net condensation: A physical mechanism for topological phases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Levin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.71.045110</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">45110</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Local unitary transformation, long-range quantum entanglement, wave function renormalization, and topological order</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-C</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.82.155138</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">155138</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Bonderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Non-Abelian Anyons and Interferometry</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>California Institute of Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Ph.D. thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clebsch-gordan and 6j-coefficients for rank 2 quantum groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ardonne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Slingerland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1088/1751-8113/43/39/395205</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">395205</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bonderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Shtengel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Slingerland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.aop.2008.01.012</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Interferometry of non-abelian anyons</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">323</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2709</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diagrammatics for bose condensation in anyon theories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Eliëns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Romers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bais</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.90.195130</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">195130</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Topological quantum</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Braided fusion categories, gravitational anomalies, and the mathematical framework for topological orders in any dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1405.5858</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>cond-mat.str-el</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Symmetry fractionalization, defects, and gauging of topological phases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barkeshli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bonderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.100.115147</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">115147</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the theory of identical particles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leinaas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Myrheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/BF02727953</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Il Nuovo Cimento B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971-1996. 1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">General theory for quantum statistics in two dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-S</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevLett.52.2103</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2103</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aharonov-bohm interaction of cosmic strings with matter</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Alford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wilczek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevLett.62.1071</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1071</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discrete gauge symmetry in continuum theories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Krauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wilczek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevLett.62.1221</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1221</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linking numbers, spin, and statistics of solitons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wilczek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevLett.51.2250</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2250</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Field corrections to induced statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Goldhaber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mackenzie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wilczek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1142/S0217732389000046</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mod. Phys. Lett. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-abelian fusion, shrinking, and quantum dimensions of abelian gauge fluxes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q.-R</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.107.165117</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">165117</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fusion rules and shrinking rules of topological orders in five dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/JHEP11(2023)210</idno>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2306.14611</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JHEP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">210</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>hep-th</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A quantum field theoretic description of linking numbers and their generalization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Horowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Srednicki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/BF02099875</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commun.Math. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">83</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Composite particle theory of three-dimensional gapped fermionic phases: Fractional topological insulators and charge-loop excitation symmetry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Maciejko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fradkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.94.115104</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">115104</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theory of oblique topological insulators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Moy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Goldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sohal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fradkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.21468/SciPostPhys.14.2.023</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SciPost Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">23</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Constructing symmetric topological phases of bosons in three dimensions via fermionic projective construction and dyon condensation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.89.045127</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">45127</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Braiding statistics and link invariants of bosonic/fermionic topological quantum matter in 2+1 and 3+1 dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Putrov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-T</forename><surname>Yau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.aop.2017.06.019</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">384</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">254</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">)-dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q.-R</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-C</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.99.235137</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Topological quantum field theory for abelian topological phases and loop braiding statistics in</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">235137</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Topological quantum field theory of three-dimensional bosonic abelian-symmetryprotected topological phases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-C</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.93.205157</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">205157</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Entanglement entropy for (3+1)-dimensional topological order with excitations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tiwari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.97.085147</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">85147</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Braiding with borromean rings in (3 + 1)-dimensional spacetime</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P O</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ryu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevLett.121.061601</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">61601</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compatible braidings with Hopf links, multi-loop, and Borromean rings in (3+1)-dimensional spacetime</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevResearch.3.023132</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">23132</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vortex-line condensation in three dimensions: A physical mechanism for bosonic topological insulators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-C</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevX.5.021029</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. X</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21029</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Symmetry-protected topological phases with charge and spin symmetries: Response theory and dynamical gauge theory in two and three dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.88.235109</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">235109</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schafer-Nameki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2305.18296</idno>
		<title level="m">Ictp lectures on (non-)invertible generalized symmetries (2023)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>hep-th</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-invertible global symmetries and completeness of the spectrum</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Heidenreich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mcnamara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Montero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Reece</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Rudelius</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Valenzuela</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/JHEP09(2021)203</idno>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2104.07036</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of High Energy Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2021</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">203</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>hep-th</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kramers-wannier-like duality defects in (3 + 1)d gauge theories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kaidi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ohmori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevLett.128.111601</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">111601</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Noninvertible duality defects in 3 + 1 dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Córdova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P.-S</forename><surname>Hsin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Lam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-H</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevD.105.125016</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">125016</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Roumpedakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seifnashri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-H</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00220-023-04706-9</idno>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2204.02407</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Higher Gauging and Non-invertible Condensation Defects</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">401</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>hep-th</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-invertible symmetries of N = 4 SYM and twisted compactification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kaidi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zafrir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/JHEP08(2022)053</idno>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2205.01104</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of High Energy Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2022</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>hep-th</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kaidi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ohmori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00220-023-04859-7</idno>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2209.11062</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Symmetry TFTs for Non-invertible Defects</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">404</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1021</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>hep-th</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Symmetry TFTs and anomalies of non-invertible symmetries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kaidi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Nardoni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zafrir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/JHEP10(2023)053</idno>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2301.07112</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of High Energy Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2023</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>hep-th</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Córdova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P.-S</forename><surname>Hsin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Lam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-H</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00220-023-04727-4</idno>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2204.09025</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Non-invertible Condensation, Duality, and Triality Defects in 3+1 Dimensions</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">402</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>hep-th</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Antinucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Benini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2401.10165</idno>
		<title level="m">Anomalies and gauging of u(1) symmetries (2024)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>hep-th</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Damia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Argurio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Garcia-Valdecasas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.21468/SciPostPhys.14.4.067</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Non-invertible defects in 5d, boundaries and holography</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">67</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the symmetry tft of yang-mills-chern-simons theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Riccardo</forename><surname>Argurio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Francesco</forename><surname>Benini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Matteo</forename><surname>Bertolini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Giovanni</forename><surname>Galati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pierluigi</forename><surname>Niro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/JHEP07(2024)130</idno>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:arXiv:2404.06601</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of High Energy Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2024</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>hep-th</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2310.01474</idno>
		<title level="m">Symmetry tft for subsystem symmetry (2024)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>hep-th</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Brennan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2401.06128</idno>
		<title level="m">A symtft for continuous symmetries (2024)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>hep-th</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Superconductors are topologically ordered</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Oganesyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sondhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.aop.2004.05.006</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">313</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">497</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Local discrete symmetry and quantum-mechanical hair</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Preskill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Krauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0550-3213(90)90262-C</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nuclear Physics B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">341</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">50</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Alford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-M</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>March-Russell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Preskill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0550-3213(92)90468-Q</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Quantum field theory of non-abelian strings and vortices</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">384</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">251</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Braiding statistics of loop excitations in three dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Levin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevLett.113.080403</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">80403</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Field-theory representation of gauge-gravity symmetryprotected topological invariants, group cohomology, and beyond</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-C</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevLett.114.031601</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31601</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">+ 1)-dimensional twisted gauge theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.91.035134</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Non-abelian string and particle braiding in topological order: Modular SL(3, Z) representation and</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">35134</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Layer construction of 3d topological states and string braiding statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-M</forename><surname>Jian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-L</forename><surname>Qi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevX.4.041043</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. X</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">41043</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalized modular transformations in (3 + 1)D topologically ordered phases and triple linking invariant of loop braiding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mesaros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevX.4.031048</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. X</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31048</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bulk-boundary correspondence for three-dimensional symmetryprotected topological phases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-H</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Levin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevX.6.021015</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. X</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21015</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wilson operator algebras and ground states of coupled BF theories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tiwari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ryu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.95.245124</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">245124</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Anomalies of discrete symmetries in various dimensions and group cohomology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kapustin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Thorngren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1404.3230</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ArXiv e-prints. hep-th</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Twisted gauge theory model of topological phases in three dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.92.045101</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">45101</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bulk-boundary correspondence in (3+1)-dimensional topological phases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tiwari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ryu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.94.045113</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">45113</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coupling a QFT to a TQFT and Duality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kapustin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Seiberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/JHEP04(2014)001</idno>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1401.0740</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JHEP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">04</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>hep-th</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Continuum field theory of three-dimensional topological orders with emergent fermions and braiding statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q.-R</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevResearch.5.043111</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">43111</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Topological insulators and superconductors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-L</forename><surname>Qi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-C</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/RevModPhys.83.1057</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rev. Mod. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1057</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Topological electromagnetic responses of bosonic quantum hall, topological insulator, and chiral semimetal phases in all dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lapa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-M</forename><surname>Jian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.95.035149</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">35149</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fractional s-duality, classification of fractional topological insulators, and surface topological order</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fradkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.96.085125</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">85125</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fermion path integrals and topological phases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Witten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/RevModPhys.88.035001</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rev. Mod. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">35001</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalized wen-zee terms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.99.205120</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">205120</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fractionalizing global symmetry on looplike topological excitations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-Q</forename><surname>Ning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.105.205137</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">205137</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Symmetry enrichment in three-dimensional topological phases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-Q</forename><surname>Ning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.94.245120</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">245120</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-dimensional anomalous twisted gauge theories with global symmetry: Implications for quantum spin liquids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.97.125127</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">125127</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Topological orders, braiding statistics, and mixture of two types of twisted BF theories in five dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/JHEP04(2022)138</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. High Energ. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2022</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">138</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/nsr/nwv077</idno>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1506.05768</idno>
		<title level="m">A theory of 2+1D bosonic topological orders</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Iqbal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tantivasadakarn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Verresen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dreiling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Figgatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gaebler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Johansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Moses</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ransford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Siegfried</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Stutz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Foss-Feig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vishwanath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Dreyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41586-023-06934-4</idno>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2305.03766</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Non-Abelian topological order and anyons on a trappedion processor</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">626</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">505</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>quant-ph</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
