<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Correlation among School Principal Leadership, Work Culture and Work Motivation toward Job Satisfaction of Junior High School Teachers in Balangan Regency</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Risna</forename><surname>Hidayati</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master of Educational Administration Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70123</postCode>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ahmad</forename><surname>Suriansyah</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master of Educational Administration Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70123</postCode>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Sulistiyana</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master of Educational Administration Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70123</postCode>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Correlation among School Principal Leadership, Work Culture and Work Motivation toward Job Satisfaction of Junior High School Teachers in Balangan Regency</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-69</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T21:49+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>principal leadership</term>
					<term>work culture</term>
					<term>motivation</term>
					<term>job satisfaction</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This study aims to determine and analyze the direct and indirect correlation between the principal leadership and work culture through work motivation on job satisfaction. This research is a descriptive correlation al research with path analysis. The research sample was 167 people. The data was collected using instruments consisting of principals' leadership (26 items), work culture (15 items), work motivation (23 items), job satisfaction (22 items) that have been tested for validity and reliability.</p><p>The data analysis of this research used path analysis. The results showed that there was a correlation between the principal leadership and work culture through work motivation on job satisfaction, either directly or indirectly.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Teachers are considered as people who carry out the role of organizing teaching and providing education with the main task of educating, teaching, guiding, directing, training, assessing and evaluating students. For this reason, teachers are considered to have a very strategic position in guiding and fostering and educating children who are the nation's next generation with a variety of knowledge, so that they can become provisions for them to face life in the future.</p><p>One of the factors that is closely related to the development of the quality of education is the work motivation of teachers. As has been explained that the teacher has a direct role in improving the quality of learning which of course is greatly influenced by the teacher's motivation in carrying out learning because in essence motivation is an encouragement both from within the teacher, and from outside which greatly influences the implementation of the teacher's duties. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Rivai (2012)</ref> states that motivation is a set of attitudes and values that influence individuals to achieve specific things according to individual goals. These attitudes and values are something that is not visible which gives the strength to encourage individuals to behave in achieving goals. Motivation is a driving factor for achieving satisfaction or goals that are closely related to behavior and is an important response force in increasing job performance or satisfaction. One of the problems in the organization is the lack of enthusiasm of employees in carrying out their work so that it hinders the progress and achievement of organizational goals <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Daeli, 2017)</ref>.</p><p>Low work motivation of teachers in public junior high schools throughout Balangan Regency is due to the influence of various factors, as stated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Siagian (2019)</ref> that the factors that influence one's work motivation include job satisfaction. Teacher job satisfaction indicates the end result of the magnitude of the responsibility of a teacher with the tasks that have been given to him. Teacher job satisfaction makes the goals to be achieved, especially to improve the quality of education, easy to achieve and can be realized. Satisfaction is the most important thing that needs to be instilled in educational institutions, because the more satisfied the teacher's work is, the higher the work performance produced <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Wahyuningsih, 2012)</ref>.</p><p>Leadership is a process of influencing the activities of an organized group, leading to the achievement of goals, the success and failure of the leader is determined by the nature and style of leadership in directing the dynamics of the group. To influence others, a leader must have maturity, intelligence, high self-confidence, consistency, assertiveness, willingness to supervise, partnership and others <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Daryanto, 2017)</ref>. In addition to the principal leadership, an aspect that is also related to work motivation and teacher job satisfaction is work culture. Work culture is also considered a factor that affects teacher job satisfaction. In accordance with research according to Nawawi (2019) work culture is a habit that is carried out repeatedly by employees in an organization, violations in this habit do not have strict sanctions, but from the behavior of the organization morally has agreed to these habits in the context of achieving goals. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Sukiyanto, &amp; Mauidah, 2020</ref>) stated that work culture in an organization affects teacher work motivation. Likewise with the opinion (Masykur, R., 2019) which states that work culture affects work motivation. Meanwhile, regarding the correlation between culture and work motivation, (Rahayu, 2017) states that organizational culture affects work motivation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Siagian, 2019)</ref> which states that work culture affects job satisfaction. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Robbins, 2018)</ref> suggests a model of the correlation between Organizational Culture and Job Satisfaction. A strong culture will lead to high job satisfaction. In addition to having a correlation with job satisfaction, work culture is also related to leadership. As O'Reilly's opinion <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Albardi, 2019)</ref> which states that the process of forming work cultural norms begins with the words and actions of leaders.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. METHOD</head><p>This research is a descriptive correlation al research, which is a research that aims to examine the correlation or influence between variables and make predictions based on correlation s. The population in this study were teachers of State Junior High Schools in Balangan Regency. A sample of 167 people, the method of determining sample members was taken using the Proportional technique Random Sampling. The data were collected through the principal leadership instrument 23 items (ideal influence, inspirational motivation, intellectual stimulation, individual considerations), work culture 16 items (attitudes towards work and behavior at work) work motivation 23 items (internal motivation, external motivation) job satisfaction 22 items (the job itself, salary, promotion, supervision, co-workers) instruments were analyzed by means of testing the validity and reliability of the description of the collected data using path analysis to see direct and indirect relationships, by first testing normality, linearity, homogeneity <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Mardalis, 2010)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. FINDINGS AND DISCUSSION</head><p>The results of linear regression analysis show the correlation model between the principal leadership (X1), work culture (X2) and work motivation (Z) with teacher job satisfaction (Y) as presented in the following description: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1. The results of the analysis of the correlation among variables</head><p>Based on Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>, the rejection of the hypothesis in this study can be seen in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_4">5</ref>. The results of the path analysis as can be seen in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> are used to answer the seven research hypotheses that have been formulated whose decisions are given in Table <ref type="table">2</ref> and Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref> is a summary of the decisions of H 1 , H 2 , H 3 , H 4 , and H 5 with the criterion of significance value is less than 0.05, then the hypothesis is accepted. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">5</ref> is a summary of the decisions on hypothesis testing H 6 and H 7 provided that if the direct correlation coefficient is smaller than the indirect correlation coefficient, then the hypothesis is accepted. Based on the results of the analysis in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1,</ref><ref type="table">2</ref>, and 3, in this study, the correlation between variables was found to be successful.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. There is a direct correlation between principal leadership with work motivation at State Junior High Schools in Balangan Regency</head><p>The principal is the leader who is responsible for the continuity of the school organization. The principal is an educational component that plays a very important role in optimizing the quality of education. The school principal is responsible for macro education management, which is directly related to the learning process in the school concerned. are required to have creativity and be productive in innovating in the field of education in order to realize a better quality of education <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Danumiharja, 2017)</ref> . The principal leadership directly has a direct and significant correlation with work motivation at State Junior High Schools throughout Balangan Regency, which is indicated by a beta value of 0.550 category of medium closeness.</p><p>Principal leadership is an important role in the sustainability of the world of education. The sustainability of the world of education can be seen if there are subjects who take the lead in achieving the goals that have been set. Therefore, the principal leadership should be based on the ability of the principal who is proficient in personality, knowledge of education staff, school vision and mission, making decisions, and communicating. If the principal is able to work with good leadership, the condition of the school will also be good, especially achievement motivation which is directly related to the quality of education based on the learning process.</p><p>In motivating employees, leaders should create a good work atmosphere, provide opportunities for promotion. Thus enabling employees to increase their morale to achieve the need for achievement, affiliation and power as desired. In terms of needs related to the place and atmosphere of the work environment, it can be measured by the following indicators: (1) fair and decent wages, (2) opportunities for advancement, (3) recognition as individuals, (4) job security, (5) good workplace, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> acceptance by the group, (7) fair treatment, (8) recognition for achievements <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Hasibuan, 2019)</ref> .</p><p>The results of this study are in line with research <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Nasrun, 2019)</ref> which states that the principal leadership has a significant influence on work motivation . <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Zubaidah, 2016)</ref> states that the principal leadership has an effect on work motivation. (Sumartono, M., Karta, W., &amp; Setiadi, 2017) revealed that the principal leadership has an effect on work motivation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Kamdron, 2015)</ref> states that leadership has an effect on work motivation. So is research <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Wahyuningsih, 2012)</ref> which states that the principal leadership has a direct effect on work motivation. (Rahayu, 2017) states that leadership is directly related to teacher work motivation. Munawar et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Sukiyanto, &amp; Mauidah, 2020</ref>) stated that the principal leadership directly affects the work motivation of teachers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. There is a direct correlation between work culture and work motivation at State Junior High Schools in Balangan</head><p>Regency Work culture directly has a direct and significant correlation with work motivation at public junior high schools throughout Balangan Regency, which is indicated by a Beta value of 0.558 category of medium closeness.</p><p>The essence of motivation is the urge to do things better than others in carrying out activities to achieve goals. Organizational culture that can be managed and changed allows each individual to change old behavior into new behavior and a positive organizational culture will encourage employee motivation and increase organizational effectiveness. So it can be concluded that the stronger the employee's organizational culture, the higher his work motivation. Work culture is a value system that serves as a guide for those involved in an organization, which can be used as a differentiating factor against other organizations, in addition to being a reference for controlling organizational behavior and the behavior of organizational members in interactions between organizational members and interactions with other organizations. Meanwhile, work motivation is the encouragement of efforts and desires that exist in humans that activate tasks within the scope of their work. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Fridantara (2015)</ref> in his research revealed that the culture of an institution or organization providing education affects the work motivation of teachers in the organization. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Rimbano &amp; Rahma (2019)</ref> states that organizational culture such as the application of the rules given by employees affects work motivation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Nasrun (2019)</ref> in his research states that culture has a direct effect on work motivation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Setyaningsih &amp; Haitami, (2018)</ref> stated that organizational culture has a positive and significant effect on work motivation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Murtedjo (2016)</ref> states that culture affects work motivation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kamdron (2015)</ref> stated that work culture has a positive and meaningful impact on work motivation. Antariksa (2020) in his research stated that organizational culture has a direct influence on work motivation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. There is a direct correlation between the principal leadership and the job satisfaction of state junior high school teachers in Balangan Regency</head><p>The principal leadership directly has a direct and significant correlation with job satisfaction at State Junior High Schools in Balangan Regency which is indicated by a Beta value of 0.586 category of medium close relationship.</p><p>Leadership is a behavioral norm that a person uses when that person tries to influence the behavior of others as he sees it. Thus, a leader who is defined as someone who is able to influence other parties to do something according to his will, will at least be able to influence the spirit.</p><p>One of the theories related to job satisfaction related to leadership itself can be seen from the theory of Colquitt, LePine and Wesson that one of the causes of job satisfaction is the leadership factor or in other words Supervision satisfaction which means workers' feelings about their superiors. From the theoretical description above, it is known that there are determining factors for increasing teacher job satisfaction in schools, including the leadership of the principal. The role of the principal as a leader in the world of education as popularized by Mr. Ki Hajar Dewantara, the first Ing Ngarso Sun Tulodo, which requires school leaders/principals to be role models for every school member; the second, Ing Madyo Mangun Karso, which requires school leaders/principals to be able to arouse or upload enthusiasm and build cooperation, cohesiveness, togetherness among school members; the third is Tut Wuri Handayani, a school leader/principal who is able to teach an attitude of being able to be independent and not dependent on others and always provide support or support, especially to teachers as the most cohesive asset for the world of education. So that the principal leadership is reflected in being able to increase teacher job satisfaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Rimbano &amp; Rahma, 2019)</ref>.</p><p>The results of this study are in line with research by Deali (2017) stating that leadership has a positive and significant effect on job satisfaction. Likewise Sulistyo which stated that the principal leadership directly affects job satisfaction. Similarly, Rahayu (2017) stated that the principal leadership contributes directly to job satisfaction. stated that principal leadership is directly related to teacher job satisfaction. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kamdron (2015)</ref> states that leadership has a significant effect on job satisfaction. states that leadership is directly correlated with job satisfaction. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hasibuan (2019)</ref> states that leadership is related to teacher job satisfaction. (Sumartono, Karta, &amp; Setiadi, 2017) stated that leadership has a significant role on job satisfaction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. There is a direct correlation between work culture and job satisfaction of state junior high school teachers in</head><p>Balangan Regency Work culture directly has a direct and significant correlation with job satisfaction at State Junior High Schools in Balangan Regency which is indicated by a Beta value of 0.255, the category of close correlation is weak. Organizational culture is very important, because it is the habits of an organization that has behavioral norms that are also followed by its members. Robbins (2018) states that organizational culture is a system of meaning shared by organizational members that distinguishes the organization from others.</p><p>Organizational culture can help employees work, because it creates an extraordinary level of motivation for employees to give the best ability to take advantage of the opportunities provided by the organization. Shared values make employees feel comfortable working, have commitment and loyalty and make employees maintain excellence in the midst of competition between employees.</p><p>Member satisfaction is one aspect that is used to see the condition of an organization. Satisfaction of members of an organization will be realized in the form of optimal performance. The attitude of employees towards the work itself, work situations, cooperation between leaders and fellow employees is a form of job satisfaction.</p><p>Robbins (2018) suggests a model of the correlation between Organizational Culture and Job Satisfaction. A strong culture will lead to high job satisfaction. On the other hand, a weak culture will bring the organization to low job satisfaction. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Palar (2016)</ref> states that there is a very significant positive correlation between organizational culture and employee job satisfaction. The positive correlation from this research can be illustrated that the higher the organizational culture, the higher the job satisfaction of employees, on the other hand, if the organizational culture is low, the job satisfaction will be lower.</p><p>The results of this study are in line with research by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Handayani (2016)</ref> which states that culture has a positive and significant effect on job satisfaction. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Sutrisno (2018)</ref> which states that culture has an influence on job satisfaction. Antariksa (2020) also states that culture influences job satisfaction. Juwaini &amp; Fahlevi (2021) stated that work culture has a significant role in job satisfaction. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Murtedjo (2016)</ref> states that the culture that takes place in a turn educational institution contributes to teacher job satisfaction. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hamonangan (2021)</ref> in his research stated that work culture had an effect on teacher job satisfaction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. There is Direct correlation between work motivation and job satisfaction of state junior high school teachers in</head><p>Balangan Regency Job satisfaction directly has a direct and significant correlation with work motivation at State Junior High Schools in Balangan Regency which is indicated by a Beta value of 0.117, the category of closeness of the correlation is very weak.</p><p>Job satisfaction is a person's feelings and assessment of his work, especially regarding his working conditions, in relation to whether his work is able to meet his expectations, needs and desires. Meanwhile, work motivation is the drive, effort and desire that exists in humans that activates, empowers, and directs behavior to carry out tasks well within the scope of work.</p><p>Motivation as a driving factor for achieving satisfaction or goals, is closely related to behavior and is an important response force in improving employee performance or job satisfaction. One of the problems in the organization is the lack of enthusiasm of employees in carrying out their work so that it hinders the progress and achievement of organizational goals <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Daeli, 2017)</ref>. Furthermore, he revealed that leadership has an effect on job satisfaction, because if employees get support from the leadership, employees will get job satisfaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Daeli, 2017)</ref>.</p><p>Work motivation, among others, is characterized by an urge to work well and maintain feedback. A person who works in an organization aims to earn income to meet their needs, also has some hopes, desires and aspirations that are expected to be fulfilled from where they work. If in carrying out the work there is a match between expectations and the reality faced, satisfaction will arise in employees. An employee will get job satisfaction when he feels that the reward he receives is higher than his sacrifice. The advantages they get are still sufficient to meet their other needs and desires. In relation to work motivation, the decisions obtained by these workers can have a positive influence on their morale and performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Handayani, 2016)</ref>. Singh, &amp; Tiwari state that motivation is a function of job satisfaction and its value is influenced by changes in the value of satisfaction, namely, the value of motivation increases with increasing the value of job satisfaction and vice versa. This means that there is a reciprocal correlation between job satisfaction and work motivation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kamdron (2015)</ref> in his research revealed that there is a strong and significant correlation between motivation and job satisfaction. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Palar (2016)</ref> states that there is a correlation between work motivation and job satisfaction and they influence each other. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Wahyuningsih (2012)</ref> in his research states that job satisfaction has a direct effect on work motivation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Daeli (2017)</ref> states that job satisfaction affects work motivation because if job satisfaction increases, work motivation will also increase. <ref type="bibr">(Sulistyo, nd)</ref> states that there is a mutually influencing correlation between job satisfaction and work motivation. (Dekawati, Pujiyat, &amp; Sitoresmi, nd) stated that there is a correlation between job satisfaction and work motivation. F. There is indirect correlation between principal leadership and work motivation on job satisfaction of state junior high school teachers in Balangan Regency The principal leadership indirectly has a direct and significant correlation with work motivation through job satisfaction at State Junior High Schools throughout Balangan Regency, namely 0.068 the category of close correlation is very weak.</p><p>The whole series of activities in the school is an effort to fulfill the goals of the school, so that all activities of the school organization should be managed more optimally. In order to realize this goal, the quality of teacher work needs to be improved. Therefore, the role of the principal is needed to encourage his subordinates/teachers to work more optimally. One of the principal duties is as a leader, which is to lead all school activities, especially teachers. If the principal as a leader can carry out his duties and responsibilities properly and carry out leadership effectively and professionally, logically the principal leadership will encourage the creation of teacher job satisfaction which ultimately leads to an increase in teacher work motivation.</p><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hasibuan (2019)</ref> it is the obligation of every leader to create job satisfaction for his subordinates, because job satisfaction is a factor that is believed to be able to encourage and influence the morale of subordinates so that subordinates can work well and will directly affect employee performance. A leader is also required to provide a good and pleasant work atmosphere, as well as work safety guarantees so that subordinates will feel satisfied.</p><p>Job satisfaction is an employee's satisfaction with his job between what the employee expects from his job/office <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Davis, 2014)</ref>. Teacher job satisfaction is a feeling of satisfaction and dissatisfaction felt by the teacher regarding his role and function as a teacher. With job satisfaction, every teacher will have a positive spirit and attitude towards the work to be done which in turn will form work motivation. In line with <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Setyaningsih &amp; Haitami (2018)</ref> who state that leadership can affect work motivation through job satisfaction.</p><p>The results of this study are in line with research <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Kamdron, 2015)</ref> which reveals that a number of studies have been conducted on the correlation between personality and work motivation. The congruent temperament model of work motivation asserts that traditional motivational theories are incomplete, and the model should include the elements of personality, as well as aspects of effort, individual abilities, expectations, instrumentality, valence, goal-directed behavior, intrinsic and extrinsic rewards, job satisfaction, leadership and perceived equality. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Kamdron, 2015)</ref> also revealed that a worker including teachers experience job satisfaction if they feel that their abilities, competencies, and values are used in the organization and they receive rewards and opportunities from the organization, based on their perceived abilities and performance. Thereforepeople with an internal locus of control are more likely than those externally oriented to higher levels of job satisfaction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G. The indirect correlation of work culture and work motivation toward job satisfaction of state junior high school teachers in Balangan Regency</head><p>Work culture indirectly has a direct but not significant correlation with work motivation through job satisfaction at State Junior High Schools in Balangan Regency, which is 0.029 the category of closeness of correlation is very weak.</p><p>Work culture is one of the key elements of human resource management that determines the success and destruction of an organization. Work culture is a value that makes HR guidelines to deal with external problems and efforts to adjust integration into the organization, so that each member of the organization must understand the existing values and how they should act and behave. Value is something that is held and accepted by all people in an organization. If what is held is good, then the value is good and positive. Otherwise, it is considered unfavorable and negative then it will be rejected. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Masykur (2019)</ref> argues that work culture in an organization has an impact on work motivation.</p><p>Job satisfaction reflects a person's feelings towards his job. This can be seen from the attitude of employees towards work and everything in their work environment. An employee or a subordinate who is satisfied with his job will have a strong motivation or drive to be able to work well.</p><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Sutrisno (2018)</ref>, motivation is a factor that encourages someone to do a certain activity, therefore motivation is often interpreted as a factor driving a person's behavior. Every activity carried out by someone must have a factor that drives the activity. The driving factor of a person to carry out a certain activity in general is the person's needs and desires. One person's needs and wants are different from the needs and desires of others. The difference between a person's needs and desires occurs because of the mental processes that occur within that person. The mental process is the formation of perceptions in the person concerned and the process of forming self-perceptions is essentially a person's learning process of everything he sees and experiences from the environment around him.</p><p>Job satisfaction is an important aspect of an employee in the organization because with the existence of job satisfaction in an employee at work and will further stimulate his motivation in every activity to achieve organizational goals. That the aspects of work that affect job satisfaction are communication and co-workers, promotion, job security, salary, company and supervisory management, intrinsic factors of work working conditions, social aspects of work. While the factors that influence it are that the aspects of work that affect job satisfaction are salary promotion, work itself, supervision, coworkers, job security, working conditions, administration/policy, communication, responsibility, recognition, work performance, and opportunities for developing <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Robbins, 2018)</ref> .</p><p>The results of this study are in line with research conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kamdron (2015)</ref> showing that a worker including a teacher looks for opportunities to identify the match point between their personality and work situation. The current study focuses on topics broadly related to human-environment relations. The theoretical starting point for understanding job satisfaction is to identify satisfaction with the emotional state that results from the correlation , or lack thereof, between needs, values and beliefs, and characteristics of the work environment. Internal job satisfaction is higher because of teacher beliefs, teachers are less dependent on the external environment because teachers or workers are more dependent on school work culture in shaping motivation and job satisfaction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. CONCLUSION</head><p>There is a direct and indirect correlation between the principal leadership, work culture and work motivation toward teacher job satisfaction. Teachers should further improve mastery of the basic competencies of the subjects they teach, namely by first studying the basic competencies of each subject so that they are able to realize the objectives of learning.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 . Regression Analysis X1, X2, and Z against Y Coefficients a</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Unstandardized</cell><cell>Standardized</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Coefficients</cell><cell></cell><cell>Coefficients</cell><cell>t</cell><cell>Sig.</cell><cell cols="2">Collinearity Statistics</cell></row><row><cell>Model</cell><cell></cell><cell>B</cell><cell>Std. Error</cell><cell>Beta</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Tolerance</cell><cell>VIF</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>(Constant)</cell><cell>,281</cell><cell>2,753</cell><cell></cell><cell>,102</cell><cell>,919</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Principal Leadership (X1) ,353</cell><cell>,024</cell><cell>, 690</cell><cell>8,211</cell><cell>,000</cell><cell>,601</cell><cell>1,664</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Work Culture (X2)</cell><cell>,832</cell><cell>0.047</cell><cell>, 452</cell><cell>5,765</cell><cell>,000</cell><cell>,869</cell><cell>1,150</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Work Motivation (Z)</cell><cell>, 5 01</cell><cell>,034</cell><cell>, 795</cell><cell cols="2">10,031 ,00 0</cell><cell>,541</cell><cell>1,848</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">a. Dependent Variable: Job Satisfaction (Y)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Source: Calculation Results of Relationships Among Variables Moving on from the results of the analysis as table 1 above shows the correlation between Principal Leadership (X1) and Work Culture (X2) on Teacher Job Satisfaction (Y) through Work Motivation (Z) as presented in the following figure: Table 2. Mean, Standard Deviation, and Stage of Research Variables</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Mean</cell><cell>Standard Deviation</cell><cell>Stage</cell></row><row><cell>Principal Leadership</cell><cell>95.39</cell><cell>8.58</cell><cell>Tall</cell></row><row><cell>Work Culture</cell><cell>51.63</cell><cell>3.68</cell><cell>Tall</cell></row><row><cell>Motivate the Work</cell><cell>85.53</cell><cell>5.50</cell><cell>Tall</cell></row><row><cell>Job Satisfaction</cell><cell>85.92</cell><cell>6.41</cell><cell>Tall</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 . Summary of path analysis results</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Structural 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Leadership, Work Culture on Work Motivation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell cols="2">Path Coefficient T</cell><cell>p</cell><cell>R2 _</cell></row><row><cell>Principal Leadership Work Culture</cell><cell>0.567 0.423</cell><cell>10,324 8,563</cell><cell>0.000 0.000</cell><cell>0.807</cell></row><row><cell>Structural 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Leadership, work culture, work motivation on job satisfaction</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell cols="2">Path Coefficient T</cell><cell>p</cell><cell>R2 _</cell></row><row><cell>Principal Leadership</cell><cell>0.690</cell><cell>8,211</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Work culture</cell><cell>0.452</cell><cell>5,765</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>0.758</cell></row><row><cell>Work motivation</cell><cell>0.795</cell><cell>10,031</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4 . Summary of Hypothesis Testing Decisions H 1 H 2 H 3 H 4 H 5 Hypothesis p</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Decision</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 5 . Summary of H6 and Hypothesis Testing Decisions H 7</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Hypothesis</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Correlation Among School Principal Leadership, Work Culture and Work Motivation Toward Job Satisfaction of Junior High School Teachers in Balangan Regency</head><label></label><figDesc>Professional school principals</figDesc><table><row><cell>Principal Leadership</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(X1)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Work (Z) motivation</cell><cell>0,451 0,795</cell><cell>Work (Y) Satisfaction</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0,336</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Work Culture</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(X2)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation between Leadership and Organizational Culture at the Lampung Province Representative BPK</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Albardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Visionist Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of principal Leadership Style, Organizational Culture, Work Motivation on Teacher Performance with Job Satisfaction as an Intervening Variable at SD Tarakanita 3 Jakarta</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sks</forename><surname>Antariksa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Indonesian Journal of Business Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Correlation between Leadership and Work Motivation with Job Satisfaction (Study at the Directorate General of Regional Development, Ministry of Home Affairs)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Daeli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Research and Development Agency of the Ministry of Home Affairs</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Danumiharja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">School Financial Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>UHAMKA</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Daryanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Leadership in Learning</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Gava Media</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Human Behavior at Work: Organizational Behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Erlangga</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">correlation between Leadership and Work Motivation with Job Satisfaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Deal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Independent Library</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of principal Role ang Work Motivation to Teachers Job Satisfaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Dekawati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Pujiyati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sitoresmi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Educational Management and Innovation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="115" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Implementation of the Adiwiyata Program at SMA Negeri 2 Klaten. Faculty of Education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Usa</forename><surname>Fridantara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Yogyakarta State University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Motivation, Work Culture and Their Impact on Satisfaction and Performance of Santo Yosef School Teachers, Mandau District, Bengkalis Regency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hamonangan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of KIAT Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="145" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Correlation between Organizational Culture and Work Motivation with Job Satisfaction of Employees and Lecturers at the Faculty of Economics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Handayani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="144" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Pancasila University, Jakarta. Creative, Journal of Pamulang University Management Study Program</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Human Resource Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hasibuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Earth Literature</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Work Motivation: Relationships with Job Satisfaction, Locus of Control and Motivation Orientation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kamdron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Liberal Arts and Social Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mardalis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Qualitative Research Methods. Grammar</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Organizational Culture on Teacher Work Motivation at Ar-Raudah Elementary School Bandar Lampung</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Masykur</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Al-Idara Journal of Islamic Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Contribution to Cultural Organization, Working Motivation and Job Satisfaction on the Performance of Primary School Teacher</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">&amp;</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Murtedjo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Higher Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of principal Leadership on Teacher Work Motivation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Nasrun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Theory and Practice Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Human Resource Management for Competitive Business</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Nawawi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>Gadjah Mada University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">the Effect of Work Motivation and Job Satisfaction on Employee Performance at Bank Sulutgo Tomohon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Palar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Efficient Scientific Periodic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interpersonal Communication Principal Leadership and Organizational Work Culture on Work Motivation and Its Impact on Junior High School Teacher Job Satisfaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Grace</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Environmentally Based Curriculum Policy Through the Adiwiyata Program in High Schools</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rimbano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rahma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.35760/eb.2019.v24i3.1876</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.35760/eb.2019.v24i3.1876" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific Journal of Business Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="274" to="287" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Commercial Bank Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rivai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Rajagrafindo</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principles of Organizational Behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Robbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Erlangga</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Work Motivation, Organizational Culture, Principal Leadership on Job Satisfaction and Teacher Performance in Private High Schools in Palembang</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Setyaningsih</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Haitami</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Islamic Education Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Human Resource Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Siagian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Earth Literature</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Correlation between Motivation And Job Satisfaction Of The White Collar Employees: A Case Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Tiwari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Management Insights</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of principal Leadership Style and Organizational Culture on Teacher and Employee Motivation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sukiyanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mauidah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Edutama Education Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of Work Motivation and Leadership toward Work Satisfaction and Employee Performance: Evidence from Indonesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sulistyo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">KoreaScience: The Journal of Asian Finance, Economics and Business</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="387" to="397" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Principal Leadership and the Provision of Work Compensation on the Motivation of Vocational High School Teachers in Lingsar District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sumartono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Karta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Setiadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific Journal of the Educational Profession</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Human Resource Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sutrisno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Date</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The correlation Between Job Satisfaction with Employee Performance at PT. Solo Pure Boyolali Branch</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wahyuningsih</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>PT. Solo Pure Boyolali Branch. UMSLbrary</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">the Influence of Principal Leadership and Teacher Competence on Teacher Work Motivation and Its Implications on Teacher Performance at SMP Negeri Palembang City</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Zubaidah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Global Economent</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>There is an Open Access article, distributed under the term of the Creative Commons Attribution -Non Commercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0. which permits remixing, adapting and building upon the work for non-commercial use, provided the original work is properly cited</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
