<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Correlation among Teacher Professionalism, Work Motivation and Work Discipline on Teacher Performance</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Karyono</forename><forename type="middle">Ibnu</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master in Educational Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Metroyadi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master in Educational Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Correlation among Teacher Professionalism, Work Motivation and Work Discipline on Teacher Performance</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-30</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T21:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Professionalism</term>
					<term>motivation</term>
					<term>discipline</term>
					<term>performance</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This study aims to find and analyze the correlation among teacher professionalism, work motivation and work discipline on teacher performance. This research study uses a descriptive correlational research. The research population was 152 with a research sample of 110 people. The data was collected using instruments consisting of teacher professionalism (43 items), work motivation (24 items), work discipline (35 items), teacher performance (23 items) which had been tested for validity and reliability. The data analysis of this research used path analysis. The results of the study showed that teacher professionalism has a relationship with work discipline, work motivation has a relationship with work discipline, work discipline has a relationship with teacher performance, teacher professionalism has a relationship with teacher performance, work motivation has a relationship with teacher performance, teacher professionalism has a relationship with teacher performance, and work motivation has a relationship with work discipline.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Correlation among Teacher Professionalism, Work Motivation and Work Discipline on Teacher Performance</head><p>In general, a phenomenon that often occurs in the field is that there are still teachers who are lacking in terms of evaluating their performance. Also, there are still many teachers who carry out their obligations in teaching only carry out their profession's guidance without being wholeheartedly, resulting in low teacher performance which will result in the low quality of educational output declining. Based on UNESCO data in the 2016 Global Education Monitoring (GEM) report in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Khumaira, 2020)</ref>, education in Indonesia ranks 10th out of 14 developing countries and teacher quality ranks 14th out of 14 developing countries in the world. The number of teachers has increased by 36% to more than 3 million people, and the increase in the number of educators is only 17%. Of the 3.9 existing teachers, there are still 25% of teachers who meet the academic qualification requirements and 52% of them do not have a professional certificate. This shows that quantity does not guarantee the quality of an education, but the educational process must be of quality so that it will produce quality educational output as well. Thus, it is very necessary to improve the performance of teachers in order to carry out their duties and obligations to the fullest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHOD</head><p>This research is a correlational descriptive research. It aims to examine and analyze direct and indirect relationships. The population in this study were SDN teachers, North Tapin District, Tapin Regency, with a population of 152 teachers. The sampling technique used is Proportional Random Sampling. the number of samples was determined based on the slovin formula as many as 110 people. Data were collected through teacher professionalism instruments (pedagogic competence, personality competence, social competence, professional competence) work motivation (internal motivation, external motivation) work discipline (job goals and work abilities, attendance list, exemplary leader, remuneration, fairness, supervision attached to legal sanctions, human relations) teacher performance (quality of work, quantity, timeliness, effectiveness) instruments were analyzed through validity and reliability tests of descriptions of data collected using path analysis to see direct and indirect relationships, by first testing normality, linearity, homogeneity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head><p>Based on the findings of rock data with SPSS, found direct and indirect correlation coefficients as described in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.  <ref type="table">1</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>, the hypothesis in this study can be seen in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> above, this study found a relationship between variables which can be explained as follows.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 1. Summary of path analysis results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Structural 1</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Correlation among Teacher Professionalism, Work and Work Discipline on Teacher Performance</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. There is a relationship Teacher Professionalism towards Work Discipline</head><p>The results of this study indicate that there is a direct positive and significant relationship between teacher professionalism and teacher work discipline of 0.635. This indicates that in order to improve work discipline, it can be done by increasing teacher professionalism. The teachers in carrying out their duties must still refer to the applicable provisions which are the discretion of the teachers in the field of education. Teachers are required to comply with all government regulations in carrying out their duty's dedication, so that the teacher is not negatively affected by the wider party who impose their ideas through the world of education. The teachers' obedient attitude to all applicable laws and regulations will directly shape the discipline of the teacher concerned.</p><p>Teacher professionalism can also be seen from the attitude or treatment of colleagues. As regulated in the teacher's code of ethics which states that teachers in maintaining professional relationship, family spirit, and infidelity social. This means that teachers are required to maintain relationships fellow teachers in their work environment, and outside their work environment. If the teacher maintains communication and interaction with colleagues, it means that the teacher acts according to the teacher's code of ethics and this can be categorized as a disciplined action. Teacher professionalism can be seen based on the teachers' attitude towards students. Devoted teachers guide students to form a complete Indonesian human who has the spirit of Pancasila. In addition, it is also the principle of the teacher who must guide students, not only teaching and learning only educate and guide students by paying attention to the character of each student.When carrying out their duties, teachers must have an attitude towards the area or situation where they are placed. There are two things that must be considered, namely: (a) the teachers themselves, and (b) the teachers' relationship with parents and the local community. A teacher creates an atmosphere school in the best possible way that supports and strives for the best possible atmosphere in various ways, using appropriate teaching methods, as well as by providing learning tools adequate and a solid class organization arrangement or with another approach. Every time teachers carry out their duties, they have a supervisor or leader. A leader is someone who has a wisdom direction in terms of leading the organization, therefore the attitude of the teachers towards the leader must be positive in the sense of working together in the success of the agreed school program, good at school and outside of school. Professionalism towards work discipline as the results of this study is in line with {Formatting Citation}which states that professionalism directly has a significant effect on work discipline.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Relationship between work motivation and work discipline</head><p>The results of this study shows that there is a direct positive and significant relationship between work motivation and teacher work discipline of 0.321. This means that the higher the work motivation of the teacher, the higher the work discipline of the teacher. One of the motivations is caused by internal factors which include responsibility for work, having an interest in work, job satisfaction, needs must be met, and enthusiasm at work. Someone who has good internal motivation is expected to be able to carry out high work discipline, both in terms of controlling behavior, obeying regulations, willingness or awareness to carry out tasks and willing to accept sanctions. The second motivation comes from external actors, for example wanting to get praise or attention from others, wanting to get money/intensive/reward, the desire to get awards or achievements, encouragement from superiors, interpersonal relationships and good working conditions, if the external motivation is owned. well by someone, a high work discipline is created both from the aspect of purpose and willingness, exemplary leadership, remuneration, justice and waskat. The results of this study are in line with research study of <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Marlina et al., (2019)</ref> which states that motivation is related to work discipline, as well as Sulaxono, (2020) which states that motivation is related to work discipline.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Relationship Work Discipline on Teacher Performance</head><p>The results of this study shows that there is a direct positive and significant relationship between work discipline and teacher performance of 0.729. This means that the higher the work discipline of the teacher, the higher the teacher's performance. Discipline of each teacher always affects the results of work performance. Therefore, in every organization, including in the school environment, it is necessary to emphasize teacher discipline. Through high discipline, teacher work productivity can be increased. Good discipline reflects the magnitude of a person's responsibility for the tasks assigned to him/ her. This encourages work passion, morale, and the realization of organizational goals. Discipline will reflect strength because commonly someone who succeeds in his/ her work is the one who has high discipline. In order to realize the company's goals, the first thing that the company must build and enforce is the discipline of the employees. Teachers who have high work discipline are capable of controlling behavior, obeying regulations, receiving sanctions if they make a mistake, then being aware and willing to carry out tasks so that teachers can communicate well with students, teachers, education staff, parents and the community. In addition, it can recognize the characteristics of students, understand, develop potential, carry out educational learning activities, master learning theories, conceptual structure materials and scientific mindsets that support subjects, educational learning principles, and be able to develop curriculum types and how to assess them. . Then teachers who have discipline in carrying out their duties have responsibility for goals and abilities, exemplary leaders, justice, waskat and remuneration will produce good performance, including being able to act in accordance with Indonesian religious, legal, social and national cultural norms, able to show personal and mature and exemplary, has a high responsibility work ethic, feels proud to be a teacher, is inclusive, acts objectively and is not discriminatory and can develop professionalism through reflective action. The results of this study corroborate with the research study of Shaleh &amp; Suhaimi, Marlina (2019) which states that discipline directly related to performance. Similarly, research study of Mardianti (2019) and Sulaxono (2020) which states that discipline is directly related to performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. The Relationship of Teacher Professionalism to Teacher Performance</head><p>The results of this study shows that there is a direct positive and significant relationship between teacher professionalism and teacher performance of 0.187. This means that the higher the professionalism of the teacher, the higher the teacher's performance. Teachers who in carrying out their duties and responsibilities can demonstrate obedience and compliance with applicable laws and regulations are able to maintain and utilize professional organizations to the maximum, maintain good relationships and communication with colleagues, and be fair to students and provide guidance. In order to form the character of students who have the spirit of Pancasila, teachers are able to work well in creating an atmosphere school as well as possible, and teachers who are able to work well with the principal will certainly produce maximum performance. The results of this study are in line with the findings Saputra (2011) which states that teacher professionalism is related to performance. Likewise, Shaleh &amp; Suhaimi, Murniati, Jihad &amp; Yusrizal (2019) stated that professionalism is related to teacher performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. The Relationship between Work Motivation and Teacher Performance</head><p>The results of this study shows that there is a direct positive and significant relationship between work motivation and teacher performance of 0.087. This means that the higher the work motivation, the higher the teacher's performance. One of the motivations is caused by internal factors which include responsibility for work, having an interest in work, job satisfaction, needs that must be met, and enthusiasm at work. Someone who has good internal motivation is expected to be able to perform well, including being able to recognize students, mastering the learning theories and educational principles of learning, being able to develop curriculum types and how to assess them, and mastering the material and conceptual structures and scientific mindsets that support the subjects studied. This people is also able to learning activities that educate, understand and develop potential, both in communicating with students, assessment and evaluation, acting in accordance with Indonesian religious, legal, social and national cultural norms, being inclusive, acting objectively and non-discriminatory, showing a mature personality and example.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Correlation among Teacher Professionalism, Work Motivation and Work Discipline on Teacher Performance</head><p>The second motivation comes from external actors, for example wanting to get praise or attention from others, wanting to get money/intensive/reward, wanting to get awards or achievements, encouragement from superiors, interpersonal relationships and good working conditions, if the external motivation is owned well by someone so that the teacher can show a mature and exemplary personality, communicate well with fellow teachers, education staff, parents and the community, have a high responsibility work ethic, feel proud to be a teacher and finally be able to develop professionalism through reflective action. The results of this study support the findings of Shaleh and Suhaimi, Marlina, et al,. (2019) which stated that there was a direct relationship between work motivation and teacher performance. Similarly, Sulaxono's research (2020) states that there is a direct relationship between work motivation and teacher performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F. There is an indirect relationship between teacher professionalism and teacher performance through work discipline</head><p>Research result This shows that indirectly there is a positive and significant relationship between teacher professionalism and teacher performance through teacher work discipline of 0.374 and t count 11.575. Teachers who show an obedient and obedient attitude to applicable laws and regulations, are able to maintain and utilize professional organizations to the maximum, are able to maintain and establish good relationships and communication with colleagues, be fair to students and provide guidance to shape the character of students who have the spirit of Pancasila, teachers at work are good at creating an atmosphere schools as well as possible, and teachers who are able to work well with the principal will certainly produce maximum performance that can be seen from knowing the characteristics of students, mastering learning theories and educational principles of learning, being able to develop curriculum types and how to assess them, mastery of material and the structure of scientific concepts and mindsets that support the subjects taught, learning activities that educate, understand and develop potential, both in communicating with students, assessment and evaluation, acting in accordance with Indonesian religious, legal, social and national cultural norms, being inclusive, acting objectively and non-discriminatory, showing a mature and exemplary personality, communicating well with fellow teachers, education staff, parents and the community, having a high responsibility work ethic, being proud to be a teacher and finally being able to develop professionalism through action. ref lective. The professionalism of a good teacher will be positively related to teacher performance so that indirectly the individual has applied good work discipline as well. Work discipline is the attitude of a teacher in controlling behavior, obeying regulations, awareness, willingness, responsibility in carrying out tasks, having goals and desires, exemplary leaders, remuneration, fairness, discretion and being able to accept sanctions if they make a mistake. Referring to the description, the better the professionalism of the teacher through the discipline of the teacher, the better the teacher's performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G. There is an indirect relationship between work motivation and teacher performance through work discipline</head><p>The results of this study shows that indirectly there is a positive and significant relationship between work motivation and teacher performance through teacher work discipline of 0.234 and t count 2,925. One of the motivations is caused by internal factors which include responsibility for work, having an interest in work, job satisfaction, needs that must be met, and enthusiasm at work. Someone who has good internal motivation is expected to be able to perform well, including being able to recognize students, mastering learning theories and educational principles of learning, being able to develop curriculum types and how to assess them, mastering material and conceptual structures and scientific mindsets that support the subjects studied. capable, learning activities that educate, understand and develop potential, both in communicating with students, assessment and evaluation, acting in accordance with Indonesian religious, legal, social and national cultural norms, being inclusive, acting objectively and nondiscriminatory, showing a mature personality and example. The second motivation comes from external actors, for example wanting to get praise or attention from others, wanting to get money/intensive/reward, wanting to get awards or achievements, encouragement from superiors, interpersonal relationships and good working conditions, if the external motivation is owned. well by a teacher so that he can show a mature and exemplary personality, communicate well with fellow teachers, education staff, parents and the community, have a high responsibility work ethic, feel proud to be a teacher and finally be able to develop professionalism through reflective action. Individuals who have internal and external motivations in themselves indirectly have good performance so that their work discipline can indirectly increase to the maximum, for example, from the attitude of a teacher in controlling behavior, obeying regulations, awareness, willingness, responsibility in implementing duty, has a purpose and a will, exemplary leader, remuneration, justice, waskat and able to accept sanctions when making a mistake. From this description, the better work motivation through teacher work discipline, the better the teacher's performance. The results of this study are in line with research by Marlina, et al,. (2019) which states that there is an indirect relationship between work motivation and performance through work discipline. Similarly, Sulaxono's research study results (2020) stating that there is an indirect relationship between motivation and teacher performance through work discipline. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>It is concluded that there is a direct and indirect relationship between teacher professionalism, work motivation and work discipline on teacher performance. Teachers should further improve mastery of the basic competencies of the subjects they teach, The Correlation among Teacher Professionalism, Work Motivation and Work Discipline on Teacher Performance</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="2,77.25,572.10,426.75,131.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 . Summary of Hypothesis Testing Decisions H 1 H 2 H 3 H 4 H 5</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Hypothesis</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 . Summary of H6 and Hypothesis Testing Decisions H 7</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Hypothesis</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>is a summary of the decisions H1 , H 2 , H 3 , H 4 , and H 5 with a significance value criterion of less than 0.05; therefore, the hypothesis is accepted. Table3is a summary of the decisions on hypothesis testing H 6 and H 7 provided that if the direct correlation coefficient is smaller than the indirect relationship coefficient, then the hypothesis is accepted. Based on the results of the analysis in Tables</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>namely by first studying the basic competencies of each subject so that they are able to realize the objectives of learning.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Relationship between Work Motivation and Principal Supervision with the Performance of State Middle School Teachers in Babahrot District, Southwest Aceh</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jihad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Administration</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Incentives and Professionalism on Discipline and Employee Performance at the General Bureau of the Regional Secretariat of Riau Province</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Khumaira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">KIAT Economic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Effect of Organizational Climate, Work Discipline on Job Satisfaction and Teacher Performance in State Senior High Schools in Hulu</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mardianti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Sungai Tengah Regency. Lambung Mangkurat University Banjarmasin</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Transformational Leadership and Work Motivation on Teacher Performance Through Teacher Discipline</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Marlina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Suriansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Metroyadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of K6 Education and Management (JK</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="340" to="348" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Becoming a Professional Teacher Creates Creative and Fun Learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mulyasa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Rosdakarya Youth</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Teachers professional management through teachers working group in Aceh Province</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Murniati</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Management Accounting</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Relationship Between Teacher Professional Competence and Teacher Performance at SMA Tangerang</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Saputra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Esa Unggul University</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Management of Indonesian Migrant Workers Administrative and Operational Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sastrohadiwiryo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Earth Literature</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Relationship between Work Motivation, Work Discipline, Teacher Professional Attitude and Teacher Performance in Public Elementary Schools in South Labuan Amas District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Salih</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Suhaimi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<pubPlace>Hulu Sungai Tengah Regency</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Master of Education Management at Lambung Mangkurat University Banjarmasin</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Relationship of Transformational Leadership and Work Motivation Through Discipline and Teacher Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Sulaxono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="65" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Journal of K6 Education and Management (JK6EM). There is an Open Access article, distributed under the term of the Creative Commons Attribution -Non Commercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0. which permits remixing, adapting and building upon the work for non-commercial use, provided the original work is properly cited</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
