<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Correlation Between Principal Instructional Leadership, Achievement Motivation and Teacher Performance through Job Satisfaction in State Elementary Schools in Kandangan District, Hulu Sungai Selatan Regency</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Muhammad</forename><surname>Birhasani</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master of Educational Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Metroyadi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master of Educational Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Correlation Between Principal Instructional Leadership, Achievement Motivation and Teacher Performance through Job Satisfaction in State Elementary Schools in Kandangan District, Hulu Sungai Selatan Regency</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-71,Impact</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T21:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Principal Instructional Leadership</term>
					<term>Achievement Motivation</term>
					<term>Job Satisfaction</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Until now the quality of education is still not as expected, and one of the factors of the quality of education is the performance of teachers in school organizations. Other factors that influence teacher performance include the principal instructional leadership, achievement motivation, and job satisfaction. As a result, this study aims to analyze the direct and indirect correlation between the principal instructional leadership, achievement motivation, and teacher performance through job satisfaction. The method used in this research was a descriptive correlation with a quantitative approach which is formulated into a path analysis model. The research population was 384 teachers from 41 elementary schools in Kandangan District and the research sample was 196 using the proportional allocation formula. The data was collected using a questionnaire consisting of principal instructional leadership (40 items), achievement motivation (40 items) and job satisfaction (40 items) using a questionnaire instrument that has passed the validity and reliability test using the product moment person correlation. Meanwhile, teacher performance data (51 items) were taken from the teacher assessment performance documentation. The stages of data analysis started from descriptive analysis, classical assumption test, hypothesis testing, and path analysis. The results of this study indicate that there is a direct and indirect correlation among the principal instructional leadership, achievement motivation, and teacher performance through job satisfaction.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Improving the quality of teachers in school organizations is one strategy to improve the quality of education in Indonesia. The performance of teachers, which leads to the existence and duty of teachers in carrying out their duties as teachers and other activities, demonstrates their excellence. Teachers are a prominent component of the curriculum in enhancing the quality of education because they are directly involved in the learning process in schools. The teacher must be qualified and professional in order for the learning process to be of good quality <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Mulyasa, 2013)</ref>.</p><p>Teacher performance plays an important role, considering that efforts are needed to improve teacher performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Koswara and Rasto, 2016)</ref>. Improvement of the quality of teacher performance is expected to improve the quality of education. Gaynor in <ref type="bibr">Aslamiah (2015)</ref> asserts that "Performance relates to what teachers do in the classroom and how that affects student learning", meaning that performance is closely related to what teachers do in the classroom and how it affects student learning activities. This is in accordance with the results of research study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Erwanto (2018)</ref> concluding that 77% of the effective contribution or contribution given by teacher performance to student learning achievement, while 23% is influenced by other factors. According to observations and interviews with several primary school principals in the Kandangan District of the Hulu Sungai Selatan Regency, teacher performance remains below expectations, such as teachers' abilities to prepare learning in class. In terms of planning the learning process, conducting the learning process, measuring learning outcomes, and overseeing the learning process, teachers have no notion what to do in class. There is still a disconnect between theory and classroom application in the learning process; teachers do not grasp the characteristics of students, making them less able to detect students' potential progress through learning programs.</p><p>Improving teacher performance is challenging since many factors influence teacher performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Suriansyah, 2020)</ref>. Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Allen and Meyer (2013)</ref> stated that performance is related to a set of factors that affect various things, including the quality of work life. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Mulyasa, 2014)</ref> states that there are several factors that influence teacher performance, namely: leadership, motivation, job satisfaction, discipline, and many more.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Principal Instructional Leadership</head><p>Teacher performance is influenced by principal leadership. Many leadership models are used in various organizations/institutions, both for-profit and non-profit; however, instructional leadership is the most appropriate to use in schools (instructional leadership or leadership for improving the learning). Several studies such as Suriansyah and Suhaimi (2020), <ref type="bibr">Aslamiah (2018)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Margarita (2017)</ref> conclude that principals who focus on instructional leadership produce better teacher performance than principals who focus less on instructional leadership.</p><p>The importance of instructional leadership in increasing teacher performance has long been acknowledged as a deciding factor in school structure, particularly in terms of its obligation to promote school learning quality. Teaching and learning, as well as teacher performance in relation to student achievement, are the emphasis of instructional leadership. Teacher job satisfaction is also linked to instructional leadership. Because teachers are a key instrument in enhancing school quality, the subject of teacher satisfaction must be treated seriously by the principal instructional leadership.</p><p>The principal instructional leadership style in carrying out his duties and responsibilities greatly influences teacher performance because successful leaders are the leaders who are able to manage and empower the resources available in schools effectively and efficiently to achieve school goals or educational goals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACHIEVEMENT MOTIVATION</head><p>Achievement motivation is also an important part since people who have high achievement motivation will be very happy if they succeed in winning a competition, and dare to take all risks as a consequence of their efforts to achieve goals <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Hallinger, 2015)</ref>. Hilgard in Siagian (2013) stated that achievement motivation is a social motive to do something valuable or important well and perfectly to meet the standard of excellence of what one does. Meanwhile, according to Jackson in Hidayat (2018) achievement motivation is a very strong impetus to try and work hard in order to achieve success and excellence. The close correlation of achievement motivation to improving teacher performance is evidenced by research study conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Aslamiah and Murdayanti (2019)</ref> whose research results showed a positive influence of achievement motivation on teacher performance, meaning that the higher the achievement motivation, the higher the teacher's performance.</p><p>Teachers with high achievement motivation make themselves happy and find enjoyment in their work. A teacher with strong achievement motivation will strive for maximum results with high enthusiasm, and will always strive to improve their tasks and themselves. It is possible to improve teacher job satisfaction by increasing work motivation.</p><p>The desire to communicate, work efficiently, and be completely involved in all efforts to obtain fulfillment is the driving force behind achievement motivation. By improving work motivation, it is feasible to improve teacher job satisfaction. When someone desires something, he will have an expectation, which will motivate him to act in order to fulfill those expectations. And if his expectations are met, he will be completely satisfied. According to Herzberg, achievement is a factor that contributes to job satisfaction, and someone who does not achieve would be dissatisfied with their employment. This component is found in achievement motivation, which emphasizes responsibility, development, the task itself, accomplishments, and acknowledgment, among other things <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Robbins, 2014)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>JOB SATISFACTION</head><p>Job satisfaction is also an important factor that affects performance because teachers who are satisfied with their jobs will work with enthusiasm to provide opportunities for high work results, whereas teachers who are dissatisfied with their jobs will work carelessly, which will have an impact on the resulting performance.</p><p>Teacher job satisfaction is defined as the appearance of a sense of fulfillment and timely completion of duties that are the teacher's duty, as well as the appearance of dedication, enthusiasm, craft, perseverance, initiative, and high work inventiveness at work <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Cascio, 2016)</ref>. According to Herzberg in <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Robbins (2014)</ref>, motivational factors such as achievement, progress, recognition, responsibility, and work achievement influence job satisfaction. Teachers who have achievement motivation will have a high responsibility to work enthusiastically and as best as possible to mobilize all abilities and skills in order to achieve optimal performance so as to foster satisfaction with the results they get.</p><p>The issue of enhancing teacher effectiveness, as described above, is non-negotiable; it is an absolute necessity. Teachers' performance as teaching professions must be continuously and proportionally improved and developed, so it is necessary to evaluate or evaluate teacher performance to ensure that they can provide quality educational services and that a quality learning process occurs at all levels of education.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHOD</head><p>The research design used is correlational research. It is a research that connects between two or more variables and observed simultaneously at the same time. The study's population consisted of 384 teachers from 41 schools, with 196 teachers as research samples (respondents) utilizing the proportionate allocation formula and a probability simple random selection technique.</p><p>According to the conceptual design of this study, data were collected using instruments such as teacher performance assessment documentation and 3 a questionnaire with four scales that passed the validity and reliability test, including a leadership questionnaire principal's instructional, motivation achievement, satisfaction work, and teacher performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1. Research Conceptual Design</head><p>According to the conceptual design of the research in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>, the analytical test uses path analysis to answer the hypothesis: H1: there is a direct correlation between principal instructional leadership and teacher performance, H2: there is a direct correlation between principal instructional leadership and job satisfaction, H3: there is a direct correlation between achievement motivation and teacher performance, H4: there is a direct correlation between achievement motivation and job satisfaction, H5: there is a direct correlation between job satisfaction and teacher performance, H6: there is an indirect correlation between principal instructional leadership and teacher performance through job satisfaction, and H7: there is an indirect correlation between achievement motivation with teacher performance through job satisfaction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>FINDINGS AND DISCUSSION</head><p>Descriptive statistics analyze data from questionnaires that describe respondents' responses to the variables of principal's instructional leadership, achievement motivation, job satisfaction and teacher performance can be seen in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. The results of descriptive data show principal instructional leadership, achievement motivation, job satisfaction and teacher performance fall into the category hugh. The pre-requisite analysis stage was the normality test using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov non-parametric statistical test. The result is that all variables show a significance value (Sig.) of more than 0.05 (sig. &gt; 0.05), meaning that the variables are normally distributed. on the results of linearity test and multicollinearity test all variables show a linear form and there is not any multicollinearity. After the prerequisite test was met, then it was proceed with hypothesis testing through path analysis. The results of the summary analysis are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>. Based on the summary of the results of the analysis in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2,</ref><ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> , and 4, in this study, the correlation between variables that can be explained as follows:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. There is a Direct Correlation between Principal's Instructional Leadership and Teacher Performance</head><p>Based on the results of hypothesis testing, there is a direct correlation between instructional leadership and teacher performance. Instructional leadership is a type of leadership that is considered capable of improving the performance of its subordinates because instructional leadership not only pays attention to the need for self-actualization and appreciation but also raises awareness for leaders to do their best by paying more attention to human factors, performance, and organizational growth.</p><p>The results of this analysis strengthen the research study conducted by Ibrahim (2019) , Iresha (2020) and Margarita (2017) who carried out research studies on instructional leadership on performance with the results of their research concluding that the principal instructional leadership is positively and significantly related to teacher performance. The results of research by Shatzer in Aslamiah (2018) , and Andrews &amp; Soder in Suriansyah and Suhaimi (2020) show a direct influence of principal instructional leadership on student achievement. Principals with their instructional leadership have a positive impact on the performance of teachers. The better the principal instructional leadership, the better the performance of the teachers. For this reason, as the principal, he must maximally empower his instructional leadership to be able to simultaneously mobilize all human resources in the school in order to provide performance that is good for teachers. Rigsbee in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Daryanto (2016)</ref> suggests that a good principal is an instructional leader who helps teachers create the best way for students to learn. Instructional principals place the learning agenda in the first order of all their activities as well as provide appropriate support for improving the quality of teacher teaching performance and learning success in the classroom. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Hallinger (2015)</ref> emphasizes that an instructional principal is able to create a positive learning environment by supporting professional development, sharing a vision and providing strong motivation and inspiration for teaching staff or teachers in learning. The principal of schools motivates teachers to develop professionalism so that teachers can improve the quality of teaching . </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. There is a Direct correlation between Principal Instructional Leadership and Job Satisfaction</head><p>Based on the results of hypothesis testing, there is a significant correlation between instructional leadership and teacher satisfaction.</p><p>The results of this study strengthen the research conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Verawati (2017)</ref> that instructional leadership has a significant effect on job satisfaction for teachers and elementary school student performance. Likewise, a research study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Margarita (2017)</ref> concludes that leadership has a positive and significant effect on teacher job satisfaction. De Roche in Hoy and Miskel (2014) suggests that the sources of teacher job satisfaction are teacher involvement in making school decisions, teacher perceived recognition, teacher expectations, interpersonal correlations that occur in the work environment and the authority received by teachers. While Holdaway in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Hoy and Miskel (2014)</ref> argues that the factors that influence teacher job satisfaction are the leadership ability of the principal through the recognition and status of teachers, the availability of teaching resources, freedom to manage teaching, creating a conducive organizational climate and the ability of the principal in helping to improve the quality of teachers.</p><p>The principal instructional leadership plays a pivotal role in enhancing teacher job satisfaction. The amount of teacher work satisfaction is inextricably linked to the principal's leadership abilities. In this situation, the principal's instructional leadership is more focused on the learning function, and the principal's attention is more devoted to thinking about how to ensure that learning runs smoothly in order to meet the goals that have been set. Teachers will see the principal as a suitable example to follow if he or she provides excellent instructional leadership. This is in accordance with the opinion of Aslamiah (2019) that job satisfaction is related to a person's attitudes and feelings towards his work. If an individual is positive about his work, then he will get job satisfaction, and vice versa. A teacher who is satisfied with his work has a favorable evaluation of his work, which is based on observation and emotional experience. This result also corroborates the results of previous research that has been carried out by Ibrahim (2019) in his research study, which found that the principal's instructional leadership variable had a positive and significant effect on the teacher satisfaction variable. The same result was found by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Destiana (2018)</ref> that instructional leadership has a positive and significant effect on employee satisfaction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. There is a Direct correlation between Achievement Motivation and Teacher Performance</head><p>Based on the results of the regression test, the coefficient value of the achievement motivation variable with teacher performance is established. Achievement motivation is a teacher's strong impetus to continue to give his best performance, so that both of them influence each other. As a result, work motivation must always be maintained in order to produce good teacher performance. This study strengthens a number of studies which empirical has proven that there is a positive correlation between achievement motivation and the achievement of teacher performance such as research study by Aslamia (2018) stating that there is a significant influence of achievement motivation on teacher performance. The results of the study by Wardana (2020) also found that there was a significant influence between achievement motivation and teacher performance and the results of research <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Wardani, 2019)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Yovitha, 2020)</ref> to which both concluded that there was a significant effect of achievement motivation on teacher performance.</p><p>Robbins (2014) defines achievement motivation as an individual's encouragement to do something optimally by using all his abilities to excel from other individuals until the individual achieves success. Therefore, teachers who have high achievement motivation have a strong drive to succeed, where teachers only focus on pursuing achievements rather than rewards for success, teachers will also be more eager to do something better and always complete their tasks and responsibilities. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Danim (2014)</ref> explains that a teacher who has low achievement motivation will usually remain silent when facing difficulties in carrying out his work so that it is easy to give up on the situation rather than trying to overcome it. In contrast to a teacher who has high achievement motivation, if there are difficulties in carrying out their duties and work, they will continue to try to overcome them and improve their performance. Motivation becomes the actualization of a teacher to improve his performance. Based on this, teacher work motivation is a very important factor so that teacher performance can be achieved as expected <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Katz, 2014)</ref> .</p><p>Even though teachers already have high achievement motivation, there are several things that need to be improved, such as in the sub-section variables of creativity and innovation, without high creativity and innovation the teachers will hinder the realization of the desire to get optimal results at work, teachers must be better able to use the opportunity to show their potential and expertise so that they get the impetus to take more initiative in work , as well as encouragement to do Innovative work still needs to be improved so that the achievement motivation of teachers in SDN throughout the Kandangan District is better. This is in accordance with Southworth's opinion in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Hasibuan (2014)</ref> explaining that achievement motivation is closely related to the creativity of teacher performance in teaching. This statement is supported by Hallinger in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Acep and Suyanto (2016)</ref> which states that the teacher is the main factor in the education process. Even though the facilities are complete and sophisticated, if they are not supported by high teacher creativity, it is impossible for a maximum learning and teaching process to occur.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. There is a Direct correlation between Achievement Motivation and Job Satisfaction</head><p>Teachers who work with high achievement motivation will also have high job satisfaction. The existence of this correlation will give a view that a teacher with achievement motivation is based on two things, namely the tendency to achieve success and the tendency to avoid failure. Teachers who have high achievement motivation will make every action taken is a personal responsibility. Study this strengthen a number of studies that prove that there is a positive correlation between achievement motivation and the achievement of Correlation Between Principal Instructional Leadership, Achievement Motivation and Teacher Performance through Job Satisfaction in State Elementary Schools in Kandangan District, Hulu Sungai Selatan Regency teacher performance such as research study by <ref type="bibr">Aslamiah (2015)</ref> which states that there is a significant influence of achievement motivation on teacher performance. The results of Purnomo's research study (2020) also found that there was a significant influence between achievement motivation and teacher satisfaction. The results of the research study by Yovitha (2020) and Wardana (2020) both concluded that there was a significant influence of achievement motivation on teacher job satisfaction.</p><p>Blum in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Dessler (2015)</ref> suggests that job satisfaction is a general attitude that is the result of several specific attitudes towards work factors, self-adjustment, and individual social correlations outside of work. A teacher with a high drive for achievement motivation differs from others in their strong desire to do things better. Teachers with high achievement motivation look for opportunities where they have personal responsibility in finding answers to problems. Teachers who have high achievement motivation prefer jobs where they have personal responsibility, will get feedback and work assignments have moderate risks. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Mangkunegara (2015)</ref> states that teachers will feel more motivated in achievement if they are satisfied in the field of work because what they do is also to meet their needs so that they feel more serious about completing their responsibilities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. There is a Direct correlation between Job Satisfaction and Teacher Performance</head><p>Stoner and Freeman's research in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Priansa (2016)</ref> shows that job satisfaction shows a match between the expectations that arise with the rewards provided by the job, so job satisfaction is also related to performance. Job satisfaction is a set of feelings whether or not the job is fun. A person who works in an organization brings with him a set of wants, needs, desires, and past experiences that coalesce to form job expectations. Job satisfaction shows the match between one's expectations that arise and the rewards provided by the job <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Suhardan, 2014)</ref> .</p><p>These results are in accordance with research study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Knox (2014)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Rifqi, 2019)</ref> concluded that they both concluded that job satisfaction will affect performance. The results of this study also strengthen research study by Ibrahim (2019) and Hairina (2020) concluding that job satisfaction is a predictor of performance because job satisfaction has a moderate correlation with performance. Thus, it can be concluded that the level of teacher job satisfaction will affect performance.</p><p>According to Suhardan (2014) in his explanation, he stated that someone with a high level of job satisfaction shows a positive attitude towards the job, while someone who is dissatisfied with his job shows a negative attitude towards the work being done. Someone who experiences job satisfaction with the work done will produce maximum performance. The more fulfilled the aspects of job satisfaction, the higher the level of job satisfaction. Job satisfaction can be formed, one of which is the provision of salaries that are expected by teachers to meet their daily needs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Daryanto (2016)</ref> explains that teachers at work need satisfaction that supports interacting and collaborating with colleagues or work groups. The benefits of interaction between individuals in the workplace is that they can exchange information, experience, and most importantly, the social relations of co-workers can be harmoniously established so that teachers feel comfortable and happy, not feeling pressured and free to be able to realize themselves in showing their abilities. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Hasibuan (2014)</ref> someone in an organization needs to get satisfaction at work which can also have an impact on increasing performance, such as Priansa (2016) who states that job satisfaction causes increased performance, so satisfied workers will be more productive at work. F. There is an Indirect correlation between Principal's Instructional Leadership and Teacher Performance through Job Satisfaction Indirect correlation of principal's instructional leadership through job satisfaction with teacher performance, meaning that job satisfaction is able to function as a mediation/intervening of principal's instructional leadership and performance. The results of this study strengthen Bass' theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Aslamiah and Murdayanti, 2019)</ref> which states that the interaction between instructional leaders and subordinates is able to change the behavior of subordinates to feel capable and high satisfaction so that they strive to achieve higher and quality work performance. Furthermore, Bass said that creating job satisfaction by aligning the wishes of the leader with the wishes and needs of the teacher in achieving learning objectives, namely student achievement and this can only be done with instructional leadership. The results of this study also Strengthening the opinion of Tarter, Hoy &amp; Kottkamp <ref type="bibr">(Aslamiah, 2018</ref>) stated that given the importance of principal leadership on school achievement, a school principal must be able to encourage and create a conducive atmosphere, which allows teachers to work comfortably and calmly, full of intimacy and mutual respect. appreciate so that job satisfaction and high commitment to the organization grow, which will then affect performance. The same thing was also stated by Miner <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Erwanto, 2018</ref>) that the interaction between quality superiors and subordinates will have an impact such as job satisfaction, productivity and employee performance.</p><p>principal 's instructional leadership motivates teachers to develop professionalism so that teachers can improve the quality of learning. This is in accordance with the opinion from Daryanto (2016) stating that instructional leadership facilitates quality learning, so that students can increase their achievement, learning satisfaction, motivation, curiosity, creativity, innovation, and awareness to learn continuously throughout life, through learning activities of what the teacher does.</p><p>Teacher job happiness, performance productivity, and loyalty can all be improved with effective instructional leadership. Instructional leadership is the best leadership style because it allows an instructional leader to focus on the quality of his subordinates' ability, resulting in job satisfaction. According to the study's findings, one evidence that instructional leadership might improve Correlation Between Principal Instructional Leadership, Achievement Motivation and Teacher Performance through Job Satisfaction in State Elementary Schools in Kandangan District, Hulu Sungai Selatan Regency teacher satisfaction is the correlation between intimacy and closeness both between employees and with leadership, so that employees feel at ease at work and give inspiration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G. There is an indirect correlation between achievement motivation and teacher performance through job satisfaction</head><p>The results of the Sobel test showed that the mediating variable of job satisfaction is able to function as a mediation/intervening of the correlation between achievement motivation and teacher performance. This strengthens the opinion of <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Dessler (2015)</ref> explaining that teacher performance is the achievement of work results from what is expected, resulting from the ability of individual achievement motivation to achieve job satisfaction providing encouragement in doing the best effort. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Siagian (2013)</ref> suggests that high teacher achievement motivation will encourage teachers to be more productive to achieve a satisfaction that has an impact on achieving maximum performance. This is evidenced by research study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Verawati (2017)</ref> showing that work motivation and job satisfaction have a positive and significant effect on teacher performance, both partially and simultaneously. Thus, the performance of teachers can be improved through increased job satisfaction.</p><p>The realization of optimal performance cannot be separated from the achievement motivation of teachers and the fulfillment of job satisfaction in an organization. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Mangkunegara (2015)</ref>, teachers who have high achievement motivation are always responsible for success at work, have effectiveness in programs that have been prepared so that they can be completed briefly and produce satisfactory results, have the ability to make decisions and dare to take risks they face and complete it with satisfactory results. The teacher always tries to complete the tasks that have been chosen with satisfactory results because individuals who have high achievement motivation will exert all their abilities to excel.</p><p>Teachers who have high achievement motivation will feel high satisfaction if all of their desires can be achieved. This is in accordance with the opinion <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Susanto, 2018)</ref> which states that individuals with high achievement motivation desire to become prominent people who master certain fields, individuals always want to be better so they have the desire to master everything that can still include the abilities of the individual , Individuals will pursue maximum success to get satisfaction from doing something better and generate a level of satisfaction for themselves.</p><p>The results of this study Proving achievement motivation through job satisfaction is related to teacher performance, it can be seen from teachers being motivated in achieving achievements because teachers get comfortable conditions in the work environment, build good cooperation at work, conducive correlation patterns with school principals as well as comfortable interactions with teachers. other teacher co-workers create job satisfaction. This strengthens the opinion of McClellan in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Danim (2014)</ref> stating that in an organization, a person can have achievement motivation if in the organizational or company environment there is interaction between employees. This interaction can take place between an employee and other employees and also with leaders. Individual achievement motivation increases influenced by members who are in the company environment .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSION</head><p>Description of the principal instructional leadership, achievement motivation, job satisfaction, and teacher performance in the majority of primary schools in Kandangan district are in the high category. Principal instructional leadership has a correlation with teacher performance, principal instructional leadership has a correlation with job satisfaction, achievement motivation has a correlation with teacher performance, achievement motivation has a correlation with job satisfaction, job satisfaction has a correlation with teacher performance, principal instructional leadership has a correlation with teacher performance through job satisfaction and achievement motivation has a correlation with teacher performance through job satisfaction.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="3,103.30,108.50,417.00,222.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 . Descriptive Statistics of Research Variables</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Minimum Score</cell><cell cols="2">Maximum Score Mean</cell><cell>Category</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Principal Instructional Leadership 86.00</cell><cell>135.00</cell><cell>109.69</cell><cell>High</cell></row><row><cell>Achievement motivation</cell><cell>86.00</cell><cell>126.00</cell><cell>107.18</cell><cell>High</cell></row><row><cell>Job satisfaction</cell><cell>102.00</cell><cell>148.00</cell><cell>124.09</cell><cell>High</cell></row><row><cell>Teacher Performance</cell><cell>29,00</cell><cell>52.00</cell><cell>41.01</cell><cell>High</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 . Summary of Pathway Analysis Results</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Path Coefficient</cell><cell cols="2">Partial Test (T-Test) P-value T-value</cell><cell cols="2">Termination Test SE SR</cell></row><row><cell>Principal Instructional Leadership</cell><cell>0.374</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>6,909</cell><cell>25.36%</cell><cell>39.88%</cell></row></table><note><p>Substructural 1 The Correlation of Principal Instructional Leadership, Achievement Motivation, Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 . Summary of Direct Effect Hypothesis Test Results</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Hypothesis</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4 . Summary of Indirect Effect Hypothesis Test Results</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">Hypothesis</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Path Coefficient</cell><cell>Sobel Test</cell><cell>Decision</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Direct</cell><cell>Indirect</cell><cell>T-value</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">There is not any direct correlation between</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">H 6 :</cell><cell cols="4">principal instructional leadership and teacher</cell><cell>0.374</cell><cell>0.055</cell><cell>3,601</cell><cell>Accepted</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">performance through job satisfaction.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">There is not any direct correlation between</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H 7</cell><cell>:</cell><cell>achievement</cell><cell>motivation</cell><cell>and</cell><cell>teacher</cell><cell>0.428</cell><cell>0.038</cell><cell>2,429</cell><cell>Accepted</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">performance through job satisfaction</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Substructural 2 The correlation between Principal Instructional Leadership and Achievement Motivation with Job Satisfaction</figDesc><table><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Path Coefficient</cell><cell cols="2">Partial Test (T-Test) P-value T-value</cell><cell cols="2">Termination Test SE SR</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Principal Instructional Leadership 0.329</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>4,425</cell><cell>14.83%</cell><cell>61.70%</cell></row><row><cell>Achievement motivation</cell><cell>0.288</cell><cell>0.002</cell><cell>3.065</cell><cell>9.21%</cell><cell>38.30%</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Strategic Management in Improving the Quality of Education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Acep</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Suyanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Alphabet</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Theories of Educational Leadership and Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Meyer</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Age Publications</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>th Edition. th ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Natural</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://eprints.ulm.ac.id/5213/" />
		<title level="m">Principals, Teachers, Parents, and Community Leadership Strategies in Shaping Students&apos; Character</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The correlation between Principal Instructional Leadership, Professional Learning Community (PLC), and Motivation on Teaching Performance of Elementary School Teachers in East Banjarmasin District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Natural</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://eprints.ulm.ac.id/5225/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Peer Review: The correlation between Instructional Leadership Work Motivation and Job&apos;s Satisfaction with Teacher&apos;s Performance of Public Elementary School in South Banjarmasin District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Natural</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<pubPlace>Indonesia</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Peer Review: The correlation between Instructional Leadership and Work Motivation with Teacher&apos;s Performance of Public Elementary School in South Banjarmasin District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Aslamiah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Murdayanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Indonesia. Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Managing Human Resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Cascio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Leadership Motivation &amp; Group Effectiveness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Danim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Rineka Cipta</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Professional Educator. King Grafindo Persada</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Daryanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dessler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Human Resource Management. Salemba Four</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">the Influence of the Principal&apos;s Instructional Leadership Role, Achievement Motivation and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance in Elementary Schools in Pedes District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Destiana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Karawang Regency. Emba</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Effect of Instructional Leadership, Motivation and Job Satisfaction on Improving Teacher Performance at SMPN Tabanan District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Erwanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<pubPlace>Bali Tabanan University</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The correlation of emotional intelligence and work motivation through work Satisfactions on the performance of state vocational high school teachers in Banjarmasin city</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hairina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hallinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/15700760500244793</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/15700760500244793" />
		<title level="m">Instructional Leadership and the School Principal: A Passing Fancy that Refuses to Fade Away. Leadership and Policy in Schools</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Organization &amp; Motivation, Basic Productivity Improvement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hasibuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Earth Literature</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Influence of Principal Instructional Leadership, Achievement Motivation and Teacher Job Satisfaction on Teaching Performance of State Elementary School Teachers in Sukabumi City</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hidayat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Indonesian Education University</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Educational Administration: Theory, Research, and Practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Miskel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Student Library</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Influence of Principal Instructional Leadership, Commitment and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance at MTs Negeri Sumberlawang</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Abraham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<pubPlace>Sragen Regency</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Sunan Kalijaga State Islamic University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Influence of Instructional Leadership, Job Satisfaction, and Self-Efficacy on Teacher Performance at SMPN Pelaihari Tanah Laut District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Iresha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motivational Basis of Organizational Behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Behavioral Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Job Satisfaction and Teachers Performance An Emperical Study at Higher Learning Institution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Knox</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Contemporary Research in Business</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rasto</forename><surname>Koswara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Ethics and the Educational Profession . Ar-ruzz Media</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Company Human Resources Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mangkunegara</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PT Youth Rosda Karya Offest</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The correlation between Principal Instructional Leadership and Job Satisfaction with Teacher Performance on Student Learning Outcomes in Serang Regency Senior High School</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Margarita</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Islamic Education Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Become a Professional Teacher</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mulyasa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Becoming a Professional Teacher</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Become a Professional Principal</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mulyasa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Rosdakarya Youth</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Bandung</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Priansa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Service, Quality &amp; Satisfaction, Fourth Edition</title>
		<title level="s">CV. Andi Offset</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>th ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Achievement Motivation and Job Satisfaction on Organizational Citizenship Behavior of Civil Servants in Bappeprop East Java</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rifqi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Journal of Educational Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Robbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Organizational Behavior 11th edition</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Pearson Prentice Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>11 ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Motivation Theory and Its Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Siagian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Rineka Cipta</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Suhardan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Education Management. Alphabet</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">the Educational Profession &quot;Professional Teacher Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Suriansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Paradigms</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">47</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">correlation of Instructional Leadership, Organizational Climate and Teacher&apos;s Commitment to Job Satisfaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Suriansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Suhaimi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of K6 Education and Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">45</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Concept of Strategy and Implementation of Teacher Performance Improvement Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Susanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Prenamedia Group</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">the Influence of Instructional Leadership, Achievement Motivation, and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance and Primary School Student Achievement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Verawati</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The correlation between Principal Instructional Leadership and Achievement Motivation on Teacher Performance with Job Satisfaction as a mediator at State Vocational Schools in Indramayu Regency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wardana</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Teacher&apos;s Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">23</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Leadership, Work Motivation and Organizational Commitment on Job Satisfaction in Improving Teacher Performance at Tegal City State Junior High Schools</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Wardani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Teacher&apos;s Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">34</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">correlation of Instructional Leadership, Task Load, Achievement Motivation, and Teacher Job Satisfaction with Elementary School Teacher Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Yovitha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific Journal of Applied Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>There is an Open Access article, distributed under the term of the Creative Commons Attribution -Non Commercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0. which permits remixing, adapting and building upon the work for non-commercial use, provided the original work is properly cited</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
