<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Modelling the effect of continuous mixer operating parameters on mixture quality</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alexey</forename><surname>Kaliganov</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Penza State Agrarian University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>30 Botanicheskaya St.</addrLine>
									<postCode>440014</postCode>
									<settlement>Penza</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Vladimir</forename><surname>Konovalov</surname></persName>
							<email>konovalov-penza@rambler.ru</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Machine Building Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Penza State Technological University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1A/11</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alexey</forename><surname>Chupshev</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Penza State Agrarian University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>30 Botanicheskaya St.</addrLine>
									<postCode>440014</postCode>
									<settlement>Penza</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Vyacheslav</forename><surname>Teryushkov</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Penza State Agrarian University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>30 Botanicheskaya St.</addrLine>
									<postCode>440014</postCode>
									<settlement>Penza</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Proezd Baydukova / Gagarina St</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>440039</postCode>
									<settlement>Penza</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Modelling the effect of continuous mixer operating parameters on mixture quality</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1051/e3sconf</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T19:04+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The aim of the research was to obtain a regression model of the influence of some structural and kinematic parameters of a continuous mixer working element on the quality of the prepared mixture. The research methodology included the analysis of the design of the mixing unit and the identification of factors that could significantly affect the quality of the mixture. Later, on the basis of the experimental studies, the quality of the mixture at given values of factors was determined and a regression model was established. The developed functional diagram of a continuous mixing unit made it possible to establish factors that most intensively affected the quality of the prepared mixture. The obtained adequate regression model of the coefficient of variation of the content of the control component in the samples of the mixture indicated an improvement in the quality of the mixture with an increase in the frequency of rotation of the mixers and the number of the arms levels. In terms of quality indicators, a rotation frequency of about 1500 rpm was most preferable with a number of mixer levels of at least 5.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>In modern society, composites and mixtures are widely used in industry and construction. For the preparation of these mixtures, mixers of different designs and with different working elements are used. Drum mixers with a rotating container <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref> prepare mixtures with low energy consumption, but in this case it is problematic to achieve high uniformity of the mixture. Mixers with a screw working element <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">6]</ref> are more energyconsuming, but can produce better mixtures. High-speed and low-speed circulation mixers <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">8]</ref> are applicable for liquids, but problematic for bulk mixtures. Paddle-type mixers require more energy, but they evenly distribute the components throughout the volume of the mixture <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">10]</ref>.</p><p>Regardless of the design of the mixing device, the designers are trying to ensure high quality of the mixture with a short mixing time and low energy costs <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">13]</ref>. This is ensured by both the design and kinematic parameters of the mixers, and the technological conditions for their use. A significant effect is observed with multistage mixing of the components. The use of continuous mixing units significantly reduces the energy consumption of mixture formation, however, increases the requirements for accuracy and uniformity of component supply <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">13]</ref>.</p><p>The aim of the research was to obtain a regression model of the influence of some structural and kinematic parameters of a continuous mixer on the quality of the prepared mixture.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods and Materials</head><p>The research methodology included the analysis of the design of the mixing unit and the identification of factors that could significantly affect the quality of the mixture. Later, on the basis of the experimental studies, the quality of the mixture at given values of factors was determined and a regression model was established.</p><p>To improve the distribution of additional components in the dry mixture, multistage mixing of the components was used. Initially, as a result of the interaction of the sprayed streams of the feed components, a primary mixture is obtained, which is further mixed in the second main stage.</p><p>The mixing unit consists of two component feed systems (additive feeders), and a mixing system (Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>,2), the components feed systems into the hopper 1 for additives, under which a multicomponent drum (paddle) dispenser 2 with adjusting flaps 3 is placed. The dispenser paddles provide the supply of a specific additive with the required capacity and its continuous spray at the outlet of the dispenser opening. The feed system of the main component (mixture filler) consists of a hopper 8 with a spiral conveyor 7 mounted on the shaft 6. Radial beaters 5 with a net 4 are installed in the discharge zone. The mixing system includes a preliminary mixing chamber 9 and main mixing chamber 16. The operation of these devices in high-speed mode not only provides spraying of feeds, but also helps to increase the uniformity of the supply of the mixture components. Inside the main mixing chamber (in the mixer housing) there installed a shaft with several levels of paddle mixers 13 located on it and an unloading hole blocked by a gate valve 14.</p><p>During the experiments with the mixer, the rotational speed of the working body (n = 750; 1000; 1500 min -1 ) and the number of levels of six-blade mixers (Zr = 1; 3; 5 pcs.) located on the central vertical shaft were changed. The performance of the mixer corresponded to 1.6 kg/s with a bulk density of the mixture of 620 kg/m3. When these parameters changed, their influence on the mixture non-uniformity  was studied (coefficient of variation of the proportion of the control component in the samples, 0.01%). The proportion of the control component in the experiments was 8%. The experiments were repeated three times. The number of samples to determine the coefficient of variation was 20. The mass of one sample was 100 g. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">The Results of the Studies</head><p>The main evaluation criteria of the functional scheme of the proposed mixing unit are (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>): productivity (mass supply) of dispensers /Y0i-1, Y1i-1/, as well as of the mixing device as a summing value of all dispensers; the proportion of components in the mixture /Y21, Y31/ and the unevenness of mixing as a coefficient of variation /Y23, Y33/ for a component with a smaller fraction in the mixture in the first and second mixing stages.</p><p>Considering that the mixture can be used only if its quality is high, this indicator is the main one.</p><p>The analysis of the functional diagram showed that the parameters of the dispensers affect the formulation of the mixture, and the quality of the mixture is not significantly affected. The turbulence of mixing and the duration of exposure have a strong influence. In the abovementioned device, these effects are determined by the speed of rotation of the working unit and the number of levels of paddle mixers. The design parameters of the used mixers were substantiated in the works <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">14]</ref>.</p><p>An analysis of the correlation of these factors and the quality of the mixture showed the absence of a direct linear dependence (Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>). The studied independent factors did not correlate with each other. After processing the obtained experimental data on the quality of the mixture, the dependence of the non-uniformity of the mixture  (%) on the studied parameters was obtained (Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>): [-36.4•(-4.47+7.77•𝑍𝑟 -0.0334 +20.688•𝑛 -0.486 )] ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_0"> = 1 -𝑒</formula><p>(1) where Zr -the number of levels of paddle mixers , units; n -agitator speed, min -1 . At that, the Pearson correlation coefficient is R = 0.97378.   Comparing the calculated values of the regression model (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref>) with the experimental results, we can see their good accordance. The residues unaccounted by the model (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref>) are random in nature. An analysis of the graph of the obtained regression model (Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>) indicates an improvement in the quality of the mixture with an increase in both the frequency of rotation of the mixers and the number of levels of the paddles. In terms of quality indicators, the rotation frequency of about 1500 rpm is most preferable with the number of levels of the mixers of not less than 5. The indicated rotation frequency of the mixers corresponds to the frequency of rotation of the electric motors, which makes it possible to use coaxial arrangement of the shafts of the electric motor and the mixers. This reduces energy loss. However, additional studies are required to justify the working area of the mixing unit by the interval of the fraction of the smaller component in the mixture. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusion</head><p>The developed functional diagram of a continuous mixer made it possible to establish factors that most intensively affect the quality of the prepared mixture. The obtained adequate regression model of the coefficient of variation of the content of the control component in the samples of the mixture indicates an improvement in the quality of the mixture with an increase in the frequency of rotation of the mixers and the number of the levels of the paddles. In terms of quality indicators, the rotation speed of about 1500 rpm is most preferable with the number of levels of the mixers of not less than 5. Additional studies are required to justify the working area of the mixing unit by the interval of the fraction of the smaller component in the mixture.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .Figure 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 1.Structural and technological scheme of the mixing unit for supplying additives to dry feed: 1 and 8 -additives and filler hoppers; 2-drum (paddle) multisection dispenser (rotated); 3 -adjusting flap for supplying additives; 4 -discharge opening net of filler supply; 5 -beater with blades; 6feeder shaft; 7 -spiral conveyor; 9 -pre-mixing chamber; 10 -guide funnel; 11 -distribution cone; 12 -mixer shaft; 13 -mixer paddles; 14 -gate valve; 15 -unloading tray; 16 -mixer housing (main mixing chamber)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Functional diagram of a mixing unit for adding additives to bulk materials: 𝑃 𝑑 1 , 𝑃 𝑑 2 , 𝑃 𝑑 3 -bulk filler and additive feeders; D1, D2, D3, P1, P2, P3 -dispensers and sprayers of the corresponding components of the mixture; C, C1, C2 -a mixing system including a mixer of preliminary C1 and main C2 mixing; f1, f2, f3 -generalized statistical indicators characterizing the particle size distribution of the components of the mixture supplied to the dosing, their physical and mechanical properties; Xd1, Xd2, Xd3-generalized values of the internal factors of the components dosing devices; Хp1, Хp2, Хp3 -generalized values of the internal factors of the components spraying devices; Xc1, Xc2 -generalized values of the internal factors of the mixing devices of the preliminary and main mixing; Y0i-1, Y0i-2, Y0i-3 -productivity (mass supply) of the i-th component fed to mixing; deviation from the set flow rate; uneven feed; Y1i-1, Y1i-2, Y1i-3 -mass feed, flight path of the material flow, particle size distribution of particles, etc .; Y21, Y22, Y23, Y31, Y32, Y33the proportion of the component in the mixture, the deviation of the proportion of components from the recipe, the quality of the mixture (uneven mixing/coefficient of variation/) of the mixing devices of the preliminary and main mixing.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,97.75,274.73,302.14,230.05" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>E3S</head><label></label><figDesc>Web of Conferences 164, 08009 (2020) TPACEE-2019 https://doi.org/10.1051/e3sconf /202016408009</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .Figure 5 .</head><label>45</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Correlation of factors Zr (number of levels of mixers) and n (their rotation speed) on the coefficient of variation  of the content of the control component in the samples</figDesc><graphic coords="5,122.80,215.67,252.05,158.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. Compliance of the calculated values with the experimental data</figDesc><graphic coords="5,84.59,451.86,328.20,148.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. Distribution of residues unaccounted by the regression model.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,86.50,136.99,324.65,154.05" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design and Experimental Optimization of Combined-type Ration Mixer of Drum and Blade</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ping</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.6041/j.issn.1000-1298.2017.10.008</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nongye Jixie Xuebao Transactions of the Chinese Society for Agricultural Machinery</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">67</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rodionov Modeling and force analysis of drum devices based on the geometry of the material segment IOP Conf</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Teruchcov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cupschev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Konovalov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yu</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1088/1742-6596/1278/1/012012</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Series: Journal of Physics: Conf. Series 1278</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">12012</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Means to enhance operating efficiency of the means to enhance operating efficiency of the concrete mixer trucks with the purpose of highly-homogeneous concrete mix</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Emeljanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Anishchenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Dobrohodova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.14419/ijet.v7i3.2.14383</idno>
		<ptr target="https://DOI:10.14419/ijet.v7i3.2.14383" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Preparation Int. J. of Eng. and Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7/3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">102</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Evaluation of effect of paddle element stagger angle on the local velocity profiles in a twin-screw continuous mixer E3S Web of Conferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Vyakaranam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ashokan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kokini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1051/e3sconf/202016408009</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1051/e3sconf/202016408009" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">164</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2019</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">with viscous flow using Finite Element Method simulations</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2010.12.001</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2010.12.001" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Food Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="585" to="599" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel experimental setup for characterization of polymer blends in single-screw extruders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Celik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bonten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.5084809</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1063/1.5084809" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AIP Conference Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2055</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20008</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kearns Ingredient consideration, preparation of feeds, selection of extrusion equipment and automatic controls for extrusion of pet and aquatic feeds Int</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Symp. on Animal and Aquaculture Feedstuffs by Extrusion Technology/Int. Seminar on Advanced Extrusion Technology in Food Applications</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Sao Paulo, Brazil</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Habchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ghanem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lemenand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Della</forename><surname>Valle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Peerhossaini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cherd.2018.12.010</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cherd.2018.12.010" />
		<title level="m">Mixing performance in Split-And-Recombine Milli-Static Mixers -A numerical analysis Chemical Engineering Research and Design</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="298" to="306" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compact coiled flow inverter for process intensification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Soni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Meena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Roy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D P</forename><surname>Nigam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ces.2018.09.008</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ces.2018.09.008" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chemical Engineering Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">193</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="312" to="324" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mixing assessment of noncohesive particles in a paddle mixer through experiments and discrete element method (DEM)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Yaraghi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ebrahimi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ein-Mozaffari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lohi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.apt.2018.07.019</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apt.2018.07.019" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Advanced Powder Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2693" to="2706" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of impeller configurations on particle mixing in an agitated paddle mixer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ebrahimi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Yaraghi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ein-Mozaffari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lohi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.powtec.2018.03.061</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.powtec.2018.03.061" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Powder Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">332</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="158" to="170" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chupshev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Konovalov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fomina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1088/1742-6596/1084/1/012010</idno>
		<title level="m">Optimization in work modeling of a mixer IOP Conf. Series: Journal of Physics: Conference Series 1084 012010</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional model of energy consumption for mixing with a vertical paddle mixer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chupshev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Teryushkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Konovalov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mishanin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Novikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fomina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1088/1755-1315/403/1/012102</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IOP Conf. Series: Earth and Environmental Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">403</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12102</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimization of mixer parameters to minimize mixing energy consumption</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Chupshev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Konovalov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Petrova</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bulletin of Samara State Agricultural Academy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influence of blade diameter and number on mixture unevenness and mixing power consumption. Vestnik of federal state educational establishment of higher professional education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Chupshev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Konovalov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Teryushkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1051/e3sconf/202016408009</idno>
		<idno>TPACEE-2019</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1051/e3sconf/202016408009" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Moscow state agroengineering university named after V.P. Goryachkin</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008. 2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8009</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>E3S Web of Conferences</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
