<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Segmentation for Path Models and Unobserved Heterogeneity: The Finite Mixture Partial Least Squares Approach</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Prof</roleName><forename type="first">Geschäftsführender</forename><surname>Direktor</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department Wirtschaftswissenschaften Institut für Handel und Marketing Arbeitsbereich Marketing und Branding</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universität Hamburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Tor zur Welt der Wissenschaft Von-Melle-Park 5</addrLine>
									<postCode>20146</postCode>
									<settlement>Hamburg • www.henriksattler.de</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Henrik</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department Wirtschaftswissenschaften Institut für Handel und Marketing Arbeitsbereich Marketing und Branding</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universität Hamburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Tor zur Welt der Wissenschaft Von-Melle-Park 5</addrLine>
									<postCode>20146</postCode>
									<settlement>Hamburg • www.henriksattler.de</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Segmentation for Path Models and Unobserved Heterogeneity: The Finite Mixture Partial Least Squares Approach</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T18:54+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>segmentation</term>
					<term>latent variable models</term>
					<term>mixture models measurement</term>
					<term>customer satisfaction</term>
					<term>brand preference</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Partial least squares-based path modeling with latent variables is a methodology that allows to estimate complex cause-effect relationships using empirical data. The assumption that the data is collected from a single homogeneous population is often unrealistic. Identification of different groups of consumers in connection with estimates in the inner path model constitutes a critical issue for applying the path modeling methodology to form effective marketing strategies. Sequential clustering strategies often fail to provide useful results for segment-specific partial least squares analyses. For that reason, the purpose of this paper is fourfold. First, it presents a finite mixture path modeling methodology for separating data based on the heterogeneity of estimates in the inner path model, as it is implemented in a software application for statistical computation. This new approach permits reliable identification of distinctive customer segments with their characteristic estimates for relationships of latent variables in the structural model. Second, it presents an application of the approach to two numerical examples, using experimental and empirical data, as a means of verifying the methodology's usefulness for multigroup path analyses in marketing research. Third, it analyses the advantages of finite mixture partial least squares to a sequential clustering strategy. Fourth, the initial application and critical review of the new segmentation technique for partial least squares path modeling allows us to unveil and discuss some of the technique's problematic aspects and to address significant areas of future research.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Structural equation modeling (SEM) and path modeling with latent variables (LVP) are used to measure complex cause-effect relationships <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Fornell/Larcker 1981;</ref><ref type="bibr">Chin 1998a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Steenkamp/ Baumgartner 2000)</ref>. Such models are often applied in marketing to perform research on brand equity <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Yoo et al. 2000)</ref>, consumer behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Sargeant et al. 2006)</ref> or customer satisfaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Anderson/Sullivan 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Chun/Davies 2006)</ref>. Covariance-based structural equation modeling <ref type="bibr">(CBSEM, Jöreskog 1978</ref>) and partial least squares analysis <ref type="bibr">(PLS, Lohmöller 1989</ref>) constitute the two corresponding, yet distinctive <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Schneeweiß 1991)</ref>, statistical techniques for assessing causeeffect-relationship-models with latent variables. Compared to CBSEM, <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Wold's (1982)</ref> basic PLS design or basic method of soft modeling is rather a different than alternative methodology for estimating these models <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Fornell/Bookstein 1982)</ref>. Soft modeling refers to the ability of PLS to be more flexible in handling various modeling problems in situations where it is difficult or impossible to meet the hard assumptions of more traditional multivariate statistics. Within this context, "soft" is only attributed to distributional assumptions and not to the concepts, the models or the estimation techniques <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Lohmöller 1989</ref>). However, CBSEM is customarily used in marketing to estimate relationships in cause-effect models via latent variables and empirical data. Apparently, there has been little concern about the frequent inability of marketing data to meet methodological requirements or about the common occurrence of improper solutions <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Fornell/ Bookstein 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Baumgartner/Homburg 1996)</ref>. Representing a well-substantiated alternative to CBSEM, PLS is relatively unknown and rarely used in marketing research, which fails to appreciate its importance for estimating LVP in a variety of contexts, ranging from theoretical and applied research in marketing, management and other social sciences disciplines. Recognizable PLS-based LVP analyses in business research are presented by, for example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Fornell et al. (1985)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Fornell et al. (1990)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Fornell et al. (1996)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Gray/Meister (2004)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Venkatesh/Agarwal (2006)</ref>. Nevertheless, the statistical instruments needed to complement the PLS method for business research are not well developed. This paper addresses a key extension of PLS for segmenting data on the heterogeneity in inner path model estimates. We focus on customer satisfaction to identify and treat heterogeneity among consumers by segmentation as a means of presenting the benefits of the method for PLS path modeling in marketing research. Customer satisfaction has become a fundamental and well documented construct in marketing that is critical to demand and to any business's success given its importance and established relation to customer retention and corporate profitability <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Anderson et al. 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Mittal et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Morgan et al. 2005)</ref>. Although it is often acknowledged that truly homogeneous segments of consumers do not exist, recent studies report that unobserved customer heterogeneity does exists within a given product or service class <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Wu/Desarbo 2005)</ref>. This is critical for forming groups of consumers that are homogeneous in terms of the benefits they seek or their response to marketing programs (e.g. product offering, price discounts). Segmentation is therefore a key element for marketers in developing and improving their targeted marketing strategies.</p><p>Since its formal introduction in the 1950s, market segmentation remains one of the primary marketing ideas for product development, marketing strategy and understanding customers. However, the true distribution heterogeneity is never known a priori and, thus, there are cases where it is hard to find homogeneous customer segments. The development of analytic methods for segmenting markets has lagged behind their need in business applications <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Cohen/Ramaswamy 1998)</ref>. In SEM, for example, sequential clustering techniques, such as K-means or tree clustering, usually do not provide outcomes that further distinguish segment-specific estimates because they cannot account for heterogeneity of latent variables and their relationships within the structural model. We believe that latent segmentation models will assume an imperative role in enhancing CBSEM and PLS in the next wave of analytic procedures.</p><p>Latent class modeling <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Kamakura/Russell 1989</ref>) is a useful classification tools for uncovering groups of persons with similar preferences and sensitivities. In CBSEM, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Jedidi et al. (1997)</ref> pioneered this field of research and proposed the finite mixture SEM approach, i.e., a procedure that blends finite mixture models and the expectation-maximization (EM) algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(McLachlan/ Basford 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Wedel/Kamakura 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">McLachlan/Krishnan 2004)</ref>. Although the original technique extends CBSEM, and is implemented in software packages for statistical computations, e.g. Mplus <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Muthén/Muthén 1998)</ref>, it is inappropriate for PLS because of dissimilar methodological assumptions <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Fornell/Bookstein 1982)</ref>. For this reason, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hahn et al. (2002)</ref> introduced the finite mixture partial least squares (FIMIX-PLS) method that combines a finite mixture procedure with an EM-algorithm specifically coping with the ordinary least squares (OLS)-based predictions of PLS.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>: Analytical steps of FIMIX-PLS Building on the guiding articles by <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Jedidi et al. (1997)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hahn et al. (2002)</ref>, this paper presents FIMIX-PLS as it is implemented for the first time in a statistical software application and, thereby, is made broadly applicable for research in social sciences as primary approach for segmenting data based on PLS path modeling results. This research is important to expand the methodological toolbox in PLS. We systematically apply FIMIX-PLS, as depicted in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>, on the first numerical example presented in literature with experimental data and on the second application with empirical data. These kinds of segmentation results allow to further differentiate standard PLS path modeling estimates and, hence, to demonstrate the potentials of FIMIX-PLS for uncovering distinctive groups of customers for the relationships within the inner PLS path model. Furthermore, these analyses reveal important methodological implications that have not been addressed yet.</p><p>The following sections of this paper, which introduce the methodology, evaluate results and cover ex post analysis of FIMIX-PLS results, are dedicated to the different analytical steps presented in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>. We particularly focus on step two to show that FIMIX-PLS accurately identifies a priori created segments for the simulated data presented in section 4. In section 5, we employ a marketing related LVP example and empirical data to apply all four steps of FIMIX-PLS for identifying a key customer segment for shaping targeted marketing strategies. Finally, we address the issue of whether the new segmentation technique is advantageous for PLS path modeling compared with a sequential data analysis strategy (section 6). Before drawing our conclusions (section 8), we distinguish, in section 7, sets of problems and discuss the need for future research that emerges from our numerical examples and initial review of the FIMIX-PLS methodology.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Methodology</head><p>SmartPLS 2.0 <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Ringle et al. 2005)</ref> was the first statistical software application for (graphical) path modeling with latent variables employing both the basic PLS algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Wold 1982</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Wold , 1985;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Lohmöller 1989</ref>) as well as FIMIX-PLS capabilities for the kind of segmentation proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hahn et al. (2002)</ref>. This section concisely presents the new approach for segmentation as it is implemented into the statistical software application. In the first step of FIMIX-PLS (Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>), a path model is estimated by using the PLS algorithm for LVP and (empirical) data for manifest variables in the outer measurement models. The resulting scores for latent variables in the inner path model are then employed to run the FIMIX-PLS algorithm in a second methodological step (Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). The equation below expresses a modified presentation of the relationships (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">11</ref> in the appendix provides a description of all of the symbols used in the equations presented in this paper):</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">i i i ζ = ξ Γ + η Β</formula><p>(1) Segment-specific heterogeneity of path models is concentrated in the estimated relationships between latent variables. FIMIX-PLS captures this heterogeneity and calculates the probability of each observation so that it fits into each of the predetermined K numbers of classes. The seg- ment-specific distributional function is defined as follows, assuming that i η is distributed as a finite mixture of conditional multivariate normal densities</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">) ( f k | i ⋅ : ) , , B , | ( f ~k k k i i k | i k K 1 = k i Ψ Γ ξ η ρ η ∑ (2) Substituting ) , , B , | ( f k k k i i k | i Ψ Γ ξ η</formula><p>results in the following equation: <ref type="formula">4</ref>) represents an EM-formulation of the log-likelihood ( lnL ) as the objective function for maximization:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">⎥ ⎥ ⎦ ⎤ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ ⎡ ξ Γ + η Ψ ′ ξ Γ + η Ψ π ρ η - - ∑ )) B ( ) e | | 2 | B | ~i k i k 1 k i k i k B ( 2 1 k M k k K 1 = k i (3) Equation (</formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">) ( ln z )) , , B , | ( f ( ln z = lnL k ik k i k k k i i ik k i ρ + Ψ Γ ξ η ∑ ∑ ∑ ∑ (4)</formula><p>An EM-formulation of the FIMIX-PLS algorithm (figure Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>) is used for statistical computations to maximize the likelihood and to ensure convergence in this model. The expectation of Equation ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>) is calculated in the E-step, where ik z is 1 if subject i belongs to class k (or 0 otherwise). The segment size k ρ , the parameters i ξ , k B, k Γ and k Ψ of the conditional probability function are stated (as results of the M-step), and provisional estimates (expected values),</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">ik ik P = ) z ( E</formula><p>, for ik z are computed according to <ref type="bibr">Bayes' (1763</ref><ref type="bibr">Bayes' ( /1958) )</ref> theorem (E-step in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>).</p><p>-  <ref type="figure">------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref>Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>: The FIMIX-PLS algorithm Equation ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>) is maximized in the M-step (Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>). This part of the FIMIX-PLS algorithm accounts for the most important changes to fit the finite mixture approach to PLS compared with the original finite mixture structural equation modeling technique <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Jedidi et al. 1997)</ref>. Initially, new mixing proportions k ρ are calculated by the average of adjusted expected values ik P that result from the previous E-step. Thereafter, optimal parameters for k B , k Γ and k Ψ are determined by independent OLS regressions (one for each relationship between latent variables in the structural model). ML estimators of coefficients and variances are assumed to be identical to OLS predictions. The following equations are applied to obtain the regression parameters for latent endogenous variables:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">------------------------------------------------------------------------------------ // initial</formula><formula xml:id="formula_6">k I P = ik I 1 = i k ∀ ρ ∑ determine k B, k Γ , k Ψ , k ∀ calculate lnL current lnL lnL last current = - ∆ // the E-step starts here if S ≥ ∆ then begin k , i ) , , B , | ( f ) , , B , | ( f = P k k k i i k | i k K 1 = k k k k i i k | i k ik ∀ Ψ Γ ξ η ρ Ψ Γ ξ η ρ ∑ lnL lnL current = last end end until S &lt; ∆ -</formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">) N , E ( = X and = Y mi mi mi mi mi ′ η (5) ⎩ ⎨ ⎧ ∅ ∧ ≥ else m of regressor is ξ A 1,..., = a 1, A , } ξ ,..., {ξ = E m a m m m m A 1 mi (6) -5 - ⎩ ⎨ ⎧ ∅ ∧ ≥ else m of regressor is η B 1,..., = b 1, B }, η ,..., {η = N m b m m m m B 1 mi (7)</formula><p>The closed form OLS analytic formula for mk τ and mk ω is expressed as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">⎥ ⎦ ⎤ ⎢ ⎣ ⎡ ′ ⎥ ⎦ ⎤ ⎢ ⎣ ⎡ ′ ⎟ ⎠ ⎞ ⎜ ⎝ ⎛ β γ τ ∑ ∑ - ) Y X ( P ) X X ( P = ) mk ( ), mk ( = mi mi ik i 1 mi mi ik i m b m a mk (8) k mk mi mi mk mi mi ik i k mk I ) X Y )( X Y ( P = Ψ of m) (m cell = ρ ′ τ - τ - × ω ∑ (9)</formula><p>As a result, the M-step determines new mixing proportions k ρ , and the independent OLS regressions are used in the next E-step iteration to improve the outcomes for ik P . The EM-algorithm stops whenever lnL hardly improves, and an a priori specified convergence criterion is reached. This and other problematical issues linked to FIMIX-PLS are pointed out in the following sections and summarized in section 7.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Identifying an appropriate number of segments and ex post analysis</head><p>The most important FIMIX-PLS computational results are the probability ik P , the mixing proportions k ρ , class-specific estimates k B and k Γ for the inner relationships of the path model and k Ψ</p><p>for the regression variances. In particular, with regard to the finite mixture's probabilities ik P of observations to fit into the predetermined number classes, it must be decided if FIMIX-PLS allows to detect and treat heterogeneity among consumers in the inner PLS path model estimates by (unobservable) discrete moderating factors. This is explored in the next analytical step with analyses for different numbers of K classes (step 3 in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>).</p><p>The number of segments is usually unknown and the process of identifying an appropriate number of classes is not clear-cut when applying FIMIX-PLS. A statistically satisfactory solution for this analytical procedure does not exist for several reasons <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Wedel/Kamakura 2000)</ref>. One reason is that the mixture models are not asymptotically distributed as chi-squares and disallow the likelihood ratio statistic. Consequently, the FIMIX-PLS procedure must be repeatedly performed with consecutive numbers of latent classes K (e.g. 2 to 10 ). Another reason is that the algorithm (Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>) converges for any given number of K classes. This means that statistically noninterpretable outcomes for the class-specific estimates k B and k Γ of the inner path model relationships and for k Ψ of the regression variances for latent endogenous variables are computed when the number of classes is increased. Segment size is a useful indicator for stopping the analysis of additional numbers of latent classes for the sake of avoiding unreasonable FIMIX-PLS results is the segment size (section 5). At a certain point, an additional class has only a small segment size, which explains a marginal portion of heterogeneity in the overall set of data.</p><p>The emerging statistically comprehensible FIMIX-PLS estimates for different K numbers of classes are then compared for criteria such as the K lnL , the Akaike Information Criterion ( K AIC ), the AIC Controlled ( K AICC ) or the Bayesian Information Criterion ( K BIC ). These heuristic measures permit an evaluation of FIMIX-PLS computations and the quality of their -6 -segmentation. The main goal of this analysis is to capture the heterogeneity of the inner PLS path model grouping data in accordance with the FIMIX-PLS results. Within this context, the normed entropy statistic <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Ramaswamy et al. 1993</ref>) is a critical criterion for analyzing class specific FIMIX-PLS results. This criterion indicates the degree of separation for all observations and their estimated membership probabilities ik P on a case-by-case basis, and it subsequently reveals the most appropriate number of latent classes for segmentation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">) K ( Iln ) P ( ln P 1 = EN ik ik k i K ⎥ ⎦ ⎤ ⎢ ⎣ ⎡ - - ∑ ∑ (10)</formula><p>The EN is limited between 0 and 1, and the quality of separation of derived classes commensurate with the increase in K EN . Application of FIMIX-PLS furnishes evidence that values of EN above 0.5 result in estimates for ik P that permit unambiguous segmentation. The example with empirical data in section 5 demonstrates this kind of segmentation. In this case, most observations are associated with high probabilities of membership in a certain class. Hence, the entropy criterion is especially relevant for assessing whether a FIMIX-PLS solution is interpretable or not. The segments are fuzzy in situations where a certain number of classes is identified as most appropriate, based on the heuristic evaluation, but the K EN is considerably below 0.5 . This means that only parts of the subjects belong to a certain class. Fuzzy class memberships prevent meaningful a priori segmentation for specific PLS estimations, a comprehensible interpretation of results and sound establishment of managerial implications. Under such circumstances, and in cases where the differences between the evaluation criteria for FIMIX-PLS results of different numbers of classes only slightly differ, the highest probability per observation and its distribution regarding the entire set of data needs to be analyzed (section 5). The more that observations exhibit high membership probabilities, e.g. higher than 0.8 , the better they uniquely belong to a specific class and can be well separated.</p><p>An explanatory variable must be uncovered in the ex post analysis (step 4 in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>) in situations where FIMIX-PLS results indicate that heterogeneity in the overall set of data can be reduced by segmentation using the best fitting number of K classes. Correspondingly, data is segmented and used as new input for segment-specific LVP computations with PLS. This process produces differentiated PLS modeling results and facilitates multigroup PLS analyses <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Chin/ Dibbern 2006</ref>). An explanatory variable must include both similar grouping of data, as indicated by the FIMIX-PLS results, and interpretability of the distinctive clusters. This kind of analysis is essential for exploiting FIMIX-PLS findings for PLS path modeling, and it is the most challenging analytical step to accomplish. For this reason, an ex post analysis of the estimated FIMIX-PLS probabilities of membership employs an approach proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Ramaswamy et al. (1993)</ref>. While this systematical search uncovers explanatory variables that fit well with the FIMIX-PLS results in terms of data grouping, a logical search alternatively focuses for the most part on the interpretation of results. In this case, certain variables with high relevance for explaining the expected differences in segment-specific PLS path model computations are examined for their ability to form groups of observations that match FIMIX-PLS results. Both approaches may lead to different nonetheless reasonable results as demonstrated by a full FIMIX-PLS analysis in the example using empirical data (section 5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Numerical example using experimental data</head><p>Suppose that a market researcher has formulated a LVP on theoretically well developed causeeffect relationships. The researcher suspects, however, that an unobserved moderating factor accounts for heterogeneity or that the data belongs to a finite number of segments. In this instance, the theoretical assumptions can be used to identify a priori moderating factors that account for consumer heterogeneity in PLS path models. But this strategy is not feasible in many marketing applications <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Jedidi et al. 1997</ref>) and gives rise to analytical techniques like FIMIX-PLS. To demonstrate the potentials of FIMIX-PLS to detect and treat unobserved heterogeneity in the inner path model relationships, this methodology is applied on a numerical example using experimental data for the manifest indicator variables in the outer measurement model. Although the process of naming variables in this test set is not relevant, we use a marketing related example to demonstrate that FIMIX-PLS reliably identifies and separates distinctive groups of customers in the overall set of simulated data. In terms of heterogeneity in the structural model, it might be desirable to identify and describe price sensitive consumers <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Kim et al. 1999</ref>) and consumers who have the strongest preference for another particular product attribute <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Allenby et al. 1998</ref>), e.g. quality. Thus, the path model for our example with experimental data consists of one endogenous latent variable Satisfaction, two exogenous latent variables Price and Quality in the inner model <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Dillon et al. 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Desarbo et al. 2001</ref>). The used experimental set of data consist of the following equally sized segments:</p><p>• Price-oriented customers (segment 1): This segment is characterized by a strong relationship between Price and Satisfaction and a weak relationship between Quality and Satisfaction. estimates for path coefficients are at high levels. We follow the suggestion for a PLS model evaluation by <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chin (1998b)</ref>, and all minimum requirements for the outer and inner measurement model are met (Table <ref type="table">12</ref>, appendix). For example, the outer loadings are all above 0.7 while the inner model weights of Price and Quality on Satisfaction both have a value of 0.7 and therefore attain highly significant levels. This causes a substantial 2 R of 0.932 for the latent endogenous variable Satisfaction.</p><p>This kind of analysis determines the quality of PLS path model estimations by assessing outer and inner measurement models and, thus, partial model structures for certain non-parametric evaluation criteria that must satisfy minimum requirements <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Wold 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chin 1998b</ref>). Methodological implications of PLS path modeling <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Wold 1982</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Wold , 1985;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Lohmöller 1989</ref>), especially its distribution-free character, do not permit the application of parametric global goodness of fit measures that are used for CBSEM <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Jöreskog 1993)</ref>. As a substitute, <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Tenenhaus et al. (2005)</ref> propose the geometric mean of the average communality (outer model) and the average 2 R (inner model) that is limited between values of 0 and 1 as overall goodness of fit (GoF) measure for PLS:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">0.898 = 0.932 0.865 = R y communalit = GoF 2 ⋅ ⋅ (11)</formula><p>An interpretation of these PLS path modeling results -without testing for different segments in relation to heterogeneity in the estimates for the inner model -causes insufficient and misleading conclusions. In our example, Satisfaction could be comprehended as being explained by the Price and by the Quality construct for all customers, accompanied by recommendations that are adjusted accordingly for the marketing strategy <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Dillon et al. 1997)</ref>. By contrast, application of FIMIX-PLS uncovers heterogeneity and permits further differentiated conclusions. The consequences are demonstrated by applying FIMIX-PLS to 2 = K classes and the latent variable scores that emerge from the standard PLS procedure (step 2 in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). Since the customer segments for the underlying simulated data is known, testing different numbers of classes and comparing the results for FIMIX-PLS evaluation criteria is not required for this example. An analysis for an unknown number of K classes is presented in section 5.</p><p>The FIMIX-PLS results in Table <ref type="table">2</ref> show that both groups of consumers in the experimental set of data are identified. Segment 1 has a strong effect of Price on Satisfaction and indicates a week relationship between Quality and Satisfaction. Segment 2 has a strong effect of Quality on Satisfaction and indicates a week relationship between Price and Satisfaction. Cases 20 1-and cases 60 41-are perfectly assigned to segment 1, and cases 40 21-and cases 80 61-are perfectly assigned to segment 2 ( ik P has either a value of 0 or 1 for the final segmentation). Consequently, EN has a value of 1.0 indicating perfect separation of the two groups of observations. Price → Satisfaction Quality → Satisfaction Standard PLS 0.7 0.7 FIMIX-PLS segment 1 0.7 0.0 FIMIX-PLS segment 2 0.0 0.7 Table <ref type="table">2</ref>: Inner model weights In the above numerical example with simulated data, we do not perform step 3 of the full FIMIX-PLS analysis. Rather we test the FIMIX-PLS results for segment-specific PLS analyses according to step 4 in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>. Therefore, the full set of experimental data is divided into two sets of data regarding the probability of membership ik P of case i to class k . This data is separately used as input matrices for manifest variables to estimate the path model for each group of consumers with PLS. This final analytical step essentially achieves the FIMIX-PLS results for segment-specific relationships in the structural model. While the lower relationship in the inner path model for each group of price or quality oriented consumers remains at a value of 0.0 , the stronger relationship rises above 0.7 causing excellent levels in the values for 2 R of Satisfaction. As illustrated by this numerical example with simulated data, FIMIX-PLS is capable to identify and treat heterogeneity of inner path model estimates by segmentation. Subsequent group-specific PLS analyses are important for further differentiated path model estimates for heterogeneous groups of consumers in the overall set of observations to guide additional interpretations and specific recommendations for the targeted use of the marketing-mix instruments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Marketing example using empirical data</head><p>When researchers work with empirical data and do not have a priori segmentation assumptions to capture unobserved heterogeneity in the inner PLS path model relationships, FIMIX-PLS is often not as clear-cut as demonstrated in the foregoing example that is based on simulated data. Until now, research efforts to apply FIMIX-PLS and to assess its usefulness for expanding the methodological toolbox in marketing was restricted by the unavailability of a statistical software application for this kind of analysis. Since such functionalities are provided as presented in section 2, extensive use of FIMIX-PLS with empirical data in future research ought to furnish additional findings about the methodology and its applicability. For this reason, we make use of that technique for a marketing related path model and empirical data from Gruner+Jahr's 'Brigitte Communication Analysis 2002'.</p><p>Gruner+Jahr is one of the leading publishers of printed magazines in Germany. They have been conducting their Communication Analysis Survey every other year since 1984. In the survey, over 5,000 women answer numerous questions on brands in different product categories and questions regarding their personality. The women represent a cross section of the German female population. We choose answers to questions on the Benetton fashion brand name (on a four-point scale from 'low' to 'high') in order to use the survey as a marketing-related example of FIMIX-PLS-based customer segmentation. We assume that Benetton's aggressive and provocative advertising in the 1990s resulted in a lingering customer heterogeneity that is more distinctive and easier to identify compared with other fashion brands in the Communication Analysis Survey (e.g. Esprit or S.Oliver).</p><p>The scope of this paper does not include a presentation of a theoretically hypothesized LVP in the field of marketing and its PLS-based estimation by empirical means <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Bagozzi 1994)</ref>. Consequently, we do not provide an extensive presentation of the survey data or a discussion if one ought use CBSEM or PLS to estimate model parameters <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Bagozzi/Yi 1994)</ref> or if the measurement models of the latent variables should be operationalized as formative or reflective <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Diamantopoulos/Winklhofer 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Rossiter 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Jarvis et al. 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">MacKenzie et al. 2005)</ref>. Our goal is to demonstrate the applicability of FIMIX-PLS to empirical data and to illustrate a reduced cause-effect-relationship-model on branding <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Yoo et al. 2000)</ref> that principally guides all kinds of marketing-based LVP analyses that employ the new segmentation technique. The PLS path model for Benetton's brand preference consists of one latent endogenous Brand Preference variable, and two latent exogenous variables, i.e., Image and Person, in the inner model. All latent variables are operationalized via a reflective measurement model and the manifest variables from Gruner+Jahr's 'Brigitte Communication Analysis 2002'. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">3</ref> illustrates the path model that employs the latent and the particular manifest variables. The basic PLS algorithm Loh89 is applied to estimate LVP using the SmartPLS 2.0 software application (step 1 in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>).  As in section 4, we follow the suggestions of <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chin (1998b)</ref> for evaluating PLS estimates. An overview of the evaluation criteria for the results of PLS path modeling is provided in table Table <ref type="table">13</ref> in the appendix. All relationships in the reflective measurement models have factor loadings at sufficiently high levels (the smallest loading has a value of 0.795 ). Moreover, the average variance extracted (AVE) and c ρ exhibit satisfactory results. Both relationships in the inner path model are at statistically significant levels for explaining the latent endogenous variable (Table <ref type="table">13</ref> in the appendix provides results of the bootstrapping procedure). The latent exogenous Image variable (weight of 0.423 ) exhibits a strong relationship to the latent endogenous Brand Preference variable while the influence of the latent exogenous Person variable is considerably weaker (weight of 0.174 ). Thus, the 2 R of Brand Preference has a value of 0.239 , which is a moderate level for PLS path models. The average communality of the three reflective measurement models is relatively high, so that 2 R of the latent endogenous Brand Preference variable mainly causes a GoF outcome that only is at a moderate level:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">0.423 = 0.239 0.748 = R y communalit = GoF 2 ⋅ ⋅<label>(12)</label></formula><p>In the next analytical step, the FIMIX-PLS module of SmartPLS 2.0 is applied to customer segmentation based on the estimated scores for latent variables (step 2 in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). In this example, -11 -FIMIX-PLS results are computed for two classes. Thereafter, the number of K classes is successively increased. A comparison of the class-specific FIMIX-PLS computations for heuristic evaluation criteria (section 3), as presented in  <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hahn et al. (2002)</ref>. As illustrated in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref>, two thirds of all our observations are well assigned to one of the two classes with a probability ik P of more than 0.7 . These probabilities considerably decline for higher numbers of K classes, which indicates an increased fuzziness of segmentation that is also depicted by the lower EN. Consequently, a result of EN of 0.5 or higher for a certain number of FIMIX-PLS classes permits unambiguous segmentation of data.  classes). (b) Considering the decline of the outcomes for additional numbers of classes based on the EN criterion, it can be concluded that the overall set of observations for this particular analysis of the Benetton brand preference consists of a large, fuzzy group of female consumers and a small homogeneous group of female consumers. (c) The fuzziness of the larger segment cannot be further reduced by FIMIX-PLS. In the process of selecting additional classes, FIMIX-PLS can still identify the smaller group of consumers with comparable probabilities of membership, but is somehow ambivalent when processing the large group with heterogeneous observations. The additional classes are mainly created by splitting the larger segment. As a consequence the probability of membership ik P declines resulting in the drop of EN. This indicates methodological complexity in the process of assigning the observations in this set of data to additional classes. FIMIX-PLS computation forces observations to fit into a given number of K classes. As a result, FIMIX-PLS generates outcomes that are statistically problematical for the segmentspecific estimates k B and for k ). The variance is explained by the latent exogenous Image variable, with its weight of 0.343 , and the latent exogenous Person variable, with its weight of 0.177 . A smaller segment (size of 0.191 ) has a relatively high 2 R for Brand Preference (value of 0.930 ). The influence of the Person variable does not change much for this segment. However, the weight of the Image variable is more than twice as high and has a value of 0.759 . This result reveals that the preference for Benetton is explained to a high degree whenever the image of this brand is far more important than the individuals' personality. The next step of FIMIX-PLS involves identification of a certain variable to characterize the two uncovered customer segments. For this reason, we conducted an ex post analysis for finite mixture models according to the approach proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Ramaswamy et al. (1993)</ref>. We reviewed several potential explanatory variables. Our review analysis identifies: I am very interested in the latest fashion trends, I get information about current fashion from magazines for women Brand names are very important for sports wear and I like to buy fashion designers' perfumes as significant descriptors for segmentation (t-statistics ranging from 1.462 to 2.177 ). These variables may be appropriate for Benetton's brand preference PLS path model as a means of explaining the separation of female consumers in the underlying survey into two groups to account for heterogeneity in the inner model relationships. Table <ref type="table">7</ref> shows PLS results using the I like to buy fashion designers' perfumes variable for an a priori customer segmentation into two classes. Both outcomes for segment-specific LVP estimations (Table <ref type="table">13</ref> in the appendix) satisfy the relevant criteria for model evaluation <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Chin 1998b)</ref>. Segment 1 represents customers that are not interested in fashion designers' perfumes (size of 0.223 ). By contrast, segment 2 (size of 0.777 ) is characterized by female consumers that are attracted to Benetton and who would enjoy using Benetton products in other product categories, such as perfumes. From a marketing viewpoint, these customers are very important to fashion designers who want to plan brand extensions.  <ref type="table">7</ref>: A priori segmentation based on "I like to buy fashion designers' perfumes"</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">P 2 = K 3 = K 4 = K 5 = K 6 = K 1.</formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">1 = K 2 = K</formula><p>Besides their applicability to explaining the FIMIX-PLS segmentation for the structural model, the variables identified in the ex post analysis do not offer much potential for meaningful a priori segmentation, except for the I like to buy fashion designers' perfumes variable. The other three variables with high t-statistics do not result in different measurements for segment-specific path models when segmented a priori into two classes. We therefore consider reasonable alternatives and test the Customers' age variable for an a priori segmentation of Benetton's brand preference LVP. The ex post analysis of FIMIX-PLS results using the method of <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Ramaswamy et al. (1993)</ref> fails to furnish evidence for the relevance of this variable (t-statistic = 0.690 ). This fact reveals potential problems of this technique for PLS path modeling. Yet, when creating a customer segment for females over age 28 years (segment 1; segment size: 0.793 ) and for younger women (segment 2 ; segment size: 0.207 ), we do achieve a result (Table <ref type="table">8</ref>) that is nearly identical to the a priori segmentation using I like to buy fashion designers' perfumes. Evaluation of the PLS path modeling estimates <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Chin 1998b</ref>) for these two a priori segmented sets of data related to Customers' age confirms satisfactory results (Table <ref type="table">13</ref> in the appendix). In this case, another important marketing result is achieved by separating out Benetton's target segment of customers. Overall PLS path model estimates must provide satisfactory results <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Jedidi et al. (1997)</ref> whenever FIMIX-PLS is applied for additional analytic purposes. This rule applies to our numerical example with empirical data. FIMIX-PLS can be employed for guiding essential differentiations of overall PLS path model estimations by detecting and treating unobserved heterogeneity in the inner path model. According to the results of analyzing 2 = K classes, a smaller and a larger group of distinctive female consumers is identified for Benetton's brand preference. Two kinds of analytical results can be obtained from this FIMIX-PLS analysis:</p><p>• Identification of two homogeneous segments that both have improved results compared to the overall PLS path model estimates. This is the more common kind of result that one would expect from the example with simulated data in section 4. Distinction of one segment with improved results and another segment with estimates at comparable levels in terms of overall PLS model estimates. This is the more unusual kind of outcome that fits the example with empirical data presented in this section. • The larger segment tends to have a lower 2 R for the latent endogenous variable Brand Preference compared to overall model estimates. Most important, the larger segment is fuzzy and cannot be segmented into further numbers of classes. This group of customers is not the subject of supplementary findings. Thus, this group of customers is not the subject of supplementary findings and the analysis must focus on the smaller segment. According to the small changes of its segment size when additional numbers of K classes are analyzed as well as the results for EN, 2 R and probabilities ik P , this group of consumers is relative homogeneous and well separable.</p><p>The small segment exhibits a substantial relationship between Image and Brand Preference, and it is highly relevant from a marketing perspective. Regarding this group of female consumers, Brand Preference of Benetton is primarily explained by aspects that marketing activities can potentially control to create a specific Image. Characteristics of the individual Person that are more difficult to influence are not an issue for Benetton's brand preference in this segment of costumers. Furthermore, two kinds of explanatory variables are uncovered. The smaller group of consumers is accordingly characterized by females who would also like to buy Benetton's perfume or by younger female consumers. The process of forming these segments a priori and subsequently performing a specific PLS path analysis on them produces further differentiated results. In the example of Benetton's brand preference model, the PLS outcomes for the smaller group of customers are particularly significant for originating marketing strategies in terms of potential brand extensions or this brand's target group of customers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Comparison of FIMIX-PLS to sequential data analysis</head><p>The subject arises, when applying FIMIX-PLS, of whether similar results could be achieved with traditional clustering methods for manifest variable scores. K-means <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Wedel/Kamakura (2000)</ref> is one of the best clustering techniques for market segmentation. Parallel to reviewing analyses by <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Jedidi et al. (1997)</ref> or <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Hofstede et al. (1999)</ref>, we compare the effectiveness of FIMIX-PLS to a sequential data analysis strategy by performing a K-means cluster analysis of the observed variables followed by multigroup PLS path modeling. We ensure comparability with prior FIMIX-PLS findings by using K-means to split both manifest experimental data and empirical data into two clusters. We likewise cluster the latent variables scores of both previous LVP examples into two segments with K-means since FIMIX-PLS uses inner path model estimates. The clustering results are then used for an a priori segmentation of data and for computing their specific PLS path model (Table <ref type="table">9</ref> and<ref type="table">Table 10</ref>). group with lower (segment two) differences between the two weights in the structural model. However, these groups of customers are not as distinctive as they are in FIMIX-PLS segmentation. It is also important to note, regarding the numerical example with experimental data (section 4), that K-means clustering does not identify the two groups of price-and quality-oriented customers and their distinctive segment-specific path coefficients within the structural model.</p><p>The results of these kinds of comparisons show that FIMIX-PLS supplements traditional segmentation techniques as a useful methodology for further differentiating PLS-based LVP. Both techniques have much in common, i.e., the extraction of several homogeneous groups for achieving a more diverse and heterogeneous data set <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Cohen/Ramaswamy 1998)</ref>. FIMIX-PLS nevertheless consistently outperforms the sequential data analysis strategy <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Jedidi et al. 1997)</ref> for two main reasons:</p><p>• In contrast to deterministic classification with K-means, FIMIX-PLS uses a probabilistic classification method that accounts for different segment sizes <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Hofstede et al. 1999</ref>). • FIMIX-PLS differs from the data-driven traditional approach in terms of its simultaneous model-based segmentation and prediction. One regression equation for each segment captures the predictor-outcome relationship at the same time that the uncovered segments are captured, and this process accounts for heterogeneity in the inner path model. Cluster analysis, by contrast, is a descriptive methodology with no independent-dependent, predictor-outcome relationship <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Cohen/Ramaswamy 1998)</ref>.</p><p>K-means performs well in classifying observations but is poor in parameter recovery if data is separated well into a finite number of classes. K-Means performs poor in both classification and parameter recovery, if data is not well separated. In contrast, finite mixture performs well in all cases and provides useful diagnostic information <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Jedidi et al. 1997)</ref>. Distinctive groups of observations in the overall set of data cause heterogeneity in the estimates for the structural model. FIMIX-PLS, in comparison, provides superior results compared to sequential data analysis techniques whenever the researcher is interested in improved inner path model estimates for more homogeneous groups of observations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Methodological problems and fields of future research</head><p>The FIMIX-PLS approach is theoretically linked to finite mixture models. It shares methodological implications and problems. Incorporating this approach into statistical software and applying it, also reveals new problems that were not addressed prior to its initial introduction to social science research. Most important problems and fields of future research are connected to local optimum solutions, inappropriate FIMIX-PLS estimates and the identification of an explanatory variable in the ex post analysis.</p><p>Finite mixture models are subject to local optimum problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Jedidi et al. 1997)</ref>. The EMalgorithm always converges and monotonically increases lnL towards an optimum. The stop is more a measure of lack of progress than a measure of convergence, and there is evidence that the algorithm is often stopped too early <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Wedel/Kamakura 2000)</ref>. Experience shows that FIMIX-PLS frequently stops in local optimum solutions. This is caused by multimodality of the likelihood causing the algorithm's sensitivity to starting values. Moreover, the problem of convergence in local optima seems to increase in relevance whenever component densities are not well separated, the number of parameters estimated is large and the information embedded in each observation is limited. This results in relatively weak updates of membership probabilities in the E-step. Some examples of simple strategies for escaping local optima include beginning the EM-algorithm from a wide range of (random) starting values or using clustering procedures, such as K-means, to obtain an initial partition of data <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Wedel/Kamakura 2000)</ref>. If alternative initializations (starting values) of the algorithm result in different local optima, then the solution with the maximum value of likelihood is recommended as the best solution. Concerns still remain whether this kind of unsystematically selected solution reaches the global optimum. Future research is required to determine appropriate strategies for identifying convergence towards local optimum FIMIX-PLS solutions.</p><p>Another implication addresses the FIMIX-PLS segment-specific estimates for relationships in the structural model and the 2 R of latent endogenous variables. FIMIX-PLS is successively run with increasing numbers of classes to determine an appropriate number of segments. Ideally, the evaluation criteria should improve and then worsen while successively running the FIMIX-PLS procedure with increased numbers of classes. The outcome for the evaluation criteria indicates if an appropriate number of segments is identified. However, running this procedure often produces segment-specific FIMIX-PLS results that are improper for reasonable analyses. In most cases, the standardized weights in the structural model report values that are higher than one and/or the residual variance of latent endogenous variables exceeds the value of one (or becomes negative). Such outcomes might indicate that the heterogeneity in the structural model cannot be segmented by FIMIX-PLS for the chosen number of classes. These findings indicate the need for further improvement of this methodology. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hahn et al. (2002)</ref> suggest to limit segment-specific FIMIX-PLS estimates between reasonable bounds. Future research will need to determine if any such bounds for FIMIX-PLS computation impart useful methodological improvements in terms of identifying an appropriate number of segments.</p><p>The ex post analysis is essential for this kind of methodology. It confronts the researcher with the task that is most difficult to accomplish. This task involves identifying of an explanatory variable that permits a priori grouping of data for segment-specific PLS path modeling, which fits the FIMIX-PLS results and that also offers a characteristic interpretation of the formed groups. A technique for uncovering such variables proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Ramaswamy et al. (1993)</ref> does not imply coherent results for PLS path modeling, as demonstrated in the example with empirical data (section 5). Consequently, significant FIMIX-PLS analysis must be conducted, by means of complicated trial and error testing routines, until future research presents reliable procedures for identifying appropriate explanatory variables.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Summary and Conclusion</head><p>Unobserved heterogeneity and measurement errors are epidemic problems in social sciences. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Jedidi et al. (1997)</ref> have addressed these problems for SEM. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hahn et al. (2002)</ref> have further developed their finite-mixture SEM methodology for PLS path modeling, which represents an important alternative to CBSEM for researchers and practitioners. This paper introduces the FIMIX-PLS approach implemented for the first time into a statistical software application. We show that FIMIX-PLS is applicable for LVP with PLS in marketing, management and other social science fields. For example, marketing-related PLS path modeling can exploit this approach for response-based market segmentation by identifying certain groups of customers provided that unobserved moderating factors account for consumer heterogeneity within inner path model relationships. We demonstrate the potentials of FIMIX-PLS by presenting the first published numerical example ever that uses experimental data and the second published numerical example ever that uses empirical data. Our pioneering work in this field also involves comparing the results from our applications with a sequential data analysis strategy.</p><p>Our fist example application, which uses experimental data, shows how FIMIX-PLS identifies and separates two a priori created segments of price-and quality-oriented customers and our second example application, which is based on empirical data, involves a marketing-related path model for Benetton's brand preference. It also demonstrates that FIMIX-PLS reliably identifies an appropriate number of customer segments provided that distinctive groups of customers exist that result in heterogeneity within the inner model. In this case, FIMIX-PLS enables us to identify: (1) a large segment of female consumers that shows similar results when compared to the original model estimation and (2) a smaller segment of female customers that reveals a strong relationship between Image and Brand Preference. Furthermore, two kinds of explanatory variables for a priori segmentation are uncovered. The smaller group of consumers is characterized by females who would also like to buy Benetton's perfume or by younger female consumers. We accordingly conclude that FIMIX-PLS reliably identifies distinctive customer segments, if heterogeneity exists within the structural model. These kinds of findings result in segmentspecific LVP estimations and provide a platform for arriving at further conclusions for differentiated, segment-specific PLS path modeling. The additional analytic potentials are particularly relevant for LVP-based customer segmentation and multigroup path analyses in terms of forming effective marketing strategies.</p><p>FIMIX-PLS performs well in both numerical examples and provides useful diagnostic information. By contrast, a sequential data analysis technique does not offer results that are exploitable for segment-specific analyses. K-means clustering will classify observations whenever data is heterogeneous and belongs to well separated numbers of finite groups. However, recovery of distinctive estimates for inner path model relationships is not satisfactory (example using experimental data). In situations when heterogeneity is caused by groups that are not well separated groups, K-means performs poorly both in classification and segment-specific PLS path model estimation (example using empirical data). Given that researchers cannot determine segments a priori and are primarily interested in accurately identifying different segments regarding the model structure, the prudent strategy is therefore to use the finite mixture approach. However, this methodology does not identify outliers <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Jedidi et al. 1997)</ref>. Researchers can exploit the potentials of FIMIX-PLS when theory essentially supports the LVP and data is heterogeneous and belongs to a finite number of groups. We expect that these conditions will hold true in many marketing related PLS path modeling applications. For this reason, we presume reasonable segmentation and multigroup analyses (e.g. regarding different groups of customers) based on the FIMIX-PLS results. Future research will require extensive use of FIMIX-PLS on marketing examples, with typically heterogeneous data, to illustrate the applicability and the problematic aspects of FIMIX-PLS from a practical point of view. Researchers will also need to test FIMIX-PLS methodology based on simulated data, with a wide range of statistic distributions and a large variety of LVP, to gain additional implications. Finally, theoretical research should provide satisfactory improvements for problematic areas such as convergence to logical optimum solutions, computation of improper segment-specific FIMIX-PLS results and identification of suitable explanatory variables for a priori segmentation.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: The brand preference model</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>ik</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the K mixing proportions of the finite mixture k ρ mixing proportion of latent class k</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Table 3, reveals that the choice of two groups is appropriate for customer segmentation purposes. All relevant evaluation criteria considerably decrease in the ensuing numbers of classes. It is at a relatively high level compared to the EN of 0.43 arrived at in the only other proficient FIMIX-PLS segmentation presented thus far in literature by</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="5">Number of segments 2 = K 3 = K 4 = K 5 = K 6 = K</cell><cell>lnL 713.233 942.215 1053.389 ---1117.976 -1140.018 -</cell><cell>AIC 1448.466 1954.431 2192.793 2441.388 2326.037</cell><cell>BIC 1493.520 2097.784 2450.830 2846.874 2420.241</cell><cell>AICC 1493.545 2097.863 2450.972 2847.097 2420.293</cell><cell>EN 0.501 0.216 0.230 0.214 0.270</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Table 3: Model selection</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">The choice of two groups for a priori segmentation of the data is primarily supported by the EN</cell></row><row><cell>of 0.501 for</cell><cell>K</cell><cell>=</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>classes.</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Overview of observations' highest probability of assignment to a certain classTable5indicates additional kinds of assumptions regarding the number of classes and the kind of data heterogeneity in the inner PLS path model. (a) As the number of classes increases, the large sized class is mainly reduced to create additional segments, while the size of the smaller class</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.900 -0.800 -0.700 -0.600 -0.500 -0.400 -0.300 -0.200 -0.100 -0.000 -</cell><cell>000 0.900 0.800 0.700 0.600 0.500 0.400 0.300 0.200 0.100</cell><cell>0.491 0.063 0.083 0.128 0.234</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">0.250 0.320 0.387 0.043</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">0.002 0.011 0.761 0.225</cell><cell>0.002 0.011 0.306 0.221 0.227 0.232</cell><cell>0.339 0.232 0.369</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Sum</cell><cell>1.000</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">1.000</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">1.000</cell><cell>1.000</cell><cell>1.000</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">remains relatively stable (about 0.19 for</cell><cell>K</cell><cell>=</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>to</cell><cell>K</cell><cell>=</cell><cell>4</cell><cell cols="2">classes and about 0.145 for</cell><cell>K</cell><cell>=</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>and</cell></row><row><cell>K</cell><cell>=</cell><cell>6</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Γ , i.e., for the inner relationships of the path model, and for k Ψ , i.e., for the regression variances of latent endogenous variables. In this example, such results exhibiting inner path model relationships and/or regression variances above one are obtained for 7 = K classes. Consequently, the analysis of additional numbers of classes can stop at this juncture in accordance with development of segment sizes in Table5. Segment sizes for different numbers of classes Table6presents the FIMIX-PLS results for two latent classes. In a large segment (size of 0.809 ), the explained variance of the latent endogenous Brand Preference variable is at a relatively weak</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="9">Number of K classes Class 1 Class 2 Class 3 Class 4 Class 5 Class 6</cell><cell>Sum</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell cols="3">0.809</cell><cell>0.191</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.000</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell cols="3">0.525</cell><cell>0.288</cell><cell>0.188</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.000</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell cols="3">0.390</cell><cell>0.191</cell><cell>0.222</cell><cell>0.197</cell><cell></cell><cell>1.000</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell cols="3">0.487</cell><cell>0.256</cell><cell>0.149</cell><cell>0.092</cell><cell>0.017</cell><cell>1.000</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell cols="3">0.441</cell><cell>0.233</cell><cell>0.143</cell><cell>0.115</cell><cell>0.038</cell><cell>0.031</cell><cell>1.000</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">level for PLS path models (</cell><cell>R 2</cell><cell>=</cell><cell>0.108</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Disaggregate results (solution for two latent classes)</figDesc><table><row><cell>Segment size</cell><cell>0.809</cell><cell>0.191</cell></row><row><cell>2 R (of Brand Preference) Image → Brand Preference</cell><cell>0.108 0.343</cell><cell>0.930 0.759</cell></row><row><cell>Person → Brand Preference</cell><cell>0.177</cell><cell>0.170</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table 11 :</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Explanation of symbols</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Table 13: PLS path modeling results for the example with empirical data</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case</head><p>Price Quality Satisfaction 20 1-</p><p>We use the SmartPLS 2.0 <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Ringle et al. 2005</ref>) software application for the PLS path model estimation and the FIMIX-PLS analysis. The standard PLS procedure is executed with the overall set of simulated data for manifest variables as input to measure the LVP (step 1 in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). The above analysis of manifest variables for the example with experimental and empirical data produces estimated weights in the structural model where one relationship is higher than the other. Values for 2 R and GoF remain at levels comparable to PLS results for the full set of data. In contrast, K-means clustering of latent variable scores and segment-specific LVP computation with PLS provides very similar estimates for the two relationships in the inner path model. Although these weights only slightly differ for segment one and two of the experimental set of data, they are considerably lower for segment two compared to segment one in the example with empirical data. Employing K-means clustering results of latent variable scores might cause segment-specific inner path model weights at considerable levels. Nevertheless, 2 R and GoF are extremely low in the examples. These PLS estimates are subsequently not useful for additional segment-specific LVP interpretations and conclusions. Using traditional segmentation techniques such as K-means should be based on data for manifest variables. This will provide two equally sized groups for the empirical example, with each group having similar relationships in the inner path model compared to the original LVP estimation (section 5). In this instance, the weight is slightly higher for one path and somewhat lower for the other path in the structural model of segment one, while the opposite finding hold for segment two. This process will identify a group of customers with higher differences (segment one) and a</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PLS path model estimations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Papers on Marketing and Retailing -University of Hamburg</head><p>Im Zentrum der Reihe Research Papers on Marketing and Retailing (Hrsg.: Prof. Dr. Henrik Sattler) steht ein marktgerichtetes, wertorientiertes Management, z. B. zu folgenden Fragestellungen:</p><p>• Mit welchen Methoden kann ein monetärer Markenwert gemessen werden? • Wie können Markenstrategien im Handel bewertet werden?</p><p>• Wie soll der Handel gewinnoptimale Preise setzen?</p><p>• Wie können Konsumentenpräferenzen gemessen und in ein wertorientiertes Management integriert werden?</p><p>• Wie kann der Erfolg von Neuprodukten bestimmt werden?</p><p>• Welche Erlösmodelle sollen im eCommerce verfolgt werden?</p><p>The Research Papers on Marketing and Retailing (Ed.: Prof. Henrik Sattler) focus on market-orientated, valuebased management, e.g.:</p><p>• Which methods to be applied as a means of measuring brand equity </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the heterogeneity of demand</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Allenby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Arora</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ginter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="384" to="389" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Customer satisfaction, market share, and profitability: findings from Sweden</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Lehmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="66" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The antecedents and consequences of customer satisfaction for firms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Marketing Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Bagozzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Structural equation models in marketing research: basic principles, Blackwell</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Bagozzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Advanced topics in structural equation models</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Blackwell, Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Baumgartner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Homburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Applications of structural equation modeling in marketing and consumer research: a review</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="161" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Studies in the history of probability and statistics : IX. Thomas Bayes&apos;s essay towards solving a problem in the doctrine of chances ; Bayes&apos;s essay in modernized notation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="296" to="315" />
			<date type="published" when="1763">1763/1958</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Issues and opinion on structural equation modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Chin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MIS Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="VII" to="XVI" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The partial least squares approach to structural equation modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Chin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998b</date>
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Mahwah</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A permutation based procedure for multi-group PLS analysis: results of tests of differences on simulated data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Chin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dibbern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The influence of corporate character on customers and employees: exploring similarities and differences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Marketing Science Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="138" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Latent segmentation models: new tools assist researchers in market segmentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ramaswamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Customer value analysis in a heterogeneous market</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Desarbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Jedidi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sinha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Strategic Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="845" to="857" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Index construction with formative indicators: an alternative to scale development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Diamantopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Winklhofer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="269" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Good science: use structural equation models to decipher complex customer relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Dillon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Filak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two structural equation models: LISREL and PLS applied to consumer exit-voice theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bookstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="440" to="452" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jaesung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bryant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The American Customer Satisfaction Index: nature, purpose, and findings</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="18" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural equation models with unobservable variables and measurement error: algebra and statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Larcker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="328" to="388" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The cooperative venture formation process: A latent variable structural modeling approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lorange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Roos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1246" to="1255" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consumption experience and sales promotion expenditure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wernerfelt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1084" to="1105" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge sourcing effectiveness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Meister</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="821" to="834" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capturing customer heterogeneity using a finite mixture PLS approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Schmalenbach Business Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="243" to="269" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">International market segmentation based on consumer-product relations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Hofstede</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-B</forename><forename type="middle">E M</forename><surname>Steenkamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wedel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Jarvis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mackenzie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Podsakoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A critical review of construct indicators and measurement model misspecification in marketing and consumer research</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="218" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-fixture structural equation models for response-based segmentation and unobserved heterogeneity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Jedidi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jagpal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Desarbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Marketing Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Jöreskog</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Structural analysis of covariance and correlation matrices</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="477" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Jöreskog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Testing Structural Equation Models</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Sage, Newbury Park</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A probabilistic choice model for market segmentation and elasticity structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kamakura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Russell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="390" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying price sensitve consumers: the relative merits of domogrphic vs. purchase pattern information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B.-D</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Srinivasan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wilcox</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Retailing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Latent variable path modeling with partial least squares</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-B</forename><surname>Lohmöller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<publisher>Physica-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Heidelberg</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The problem of measurement model misspecification in behavioral and organizational research and some recommended solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mackenzie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Podsakoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Jarvis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="710" to="730" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mixture models: inference and applications to clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mclachlan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Basford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<publisher>Marcel Dekker</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mclachlan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Krishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The EM algorithm and extensions</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Chichester</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dual emphasis and the long-term financial impact of customer satisfaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Mittal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sayrak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tadikamalla</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Marketing Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="531" to="543" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding firms&apos; customer satisfaction information usage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Morgan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Mittal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="135" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Muthén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Muthén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Mplus user&apos;s guide</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Los Angeles</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Muthén &amp; Muthén</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An empirical pooling approach for estimating marketing mix elasticities with PIMS data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ramaswamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Desarbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Reibstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Marketing Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ringle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wende</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Will</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">SmartPLS 2.0 (beta), www.smartpls.de</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hamburg.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rossiter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The C-OAR-SE procedure for scale development in marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="335" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceptual determinants of nonprofit giving behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sargeant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="165" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Models with latent variables: LISREL versus PLS</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schneeweiß</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Statistica Neerlandica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the use of structural equation models for marketing modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-B</forename><surname>Steenkamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Baumgartner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Research in Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2/3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tenenhaus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Vinzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-M</forename><surname>Chatelin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lauro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">PLS path modeling, in: Computational Statistics &amp; Data Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="205" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Turning visitors into customers: a usability-centric perspective on purchase behavior in electronic channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Venkatesh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Agarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="367" to="382" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Market segmentation: conceptual and methodological foundations, 2nd ed</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wedel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kamakura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Model construction and evaluation when theoretical knowledge is scarce: theory and application of PLS</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Soft modeling: the basic design and some extensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
			<pubPlace>North-Holland, Amsterdam</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Partial least squares</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Market segmentation for customer satisfaction studies via a new latent structure multidimensional scaling model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Desarbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Applied Stochastic Models in Business and Industry</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="309" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An examination of selected marketing mix elements and brand equity, in: Academy of</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yoo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Donthu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Marketing Science Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="211" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ein empirischer Vergleich von Instrumenten zur Erhebung von Zahlungsbereitschaften</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nitschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-10">October 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Erfolgsfaktoren von Markentransfers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Völckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-03">March 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Appropriability of Product Innovations: An Empirical Analysis for Germany</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-05">May 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Wie robust sind Methoden zur Präferenzmessung?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hartmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-05">May 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Informal Cooperation in the US and Germany: Cooperative Managerial Capitalism vs. Competitive Managerial Capitalism in Interfirm Information Trading</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schrader</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lüthje</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-06">June 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hartmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Commercial Use of Conjoint Analysis in Germany, Austria, and Switzerland</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-08">August 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Evaluation of the Financial Value of Brands</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Högl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Hupp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-08">August 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Credibility of Product-Preannouncements: An International Empirical Comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Schirm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-09">September 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Methods for Measuring Consumers&apos; Willingness to Pay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Factors Affecting Consumer Evaluations of Brand Extensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Völckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-09">September 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Völckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Bestimmungsfaktoren des Markentransfererfolges. Eine Replikation der Studie von Zatloukal</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-09">2002. September 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Markentransferstrategien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-03">March 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Number of Tasks in Choice-Based Conjoint Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hartmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kröger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-12">December 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Wahrnehmung und Beurteilung von Markentransfers bei kurzlebigen Konsumgütern: Eine kausalanalytische Betrachtung</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Völckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-01">January 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Qualitative Marketingforschung. Überblick und Anbieterverzeichnis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hartmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Steffens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-02">February 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Empirical Generalizability of Consumer Evaluations of Brand Extensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Völckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-03">March 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Markentransfererfolgsanalysen bei kurzlebigen Konsumgütern unter Berücksichtigung von Konsumentenheterogenität</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Völckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-04">April 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Drivers of brand extension success: A structural equation modeling approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Völckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-04">April 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Separating Negative and Positive Effects of Price with Choice-Based Conjoint Analyses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Völckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-01">January 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Range Effects in Measuring Attribute Importance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gedenk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-04">April 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Determinanten der Informationsfunktion des Preises: Eine empirische Analyse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Völckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-01">January 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Rückwirkungen von Markentransfers auf die Muttermarke: eine empirische Auswertung von Fallbeispielen</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kaufmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kurt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-02">February 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Präferenzmessung bei unsicheren Produkteigenschaften: Berücksichtigung von Risiko in Conjoint-Analysen</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nitschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Völckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-03">March 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Empirical Generalizability of Consumer Evaluations of Brand Extensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Völckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-05">May 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Biases in Measuring Consumers&apos; Willingness to Pay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Völckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-05">May 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Präferenzstrukturen und Zahlungsbereitschaften für Online-Medieninhalte: Eine empirische Analyse am Beispiel von Online-Videoangeboten</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nitschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-06">June 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Markenbewertung: State of the Art</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-06">June 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Immaterielle Werte in der internen und externen Berichterstattung deutscher Unternehmen: Eine empirische Bestandsaufnahme</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Völckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Pirchegger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-06">June 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kaufmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Völckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Markenstrategische Optionen</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-09">September 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Methoden zur Messung von individuellen Zahlungsbereitschaften: Ein Überblick zum State-of-the-Art</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Völckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-10">October 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Dual Role of Price: Signaling and Sacrifice Effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Völckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Methoden zur Messung von Präferenzen für Innovationen</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sattler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006-02">February 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
