<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Causal Structure of Land Price Determinants</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Titus</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Awokuse</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Depr. of Food and Resource Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Delaware Newark</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>19716</postCode>
									<region>DE</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Joshua</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Duke</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Depr. of Food and Resource Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Delaware Newark</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>19716</postCode>
									<region>DE</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Causal Structure of Land Price Determinants</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T18:18+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Causality</term>
					<term>cointegration</term>
					<term>directed acyclic graphs</term>
					<term>land prices</term>
					<term>VAR</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper investigates causation contemporaneously and over time to elucidate the persistent lack of agreement about what "causes" changes in farmland prices. Using recently developed causal modeling framework of directed acyclic graphs (DAGs) and cointegrated (VAR) techniques, the assumed causal structures of existing structural and empirical models are tested directly. The results validate concerns about the nonstationarity of these series. Land price changes are found to respond to a small subset of the oft-cited causes of price change, including macroeconomic variables.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Causal Structure of Land Price Determinants</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Contradictions persist in the literature explaining the relative and absolute importance of the various causes of farmland price changes. In part, such disagreements can be attributedwithout necessarily citing methodological fault-to the idiosyncrasies of ad hoc modeling, fundamental differences between theoretical and data-driven approaches (i.e., structural versus empirical modeling), and the temporal or spatial differences in the data studied in empirical models. Within the last decade, however, two active strains in this research stand out for their inability to approach an externally (or even internally) recognized consensus.</p><p>The first strain sought to better understand the explanatory failures of the presentvalue model <ref type="bibr">(Johnson; Lloyd; Tegene and Kuchler; Hallam; Falk and Lee; Lence and Miller)</ref>, while the second offered improved structural models <ref type="bibr">(Just and Miranowski; Chavas and Thomas)</ref>. 1 These studies prompted others that use empirical models to question the robustness of the structural efforts <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Lence 2001</ref>) and the conclusions of the empirical efforts.</p><p>Thus, although the analysis of farmland price changes continues to be a vibrant area of study, greater clarity would improve the practical value of the results and more consistent structural and empirical modeling is an important first step toward achieving this clarity. The research presented in this paper comprehensively tests for causal structure of the determinants of fluctuations in farmland prices and thereby provides new insight on the appropriateness of many alternate modeling strategies.</p><p>The analysis of causal structure is not an entirely new area of research on land prices.</p><p>Several studies have considered causation with respect to price or price changes. <ref type="bibr">Falk and</ref> Lee argue that early structural models failed to predict well because of the inelasticity of supply made the simultaneous equations approach inappropriate. Not surprisingly, studies in the last 20 years all assume price is endogenous and few reflect on the possibility of simultaneous or reverse causation between price and quantity (or other variables). 2 The present paper tests for and cannot reject the endogeneity of price.</p><p>Several authors have also examined, or at least questioned, the relationships among independent variables. Specifically, potentially important explanations for the persistent controversy about the importance of various causal factors include: (1) non-spurious relationships among the independent variables; (2) correlations with omitted variables; and (3) the fit of land-price models with nonstationary price data. This paper examines these issues.</p><p>In addition, structural models differ in that they start by specifying most of the causal relationships among variables, while empirical studies often focus on a small set of explanatory variables. This paper will be the first to examine the joint consequences of these two sets of assumptions.</p><p>This study extends the literature and makes important contributions in several ways. First, it exploits the inherent causal information contained in the data to test for contemporaneous causation with the analysis of directed acyclic graphs (DAG), a recent and powerful modeling technique for analyzing contemporaneous causal structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Spirtes et al. 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">and</ref><ref type="bibr">Pearl 1995, 2000)</ref>. Although some authors have applied this methodology to economic issues <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Swanson and</ref><ref type="bibr">Granger, 1997, Bessler and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Akleman, 1998)</ref>, this study is the first to apply DAG to the causal structure of the key determinants of farmland prices.</p><p>Using data for the U.S. and three representative agricultural states (Iowa, Kansas, and Georgia)-substantially the same as used by Just and Miranowski-the analysis of DAGs rejects the contemporaneous causation by all of the commonly cited exogenous causes of land-price changes except a small subset of financial variables. The results suggest that land price changes are caused only by two macroeconomic variables: capital gains and real estate debt. Quantity variables are insignificant and, surprisingly, inflation and returns only indirectly affect land price changes. Results from the DAG and cointegrated vector autoregression (VAR) models suggest that the data warrant a simple model where macroeconomic variables cause land price changes. The collective results of these models thus simplify contemporaneous causal modeling and suggest that spurious correlations may indeed be a problem in the formulations of some existing models. The identified macroeconomic variables explain changes contemporaneously and over time, while many other determinants of farmland prices (conditioned on other variables) are found to have insignificant impact on farmland prices. The rest of the paper is organized as follows.</p><p>Section 2 provides a brief discussion of the commonly cited determinants of farmland price changes and describes the data (variables) used in analysis. Then, the third and fourth sections present the empirical methods and analysis of causation using DAG and cointegrated VAR models, respectively. The fifth section concludes the paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Determinants of Land Prices</head><p>Several papers have investigated the causal effects of various variables on the observed fluctuations in farmland prices. The commonly used "explanatory" variables can be grouped into these categories: measures of government programs, measures of net return to agriculture, measures of land quantity, and measures of financial (credit market constraints) and/or macroeconomic activity. <ref type="bibr">Gardner (2001)</ref> used cross-sectional, farm-level data to investigate the role of government programs in explaining changes in farmland prices and concluded that government payments have no significant impact on farmland prices in the past three decades. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Phipps (1984)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Melichar (1979)</ref> concluded in separate analyses that relative to measures of net return to agriculture, non-farm variables are not as important in explaining changes in farmland prices.</p><p>In contrast, others <ref type="bibr">(Alston; Burt; Hallam et al.; Just and Miranowski)</ref>  V(.) in Equations ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">1</ref>) and (2) contains the contemporaneous correlation (zero order) matrices for the thirteen variables, for the Unites States and Iowa, respectively. These zeroorder correlation matrices are used as the starting point in the analysis of causal structure inherent to the data. The order of the variables is given as listed above the matrix. As shown in equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">1</ref>), there is a relatively high unconditional correlation between land prices (LPRICES) and the other variables in the system. For example, the unconditional correlation between LPRICES and DEBT is 0.98 while the correlation between LPRICES and CAPGAINS is 0.73. Furthermore, consider the correlation matrix in equation ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>), the Iowa farmland data used in Just and Miranowski. All 12 explanatory variables have correlation coefficients in excess of 0.33 with price. Yet, they are also correlated with each other; only 16 of the 65 correlations are below 0.30 and, without AVTAX, PFDET, and CAPGAINS, all correlations exceed 0.30. Hence, there is a real need to consider all possible relationships among the variables and exclude certain associations in a systematic manner.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>LP ACRE NFARM REDET RETAX NETRg NETR INFL IREDET ISAV AVTAX PFDET CGAIN</head><p>(1) V(U.S.) = 0.5 0 0 0. 0. 0.9 1.0 1.00 0.98 1.00 0.98 1.00 1.00 0.98 1.00 1.00 1.00 0.88 0.90 0.90 0.90 1.00 0.67 0.71 0.71 0.71 0.60 1.00 5 .57 .57 57 46 6 0 0.98 1.00 1.00 1.00 0.90 0.71 0.57 1.00 0.95 0.94 0.94 0.94 0.83 0.71 0.60 0.95 1.00 0.58 0.52 0.52 0.53 0.54 0.46 0.49 0.54 0.66 1.00 0.44 0.41 0.41 0.41 0.41 0.59 0.63 0.42 0.45 0.43 1.00 0.90 0.95 0.95 0.95 0.82 0.75 0.59 0.94 0.88 0.44 0.40 1.00 0.73 0.60 0.60 0.61 0.53 0.32 0.31 0.60 0.61 0.53 0.44 0.44 1.00 Furthermore, high collinearity is observed among ACRE, NFARM, and DEBT. Both ACRE and NFARM are essentially measuring the same economic activity: quantity of land in agriculture. This initial inspection of the unconditional correlation matrix suggests that potential determinants of land prices are some measures or proxy for quantity of farmland, real estate debt, net cash rent, inflation rate, interest rate, and taxation. As DAG investigates the conditional correlation among these variables, one reasonably expects that some of the variables' effect on variability in farmland prices will cancel out each other.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>LP ACRE NFARM REDET RETAX NETRg NETR INFL IREDET ISAV AVTAX PFDET CGAIN</head><p>(2) V(Iowa) = 0 0.58 0.58 0.58 0.3 0 1.00 0 1.00 1.00 1.00 0.6 0 0.57 1.00</p><p>1.00 0.96 1.00 0.96 1.00 1.00 0.96 1.00 1.00 1.00 0.67 0.65 0.65 0.65 1.00 0.71 0.78 0.78 0.78 0.46 1.00 .53 1 .90 .96</p><p>5 .78 0.93 0.94 0.94 0.95 0.61 0.78 0.62 0.95 1.00 0.57 0.52 0.52 0.53 0.41 0.52 0.51 0.54 0.66 1.00 0.33 0.31 0.31 0.32 0.48 0.26 0.22 0.31 0.29 0.12 1.00 0.56 0.74 0.74 0.74 0.41 0.70 0.50 0.73 0.64 0.26 0.18 1.00 0.40 0.16 0.16 0.17 0.15 -0.02 0.01 0.16 0.21 0.28 0.21 -0.44 1.00</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analytical Framework and Methodological Issues</head><p>This section provides a brief discussion of the two methodological approaches adopted in this study for the analysis of the causal structure of the determinants of land prices. The conceptual framework for DAG is discussed first because it determines the contemporaneous causal relationship among the variables. Then, an abbreviated synopsis of the cointegrated VAR modeling techniques is offered, since this technique is more common in the literature than DAG.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Directed Acyclic Graphs (DAG) Theory</head><p>Structural models, such as Just and Miranowski's, often rely on prior economic theory as the source of their identifying restrictions for edge removal and assigning the direction of causal flow among the variables in the system. However, in some cases, this practice may itself be arbitrary, as theory may not always yield a clear identifying structure. The DAG bridges the gap between theory and practice by allowing theory to suggest which variables to initially include in the system. Then, the data-based DAG algorithm uses the inherent datagenerating process to help assign causal flow on observational (non-controlled) data.</p><p>The most commonly used definition of causality is that proposed by Granger, which exploits the asymmetry that a cause precedes its associated effect (and not vice versa).</p><p>Granger formally defined cause as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Y n is said to cause X n+1 if [P(X n+1 ∈ A| Ξ n )] ≠ [P(X n+1 ∈ A| Ξ n -Y n )],</formula><p>for some A, where X n and Y n are time ordered sets of variables defined for time = -∞, …, 0, 1…, n, and Ξ n is the set of non-redundant information available in time n. Alternatively, X Granger-causes Y, if a series Y is better predicted by its complete past information set than by that universe less the series X. More recently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Spirtes et al. (2000)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Pearl (1995</ref><ref type="bibr">Pearl ( , 2000) )</ref> describe DAGs-a non-time sequence asymmetry in causal relations as an alternative and more comprehensive approach for investigating causal relationships. This new approach can be used as an alternative (or complement to) Granger's time sequence asymmetry in causal systems.</p><p>A DAG is a picture representing the causal flow among a set of variables such that there are no directed cycles, i.e., it is not possible to start at a vertex and follow a directed path back to the same vertex. The vertices (nodes) of these graphs represent variables on which data has been obtained, and line segments connecting vertices (directed edges or arrows) are generated by calculations of conditional statistical dependence or independence among pairs of variables (ceteris paribus).</p><p>For the sake of illustration, we assume three economic variables, X, P, and Q. In the first scenario, we assume a causal relation such that X causes P and Q, depicted as: P X Q. The existence of a common cause in X implies that the unconditional correlation between P and Q is non-zero, but the conditional correlation between P and Q, given prior knowledge of the common cause X, is zero. This suggests that common causes screen off associations between their joint effects. In contrast, in the case of a second scenario where both X and Q cause P, depicted as X P Q, then the unconditional correlation between X and Q is zero.</p><p>However, the conditional association between X and Q, given the common effect P is not zero. This implies that common effects do not screen off association between their joint causes.</p><p>Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bessler and Yang (2003)</ref>, DAGs can be used to represent conditional independence as implied by the recursive product decomposition:</p><p>(3) Pr( , , , ... )</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">1 v 2 v 3 v n v ∏ = = n i i i pa v 1 ) | Pr(</formula><p>where Pr is the probability of vertices v , v , , ... and the realization of some subset of the variables that precede (come before in a causal sense) in order ( , , , ... ).</p><p>The concept of directional separation (d-separation) was first introduced by Pearl (1995) as a graphical representation of conditional independence. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Pearl (1995)</ref> showed that the conditional independence relations given by Equation (3) could be represented by dseparation. <ref type="bibr">Pearl's (2000)</ref> work on d-separation is significant because it shows the link between the causal graphs and the underlying probability distribution of the data generating process.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">1 2 3 v n v i pa i v 1 v 2 v 3 v n v</formula><p>In order to apply the concept of d-separation to observational data, <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Spirtes et al. (2000)</ref> developed an algorithm (PC algorithm) for building directed acyclic graphs. The PC algorithm is collection of commands that determines the causal direction among variables by using a stepwise testing approach to remove edges between variables. Edges among a set of N variables (e.g., residuals from a VAR), are removed sequentially based on zero correlation or partial correlation. PC algorithm and its more refined extensions are available as the software TETRAD II (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Scheines, et al. (1994)</ref>).</p><p>As in Awokuse and <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bessler (2003)</ref>, the Fisher's z statistic can be used to test estimated sample correlations and conditional correlations against zero. Fisher's z is expressed as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">(4)       - +       - - = |) | , (<label>1</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">| ) | , ( 1 | ln 3 | | 2 1 ) ), | , ( ( k j i k j i k n n k j i z ρ ρ ρ</formula><p>and n is the number of observations used to estimate the correlations, ρ( i,j|k) is the population correlation between series i and j conditional on series k (removing the influence of series k on each i and j), and |k| is the number of variables in k (that we condition on). If i, j and k are normally distributed and r( i,j|k) is the sample conditional correlation of i and j given k, then the distribution of z(ρ(i,j|k)n) -z(r(i,j|k)n) is standard normal.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cointegrated Vector Autoregression (VAR) Modeling</head><p>Since the cointegration and error correction methodology is fairly commonplace and welldocumented elsewhere <ref type="bibr">(Banerjee, et al.; Engle and Granger; Johansen; Johansen and Juselius)</ref>, only a brief overview is provided. The concept of cointegration is intuitively appealing because it is supported by the notion of long-run equilibrium in economic theory.</p><p>While variables in a system may fluctuate in the short run, they are expected to return to their steady state in the long run. Juselius' maximum likelihood (ML) procedure is a very popular alternative to the Engle-Granger method. The main attraction of this procedure is that it tests for the possibility of multiple cointegrating relationships among the variables. Johansen and Juselius modeled time series as reduced rank regression in which they computed the ML estimates in the multivariate cointegration model with Gaussian errors. The model is based on the error correction representation given by ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">t t i t p i i t X X X ε µ + Π + ∆ Γ + = ∆ - - - = ∑ 1 1 1</formula><p>where X t is an (nx1) column vector of p variables, µ is an (nx1) vector of constant terms, Γ and Π represent coefficient matrices, ∆ is a difference operator, k denotes the lag length, and ε t ~ N(0 , Σ ). The coefficient matrix Π is known as the impact matrix, and it contains information about the long-run relationships.</p><p>Equation ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) resembles a VAR model in first differences, except for the inclusion of the lagged level of X t-1 , an error correction term, which will contain information about the long run among variables in the vector X t . This way of specifying the system contains information on both the short-and long-run adjustment to changes in X t through the estimates of Γ and Π respectively. </p><formula xml:id="formula_6">β α ′ = Π</formula><p>In this representation β contains the coefficients of the r distinct long run cointegrating vectors that render t X ' β stationary, even though X t is itself non-stationary, and α contains the short run speed of adjustment coefficients for the equations in the system.</p><p>Johansen's methodology requires the estimation of the VAR Equation ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) and the residuals are then used to compute a likelihood ratio (LR) test statistic that can be used in the determination of the cointegrating vectors of X t . The trace test considers the hypothesis that the rank of Π is less than or equal to r cointegrating vectors, and it is expressed as: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Empirical Analysis and Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Unit Roots</head><p>An important question pertinent to time series data is whether the data series is stationary in levels or stationary after first differencing. If the data series are stationary after first differencing, then cointegration or error correction (ECM) models are needed to analyze the empirical relationships among the variables. Two univariate unit root tests were examined for each of the thirteen series. First, the augmented Dickey-Fuller (ADF) t-tests for the null of non-stationarity (unit roots). Due to the well-known low power of ADF tests, the KPSS test (proposed by <ref type="bibr">Kwiatkowski et al.)</ref> was also used to test for the null of stationarity. The combination of ADF and KPSS makes it possible to test for both the null of unit roots and that of stationarity. This approach is very robust in determining the presence of unit roots. Two time trend specifications of both tests were explored: (1) with constant only (without) linear time and (2) with linear time trend. Results for the ADF and KPSS tests are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</p><p>Overall, from the combination of the results from both the ADF and KPSS tests, the time series are found to be integrated at most of order one. This implies the possibility of cointegrating relationships among the variables.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Directed acyclic graphs (DAG) Results 4</head><p>Given the presence of unit roots in the undifferenced data, the TETRAD program, a DAG algorithm, was applied to the thirteen variables to remove edges between variables and directing causal flow of information between variables. The PC algorithm removes edges from the complete undirected graph by first checking for unconditional (zero order conditioning) and conditional correlations (first and second order conditioning) between pairs of variables. Edges connecting variables having zero correlation are removed. Remaining edges are then checked for first order partial correlation (correlation between two variables conditional on a third variable) equal to zero. Similarly, edges connecting variables having zero first order conditional correlation are removed. Edges that survive this check of first order conditional correlations are then checked against zero second order conditional correlation, etc.</p><p>As suggested by Spirtes et al, various levels of significance are considered in an attempt to achieve an unambiguous causal structure of the variables in contemporaneous time.</p><p>Figures <ref type="figure">2</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">3</ref> present graphs based on unconditional correlation matrices in equations ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">1</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) at the following nominal levels of significance: .10 and .20. As the TETRAD II search algorithm involves multiple hypotheses testing for edge removal, the final significance level is generally larger than that reported as nominal. Presenting results for alternative levels of significance allows one to assess quantitatively the robustness of the results with respect to significance levels. Regarding the significance levels and PC algorithm, <ref type="bibr">Spirtes, Glymour and Scheines (2000, p. 116)</ref> suggest that "in order for the method to converge to correct decisions with probability 1, the significance level used in making decisions should decrease as the sample size increases, and the use of higher significance levels (e.g. .2 at sample sizes less than 100, and .1 at sample sizes between 100 and 300) may improve performance at small sample sizes."</p><p>Since the sample size is limited to 35 observations , this paper presents the 20 percent significance level as the cut off for the removal of edges. 5 This implies that in order for the algorithm to not remove edges, the correlation and conditional correlation between two variables must be significantly different from zero at the 20 percent significance level. Figures <ref type="figure">2</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">3</ref> show that at the 10 percent significance levels the directed edges are represented by the arrows with dotted lines while for the 20 percent level, the edges are represented by solid lines. The resulting graphs are identical in most cases. Some of the edges were undirected <ref type="bibr">(ACRE and NFARM, and AVTAX and RETURN)</ref>. Since there is an undirected edge connecting these variables, there exists a relationship between them, but one cannot say which variable is causal.</p><p>Since the DAG results for both Iowa and the U.S. are very similar at both levels of significance, only the results for U.S. data in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>  Overall, at the 20 percent level of significance, the DAG results shows that land prices in the current time period respond directly to contemporaneous changes in the proportion of capital gains applied to taxable income and real estate debt. Land prices also change, indirectly, in response to same-period changes in a quantity measure-number of farms. A causal path from IRATE to LPRICES was marginally rejected at a 22 percent significance level. The conditional correlations of the other variables were not statistically significant.</p><p>These results are a marked departure from many of the structural models, which assumed a richer relationship among the theory-derived explanations of land price changes. Indeed, the DAG analysis suggests that land price models may be comparatively parsimonious. These results, however, do not suggest what variables explain the composition of land prices. Since these explanatory variables do not experience substantive, yearly changes, one would not expect that they explain historical changes in land prices.</p><p>Based on the DAG results, a smaller set of variables can be tested for causation over time. This is fortunate given the limited data available. Using these variables and prior knowledge from other studies' findings on the importance of inflation rate, subsequent analysis was performed on the following six variables: LPRICES, NFARM, INFLATION, IRATE, DEBT, and CAPGAINS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cointegrated VAR Test Results</head><p>Causal information given by DAG results can be used, first, to determine which of the thirteen variables to exclude from the system. Second, the DAG results are also used to assign causal flow for identifying the covariance matrix in a VAR model <ref type="bibr">(Bessler and Akelman)</ref>. As Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> shows, the six variables (LPRICES, NFARM, INFLATION, IRATE, to determine the order of the VAR suggest that the optimal lag length of two (which has white noise residuals). Subsequent analyses proceed with the use of VAR with lag length k=2. The relative impact of the other variables is considerably lower.</p><p>For completeness, Table <ref type="table">3</ref> also includes results for the remaining panels, which contain error decompositions for NFARM, INFLATION, IRATE, DEBT, and CAPGAINS, respectively. For example, in panel 2 the error decomposition for the returns to farming deflator <ref type="bibr">(RETURN)</ref> shows that in the short run, RETURN explains most of its on variation. This suggests that return to farming is exogenous in the very short run. The only other key determinant of returns to farming in this system is real estate debt (DEBT). In the last panel of Table <ref type="table">3</ref>, the error decomposition for CAPGAINS shows that it is clearly exogenous, explaining 100 percent of its own variation in the first year and up to 36 percent explained by own innovations in the long run. The overall conclusions from the variance decomposition results indicate that the following variables are key determinants of changes in farmland prices: land price expectations, the returns to farming, opportunity cost of capital, and capital gains tax variables. This finding is consistent with results from earlier studies by various researchers <ref type="bibr">(Alston; Burt; Castle and Hoch; Just and Miranowski)</ref>. The results also suggest that some commonly employed explanatory variables may not have substantively important effects on changes in land prices, over time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Concluding Remarks</head><p>Although the causal effects of various variables on the observed fluctuations in The results validate concerns about the nonstationarity of these series, which <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Lence (2001)</ref> argued was a shortcoming that undercut the analytical bite of the Just and Miranowski analysis. When causation is studied directly, one finds a much simpler modeling task. Land price changes appear to be sensitive to macroeconomic variables and the net return to farming. This implies that future structural and empirical models can focus more directly on a small set of variables without sacrificing analytical completeness.</p><p>The analyses also suggest what appears to be a new implication: some of the variables that affect land price changes might be beyond the scope of agricultural policy. Undoubtedly, this only holds given a continuation of the relatively stable institutional environment, which contributes a substantively important, stable value to agricultural land. Nevertheless, the policy importance of this result should not be underappreciated. If the welfare of farm firms derives from their role as commodity producers and investors in land, then agricultural policy seems mostly incognizant of the role of farmer as investor. Policy interventions that improve socially desirable outcomes vis-à-vis farm firms, but distort agricultural markets, may not be the cost effective. When farm-firm welfare derives in substantial measure from land price changes, which in turn are driven by the macroeconomy, it is important for policy makers to consider policies that mitigate downside risk in land markets. Given the sensitivity of DAG techniques to small sample data size, such as in this study, we recognize that the empirical results from this study must be tempered with caveats about the limitations of the methodology and the limited degrees of freedom available with use of annual time series land data. Future research efforts may address some of the methodological issues and investigate whether farmland relevant policies may have similar substantive effects on farm-firm welfare, but at lower social cost.    </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RETURNG</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>found that macroeconomic variables such as inflation, interest rates on debt, and measures of capital gains are important determinants of changes in land prices. Castle and Hoch identified a "real capital gains" component, which cause real price changes as land increases or decreases in value relative to general price levels. Castle and Hoch argued that the capitalization of real capital gains may explain up to 50 percent of fluctuations in land prices and that the landowner treats these gains as income, thus reinforcing the image of farmer-landowners participating simultaneously in land markets (as investor) and commodity markets (as suppliers). Since land can be regarded as a financial investment asset, Castle and Hoch and Hallam et al. also identified interest rates (opportunity cost of capital) and the real value of debt arising from general price level (inflation) as key determinants of changes in land prices. Just and Miranowski synthesized the literature by developing a theoretical framework that combines most of these variables in a single model of farmland changes. A priori, their model assumes that price is endogenous and excludes all other potential causal interactions except the unidirectional causation of the "explanatory" variables on price. Just and Miranowski concluded that macroeconomic variables are the dominant explanatory factors responsible for changes in farmland prices; although the assumed structural relationships are not without basis, it is valuable nonetheless to test these maintained hypotheses. To consider a contrasting model without any prior causal assumptions, consider Figure 1. Figure 1 would require data or theory to remove initial casual associations. Since economic theory does not always give clear and unambiguous direction on causal paths, it is reasonable to explore causal information contained in observed data with modeling techniques such as the DAG combined with cointegrated VAR analyses. This study follows the variable definitions and annual data sources 3 from 1963 to 1983 as outlined in Just and Miranowski and extended their data to cover the 1961 to 1995 period using the same (or similar) variables. These variables go well beyond farm-firm income and capture the various explanations for land price changes in the literature. Annual data were obtained for the U.S. and three representative agricultural states (Iowa, Kansas, and Georgia) for the following thirteen variables: land value per acre (LPRICES), acreage in farms (ACRE), number of farms (NFARM), real estate debt (DEBT), real estate tax rate (RETAX), net returns per acre to farming with government payments (RETURNG), net returns per acre to farming without government payments (RETURN), implicit GNP price deflator (INFLATION), average interest rate on farm real estate debt (IDEBT), interest rate on savings or interest rate on muni-bonds (IRATE), proportion of farmland financed by debt (PFDET), average tax rate (AVTAX), and the proportion of current land value attributable to capital gains (CAPGAINS). All data series, except interest rates, are in natural logarithms.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The error correction model (ECM) equation above allows for three model specifications: (a) If is of full rank, then X Π t is stationary in levels and a VAR in levels is an appropriate model; (b) If Π has zero rank, then it contains no long run information, and the appropriate model is a VAR in first differences (implies variables are not cointegrated); and (c) If the rank of Π is a positive number, r and is less than p (where p is the number of variables in the system), there exists matrices α and β , with dimensions (p x r), such that .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The distribution for this test is not given by the usual chi-squared distributions. The asymptotic critical values for the trace likelihood ratio tests are calculated via numerical simulations (see Johansen and Juselius; Osterwald-Lenum).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>are discussed in detail. Relative to the potential 12 edges into LPRICES in the undirected DAG in Figure 1, inspection of the graphs in Figures 2 and 3 reveals that only two edges into LPRICES remain: edges originating from CAPGAINS and DEBT. This implies that only two of these variables are direct and contemporaneous causes of changes in LPRICES. In addition to the two direct edges into LPRICES, there are also possibilities of indirect causes via the direct path from CAPGAINS and DEBT. The notable difference between DAG results for U.S. data (Figure 2) and that for Iowa (Figure 3) is the causal edge between INFLATION and IDEBT. The causal path observed from IDEBT to INFLATION for the U.S data is reversed for the case of Iowa. This may be due to the very small sample size or a reflection of the fundamental differences between in Iowa and U.S. aggregate data. Relative to results from previous studies emphasizing the role of other variables as determinants of land prices-inflation (in Feldstein; Falk and Lee; Just and Miranowski), net returns to farming (in Phipps; Falk and Lee; Lence and Miller), and interest rates (Alston and Burt)-of particular interest are the results that there are no edges remain between LPRICES and INFLATION, IRATE, and RETURN. Using the 20 percent level of significance the edge between LPRICES and INFLATION is not removed at zero order conditioning, as the correlation (0.962) has a p-value of 0.00. Although the edge connecting LPRICES and INFLATION survives an unconditional test (any test with a p-value greater than 0.2), this edge is removed at first order conditioning as the corr(LPRICES, INFLATION | DEBT) = -0.17, which has a p-value of 0.34 that is well above what is generally considered acceptable. Similarly, the edges connecting LPRICES and IRATE and the edges LPRICES and RETURN, though significant at zero order conditioning, these two edges were also removed at first order conditioning as the corr(LPRICES, IRATE | INFLATION) = 0.21 (p-value = 0.22), and corr(LPRICES, RETURN | DEBT) = -0.13 (p-value = 0.48), respectively. Similar results from the unconditional correlation test are true for the other variables. These outcomes explain why no direct edges exist between LPRICES and all other variables (except CAPGAIN and DEBT) in the system.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The rest of this section analyzes the dynamic effects of the structural innovations on each of the variables in the six-variable VAR model for both Iowa and U.S. data. The DAG results in Figures 2 and 3 are used to specify the causal path for the ordering of the Sims-Bernanke decomposition of contemporaneous innovations. Table 3 contains the forecast error variance decompositions (FEVD) associated with the VAR model for U.S. data under the ordering of innovations as suggested by the DAG given in Figure 2. FEVD is the contribution of each source of innovations to the variance of the n-period ahead forecast error for each endogenous variable for horizons 1 to 7 years. The first panel contains error decompositions for LPRICES. For U.S. data, the most significant determinant of the variation in LPRICES is the proportion of current land value attributable to capital gains (CAPGAINS). Within the first year, CAPGAINS explains 86.81 percent of the variability in LPRICES while in the long run (7 years later), 6 CAPGAINS still account for 27.88 percent of the variability in LPRICES. The other key determinant of variation in LPRICES in the U.S. data is interest rate on savings or interest rate on munibonds (IRATE). IRATE explains about 42.38 percent of the variability in LPRICES in the long run. The only other variable with notable contributions in the long run is real estate debt (DEBT), which account for up to 10.86 percent of the changes in LPRICES for the U.S. data.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Table4contains the FEVD associated with the VAR model for Iowa data under the ordering of innovations as generated by the DAG result given in Figure3. Between 10.41 and 24.10 percent of the variations in LPRICES is explained by own innovations. This implies that land price expectation is an important determinant of LPRICES. The results also reveal that CAPGAINS is an important determinant of the variation in LPRICES. In the first year, CAPGAINS explains 70.35 percent of the variability in LPRICES while in the long run (7 years later), CAPGAINS still account for about 29 percent of the variability in LPRICES. In the long run, the most significant determinant of LPRICES in Iowa is the interest rate on savings or interest rate on muni-bonds (IRATE). The innovation to IRATE explains about 37.54 percent of the variability in LPRICES in year 7. The third variable with significant contributions to variations in LPRICES is returns to farming (RETURN), which account for up to 14.63 percent of the changes in LPRICES for the Iowa data. The effect of implicit GNP price deflator (INFLATION) is relatively minimal at 2.62 percent at the 7-year horizon.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>farmland prices have been studied before, the results conflict and a lack of consensus persists about what "causes" changes in farmland prices. In order to unravel the causal relation between farmland prices and other variables, past analyses have either relied on static theorybased models or on other empirical models with ad hoc lagged relations. This paper extends previous investigations in this area by employing a combination of cointegrated VAR and directed acyclic graphs (DAG), a recently developed causal modeling technique. This study is the first to apply DAGs to help sort out the causal structure of the key determinants of farmland prices. DAG offers a powerful tool for analyzing the contemporaneous causal structure of farmland prices and its determinants. This paper used the same annual dataset (extended to cover the 1961 to 1995 period) and the same (or similar) thirteen variables definitions as outlined in Just and Miranowski. Annual data were obtained for the U.S. and three representative agricultural states (Iowa, Kansas, and Georgia), which allowed for the consideration of the main categories of variables often cited as determinants of farmland prices: measures of government programs, measures of net return to agriculture, measures of land quantity, and measures of financial (credit market constraints) and/or macroeconomic activity. DAGs investigated the contemporaneous causal relations among these variables while the cointegrated VAR model (variance decompositions) was used to sort out the lagged causal relationships. Both approaches yield similar results that confirm the importance of measures of net returns to farming, credit market constraints and/or macroeconomic activity as significant determinants of fluctuations in farmland prices.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Complete undirected graph on all thirteen variables.</figDesc><graphic coords="30,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>columns under the heading "ADF constant" refer to the Augmented Dickey-Fuller test with a drift while "ADF trend" contains a linear trend. a Reject the null hypothesis of unit roots for the ADF tests at the 5% significance level. b Reject the null hypothesis of stationarity for the Kwiatkowski, Phillips, Schmidt, and Shin (KPSS) tests at the 5% significance level. Critical values at the 5% level of significance for the ADF (with constant only) and ADF (with linear trend) are: -2.89 and -3.50 respectively. Critical values at the 5% level of significance for the KPSS (with constant only) and KPSS (with linear trend) are: 0.463 and 0.146 respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="2,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="3,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="4,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="5,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="6,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="8,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="9,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="10,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="11,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="12,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="13,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="16,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="18,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="19,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="20,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="24,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="25,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="26,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="27,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="28,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="29,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="31,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="32,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="34,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="35,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="36,153.00,243.00,306.00,306.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 . Tests for Unit Roots and Stationarity, 1961 -1995. United States Iowa State ADF ADF KPSS KPSS ADF ADF KPSS KPSS Variables constant trend constant trend constant trend constant trend</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>LPRICES</cell><cell>-2.061</cell><cell>-2.010</cell><cell>0.814 b 0.364 b -2.332</cell><cell>-2.242</cell><cell>0.360</cell><cell>0.328 b</cell></row><row><cell>ACRE</cell><cell>-1.226</cell><cell>-2.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 . Johansen Cointegration Test Results, 1961 -1995.</head><label>2</label><figDesc>: r denotes the number of cointegrating vectors for cointegration test with constant within and outside the cointegrating vectors. Johansen's cointegration test follow a sequential process for determination of the cointegration rank. We stop at the first r where we fail to reject the null hypothesis of r numbers of cointegrating vectors. The critical values for the trace tests are taken from Osterwald-Lenum). * denotes test statistics for test results with constant within the cointegrating vectors.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Critical values</cell><cell cols="2">United States</cell><cell>Iowa State</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Trace</cell><cell>Trace*</cell><cell>Trace</cell><cell>Trace*</cell></row><row><cell>r</cell><cell cols="3">C(5%) C(5%)* Statistics</cell><cell>Statistics</cell><cell>Statistics</cell><cell>Statistics</cell></row><row><cell>r=0</cell><cell>94.15</cell><cell>102.14</cell><cell>158.27 a</cell><cell>175.95 a</cell><cell>136.38 a</cell><cell>174.10 a</cell></row><row><cell>r≤1</cell><cell>68.52</cell><cell>76.07</cell><cell>106.42 a</cell><cell>119.91 a</cell><cell>82.74 a</cell><cell>109.40 a</cell></row><row><cell>r≤2</cell><cell>47.21</cell><cell>53.12</cell><cell>67.57 a</cell><cell>78.38 a</cell><cell>42.76 a</cell><cell>68.73 a</cell></row><row><cell>r≤3</cell><cell>29.68</cell><cell>34.91</cell><cell>41.81 a</cell><cell>44.13 a</cell><cell>26.63</cell><cell>34.21</cell></row><row><cell>r≤4</cell><cell>15.41</cell><cell>19.96</cell><cell>22.55 a</cell><cell>24.70 a</cell><cell>12.99</cell><cell>20.42</cell></row><row><cell>r≤5</cell><cell>3.76</cell><cell>9.24</cell><cell>9.30 a</cell><cell>11.31 a</cell><cell>5.50</cell><cell>7.30</cell></row></table><note><p>Notea Reject the null hypothesis of cointegration rank r at the 5% significance level.</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_0"><p>As shown in Figures2 and 3, even with only 35 observations, most of the edges that remain in the system are very similar at both the 10 and 20 percent significance level. This shows to some degree, the robustness of the edge removal process in the DAG PC algorithm.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_1"><p>The "long run" is arbitrarily set at</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="7" xml:id="foot_2"><p>years, since this is reasonably enough time for the effect of perturbations from various sources to have worked their way through the system.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>DEBT, and CAPGAINS) suggested by DAG are non-stationary in levels, but stationary in first differences. So, the cointegration relationship among the six variables is investigated. Following Johansen, tests are performed for both the number of cointegrating vectors and the placement of the constant in the error correction model. Table <ref type="table">2</ref> reports tests on the number of cointegrating vectors for both the constant in the cointegrating vector (*) and the constant outside of the cointegrating vector over 1961 to 1995. For the U.S. dataset, test results from both specifications indicate that there are six cointegrating vectors (full rank). As specified in earlier section, this implies that the appropriate model variant of equation ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) is the VAR in levels. For the Iowa dataset, test results from both specifications suggest the presence of three cointegrating vectors (reduced rank). Also, this implies that the appropriate model variant of equation ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) is the VAR in levels or an error correction model (ECM). As shown in <ref type="bibr">Sims, et al., if</ref> the time series are cointegrated, inference based on levels VAR is equivalent to that based on an error correction model (ECM). Throughout the remainder of this paper, the basic model of analysis is VAR in levels.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VAR-based Innovation Accounting</head><p>The six-variable levels VAR(k) variant of equation ( <ref type="formula">5</ref> Both the Schwartz's (1978) BIC and the <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hannan-Quinn (1979)</ref> HQ information criteria used Endnotes 1 A third major area of research activity centers on the effect of growth pressure. Since this paper focuses on agricultural land in Iowa, these studies are not reviewed.</p><p>2 Phipps' theoretical model considers and cannot reject the endogeneity of price.</p><p>3 For this kind of analysis, longer duration and higher frequency data series (monthly or quarterly) is usually more desirable for capturing the variability in the series over time.</p><p>However, data on farmland values at state and national levels are only available annually. So, we note the potential limitations due to data availability for achieving conclusive statistical results. 4 Although the empirical tests and analyses in this study were performed for three states (Iowa, Kansas, Georgia) and the U.S. aggregate data, to save space, only the empirical results for Iowa and the U.S. are reported. The results for the datasets from Kansas and Georgia, which are available from the authors, are very similar to those for Iowa.  </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Analysis of Growth of US Farmland Prices, 1963-82</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Alston</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Agricultural Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Co-Integration, Error Correction, and the Econometric Analysis of Non-stationary Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Banerjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dolado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Galbraith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hendry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alternative Explanations of the Money-Income Correlation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bernanke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Carnegie-Rochester Conference Series on Public Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Farm Prices, Retail Prices, and Directed Graphs: Results for Pork and Beef</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bessler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Akleman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Agricultural Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1144" to="1149" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Structure of Interdependence of International Stock Markets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bessler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. of International Money and Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="261" to="287" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Econometric Modelling of the Capitalization Formula for Farmland Prices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Burt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Agricultural Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Farm Real Estate Price Components</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Castle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hoch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Agricultural Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Dynamic Analysis of Land Prices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Chavas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Agricultural Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="772" to="784" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distribution of the Estimators for Autoregression Time Series with a Unit Root</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dickey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. of the Amer. Statistical Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="427" to="431" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Co-integration and Error Correction: Representation, Estimation, and Testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Engel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W J</forename><surname>Granger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="276" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fads versus Fundamentals in Farmland Prices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Falk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B.-S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Agricultural Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="696" to="707" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Department of Agricultural and Resource Economics Working Paper 02-02</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gardner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Maryland</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>U.S. Commodity Policies and Land Prices</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigating Causal Relation by Econometric Models and Cross-Spectral Methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W J</forename><surname>Granger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="424" to="438" />
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Co-integration Analysis and the Determinants of Land Prices: Reply</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hallam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Agricultural Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="159" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Co-integration Analysis and the Determinants of Land Prices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hallam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Machado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rapsomanikis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Agricultural Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The determination of the order of an autoregression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hannan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Quinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="195" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causality and Temporal Order in Macroeconomics or Why Even Economists Don&apos;t Know How to Get Causes from Probabilities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hoover</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British Journal of the Philosophy of Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="693" to="710" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation and Hypothesis Testing of Cointegration Vectors in Gaussian Vector Autoregressive Models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Johansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1551" to="1580" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maximum Likelihood and Inference on Cointegration with Applications to the Demand for Money</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Johansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Juselius</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oxford Bulletin of Economics and Statisitics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Farmland as a Business Asset</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Agricultural Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding Farmland Price</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Just</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Miranowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Changes American Journal of Agricultural Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="156" to="168" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Testing the Null Hypothesis of Stationarity Against the Alternative of a Unit Root</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kwiatkowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. of Econometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Farmland Prices in the Presence of Transaction Costs: A Cautionary Note</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lence</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Agricultural Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="985" to="992" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transaction Costs and the Present Value Model of Farmland: Iowa, 1900-1994</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lence</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Agricultural Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="272" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Testing a Present Value Model of Agricultural Land Values</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oxford Bulletin of Economics and Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="223" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capital Gains versus Current Income in the Farming Sector</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Melichar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Agricultural Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1085" to="1092" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Note With Quantiles of the Asymptotic Distribution of the Maximum Likelihood Cointegration Rank Test Statistics: Four Cases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Osterwald-Lenum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oxford Bulletin of Economics and Statisitics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="461" to="472" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causal Diagrams for Empirical Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="669" to="710" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>_____</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Causality</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Land Prices and Farm-Based Returns</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Phipps</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Agricultural Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="422" to="429" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Scheines</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Spirtes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Glymour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Meek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">TETRAD II: User&apos;s Manual and Software</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New Jersey</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating the dimension of a model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Schwarz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Statisitics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="461" to="464" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inference in linear time series models with unit roots</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sims</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Stock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="144" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Glymour and R. Scheines Causation, Prediction, and Search</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Spirtes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impulse Response Functions Based on a Causal Approach to Residual Orthogonalization in Vector Autoregressions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Swanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W J</forename><surname>Granger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="357" to="367" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Regression Test of the Present Value Model of U.S. Farmland Prices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tegene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Kuchler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Agricultural Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="1993-01">January 1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
