<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Environment determinants in business adoption of Cloud Computing</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Environment determinants in business adoption of Cloud Computing</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T23:28+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Adoption models</term>
					<term>Cloud Computing</term>
					<term>Environment</term>
					<term>Technology Providers</term>
					<term>Success Cases</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Purpose: This paper analyzes the influence of Technology Providers, Public Administrations and R&amp;D Institutions on Cloud Computing adoption. This research also considers Killer Applications and Success Cases as other environmental factors. Design/Methodology/Approach: Factorial analyses and structural equation models were used on a sample of High-Technology firms located in technological parks in Southern Europe, with more than 10 employees and sustained investments in R&amp;D. Findings: Results show that Technology Providers and Success Cases are determinant in Cloud Computing adoption. Moreover, Killer Applications are a forerunner for Success Cases. Originality/value: This study contributes to Cloud Computing adoption literature because it includes Technology Providers, Public Administrations and R&amp;D Institutions simultaneously as well as other variables as Killer</p><p>Applications and Success Cases. The importance of the external agents on IT adoption, especially when the technologies to be adopted are new and in an emergent stage, together with the lack of prior investigations focusing on specific environmental factors affecting the adoption of these new, emerging IT, justify the value of this research.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>In turbulent environments Information Technology (IT) combined with tangible and/or intangible resources, can be a powerful tool to attain competitive advantage <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Powell and Dent-Micallef, 1997)</ref>. A technological trend, named Cloud Computing, emerged to modify the use of information technology in a competitive way. In Cloud <ref type="bibr">Computing (Buyya et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Buyya et al., 2011)</ref>, resources are located in virtualized and distributed environments geographically disperse. They can be accessed on an ondemand basis through web-based technologies, combining Internet connectivity and pay per use systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Winans and Brown, 2009)</ref> in a new business model for IT provisioning <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Son, et al., 2014)</ref>.</p><p>The National Institute of Standards and Technology, US department of commerce defines Cloud Computing as (Mell and Grance, 2011): a model for enabling ubiquitous, convenient, on-demand network access to a shared pool of configurable computing resources (e.g., networks, servers, storage, applications, and services) that can be rapidly provisioned and released with minimal management effort or service provider interaction.</p><p>Public Administrations, R&amp;D Institutions and Technology Providers can arise as important environment factors in Cloud Computing adoption <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Arinze and Anandarajan, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Marston et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Kenji et al., 2011)</ref>, specially in the initial stages of their lifecycle <ref type="bibr">(Dos Santos and Pfeffers, 1998)</ref>. Other environmental factors that are acquiring particular relevance on IT adoption are Killer Applications and external Success Cases.</p><p>The former allows firms to visualize the great potential of a given technology. Success Cases can stimulate IT adoption because the firms can observe and understand the real benefits of its adoption <ref type="bibr">(Xu and Gutiérrez, 2006)</ref>.</p><p>Knowing the role of key environmental players on Cloud Computing adoption is a relevant issue. Throughout the company evolution of the IT towards the "cloud", firms should be able to manage their organization to adapt to a future dominated by the standardization of IT infrastructures and services <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Buyya et al., 2009)</ref>. Within this transition, companies will act depending on the role exerted by external agents such as technology providers, R&amp;D institutions and public administrations. The future behavior Environment determinants in business adoption of Cloud Computing of each of these agents will also be affected by their role on adoption itself <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Leydesdorff and Etzkowitz, 1996)</ref>. However, in spite of the relevance of this question for the business management of IT, we have not identified prior research with a focus on IT adoption using these three environmental forces simultaneously.</p><p>The aforementioned reasons (importance of external agents on IT adoption, when technologies are in emergent stage and the lack of prior investigations focusing on specific environmental factors) justify the value of this research. Thus, in this study the research problem will be focused on the role of environmental agents: Public Administrations, Technology Providers and R&amp;D Institutions in Cloud Computing adoption. This study also seeks to analyze the effect of other variables of the environment that might prove to be relevant to explain Cloud Computing adoption such as the existence and awareness of Killer Applications and Success Cases <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Low et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Lin and Chen, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Cegielski et al,. 2012</ref>). Interestingly, these latter variables have received very little attention on literature dealing with IT and particularly with Cloud Computing adoption <ref type="bibr">(Alshamalia et al., 2013)</ref>.</p><p>The rest of the paper is organized as follows: first, the theoretical background about IT adoption is presented. Next, research design, theoretical model and hypotheses are described, followed by the method and data analysis. Subsequently the results, their discussion and implications are presented. The research ends with main conclusions, limitations and suggestions for future research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theoretical Background</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IT adoption models in firms</head><p>Difussion of Innovation Theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Rogers and Shoemaker, 1971;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Rogers, 1962</ref>) -a pioneering work about IT adoption-, explained innovation adoption at the individual level in terms of the characteristics of the innovation. Various models have been used to study IT adoption in the field of the organization. An approach focusing on innovation diffusion at the organizational level <ref type="bibr">(Hovav et al. 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Dos Santos and Peffers, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Rogers, 1995)</ref> considers, in addition, the external influence arising in the environment.</p><p>Likewise, Contingent Models <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Premkumar et al., 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Tornatzky and Fleischer, 1990)</ref> explain adoption by referring to three groups of factors: (1) environmental; (2) organizational; and (3) innovation characteristics. There are also partial contingent models that focuses only on a group of factors.</p><p>Additional models have been used which stressed the modular nature of adoption, which might be split in different levels. Thus, <ref type="bibr">Nambisan and Wang (1999)</ref> propose different adoption levels for Web technologies: (1) Information access; (2) collaborative work and (3) business transaction kernell. <ref type="bibr">Teo and</ref><ref type="bibr">Pian (2003, 2004)</ref> provide five adoption levels of Web technologies: (1) level 0: e-mail;</p><p>(2) level 1:</p><p>Internet presence; (3) level 2: Prospecting; (4) level 3: Business integration and (5) level 4: Business transformation. In this paper we will use a modular model based on adoption levels to measure the evolution and use of Cloud Computing in the company.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IT adoption and environmental factors</head><p>Two mechanisms influence the adoption of a technology within a community (Dos Santos and Peffers, 1998): (1) external agents: e.g. public administrations, technology suppliers or research institutions; and (2) internal influence: when there is a sufficient critical mass <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Liao et al., 1999)</ref> of adopters, the positive network externalities <ref type="bibr">(Hovav et al., 2004)</ref> favor mechanisms of communication, learning and imitation between the members of the community, evident for example in the support of trading partners or customers who have already adopted the technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Premkumar et al., 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Soliman and Janz, 2004)</ref> or in the positive influence of the competition <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Thong, 1999)</ref>.</p><p>The influence of Public Administrations, Technology Providers and R&amp;D institutions on IT adoption have been considered in prior research <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Kuan and Chau, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Quaddus and Hofmeyer, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Salwani et al., 2009)</ref> but in a separated way. We have not found any prior piece of adoption research simultaneously analyzing the three environmental forces.</p><p>Other environmental factors have been considered in prior literature about IT adoption: competitors pressure; trading partners pressure and confidence in the business relationship <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Premkumar et al., 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Soliman and Janz, 2004)</ref>; business partners/clients support that already had implemented the technology and power-dependence relationship <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Premkumar et al., 1997)</ref>; positive network externalities <ref type="bibr">(Hovav et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Wang et al., 2005, Hsu and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Fang, 2005)</ref>; critical mass <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Liao et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">Dos Santos and Peffers, 1998)</ref> or turbulent environments <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Chau and Tam, 1997)</ref>.  <ref type="bibr">et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Nuseibeh, 2011)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research model and hypotheses</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>R&amp;D Institutions</head><p>Close collaboration between universities, firms and R&amp;D institutions can be usually related to the adoption of a particular business model or technological innovation <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Leydesdorff and Etzkowitz, 1996)</ref>. The link between R&amp;D institutions and business applications is usually supported by the creation of startups and spin-outs as a way to transfer scientific knowledge into ground-level, applied business realities.</p><p>Nowadays many firms closely cooperate with universities or R&amp;D centers and these institutions became R&amp;D departments of the firms. In the ground of GRID IT (the forerunner for Cloud Computing), CERN and its Large Hadron Collider (LHC) are acknowledged as one of the major landmarks for GRID utilization for scientific purposes. Likewise, many companies involved in the LHC Project have adopted GRID IT due to the influence of CERN. R&amp;D institutes are also cited as an important factor for dealing with firms' concerns about IT standardization, security and the interoperability of cloud solutions and to develop security standards, which jointly facilitates the Cloud Computing adoption (Low y Chen, 2012). Considering the above arguments:</p><p>H1: The higher the influence of R&amp;D Institutions over an organization, the higher the level of Cloud Computing adoption.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Technology Providers</head><p>Many small, innovative software developers and large computer manufacturers are active in GRID IT <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Maqueira et al., 2009)</ref> and Cloud Computing <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Velten and Janata, 2011)</ref>, and in its application in the business world <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Abdulaziz 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Marston et al., 2012)</ref>. This effect was already evident in the adoption of the Internet. Thus, firms like Cisco Systems raised awareness in many organizations about the strategic and competitive need to adapt Web technologies to their business strategies and value chain activities <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Chatterjee et al., 2002)</ref>. Private Technology Providers support could: (1) increase the number of organizations carrying out adoption through consortia;</p><p>(2) provoke an artificial crisis by withdrawing support for technologies based on previous standards;</p><p>(3) offer financial incentives to early adopters; and (4) develop transition technologies <ref type="bibr">(Hovav et al., 2004)</ref>.</p><p>Many large technology companies, led by Amazon, are building huge server farms to offer Cloud Computing with virtual applications and business software with selfservice interfaces so that customers can use resources when they want <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Chris, 2011)</ref>.</p><p>Furthermore, an increasing number of Cloud Computing technological providers are ready to attract companies to Cloud business models <ref type="bibr">(Marston et al., 2011)</ref>. Thus, key</p><p>Technology Providers (like Apache, EMC or Cisco) adapt their technologies to facilitate firms access to the Cloud. Established key players (as Google, IBM or Microsoft) and also innovators (as Amazom or Salesforce) exert and influence adoption through marketing action among potential customers and enablers (like CapGemini or RightScale). Furthermore, these companies closely cooperate with clients to offer products and services that use or are intimately related to Cloud computing adoption <ref type="bibr">(Marston et al., 2011)</ref>.</p><p>Furthermore, private support can become even more influential if the relationship between the customer firm and its technology provider is highly dependent <ref type="bibr">(Hsu et al., 2014)</ref>. Cloud Computing adoption will depend on the balance of bargaining power in the commercial relationship, and will be stronger when the supplier or customer with this adopted technology is key for the business of the other party that has not adopted the technology yet <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Premkumar et al., 1997)</ref>. The support for implementing and using cloud services made available by cloud services providers is likely to motivate enterprises to adopt Cloud Computing <ref type="bibr">(Alshamalia, et al., 2013)</ref>. Thus, the following hypothesis is proposed:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H2: The higher the influence of Technology Providers the higher the level of Cloud</head><p>Computing adoption.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Public Administrations</head><p>Public Administrations might have played a key role as drivers for many cloud based research and development projects <ref type="bibr">(Marston et al., 2011)</ref>, for example, in one of the most powerful GRID IT facilities in the world: the development of the EGEE infrastructure in Europe <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Maqueira and Bruque, 2007)</ref>. Recently, the governments of several countries are considering Cloud Computing potential as a way to upgrade the services offered to their citizens, specially within the tax administration service <ref type="bibr">(Navonil, 2010)</ref>. Some examples led by public administrations that also involved many private companies are the British G-Cloud, a part of the Digital Britain Plan; the United States' Apps. Gov, Japan's Kasumigaseki, the European Union's EuroCloud, and South Korea's governmental Cloud Computing plan <ref type="bibr">(Yang and Hsu, 2011)</ref>.</p><p>Public Administrations' role on technology adoption might be twofold. On the one hand, Public Administrations can be companies' clients or suppliers <ref type="bibr">(Janssen and Joha, 2011)</ref>. On the other hand, they can influence on companies with public subsides, technology promotion initiatives or by introducing legal changes favorable to IT adoption <ref type="bibr">(Hovav et al., 2004)</ref>. Public Administrations might establish, for instance, a common regulatory framework able to ensure an appropriate policy for data protection and security as well as to favor fair contractual relations between the parties (suppliers and clients of cloud services which commonly act in a globalized environment) <ref type="bibr">(Marston et al., 2011)</ref>. A wide emphasis on the importance of government regulations at the national and international levels and the lack of government regulations can hinder enterprises from adopting the cloud <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Lian et al. 2014)</ref>. These arguments lead to the following hypothesis:</p><p>H3: The higher the influence of Public Administration on a given organization the higher the level of Cloud Computing adoption.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Killer Applications</head><p>Killer Application is a service or application able to create value and that is quickly recognized and used by an increasing number of users <ref type="bibr">(Xu and Gutiérrez, 2006)</ref> and that is also an enabler or promoter of the use of related technologies. Thus, the email was a Killer Application for web technologies and SMS was a Killer Application for the use of mobile telephones <ref type="bibr">(Xu and Gutiérrez, 2006)</ref> Killer Applications might be closely related to the R&amp;D Institutions and Technology Providers. Killer Applications may act as triggers so that these two agents would be more motivated to attain quicker and deeper access to the technical foundations and knowledge underlying Cloud Computing as well as to Cloud-related know-how. The accumulated knowledge of R&amp;D Institutions may materialize in a higher likelihood of tight cooperation with companies which in turn may evolve towards higher levels of Cloud adoption. These arguments lead to the following hypotheses:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H5: The higher managers' awareness of Killer Applications based on Cloud</head><p>Computing, the higher the influence of R&amp;D institutions on Cloud Computing adoption.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H6: The higher managers' awareness of Killer Applications based on Cloud</head><p>Computing, the higher the influence of Technology Providers on Cloud Computing adoption.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Success Cases</head><p>Success Cases are specific and well defined applications able to solve a business problem in an efficient way. Unlike Killer Aplications, Success Cases are not very popular, and have not many users and, therefore, have a more limited application scope.</p><p>So, generally its use is restricted in a particular industry. Success Cases are intensively used by technology providers, who include them into their websites as a promotion instrument (Alshamaila and Papagiannidis, 2013). Thus, their potential clients can visualize the effects of the new technology. So, Technology Providers try to attract interest on their products/services, increasing their sales opportunities.</p><p>This can explain why adoption models have included Success Stories/Cases among the potential enablers of technology adoption <ref type="bibr">(Moore, 1995)</ref>. Furthermore, Success Cases in key industries can act on IT adoption in a bowling effect way: a given Success Case, through an increased, extended confidence, is able to create momentum, thus influencing many companies towards technology adoption so that adopters can cross the chasm which separates the area of early adoption, also called early market from the area of massive adoption in the first majority or principal market <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Rogers, 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr">Moore, 1991</ref><ref type="bibr">Moore, , 1995))</ref>. This thrust effect is usually assisted by a strong imitative effect <ref type="bibr">(DiMaggio and Powell, 1983)</ref>.</p><p>The European project BEINGRID (25 Cloud Computing/GRID IT success cases in different industries) tries to promote success cases in each industry, thus nurturing an imitative effect so that Cloud Computing/GRID IT could be massively adopted <ref type="bibr">(Dimitrakos et al., 2010)</ref>. IT cloud providers' demonstration of successful business cases and models are likely to increase Cloud Computing adoption rates <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Alshamaila and Papagiannidis, 2013)</ref>. Observing perceived benefits from using Cloud Computing can be an important motivation towards its adoption <ref type="bibr">(Low et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Lin and</ref><ref type="bibr">Chen, 2012, Cegielski et al. 2012)</ref>. Therefore, the following hypothesis is proposed:  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Methodology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sample and data collection</head><p>In 2013, 79 technological parks in Spain hosted 5,115 companies with an accumulated turnover of 21,256 million euro. These companies employed 136,218 workers, 23,138 of them were directly related to R&amp;D <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(APTE, 2013)</ref>. The population in this study comprises 1,330 high-technology firms located in technological parks in Spain with more than 10 employees and sustained investment in R&amp;D <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(APTE, 2013)</ref>.</p><p>A questionnaire was used to collect data. Final data gathering was carried out through a phone interview using a Computer Aided Telephone Interviewing (CATI) which ensured data had been collected randomly and that contributes to the sample representativeness <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Synodinos and Brennan, 1988)</ref>.</p><p>Informants were Chief Information Officer (CIO) or Chief Executive Officer (CEO). 281 valid questionnaires were gathered (21.13% response rate), which can be considered as an on-average or even higher response rate compared to works dealing with similar populations and research topics <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Chatterjee et al., 2002)</ref>.   <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">5</ref> shows results for the Exploratory Factor Analysis. Based on IT adoption research <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Premkumar, 2003)</ref>, the Composite Reliability Index (CRI) was used to test measures' reliability, with scores higher than 0.6 <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Bagozzi and Yi, 1988)</ref>. </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">------- KA --- --- --- ------- SC --- --- ---</formula><p>A Confirmatory Factor Analysis (CFA) was performed, using EQS 6.  <ref type="bibr">, 1998)</ref>. A structural equation model was developed (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>). We used EQS and the Robust, Maximum Likelihood Method because it is the most appropriate for non-normal settings <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Satorra, 2002)</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results, discussion and implications</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>The model yielded an overall good fit (Satorra-Bentler's scaled X 2 = 33.6067; g=19; X 2 /g =1.769, RMSEA=.052; NFI=.952; NNFI=.958; CFI=.978; IFI=.978; MFI=0.974) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>). Significant relationships (p&lt;.05) are those included in H2, H5, H6, H7, H8 and H10 whereas that hypotheses H1, H3, H4, H9 and H11 do not receive enough support.</p><p>Results show that the environmental factors that explain Cloud Computing better adoption are Technology Providers (H2) and Success Cases (H7). Conversely, neither Public Administrations nor R&amp;D Institutions exert a significant effect on adoption.</p><p>Furthermore, Technology Providers' influence is mediated by the managers' awareness of Killer Applications (H6) and Success Cases (H10) and R&amp;D Institutions' influence is mediated by the managers' awareness of Killer Applications (H5). Moreover, Success</p><p>Cases do not modify the effect of Public Administrations (H11) whereas of Killer Applications is a direct cause for Succes Cases (H8). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>Technology Providers are a key factor of Cloud Computing adoption. This result is also supported by research on other IT with a strong organizational nature such as ecommerce between companies (B2B) <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Quaddus and Hofmeyer, 2007)</ref> or innovative ITrelated services <ref type="bibr">(Frambach et al., 1998)</ref>.</p><p>Cloud Computing is creating a breakthrough in the market since it is shaping a new paradigm in the form of IT services that are commoditized and delivered in a similar way such as in traditional utilities like water, electricity, gas and telephony. This is the reason why Cloud Computing has been called the 5 th utility <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Buyya et al., 2009)</ref>.</p><p>Some reports <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Velten and Janata, 2011)</ref> highlight the role played by Technology Providers in the market of Cloud Computing and how companies like Google, Amazon, IBM, BT, HP, Fujitsu, Dell, T-Systems, Oracle or Vodafone are carrying out big investments and deploying huge infrastructures to compete and reach small and big companies through systems such as IaaS, PaaS and SaaS. Cloud Computing is being adopted quickly in the business arena (Arinze and Anandarajan, 2010; <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Low et al., 2011)</ref> for small, medium and large enterprises, in industries such as the Automotive, Aerospace, Financial Services, Logistics, Textile or Health <ref type="bibr">(Dimitrakos et al., 2010)</ref>.</p><p>With revolutionary effects on business <ref type="bibr">(Marston et al., 2011)</ref>, Cloud Computing is able to strengthen firm capabilities (Iyer and Henderson, 2010) and increase business value <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Abdulaziz, 2012)</ref>. Some Cloud Computing's benefits can be instant global platforms, elimination of hardware infrastructures and software licenses, reduced costs (Benlian and Hess, 2011), simplified scalability and the elimination or reduction of disaster recovery risks and its high costs (Tuncay, 2010).</p><p>Some reasons might explain the key role played by Technology Providers. Small companies can benefit from services provided by a cloud provider because they do not have the necessary budget and knowledge to build and maintain their own infrastructure. Large providers own scalable resources and a professionally operated infrastructure which small companies cannot afford <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Repschlaeger et al., 2013)</ref>. Cloud adoption by SMEs depends on how the cloud providers build trust through their cloud services, fostering sharing and collaboration via cloud tools <ref type="bibr">(Gupta et al., 2013)</ref>.</p><p>Medium and large firms are looking for not just technological suppliers but for actual technological partners able to provide support and valuable know-how. Thus, many firms rely on strong ties with trading partners for their IT design, implementation and operations tasks (Pan and Jang, 2008). IT providers have been able to accumulate and nurture knowledge on the factors that allows us to understand complexity related to Cloud Computing. This accumulated knowledge on the elements that disentangle Cloud complexity would be boosting adoption of hybrid clouds. Hybrid clouds have been created by IT providers to transform the company's infrastructure into private clouds that coexist and are eventually integrated within public clouds. These public clouds are also offered by a reduced number of IT providers. Likewise, clients would be able to take advantage of an appropriate fit between IT itself and the remaining bundle of complementary resources within the organization. Our results show that Technology Providers have succeeded in performing this twofold role (partner and supplier).</p><p>However, Public Administration and R&amp;D Institutions have failed in this role in light of our results. This conclusion is also supported by literature; trading partners was just the factor with a stronger influence in Cloud Computing adoption <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Low et al., 2011)</ref>.</p><p>Furthermore, <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Quaddus and Hofmeyer (2007)</ref>   <ref type="bibr">et al., 2003)</ref>. Sustained observation of incumbent providers will help managers to choose and select the ones who are more capable of providing this technology in an efficient way. Likewise, managers would be able to build up an appropriate fit between the tools and resources provided by suppliers and their internal resources to create sustained competitive advantages. Technology providers with respect to their key role on adoption as well as the increasing complexity in the IT market, should be therefore chosen according to their willingness to cooperate and their ability to provide complementary capabilities to the firm. Furthermore, managers should create the adequate environment so that firms can carry out a sustained exercise of technological surveillance that, aside from classifying and evaluating technology providers, can identify Success Cases relevant to Cloud Computing adoption. Thus, firms could implement "technological benchmarking" to seize and apply the lessons learned outside the tasks that make up the business value chain. These implications are tightly related to the adoption scale we used (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref>). Success cases would be encouraging companies to venture in the world of Cloud Computing through experimental, departmental or inter-departmental clusters. This approach to technology providers would allow the development of Micro-clouds which in turn would nurture know-how among adopters. Technology providers and their capabilities would subsequently develop Private and Community Clouds. To develop a sound Community Cloud, the close cooperation among commercial partners will be key <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Bruque et al., 2015)</ref>, and technology providers will complement the capabilities of incumbent companies acting as real technological partners. Finally, companies hosting Public Clouds will strengthen the relationship between the technological provider and the business partner that will give rise to a greater success likelihood.</p><p>These results also have some public policy implications.  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>H7:</head><label></label><figDesc>The higher managers' awareness of Success Cases in Cloud Computing, the higher the level of adoption of Cloud Computing.Killer Aplications and Success Cases might be related. A Killer Application can be visualized and widely recognized in multiple sectors, which may favor technology awareness by other agents working in different industries. Thus, awareness about Killer Applications might cause a sense of urgency among potential technology adopters to rise. Early adopters in some industries might be visualized by other potential early adopters as Success Cases. This enables to state the following hypothesis: H8: The higher the number of Killer Applications related to Cloud Computing, the higher the number of Cloud Computing Success Cases.Success Cases might be fostered by R&amp;D Institutions, Technology Providers and Public Administrations. Likewise, the higher the number of Success Cases, closely related to Cloud developers, the higher business partners are able to increase their internal technological know-how. Indirectly, through increasing the internal technological expertise, R&amp;D Institutions can increase their influence over potentially adopting organizations(Montealegre, 1999). The same rationale can be applied to Technology Providers that might be also seen by clients as the most appropriate collaborators in technology adoption. Success Cases may also act as technology transfer promoters for Public Administrations, aiming and fostering initiatives related to the diffusion of public programs among potential adopters(Dimitrakos et al., 2010). These arguments lead to the following hypotheses: H9: The higher managers' awareness of Success Cases in Cloud Computing, the higher the influence of R&amp;D Institutions on Cloud Computing adoption. H10: The higher managers' awareness of Success Cases in Cloud Computing, the higher the influence of Technology Providers on Cloud Computing adoption. H11: The higher managers' awareness of Success Cases in Cloud Computing, the higher the influence of Public Administrations on Cloud Computing adoption.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 1 depicts the research model.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Structural Equations Results</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Future</head><label></label><figDesc>research might study other industries less prone to risk themselves in high technology adoption initiatives or different countries and geographical settings so that they can make cross-national adoption comparisons, implications and recommendations. Finally, further research is needed about other internal drivers that may determine Cloud Adoption in companies, particularly in more advanced stages of adoption.DIMAGGIO PJ and POWELL WW (1983)  The iron cage revisited: institutional isomorphism and collective and collective rationality in organizational fields.American SociologicalReview 48 (2), pp. 147-160. DIMITRAKOS T, MARTRAT J and WESNER S (2010) Service oriented infrastructures and cloud service platforms for the enterprise. A selection of common capabilities validated in real-life business trials by the BEinGRID Consortium. Springer, Berlin. DOOLIN B, MCLEOD L, MCQUEEN B and WATTON M (2003) Internet Strategies for Established Retailers: Four New Zealand Case Studies, Journal of Information Technology Cases and Applications 5 (4), pp. 3-20. DOS SANTOS BL and PEFFERS K (1998) Competitor and vendor influence on the adoption of innovative applications in electronic commerce. Information &amp; Management 34 (3), pp. 175-184. FRAMBACH RT, BARKEMA HG, NOOTEBOOM B and WEDEL M (1998) Adoption of a service innovation in the business market: an empirical test of supply-side variables. Journal of Business Research 41 (2), pp. 161-174. GUPTA P, SEETHARAMAN and RAJ J R (2013) The usage and adoption of cloud computing by small and medium business. International Journal of Information Management, 33, pp. 861-874. HOVAV A, PATNAYAKUNI R and SCHUFF D (2004) A model of Internet standards adoption: the case of IPv6. Info Systems Journal 14 (4), pp. 265-294. HSU P F, RAY and LI-HSIEH Y Y (2014) Examining cloud computing adoption intention, pricing mechanism, and deployment model, International Journal of Information Management, 31, pp. 474-488. IYER B and HENDERSON J (2010) Preparing for the Future: Understanding the Seven Capabilities of Cloud Computing. MIS Quarterly Executive 9 (2), pp. 117-131. JANSSEN M and JOHA A (2011) Challenges for adopting cloud-based software as a service (SaaS) in the public sector. ECIS-2011, Nineteenth European Conference on Information Systems, Helsinki (Finland), June 9-11. MARSTON S, LI Z, BANDYOPADHYAY S, ZHANG J and GHALSASI A (2011) Cloud computing. The business perspective. Decision Support Systems 51 (1), pp. 176-189. MELL P and GRANCE T (2011) The NIST Definition of Cloud Computing. National Institute of Standards and Technology. MIDDLETON CA (2007) What if there is no killer application? An exploration of a user-centric perspective on broadband. Journal of Information Technology, 18 (4), pp. 231-246. MONTEALEGRE R (1999) A temporal model of institutional interventions for information technology adoption in less-developed countries. Journal of Management Information Systems 16 (1), pp. 207-233. MOORE GA (1991) Crossing the chasm. Marketing and selling high-tech products to mainstream customers. Harper Collins Publishers, New York. MOORE GA (1995) Inside the tornado. Marketing Strategies from Silicon Valley's cutting edge. Harper Collins Publishers, New York. NAMBISAN S and WANG YM (1999) Roadblocks to Web technology adoption. Communications of the ACM 42 (1), pp. 98-101. NAVONIL M (2010) Exploiting grid computing, desktop grids and cloud computing for e-science. Future directions. Transforming Government: People, Process and Policy 4 (4), pp. 288-298. NUSEIBEH H (2011) Adoption of Cloud Computing in Organizations. In Proceedings of the 17 th Americas Conference on Information Systems, AMCIS 2011. OLIVEIRA T, THOMAS M and ESPADA M (2014) Assessing the determinants of cloud computing adoption: An analysis of the manufacturing and services sectors, Information &amp; Management 51, (4), pp. 497-510. PAN MJ and JANG WY (2008) Determinants of the adoption of enterprise resource planning within the technology-organization-environment framework: Taiwan's communications industry. The Journal of Computer Information Systems 48 (3), pp. 94-102.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>better, comprehensive knowledge on the factors that encourage or inhibit IT adoption would allow companies to get access to a successful adoption. Revisiting environmental adoption factors for new technologies, such as cloud computing, is therefore a relevant question that should be addressed.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Computing adoption, but external pressure are not (competitors pressure, government</cell></row><row><cell>policy, partners pressure, regulations). Finally, Lian et al. (2014) state that the most</cell></row><row><cell>critical factors in Cloud Computing adoption are data security, perceived technical</cell></row><row><cell>competence, cost, top manager support, and complexity.</cell></row><row><cell>Regarding environmental factors, some studies reported a no significant</cell></row><row><cell>relationship between Public Administration and Cloud Computing adoption (Oliveira et</cell></row><row><cell>Cloud Computing Adoption al., 2014; Hsu et al., 2014). Some other authors considered R&amp;D institutes as an</cell></row><row><cell>Cloud Computing technologies can be classified in (Mell and Grance, 2011): (1) important factor for dealing with enterprises' concerns about IT standardization,</cell></row><row><cell>Private Cloud -internal cloud infrastructure in one single organization-; (2) Community security and the interoperability of cloud solutions (Low y Chen, 2012). And few</cell></row><row><cell>Cloud -distributed infrastructure made up by a group or business partners to share studies more explore the important role of the Technology Providers in facilitating</cell></row><row><cell>business resources-; (3) Public Cloud -provisioned by the general public for open use-, Cloud Computing adoption (Alshamalia</cell></row><row><cell>Platforms as a Service (PaaS), that deploys onto the cloud infrastructure consumer-</cell></row><row><cell>created or acquired applications created using programming languages, libraries,</cell></row><row><cell>services, and tools supported by the provider, and (3) Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS),</cell></row><row><cell>that provides processing, storage, networks, and other fundamental computing resources</cell></row><row><cell>where the consumer is able to deploy and run software.</cell></row><row><cell>Investigations on Cloud Computing adoption has diverse. Cloud computing is</cell></row><row><cell>affected by geographical and industrial factors. Finance and business areas in</cell></row><row><cell>educational institutions use more Cloud Computing than other industries (Tuncay,</cell></row><row><cell>2010). Arinze and Anandarajan (2010) examine the potential of Cloud Computing in</cell></row><row><cell>developing countries. Low et al. (2011), use a contingent model to analyze the factors</cell></row><row><cell>(relative advantage, complexity, compatibility, top management support, firm size,</cell></row><row><cell>technology readiness, competitive pressure, and trading partner pressure) that affect</cell></row><row><cell>Cloud Computing adoption by firms belonging to the high-tech industry in Taiwan.</cell></row><row><cell>Gupta et al. (2013) highlight the easy of use, security and privacy in their study about</cell></row><row><cell>Cloud Computing use and adoption on small and medium enterprises (SMEs). Based on</cell></row><row><cell>diffusion of innovation theory and technology-organization-environmental framework,</cell></row><row><cell>Oliveira et al. (2014) focus on innovation characteristics. Hsu et al. (2014) found that</cell></row><row><cell>the perceived benefits, business concerns and IT capability are determinants of Cloud</cell></row></table><note><p>They have been found related to IT adoption: competitors pressure, trading partners pressure, confidence in commercial relationship, commercial partners/clients support, positive network externalities and critical mass. However, Killer Applications and Success Cases, although are factors that can play a crucial role on adoption as a way to boost IT knowledge and use, have received little attention in research (Xu and Gutiérrez, 2006). A and (4) Hybrid Cloud -two or more distinct cloud infrastructures (private, community, or public)-. Cloud Computing implementation can be carried out together with the next service models: (1) Software as a Service (SaaS), uses provider's applications running on a cloud infrastructure where the applications are accessible from a thin client interface, such as a web browser (e.g., web-based email), or a program interface; (2)</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. Other examples for web technologies were the Internet search engine Google, Voice over IP such as Skype or, more recently, video screening systems through the Internet (Shin, 2006) such as YouTube or social electronic networks like Foursquare. Firms like Foursquare hold all their infrastructure hosted in the Amazon EC2 servers. Emerging cloud models the ones more appropriate to satisfy traffic and concurrency needs<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Buyya et al., 2009)</ref>.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Therefore, a positive relationship between the existence of Killer Applications in the</cell></row><row><cell>Internet age and Cloud Computing adoption could arise. Products like Google's Gmail,</cell></row><row><cell>-a Cloud killer application-, encourage many firms to use Cloud services provided by</cell></row><row><cell>Google App.</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p>In Cloud Computing literature, the Amazon EC2 models are considered as Killer Applications related to Cloud Computing</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Abdulaziz, 2012)</ref></p>. They might be succeeding in attracting many users through imitation or contagion</p>(Dos Santos and Peffers, 1998;   Middleton, 2007)</p>. In fact, many successful companies working in Internet-related services such as Reddit, Quora and Foursquare, use their IT services. Based on Institutional Theory</p>(DiMaggio and Powell, 1983)</p>, Killer Applications might favor mimesis or imitative behavior, which is a powerful explicative factor of IT adoption in companies. Therefore, we propose the following hypothesis:</p>H4: The higher managers' awareness of Killer Applications based on Cloud</p>Computing, the higher the level of Cloud Computing adoption.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 . Scales, measure variables and sources Measures Authors With regards to the institutions that carry out R&amp;D in your environment, your opinion is that</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Table 1 gathers sample distribution regarding sizes and informants. Table 2 exhibits sectorial sampling distribution.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Table 1.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sample Distribution</cell><cell cols="2">Sample</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Size (number of employees)</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Between 11 and 100</cell><cell>182</cell><cell>64.77</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Between 100 and 200</cell><cell>43</cell><cell>15.30</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Between 200 and 500</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>9.61</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>More than 500</cell><cell>29</cell><cell>10.32</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>281</cell><cell>100</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Informants</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CEO</cell><cell>52</cell><cell>18.50</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CIO</cell><cell>229</cell><cell>81.50</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>281</cell><cell>100</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Table 2.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Total firms in</cell></row><row><cell>Sectorial sample distribution</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Technological</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Sample</cell><cell></cell><cell>Parks</cell></row><row><cell>Sector</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell>Automotive and Aeronautics</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>4.3</cell><cell>102</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>Training and Human Resources</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>4.6</cell><cell>153</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>Information, Informatics and Telecommunications</cell><cell>83</cell><cell cols="2">29.5 1381</cell><cell>27</cell></row><row><cell>Health and Medicine</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>6.0</cell><cell>358</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>Agrifood and Biotechnology</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>7.8</cell><cell>205</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>Electronics</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>5.0</cell><cell>153</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>Manufacturing</cell><cell>26</cell><cell>9.3</cell><cell>307</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Engineering &amp; Consulting</cell><cell>46</cell><cell>16.4</cell><cell>716</cell><cell>14</cell></row><row><cell>Energy and Environment</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>4.3</cell><cell>307</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Technological Centres and R&amp;D</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>12.8</cell><cell>307</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Others</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1126</cell><cell>22</cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>281</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>5115</cell><cell>100</cell></row><row><cell>Measures</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="5">R&amp;D Institutions influence, Public Administrations influence and Technology</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Providers influence have been measured using instruments proposed and validated in</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">prior research. Killer Applications and Success Cases variables have been</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">operationalized through direct questions (Xu and Gutiérrez, 2006). Cloud Computing</cell></row></table><note><p>Table 3 shows measure variables. Table 4 shows the Cloud Computing adoption scale, indicating if it is a pre-adoption or adoption level.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>think that, among the Cloud Computing providers, there are some companies that are willing to:</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>1.(TP_IN1) Cooperate with my organization</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2.(TP_IN2) Hold a severe cooperative relations with my organization</cell><cell>Wu (2006)</cell></row><row><cell>3.(TP_IN3) They will not seek to take advantage of our cooperation</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>relationship</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>With regards to Public Administrations and Cloud Computing:</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1. (PA_IN1) Public Administrations are leaders with regards to these</cell><cell>Quaddus and</cell></row><row><cell>technologies</cell><cell>Hofmeyer (2007);</cell></row><row><cell>2. (PA_IN2) Public Administrations already use Cloud Computing</cell><cell>Teo et al. (1997);</cell></row><row><cell>3. (PA_IN3) Public Administrations provide direct financial support and</cell><cell>Premkumar and</cell></row><row><cell>efficient infrastructures to promote the use of Cloud Computing</cell><cell>Roberts (1999)</cell></row><row><cell>Killer Applications</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1. (KA) I know one or several applications (Killer Applications) which confirm</cell><cell>Xu and Gutiérrez</cell></row><row><cell>the great potential of Cloud Computing</cell><cell>(2006)</cell></row><row><cell>Success Cases</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1. (SC) I know one or several Success Cases which encourage to use Cloud</cell><cell>Xu and Gutiérrez</cell></row><row><cell>Computing in my Organization</cell><cell>(2006)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 4 . Cloud computing adoption scale</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>LEVEL</cell><cell>DESCRIPTION</cell><cell>ITEM</cell><cell>CLOUD</cell></row><row><cell>Level 0_1</cell><cell>Experimental cluster</cell><cell>We use a cluster made up by a limited purposes. number of computers just for experimental</cell><cell>NO</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>We use a cluster made up by a limited</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Level 0_2</cell><cell>cluster Departmental</cell><cell>local area network in a particular number of computers connected through a</cell><cell>NO</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>department for operational purposes.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>We use clusters made up by computers</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Level 0_3</cell><cell>cluster Interdepartmental</cell><cell>connecting several departments mostly for connected through a local area network,</cell><cell>NO</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>operational purposes.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>We use clusters made up by computers</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Level 1</cell><cell>MicroCloud</cell><cell>connecting several departments mostly for connected through a wide area network,</cell><cell>YES</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>operational purposes.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>In our organization, Cloud Computing is</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Level 2</cell><cell>Private Cloud</cell><cell>mostly for operational purposes within the used grouping a big number of resources,</cell><cell>YES</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>organization.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>In our organization, Cloud Computing is</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Level 3</cell><cell>Community Cloud with partners) (Private Cloud</cell><cell>used grouping a big number of resources, also provide resources and with which we interaction with other organizations which mostly for operational purposes, allowing</cell><cell>YES</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>are connected through strong links.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>In our organization, Cloud Computing is</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>used to gather a big number of resources</cell><cell>YES</cell></row><row><cell>Level 4</cell><cell>Public Cloud</cell><cell>coming from heterogeneous external</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>organizations freely associated through a</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>wide global network.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Content validity was ensured through a questionnaire analysis carried out by 5</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">academics and 2 managers directly related to Cloud Computing. Scale</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">unidimensionality was assessed through an Exploratory Factor Analysis, providing</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">eigenvalues higher than 1, standardized factorial loads of observed variables higher than</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">0.5, a significant explained variance for each extracted factor and high values for Chi-</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Squared/degrees of freedom in Barlett's sphericity test (p&lt;.05). Therefore, one single</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">factor was extracted in each of the proposed scales: Influence of R&amp;D Institutions,</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Influence of Technology Providers and Influence of Public Administrations. Table</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 5 . Exploratory Factor Analysis</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Factor</cell><cell>Variable</cell><cell>CRI</cell><cell>Standardized Factor Loading</cell><cell>Barlett Test</cell><cell>% Explained Variance</cell></row><row><cell>R&amp;D Institutions'</cell><cell>RD_IN1</cell><cell></cell><cell>.903</cell><cell>X 2 =283.276</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Influence</cell><cell>RD_IN2</cell><cell>.71</cell><cell>.911</cell><cell>g=3</cell><cell>65.135</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>RD_IN3</cell><cell></cell><cell>.557</cell><cell>sig=.00</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Technology</cell><cell>TP_IN1</cell><cell></cell><cell>.882</cell><cell>X 2 =258.669</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Providers' Influence</cell><cell>TP_IN2 TP_IN3</cell><cell>.75</cell><cell>.894 .647</cell><cell>g=3 sig=.00</cell><cell>66.481</cell></row><row><cell>Public</cell><cell>PA_IN1</cell><cell></cell><cell>.817</cell><cell>X 2 =108.316</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Administrations' Influence</cell><cell>PA_IN2 PA_IN3</cell><cell>.65</cell><cell>.754 .708</cell><cell>g=3 sig=.00</cell><cell>57.872</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 6 . Confirmatory Factor Analysis</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Factor</cell><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Standardized Factor Loading</cell><cell>R 2</cell></row><row><cell>R&amp;D Institutions'</cell><cell>RD_IN1</cell><cell>0.774</cell><cell>0.600</cell></row><row><cell>Influence</cell><cell>RD_IN2</cell><cell>1.000</cell><cell>1.000</cell></row><row><cell>Technology Providers'</cell><cell>TP_IN1</cell><cell>1.000</cell><cell>1.000</cell></row><row><cell>Influence</cell><cell>TP_IN2</cell><cell>0.731</cell><cell>0.534</cell></row><row><cell>Public Administration'</cell><cell>PA_IN1</cell><cell>0.615</cell><cell>0.379</cell></row><row><cell>Influence</cell><cell>PA_IN2</cell><cell>0.713</cell><cell>0.509</cell></row><row><cell>-------</cell><cell>KA</cell><cell>---</cell><cell>---</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p><p><p><p><p>1, to analyze scales' dimensionality and test convergent validity. First, a data exploration was carried out through normalized estimation of Mardia's test</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Bentler and Wu, 2002)</ref></p>, which confirmed multivariate non-normality of data, so we could apply the Robust Maximum Likelihood method. Thus, a factor model was designed including the 9 observed variables, three for each construct. Once the measurement model was tested, yet all indicators were significant and the overall model presented a satisfactory goodness of fit, it was necessary to rule out all the factors whose standardized loads were lower than 0.5 or which had a R 2 score lower than 0.3</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Kline, 1998)</ref></p>. The final fit of the Confirmatory Factor Analysis was highly satisfactory (Kline, 1998) (Scaled, Satorra-Bentler's X 2 = 6.245; degrees of freedom g = 6; X 2 /g=1.04; RMSEA=.012; MFI=1; NFI=.985; NNFI=.998; CFI=.999; IFI=.999). Standardized factorial loads and R 2 are shown in Table</p>6</p>.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table 7 . Descriptive statistics and correlation matrix</head><label>7</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Factor/Variable</cell><cell>Mean</cell><cell>Standard</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>deviation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1. R&amp;D Institutions influence</cell><cell>5.514</cell><cell>1.224</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2. Technology Providers Influence</cell><cell>5.324</cell><cell cols="2">1.234 .198 **</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>3. Public Administrations Influence</cell><cell>3.710</cell><cell cols="2">1.328 .135 *</cell><cell>.060</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>4. Killer Applications</cell><cell>4.655</cell><cell>1.890</cell><cell cols="3">.105 .285 ** .012</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>5. Success Cases</cell><cell>4.885</cell><cell>1.785</cell><cell cols="3">.023 .291 ** .020</cell><cell>.674 **</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>N = 281; * p &lt; 0.05; ** p &lt; 0.01</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>also found that Public Administrations are not determinant on B2B adoption whileZhang and Si (2008)  found that R&amp;D Institutions have not a direct effect on technology adoption by companies (although there might be an indirect, mediating effect). R&amp;D Institutions would be performing a remarkable role on the development of the technology itself but not on actual technology adoption by companies. R&amp;D Institutions and Public Administrations would not be that closely linked to the daily activity of firms<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Bakouros et al., 2002)</ref> since they usually work under a target and timeline framework which is not the same as the one valid for companies. For instance, CERN played an important role in the development of the World Wide Web, but its influence on actual Internet adoption by companies was really limited.<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Alshamaila and Papagiannidis, 2013)</ref>. Technology Providers usually develop a continuous work of technological surveillance to not fall behind in the competition race against other players in the market. This technology surveillance carried out by Technology Providers is probably more intense than the one carried out by Public Administrations. Finally, Killer Applications are a forerunner for Success Cases because facilitate that a given technology (for example, Cloud Computing) can be easily applied to business problems which, under certain conditions, can build up a Success Case if the application is successful, innovative and takes place in the early stages of adoption.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Probably, Public Administrations are not still aware of the actual relevance of Cloud Computing and, although efforts are being put into place to promote adoption by companies, Public Administrations have still a long way ahead to promote adoption effectively. It is particularly remarkable the effect exerted on adoption by the existence of Success Cases and its awareness among managers. Success cases can be a storefront where companies visualize the effects on Cloud Computing adoption. These success cases, boosted by IT providers, increase, through a positive feedback effect, the influence of IT providers on adoption. This loop will generate new and powerful success cases that will keep fostering adoption. Whilst Killer Applications do not exert a significant influence. This fact can be explained because of the difficulty in reproducing the success attained by a particular Killer Application in different environments. For instance, electronic social networks such as Facebook or Twitter (included within the so-called Web 2.0) are Killer Applications to Web Technologies. However, massive use of social networks for private purposes has not led firms to use them to internally interconnect their employees. Conversely, Success Cases are more directly connected to the daily reality of firms, allow to visualize how a given technology solve usual, concrete problems efficiently, can be better understood in the business setting and can be easily generalize. In turn, all these facts facilitate technology adoption and diffusion by other peer companies. Furthermore, results show how Technology Providers are aware of and use Killer Applications and Success Cases indeed to promote ulterior adoption of Cloud Managers who wish to adopt Cloud Computing in their organizations should pay special attention on the actions implemented by Cloud Computing providers which, according to our results, are one of the most relevant predictors of eventual Cloud adoption. A deep knowledge of the suppliers acting in the market, their products and their capabilities (reputation, credibility, knowledge management, know-how, etc.) is needed (Koehler et al. 2010). Nowadays, companies may acquire experience and Computing (Implications expertise by a technology provider as a partner in technologies developing (Doolin</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Some directions for future adoption policies might entail infrastructure development, support to early adopters and creation of the necessary conditions so that R&amp;D Institutions might be actually interested and connected in/to potential adopters. Public Administrations must foster cloud applications and Success Cases could be explained and shown through Pilot Centers in which Technology Providers, R&amp;D Institutions and Public Administrations might cooperate. Business associations related to IT also might deepen the diffusion activities of Cloud Computing among their partners and, particularly, he diffusion of Success Cases. In addition, public administrations should enable a stronger interconnection among the three agents, such as through new joint ventures that could be set up to lead the development of Cloud Computing applications. Furthermore, the creation of Spin-out companies from research results in universities and research centers can be another interesting future work direction for policy-makers, particularly if Technology suppliers are somehow involved in the initiative. This work is the first research attempt aiming to identify the influence exerted over Cloud Computing adoption by R&amp;D Institutions, Technology Providers and Public Administrations, considering also other environmental variables such as Killer Applications and Success Cases. The results are relevant and have important implications to business practice: the only environmental agents with a significant role on adoption are Technology Providers. Neither R&amp;D Institutions nor Public Administrations have a recognizable effect on adoption. The existence and awareness of Success Cases have an important role on adoption while Killer Applications do not influence significantly. This research has several limitations. First, data were only collected from High-Technology firms located in Technology Parks in Spain. These relationships may not be the same for all industries or regions. Second, this research uses a cross-sectional design. Furthermore, the proposed theoretical model could be considered as a submodel of contingent theoretical frameworks which in turn entails offering a partial view of adoption.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Drawing upon our analyses, it is possible to envision what is in the pipeline</cell></row><row><cell>regarding business adoption of Cloud Computing. Overall, IT is moving towards an</cell></row><row><cell>"industrialization process", by which IT is becoming a commodity. In the meantime,</cell></row><row><cell>companies, influenced by IT providers will massively adopt Cloud Computing, leaving</cell></row><row><cell>aside own IT infrastructures and services and moving onto pay-per-use models. These</cell></row><row><cell>pay-per-use models will be provided by a bundle of highly specialized public cloud</cell></row><row><cell>providers that will dominate the market. As an intermediate step, IT providers are</cell></row><row><cell>currently boosting the use of hybrid clouds where public and private clouds coexist.</cell></row><row><cell>Success cases, thanks to a positive feedback effect, will increase the influence of IT</cell></row><row><cell>providers on adoption, which in turn will create new success cases.</cell></row><row><cell>Conclusions, limitations and future research</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cloud Computing for Increased Business Value</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Abdulaziz A</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Business and Social Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="234" to="239" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cloud computing Adoption by SMEs in the North East of England: A Multi-perspective Framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alshamaila</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Enterprise Information Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="250" to="275" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cloud Computing Adoption in Greece</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Alshamaila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Papagiannidis</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of UK Academy for Information Systems Conference</title>
		<meeting>UK Academy for Information Systems Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Apte</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Directorio de Empresas e Instituciones</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Málaga</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Asociación de Parques Científicos y Tecnológicos de España</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factors that Determine the Adoption of Cloud Computing: A Global Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Arinze</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Enterprise Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the evaluation of structural equation models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bagozzi</forename><surname>Rp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Science parks, a hightech fantasy? An analysis of the science parks in Greece</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mardas</forename><surname>Bakouros Yl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Varsakelis</forename><surname>Dc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Nc</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technovation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Opportunities and risks of software-as-a-service: Findings from a survey of IT executives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hess T</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Decision Support Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bentler</forename><surname>Pm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Ejc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">EQS for Windows user&apos;s guide</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Encino, California</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Multivariate Software Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cloud computing, Web 2.0, and operational performance: The mediating role of supply chain integration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bruque</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Moyano</forename><surname>Maqueira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Journal of Logistics Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="426" to="458" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Broberg</forename><surname>Buyya R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Cloud Computing: Principles and Paradigms</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cloud Computing and emerging IT platforms: Vision, hype, and reality for delivering computing as the 5 th utility</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Buyya R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Yeo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Venugopal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Broberg</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Future Generation Computer Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="599" to="616" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factors affecting the adoption of open systems: an exploratory study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chau</forename><surname>Pyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tam</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MIS Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adoption of Cloud Computing Technologies in Supply Chains: An Organizational Information Processing Theory Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jones-Farmer</forename><surname>Cegielski Cg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>La</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hazen Bt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Logistic Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="211" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shaping up for ecommerce: institutional enablers of the organizational assimilation of Web technologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chatterjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Grewal R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sambamurthy V</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MIS Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="89" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A break in the cloud? The reality of cloud computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Chris R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Management and Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusing the Cloud: Cloud Computing and Implications for Public Policy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kenji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kushida</forename><surname>Ke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Murray</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Industry Competition and Trade</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="237" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principles and practice of structural equation modelling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kline Rb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<publisher>The Guilford Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cloud services from a consumer perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anandasivam</forename><surname>Koehler P</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dan</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Americas Conference on Information Systems</title>
		<meeting>the Americas Conference on Information Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A perception-based model for EDI adoption in small businesses using a technology-organization-environment framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chau</forename><surname>Kuan Kyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Pyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information &amp; Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="507" to="521" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emergence of a Triple Helix of University-Industry-Government Relations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Leydesdorff</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science and Public Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="279" to="286" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An exploratory study to understand the critical factors affecting the decision to adopt cloud computing in Taiwan hospital</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yen</forename><surname>Dc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wang</forename><surname>Yt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Information Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The adoption of virtual banking: an empirical study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wang</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chen</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information &amp; Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cloud Computing as an Innovation: Perception, Attitude, and Adoption</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lin</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chen</forename><surname>Nc</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Information Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="533" to="540" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding the determinants of cloud computing adoption</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Low</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chen</forename><surname>Wu M</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Industrial Management &amp; Data Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1006" to="1023" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What does Grid Information Technology really mean? Definitions, taxonomy and implications in the organisational field</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Maqueira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bruque</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Moyano J ; Maqueira</forename><surname>Jm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bruque</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technology Analysis &amp; Strategic Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="607" to="634" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2009. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>International Journal of Biotechnology</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information Technology as competitive advantage: the role of human, business, and technology resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Powell</forename><surname>Tc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dent-Micallef A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Strategic Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="375" to="405" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A meta-analysis of research on information technology implementation in small business</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Premkumar G</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Organizational Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="121" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adoption of new information technologies in rural small businesses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Premkumar G</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Roberts M</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Omega International Journal of Management Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="467" to="484" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determinants of EDI adoption in the transportation industry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Premkumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ramamurthy</forename><surname>Crum M</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="121" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An investigation into the factors influencing the adoption of B2B trading exchanges in small businesses</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="202" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cloud computing adoption: an empirical study of customer preferences among start-up companies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Repschlaeger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Erek</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Zarnekow R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electron Markets</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Diffusion of Innovations</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Free Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1962">1962</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Diffusion of Innovations</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Free Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>th ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Communications of innovations: a cross cultural approach, 2 nd ed</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rogers</forename><surname>Em</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Shoemaker Ff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
			<publisher>Free Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ecommerce usage and business performance in the Malaysian tourism sector: empirical analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Salwani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Marthandan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Norzaidi</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chong</forename><surname>Sc</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Management &amp; Computer Security</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="166" to="185" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymptotic robutness in multiple group linear-latent variable models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Satorra A</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometric Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="297" to="312" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prospectus of mobile TV: Another bubble or killer application?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Shin Dh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Telematics and Informatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="270" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An exploratory study to identify the critical factors affecting the decision to establish Internet-based interorganizational information systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Janz</forename><surname>Soliman Ks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information &amp; Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="697" to="706" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Market perception on cloud computing intitiatives in organizations: A extended resource-based view</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Son</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lee</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lee</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-N</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chang</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information &amp; Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="653" to="669" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computer Interactive Interviewing in Survey Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Synodinos</forename><surname>Ne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Brennan</forename><surname>Jm</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychology &amp; Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="137" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A contingency model of internet adoption in Singapore</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tan</forename><surname>Teo Tsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Electronic Commerce</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="118" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A contingency perspective on Internet adoption and competitive advantage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Teo Tsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Pian Y</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="92" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A model for Web adoption</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Teo Tsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Pian Y</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information &amp; Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="468" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrated model of Information Systems adoption in small businesses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jyl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Management Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="214" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Processes of Technological Innovation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tornatzky</forename><surname>Lg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Fleischer M</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<publisher>Lexington Books</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Lexington</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effective use of cloud computing in education institutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Tuncay E</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Procedia Social and Behavioral Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="938" to="942" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cloud Vendor Benchmark 2011</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Velten</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">Cloud Computing Vendors. Experton Group AG</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<pubPlace>Ismaning</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acceptance of technology with network externalities: an empirical study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hsu</forename><surname>Wang Cc</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Information Technology Theory and Application</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moving Information Technology platforms to the Clouds: Insights into IT platform architecture transformation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Winans</forename><surname>Tb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Brown</forename><surname>Js</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Service Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
