<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">How Product Representation Shapes Virtual Experiences and Repatronage Intentions: The Role of Mental Imagery Processing and Experiential Value</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Suzanne</forename><surname>Overmars</surname></persName>
							<email>suzanne.overmars@uantwerpen.be</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. Communication Sciences City campus | Sint</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Antwerp</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Jacobstraat</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Karolien</forename><surname>Poels</surname></persName>
							<email>karolien.poels@uantwerpen.be</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<address>
									<postCode>2000</postCode>
									<settlement>Antwerp</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">How Product Representation Shapes Virtual Experiences and Repatronage Intentions: The Role of Mental Imagery Processing and Experiential Value</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1080/09593969.2014.988279</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T23:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>e-retailing</term>
					<term>mental imagery</term>
					<term>virtual product experience</term>
					<term>experiential value</term>
					<term>fast fashion</term>
					<term>generation Y</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Despite the lack of physical contact, innovative technologies in online stores are able to engender compelling virtual product experiences. The primary objective of this study is to clarify the mechanisms through which these virtual product experiences occur. The study proposes and tests a model in which mental imagery processing and consumers' perceptions of experiential value function as potential mechanisms through which virtual experiences in online stores are established, thereby determining re-patronage intention. The model was tested in an experimental study investigating two versions of a fast fashion online store that varied in terms of product representations: dynamic (i.e., a mix-and-match feature allowing the creation of visual images of apparel combinations) and static (i.e., rigid pictures). A sample of 660 valid cases involving individuals of Generation Y (born in 1977-1994) was obtained. The structural equation modelling technique was used to analyze the proposed research model. The results indicate that the dynamic mix-and-match technology arouses more mental images of physical product interaction than do static pictures. Moreover, mental imagery processing can be considered an important underlying source of online experiential value, which consumers subsequently exploit with repeated visits to the online store. By introducing psychological constructs such as mental imagery and perceived value, this study augments prior research on online product experiences by proposing and validating the underlying mechanisms through which the way of representing products affect consumer responses. Finally, both theoretical and practical contributions of the findings are discussed, as well as directions for further research.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Online stores are limited in the sensory information they can offer. In a virtual environment, people simply cannot physically examine products before purchase, and they must rely on information provided by the online retailer (a source that may have a vested interest). In the same way, the lack of direct experiential contact with the product may decrease consumer enjoyment, which has proven a vital aspect of the shopping experience <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Childers et al. 2001</ref>). Nevertheless, (sensory) product information has been recognized as one of the most important determinants of successful e-retailing performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Ramanathan 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Dennis, Jayawardhena, and Papamatthaiou 2010)</ref>. To alleviate these problems, online retailers are continuously exploring new opportunities for integrating innovative technologies into online stores in order to showcase their products. For example, the literature provides evidence that three-dimensional (3D) visualizations of products are better than static images in enhancing consumers' product understanding and mitigating perceived risk <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Jiang and Benbasat 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Park, Stoel, and Lennon 2008)</ref>. Other studies show that interactive and rotating product representations have a positive effect on consumers' sense of presence in remote environments <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Klein 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Li, Daugherty, and Biocca 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Fiore, Kim, and Lee 2005)</ref>. Despite these previous endeavors, very little research has examined any integrated frameworks in which the mechanism through which virtual product experiences ease the constraints associated with consumers' lack of physical product examination in conjunction with the extent to which this mechanism facilitates a compelling shopping experience and fosters patronage intentions (e.g., repeated visits to the store).</p><p>This study therefore investigates two versions of an online store that varies in terms of product representation: dynamic (i.e., a mix-and-match feature allowing the creation of visual images of apparel combinations) and static (i.e., rigid pictures). The primary objective of this study is to test the potential role and impact of mental imagery processing (i.e., perceptual information accessed from memory) as one mechanism through which virtual product experiences are established. Along with the consequences of mental imagery for the process of value creation and ultimate consumer behavioral intentions. This current study focusses on Generation Y (Gen Y) consumers and online retailing in the fast fashion industry. Gen Y members were born between 1977 to 1994 and are considered as the next promising generation. Business are struggling to find ways to capture a piece of the Gen Y market <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Cui et al. 2003)</ref>. These emerging adults with growing buying power demand value and desire an experience when shopping (online) and therefore deserve the attention of academics and marketers <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Colucci and Scarpi 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Sullivan and Heitmeyer 2008)</ref>. At the same time, the fast fashion industry is thriving, partly thanks to Gen Y consumers who are a paradox; wanting cheap and chic <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Sullivan, Kang, and Heitmeyer 2012)</ref>. In the fast fashion industry designs move as quickly as possible from catwalk to store to capture current trends in the market at affordable prices <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(Zhenxiang and Lijie 2011)</ref>. Statistics show an enormous space to explore for online fast fashion retailing <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(Zhenxiang and Lijie 2011)</ref>. However, being able to communicate the latest style online through high qualified virtual representations might be essential to provide product distinction and further experiential value to capture and retain the attention of Gen Y consumers. This issue has not been adequately addressed in previous studies.</p><p>The paper is organized as follows. We start with a literature review on the three main constructs under study; mental imagery processing, image interactivity and value creation theory. Next, we introduce the model and corresponding hypotheses drawn from the literature review. Next, a description of the empirical study designed to address the research model follows, then we present the analyses and results. Finally, we summarize the study's conclusions, its limitations, and we suggest several opportunities for further research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Review of theoretical foundations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Defining mental imagery processing</head><p>Research in the field of advertising <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Babin and Burns 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Bone and Ellen 1992)</ref> has shown that when consumers perceive actual product experiences to be blocked (product representations are the only source of information), indirect product experiences (e.g., a picture of a car) arouse mental imagery processing (e.g., the picture might invite you to imagine yourself actually driving the car). Mental imagery occurs when perceptual information is accessed from memory, creating the experience of 'seeing with the mind's eye' and 'hearing with the mind's ear' <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Kosslyn, Ganis, and Thompson 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">MacInnis and Price 1987)</ref>. In contrast, actual perception occurs when information is registered directly from the senses. Mental imagery thus enables individuals to experience a sensory stimulus in the absence of the true stimulus <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Burns, Biswas, and Babin 1993)</ref>. Studies in the field of neuroscience reveal considerable overlap between mental imagery and actual perceptual processes. In other words, imagining an action is comparable to carrying it out, as imagination activates at least some of the same brain areas <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Anema et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Lang 1979)</ref>. According to mental imagery theory, individuals mentally represent stimuli and actions based on what they have experienced in the past, combined with perceptual information available at that moment <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Lee and Gretzel 2012)</ref>. Mental imagery can be experienced in various sensory modalities. Mental images need not result merely from the exact recall of previously perceived stimuli or actions; they can also be created by combining and modifying stored perceptual information in novel ways <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Kosslyn, Ganis, and Thompson 2001)</ref>. For online stores, this could imply that consumers do not solely recall products experienced in the past. When provided with sufficient knowledge, consumers imagine products that they have never actually encountered by combining stored perceptual information in original ways (e.g., perceptual information of a previously perceived silk dress can be used to create mental images of a soft silk cushion). Nevertheless, the degree of mental imagery processing is strongly influenced by the ways in which products are represented in mediated environments <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Schlosser 2003)</ref>. Moreover, the format in which information is presented (in this study static vs. dynamic) could either encourage or discourage processing based on mental imagery <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Childers, Heckler, and Houston 1986)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">The potential role of image interactivity</head><p>In the context of online stores, when deprived of physical product examination, mental imagery could serve as a proxy for actual sensory experiences. A consumer may respond to the representation of a product by spontaneously generating clear and vivid mental images about potential product interaction in an imagined scenario-as if it is a real experience <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Bone and Ellen 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Schlosser 2003)</ref>. Recent studies report that virtual cues (e.g., high-resolution pictures, 3D interfaces) influence the level of imagery processing <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Lee 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lee and Gretzel 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Schlosser 2003)</ref>. The present study focuses on image interactivity technology as a way of representing products. <ref type="bibr">Steuer (1992, 84)</ref> defines interactivity as 'the extent to which users can participate in modifying the form or content of a mediated environment in real time'.</p><p>Image interactivity allows users to create and manipulate product images within a virtual environment. Image interactivity technology might thus provide consumers with information resembling direct experiential contact with products. Most online stores currently employ a simple form of image interactivity technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Fiore, Jin, and Kim 2005)</ref>. In most cases, this involves zoom functions that allow consumers to enlarge frontal views of individual products.</p><p>However, online stores are now gradually starting to incorporate advanced image interactivity technology. For example, a major European apparel retailer has recently included a 'mix-andmatch' image interactivity feature to represent the apparel in their online store. This feature supports the creation of visual images of apparel combinations, thereby enhancing the sensory information about the interactions with the products, and the products with the body <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Fiore, Jin, and Kim 2005)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Kim and Forsythe (2008)</ref> found that online apparel shoppers use mixand-match features to reduce product risks and increase enjoyment in online shopping. In a similar vein, Fiore, Jin and <ref type="bibr">Kim (2005)</ref> illustrate that when a website's mix-and-match image interactivity feature produces a stimulating experience it affects feelings of pleasure and arousal, which, in turn, predict approach responses. Nevertheless, researchers have yet to investigate any integrated model of the consequences of various modes of representation for mental imagery processing and, more importantly, the consequences of mental imagery as an influential strategy for online shopping experiences and subsequent consumer judgments and behavior. <ref type="bibr">Petrova and Cialdini (2008, 515)</ref> recommend that 'future research should shed more light on the processes through which imagery influences consumers' judgments and behavior.' This study therefore suggests one as yet unexplored possibility: the process of value creation. This suggestion is based on the evidence that interaction between the consumer and product is a vital source of value <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Mathwick, Malhotra, and Rigdon 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Smith and Colgate 2007)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">A value creation perspective</head><p>The construct of perceived value has been identified as one of the most significant factors in the success of organizations <ref type="bibr">(Woodruff 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr">Gallarza, Gil-Saura, and Holbrook 2011)</ref>.</p><p>Obtaining value is a fundamental purchase goal for consumers. Therefore, value creation is important for gaining a competitive edge and an important indicator of repurchase intention <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Parasuraman and Grewal 2000)</ref>. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Zeithaml (1988)</ref>, value is what a consumer 'gets <ref type="bibr">' (e.g., benefits)</ref> relative to what a consumer must 'give up' (e.g., costs or sacrifices).</p><p>Creating added value (benefits outweigh the sacrifices) is particularly vital for retailers to obtain satisfied and loyal customers <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Sweeney and Soutar 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Lindgreen and Wynstra 2005)</ref>. However, value creation might be even more crucial for online retailers given that they are not bound to any physical place. Especially for fast fashion online stores, consumers can easily switch from one online store to another (cheaper store) in just one click (exceptionally low cost). Fast fashion online stores that solely focus on the most easily observable (and also the most straightforward to copy by competitors) store cues such as price, offer no point of differentiation and are therefore likely to foster additional store switching <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Shukla and Babin 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Willems 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Zhenxiang and Lijie 2011)</ref>. As such, finding ways to deliver superior value is a key with which fast fashion online retailers can distinguish themselves (in the eyes of consumers) from others within the virtual marketplace or in comparison to traditional brick-and-mortar stores.</p><p>We believe that, both in the empirical research of value perceptions and in the management of e-retailing, there is a need of surpassing the utilitarian approaches such as the too simple tradeoff between quality and price and the limited perceived usefulness concept. To exemplify, most internet research to date establishes the value found in the extrinsic (i.e., utilitarian) benefits of online shopping. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Overby and Lee (2006)</ref> demonstrate that consumers shop online due to the convenience of comparing products, evaluating price/quality ratios, and saving time resources. <ref type="bibr">Mathwick and colleagues (2001)</ref> suggest that online shopping is based on a small range of experiential value sources, primarily efficiency and affordability. Likewise, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">McGoldrick and Collins (2007)</ref> show that the experiential component is highly prominent when shopping in-store but is far less present when shopping online. In general, the majority of the studies conclude that consumers turn (or return) to online stores primarily for extrinsic reasons (e.g., price savings and convenience). In contrast, the current literature contains many assessments of the presence of hedonism online <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Scarpi 2012)</ref>. People repeatedly turn to the internet to seek pleasure, excitement, and gratification through such activities as playing virtual games, engaging in social media, or streaming music <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Wu and Holsapple 2014)</ref>. The search for captivating experiences to complement everyday life is very important, and it appears to be inextricably linked to the shopping experience in brick-and-mortar stores <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Babin and Attaway 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Babin, Darden, and Griffin 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Sullivan, Kang, and Heitmeyer 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Colucci and Scarpi 2013)</ref>. This might be especially true for Gen Y consumers, as this demographic cohort truly desires an enriching experience when shopping <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Sullivan, Kang, and Heitmeyer 2012)</ref>. Nevertheless, consumers who are looking for engaging experiences in online stores still encounter difficulties with finding shopping environments designed to appeal to hedonic sensation <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Scarpi 2012)</ref>. In this study we propose that advancements in the technology can blur the difference between virtual and physical retail environments. Focusing on the price, efficiency, or the functional utility provided might be too narrow to account for all of the value that online stores could provide nowadays <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Willems 2012)</ref>. Therefore, in this study we adopt the experiential perspective on the value construct, which proposes that value perceptions are not only affected by consumers' perceptions of price and quality but also by consumers' fantasies, feelings, and fun <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Holbrook 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Mathwick, Malhotra, and Rigdon 2001)</ref>. To examine experiential value based on Holbrook's typology, <ref type="bibr">Mathwick and colleagues (2001)</ref> present the experiential value scale (EVS). This multi-dimensional scale reflects two underlying orthogonal spheres (1) extrinsic versus intrinsic value and (2) active versus reactive value, hence measuring four dimensions of experiential value; aesthetics, playfulness, consumer return on investment and service excellence (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Intrinsic value</head><p>is related to the shopping experience itself but not necessarily to a specific outcome (e.g, a purchase)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Playfulness</head><p>comprises the intrinsic enjoyment that comes from participating in absorbing activities that take on an element of play</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Aesthetics</head><p>includes the consumer's reaction to the consonance and unity of an object, service, or retail environment</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Extrinsic value</head><p>the shopping experience can be appreciated because it helps the consumer to achieve some specific goal</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Consumer return of investment</head><p>refers to active investment in financial, temporal, behavioral, and psychological resources that could potentially yield positive returns</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Service excellence</head><p>reflects the consumer's perception that the store can deliver on its promises through demonstrated expertise and taskrelated performance throughout the entire process</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Active value</head><p>consumers may typically value the active collaboration between the consumer and retailer (consumers act on an object)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reactive value</head><p>consumers may value shopping experiences that enthrall them (an object acts on the consumer) With this research objective in mind, four unique aspects of the current study differentiate it from previous studies.</p><p>First, this study employs <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Holbrook's (1999)</ref> comprehensive approach to the value construct. This conceptualization provides a higher level of gradation of the value types a consumer can experience in a retail store and is strongly anchored in an experiential perspective on value, going beyond the dichotomous view that contrasts utilitarian and hedonic value.</p><p>Second, whereas the dominant focus in most in-store and online value creation studies is on the consequences of value perceptions, such as (retail) preference, purchase intention and loyalty <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Overby and Lee 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Chang and Tseng 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Kim and Forsythe 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">Gallarza and Gil Saura 2006)</ref>. The focus of this study is rather on the antecedent side of the construct.</p><p>Third, proposing mental imagery as antecedent is motivated by the considerable explanatory potential of this construct as is evidenced by many researchers (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Babin and Burns 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">MacInnis and Price 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Thompson and Hamilton 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Oliver, Robertson, and Mitchell 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Petrova and Cialdini 2008)</ref>. Mental imagery has proven to fit several contexts, such as consumer problem framing, probability assessment, advertisement effectiveness, consumption experiences, consumer satisfaction, and so forth. However, researchers are only just starting to explore mental imagery in the field of online retailing and much is still to be examined <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Schlosser 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lee and Gretzel 2012)</ref>.</p><p>Fourth, the current understanding of online shopping practices can be enhanced by incorporating the theories of mental imagery processing and experiential value under a single conceptual umbrella, thus proposing an integrated model of virtual product experiences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Proposed research model and hypotheses</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Virtual product experience affecting mental imagery processing</head><p>In virtual environments, the inability to interact physically with products makes mental imagery an important tool for attaining some of the stimulation that consumers normally derive from physical product interaction (MacInnis and Price 1987). For mental imagery processing to occur, consumers need sufficient cues that provide knowledge and concretization <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Petrova and Cialdini 2008)</ref>. Dynamic mix-and-match technology is likely to enhance the vividness of such processing by providing concrete cues that encourage consumers to imagine a product trial. Most often used in the context of clothing, this technology allows online shoppers to interact with clothing articles through such actions as simulating the appearance of apparel product combinations on virtual bodies, altering the appearance of products (e.g., tops tucked into bottoms), and adjusting colors and viewing angles, just as they would do in a fitting room. <ref type="bibr">Schlosser (2003, 185)</ref> uses the term 'as-if responding' to describe the continuous change in graphics in response to user behaviors:</p><p>'responding as if the events were occurring in the physical world.' Dynamic mix-and-match technology is therefore likely to provide precise, vivid, accessible and realistic mental images of actual product interaction. Because dynamic product representations provide richer cues with which to generate mental imagery than do static representations (in which the shift in graphic representations is less concrete and less vivid), the first hypothesis is as follows:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H1</head><p>In an online store, dynamic product representations stimulate mental imagery processing more than static product representations do.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Mental Imagery Processing Affecting the Process of Value Creation</head><p>Value perceptions imply an interaction between a consumer and a product or service, e.g., shopping trips are evaluated on the merits of the goods or services that are acquired and on numerous intangible and emotional costs/benefits that accompany product interactions (Sánchez-Fernández and Iniesta-Bonillo 2007). In other words, interactions involving both the direct usage and the distant appreciation of products provide the basis for creating experiential value for the consumers involved <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Mathwick, Malhotra, and Rigdon 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Oliver, Robertson, and Mitchell 1993)</ref>. When product interactions are needed but blocked (as is frequently the case when consumers shop online), mental imagery may be used to obtain an approximate answer. As mentioned above, mental imagery shares the same neural mechanism with actual actions and helps in the construction of detailed product-trial scenarios. Mental imagery processing is therefore likely to be salient in the process of creating value online, given that it contributes to mental representations of consumer-product interactions.</p><p>The following considerations argue for the importance of the experiential value construct as a powerful outcome of mental imagery. First, consumers could proactively choose to use mental imagery to experience the immediate personal gratification of the consumption situation itself <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Holbrook and Hirschman 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">MacInnis and Price 1987)</ref>. When the mixand-match feature provides vivid cues to imagine trying on an outfit in a fitting room, and if these mental images are used as a proxy for actual experience, one function of mental imagery is likely to involve the inference of the intrinsic benefits of the imagined scenario. Calling mental images of product trial to mind may emphasize collaboration between consumers and retailers. Consumers might derive considerable enjoyment from being actively involved in the shopping experience by combining different apparel items to create novel looks (playfulness).</p><p>Consumers might also appreciate the imagined experience aesthetically-purely for its own sake (i.e., being entertained [aesthetics])-albeit in a more passive way <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Holbrook and Hirschman 1982)</ref>. Furthermore, when product interactions are blocked, consumers might choose to use mental imagery as part of a goal-fulfilling/problem-solving approach (extrinsic value) to product-purchase decisions. Mental simulation (e.g., imagining wearing a specific jacket) helps consumers to determine whether a product will be useful in attaining a specific end-goal (e.g., the jacket will keep me warm) considering the time and money spent and, therefore, perceive consumer return on investment <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Smith, Mitchell, and Meyer 1982)</ref>. A final related function of mental imagery is that it provides additional information needed in order to assess service excellence-a store's ability to deliver on its promises through demonstrated expertise and task-related performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Zeithaml 1988</ref>). An online store that offers a feature that arouses mental images of product trials might be able to respond promptly and capably to consumer needs throughout the entire shopping process <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Oliver 1999)</ref>. In other words, arousing mental imagery could be perceived as an excellent service that compensates for shortcomings in other areas (e.g., product demonstrations or product samples). In conclusion, consumers are likely to use mental imagery to infer the four different dimensions of experiential value simultaneously. This suggests the following hypotheses:</p><p>H2a Mental imagery processing is positively associated with perceived aesthetics.</p><p>H2b Mental imagery processing is positively associated with perceived playfulness.</p><p>H2c Mental imagery processing is positively associated with perceived consumer return on investment.</p><p>H2d Mental imagery processing is positively associated with perceived service excellence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Perceived value affecting re-patronage intention</head><p>Mathwick and colleagues (2001) report that shopping-based experiential value perceptions are positively associated with retail preference. In a similar vein, Sullivan and colleagues (2012) found that perceived experiential value directly influences retail patronage in an instore context. Additional studies also conclude that consumers' responses toward the online store (attitude, purchase intentions, willingness to patronize) depends on consumers' perceptions of various sources of value attached to the shopping experience <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Chang and Tseng 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Fiore, Kim, and Lee 2005)</ref>. In efforts to mitigate store switching, the re-patronage intentions of consumers is of concern, as these intentions reflect a store's ability to engage consumers for longer periods in the future, thus differentiating itself from competitors. We propose that online shopping activities might be based on a broader range of value sources, given that advancements in the technology (i.e., mix-and-match feature) more closely resemble the actual experience than static pictures and therefore could blur the difference between virtual and real product experiences. Online stores that include advanced image interactivity arousing mental imagery are therefore likely to increase the ability to entertain and deliver intrinsic enjoyment (i.e., eliminating dullness and lifelessness). Findings from offline, in-store research indicate that utilitarian and hedonic value dimensions play nearly equal roles in predicting behavioral intentions <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Babin and Attaway 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Babin, Darden, and Griffin 1994)</ref>. Besides utilitarian benefits, experiential benefits experienced in online stores might offer another important incentive for consumers to return to a specific (online) store (Marie Fiore, Jin, and Kim 2005; Fiore, Kim, and Lee 2005; Sullivan, Kang, and Heitmeyer 2012). Although the overall relationship between experiential value and re-patronage intention is likely to be positive, the strength of this relationship is likely to be driven directly by each type of value received.</p><p>H3a Perceptions of aesthetics have a direct positive impact on re-patronage intentions.</p><p>H3b Perceptions of playfulness have a direct positive impact on re-patronage intentions.</p><p>H3c Perceptions of consumer return on investment have a direct positive impact on repatronage intentions.</p><p>H3d Perceptions of service excellence have a direct positive impact on re-patronage intentions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Integrated model of virtual product experience</head><p>The proposed research model is presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>. Each path in the model constitutes a research hypothesis of this study. In summary, the model posits that dynamic product representations involve vivid cues of product use rather than static representations, thus generating more concrete mental representations (i.e., higher levels of mental imagery processing) of products and their use. Furthermore, once aroused, mental imagery is likely to have a positive influence on the process of value creation, which consumers subsequently exploit with repeated visits. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Method</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Research design and participants</head><p>This study is based on a single-factor, between-subjects design, in which product representation (dynamic vs. static) was manipulated in an online store. Participants were recruited in two steps. First, 150 undergraduate students participated in the experiment in exchange for partial completion of a course requirement. Subsequently, each student was asked to find four other individuals (between the ages of 18 and 35 years) who would be willing to participate in the experiment. This sample population was considered appropriate, given that people this age range make up Gen Y. This emerging generation shows to be well educated, techno-literate, materialistic and therefore represent a typical consumer segment for fast fashion online stores <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Colucci and Scarpi 2013)</ref>. In all, 771 participants completed the experiment. The validity of the data was tested through two alternative procedures. First, 62 (8.0%) cases were eliminated because participants did not follow the instructions (see infra).</p><p>Second, multivariate outlier analysis was used to detect outliers and suspicious response patterns. The Mahalanobis distance was calculated for the responses relating to six central variables in the dataset (mental imagery, aesthetics, playfulness, service excellence, consumer return on investment, and re-patronage intentions), as well as for the control variables (age and duration of the website visit). This analysis revealed 31 (4.0%) outliers for which the observed Mahalanobis distance exceeded the 99.999% quantile. Another 18 (2.3%) cases were eliminated because they were more than three standard deviations removed from the mean of one of the eight variables. This left a final sample of 660 valid cases involving people between the ages of 18 years to 35 years (M age = 24.51, SD = 4.03), 372 of whom were women.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Stimuli</head><p>Apparel was selected as the experimental product for two reasons. First, apparel is familiar and relevant to the sample population. Second, the consumption of apparel involves many highly sensory experiences, as the dominant attributes of apparel (e.g., texture, fit, look, and feel) are quite tangible, and they strongly invite consumers to handle and try on the items. In this study, an actual apparel brand, H&amp;M ®, was used to increase the ecological validity and legitimacy of the experiment. The online store of H&amp;M was selected primarily because it represents the fast fashion segment of the market (Zhenxiang and Lijie 2011). Furthermore, young adults of Gen Y (both men and women) are a natural target segment of the store, as well as the online store was not operational in the region in which the study took place (thus limiting prior exposure to the online store). The original H&amp;M website (which does not ship to the study region) was used as the dynamic condition in the experiment. The site included an interactive mix-and-match technology (print-screens of the stimuli can be found in appendix A), which allowed users to simulate how apparel items would look together on a model, adjust viewing angles and background colors, and alter the appearance of products. For example, shoppers could match a top with a jacket and open the closed jacket by clicking on the jacket worn by the model. A professionally produced static version of that same online store was created specifically for this study. The static version of the online store included fixed, rigid images of the apparel (these images were of the same quality as those in the dynamic condition). The two versions were held constant with regard to design, content, and the number of apparel items, such that they differed only with regard to product representation. In a pretest, 13 undergraduate marketing students browsed both versions of the online store. They checked the operation of the stimulus websites and assessed the perceived ease of use and realism using seven-point Likert scales. All items produced means above five</p><p>(5.00-5.83), suggesting that both versions of the online store are good representations of currently available online stores. Results of t-tests revealed no significant differences between the two stimulus websites with regard to the two items (all p's &gt;.05), thus implying that the manipulation did not influence the respondents' perceptions of the user-friendliness and realism of the websites.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Procedure</head><p>As specified in the instructions, participants followed a link to an online questionnaire, and they were randomly assigned to one of the two versions of the online store. No significant differences in terms of age, gender, online shopping experience, or brand name effect (H&amp;M)</p><p>were found across the two treatment conditions (all p's &gt; .05). This implies that the two groups did not differ with regard to the individual background variables (i.e., they were two homogeneous groups). Participants were provided with brief instructions, and they were asked to perform a shopping task. More specifically, participants were asked to navigate to the appropriate section of the store (i.e., men's or women's apparel) to compose an outfit of their choice consisting of multiple items, with a budget of approximately €100. Participants were also instructed to make use of the website features to explore the apparel items thoroughly.</p><p>Finally, participants were asked to list the item numbers of the chosen apparel items in the questionnaire. Only participants who used the website's interactive features could find the item numbers. Participants who did not list item numbers were thus excluded from analysis.</p><p>Using a self-paced design, participants were in control of the length of the visit and the sequence in which they visited the online store, similar to a real situation. Next, participants were asked questions relating to the central constructs, sociodemographic variables, and manipulation checks (see 4.4 Measures). Additional checks were incorporated into the online questionnaire to confirm that participants had actually performed the shopping task. After completing the questionnaire, participants were debriefed and thanked.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Measures</head><p>To verify whether the manipulation of the representation mode was successful, the participants were asked to indicate the degree to which they agreed or disagreed with the following two seven-point Likert items: The measure for re-patronage intention was created by modifying a self-report patronage intention scale developed by <ref type="bibr">Fiore and colleagues (2005)</ref>. The ability to capture the participants' intentions to return to the online store (re-patronage) was enhanced by adding the following item: 'If I am looking for certain products in the future, this online store is one of the first stores I will visit.'</p><p>Table <ref type="table">1</ref> presents the Cronbach's alpha scores, descriptive statistics, and correlations of the above described constructs. As shown in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>, all of the Cronbach's alpha scores for the central constructs exceeded the recommended cutoff point of .70. Appendix B.1 shows the detailed questions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 1</head><p>Descriptive Statistics and Correlations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Manipulation Check</head><p>The manipulation of product representation was successful in creating variance in the perceived dynamic scores. An analysis of variance reveals that the participants perceived the dynamic product representation as more dynamic than they did the static product representation (M static = 3.89, SD = 1.50 vs. M dynamic = 5.09, SD = 1.38; F(1,658) = 109.40, p &lt;</p><p>.001, r =.39). These representations were also perceived as more animated (M static = 3.30, SD = 1.53 vs. M dynamic = 4.73, SD = 1.37; F(1,658) = 159.57, p &lt;. 001, r =.44).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Direct effects</head><p>To determine the direct effects of product representation mode on mental imagery, aesthetics, playfulness, consumer return on investment, excellence and re-patronage intention a MANOVA was conducted. Using Pillai's trace, there is a significant effect of representation mode on the six dependent variables under study V=0.24, F (5,654) = 40.71, p &lt; .001, partial η 2 =.24. Separate univariate ANOVA's on the outcome variables revealed highly significant treatment effects on mental imagery (F <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">(1,</ref><ref type="bibr">658)</ref> = 161.59, p &lt; .001, partial η 2 =.20) and aesthetics (F <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">(1,</ref><ref type="bibr">658)</ref> = 92.71, p &lt; .001, partial η 2 =.12). Significant effects were also found for playfulness partial η 2 =.01). However, a non-significant effect was revealed for consumer return of investment (F (1,658) = 3.03, NS). Indicating that the dynamic online store did not differ from the static store regarding perceived consumer return of investment. Table <ref type="table">2</ref> provides a summary of the results.</p><p>Next, to closely examine the hypothesized mediating processes of mental imagery and experiential value we opted for a latent variable structural equation modeling approach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 2</head><p>Means of constructs under study by product representation mode.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Measurement Model</head><p>The hypothesized model was tested using structural equation modeling (SEM) using Mplus software <ref type="bibr">(Muthén &amp; Muthén, 1998)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Fornell and Larcker (1981)</ref> acknowledge the advantage of SEM with observed constructs for parameter estimation and hypothesis testing in causal models. Since the proposed model is theoretically hypothesized, and all constructs are adapted from previous studies, the use of confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) and SEM is appropriate.</p><p>First, all latent constructs with multiple items in this study were subjected to CFA. This procedure thus involved fitting a fully correlated 12-factor CFA model (with three experiential value dimensions as second-order constructs) containing 25 items to the data.</p><p>Preliminary analysis of the data revealed evidence of non-normality. The estimator used for subsequent modeling is therefore MLMV, 1 a robust estimator that handles non-normality in the data and provides a mean-and-variance-adjusted χ 2 test of model fit <ref type="bibr">(Muthén &amp; Muthén, 1998)</ref>. Model fit was assessed using the MLMV χ 2 goodness-of-fit test, the comparative fit index (CFI), the Tucker-Lewis index (TLI), and the RMSEA, with recommended cutoff points of .90 for CFI and TLI and with values below .06 for RMSEA <ref type="bibr">(Hu &amp; Bentler, 1999)</ref> As expected, given its sensitivity to sample size, the model χ<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">foot_0</ref> value is statistically significant ( MLMV χ 2 (254) = 666.51, p &lt; .001), but indices generated by this measurement model demonstrate an adequate fit with the data (CFI = .94; TLI = .93; RMSEA = .050).</p><p>Discriminant validity is difficult to establish when working with multidimensional hierarchically organized constructs (as is the case with the EVS). The existence of a secondorder-factor structure implies that the dimensions of experiential value share common variance <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Mathwick et al., 2001)</ref>. The discriminant validity of the measurement instrument was therefore demonstrated in two steps, beginning with the weak assessment of the related first-order constructs for experiential value by verifying that the confidence interval (± two standard errors) for each pairwise correlation estimate did not include the value of 1.0. In this study, each of the seven first-order constructs satisfies this criterion (r &lt; .71). Secondly, the discriminant validity between the six major latent constructs in the model was assessed using a constrained analysis method, which involves setting the correlation between two constructs in a pairwise fashion 2 to unity (1.0) and running the model again <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Anderson and Gerbing 1988)</ref>. A χ 2 difference test on the values obtained from the constrained and unconstrained models was performed. The results indicate that the constructs are far from being perfectly correlated, thus confirming discriminant validity in all pairwise tests (p &lt; .001). The convergent validity of the constructs was also examined. All items have factor loadings exceeding the benchmark of .5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Steenkamp and van Trijp 1991)</ref>, and each factor loading is highly significant (p &lt; .001), thus suggesting good convergent validity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">Structural model</head><p>The structural model was assessed as follows. First, all six constructs in the proposed research model were represented as latent variables. Representation mode was analyzed as a single-item independent variable with no measurement error. It was coded as a dummy variable, with '1' representing dynamic product representation and '0' representing static product representation. Furthermore, as theoretical discussion suggests <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Holbrook 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Mathwick, Malhotra, and Rigdon 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Smith and Colgate 2007)</ref>, the dimensions of experiential value were organized hierarchically, with aesthetics, playfulness, and consumer return on investment operating as second-order factors. Service excellence, the fourth dimension, was modeled as a first-order factor. Evidence from the literature indicates that the existence of a second-order-factor structure implies that factors share common variance <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Mathwick et al., 2001)</ref>. Accordingly, all four dimensions were allowed to intercorrelate freely with each other in the CFA model (r = .42 -.60). Second, based on the hypotheses, the mode of representation was entered as the predictor variable; mental imagery processing and experiential value dimensions were entered as mediating variables; and re-patronage intention was entered as the outcome variable.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5">Hypothesis testing</head><p>As expected, the dynamic mode of representation has a positive influence on mental imagery processing (𝛽 = .48 , p &lt; .001; H1), thus indicating that the mix-and-match feature engaged consumers in higher levels of mental imagery processing than did the static product representations. The results also reveal that mental imagery processing strongly affects all four experiential value dimensions. As hypothesized, mental processing exhibits significant positive effects on aesthetics (𝛽 = .75, p &lt; .001; H2a), playfulness (𝛽 = .45, p &lt; .001; H2b), consumer return on investment (𝛽 = .28, p &lt; . 001; H2c), and service excellence (𝛽 = .51, p &lt; .001; H2d). In turn, all dimensions of experiential value have significant effects on re-patronage intention. As hypothesized, the effect of aesthetics on re-patronage intention is significant and positive (𝛽 = .33, p &lt; .001; H3a). Similarly, playfulness (𝛽 = .33, p &lt; .001; H3b) and consumer return on investment (𝛽 = .44, p &lt; .001; H3c) affect re-patronage intention positively. Surprisingly, although service excellence has a significant influence on re-patronage intention, the direction of the effect is the opposite of what was predicted (𝛽 = -.16, p &lt; .05; H3d) 3 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.6">Testing the Robustness of the Model</head><p>Although the role of gender is not formally addressed by a hypothesis, the data allow us to test the robustness of the model by estimating the moderating effect of gender in the model.</p><p>The effects of product representation on subsequent responses might depend on gender because, for example, younger women are likely to enjoy shopping for sensory stimulation more than their male counterparts are (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kotzé et al. 2012)</ref>. A multi-group analysis was conducted comparing males with females. A detailed analysis of the structural paths shows that the relationships did not differ between the male and female groups (Δχ 2 (9) = 5.10, p = .83). Males appear to imagine the apparel in use to the same extent than females do and imagery processing does play a similar role in the process of value creation. Gender does also not appear to influence the relationships between the value dimensions and re-patronage intention. In all, the conclusions do not substantially vary as a function of gender.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Discussion and Conclusion</head><p>Prior research indicates that mental imagery processing can be evoked by various external stimuli <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Babin and Burns 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Bone and Ellen 1992)</ref>, although this subject has been sparsely</p><p>3 This effect might be due to collinearity. Although we did not detect collinearity using conventional measures (VIF &lt; 2.43; tolerance &gt; 0.40), we did find Pearson correlation coefficients between 0.6 and 0.8 for service excellence. <ref type="bibr">Grewal and colleagues (2004)</ref> argue that in this case type II error rates can be substantial. Hence, we are unable to exclude the very real possibility that collinearity might have affected the results. In this regard, we have recalculated the model omitting service excellence. Both approaches yield virtually the same results with the only difference being that the relationships between the remaining EVS dimensions and re-patronage intention are slightly less intense (e.g., for playfulness 𝛽 = .30 I/O 𝛽 = .33).</p><p>addressed in contexts involving online stores or online product experiences. This study reconfirms the finding that the way in which products are represented in a mediated environment has a dominant influence on mental imagery processing. This mechanism also applies to the context of fast fashion online stores. Results of structural equation modeling indicate that dynamic mix-and-match technology provides Gen Y consumers with sufficient cues to bring mental images of actual product interactions to mind, while engaging them in higher levels of mental imagery processing than static images do. The results also confirm the proposition of <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">MacInnis and Price (1987)</ref> that the inability to examine products physically makes mental imagery an important tool for recreating some of the stimulation that consumers usually derive from actual product interaction. Although most online stores (including fast fashion stores) currently employ text and pictures to present product information <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Lee 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Scarpi 2012)</ref>, it is becoming increasingly evident that text and static pictures are insufficient to represent important experiential attributes (e.g., feel, fit, and performance) in this context. This study reveals that dynamic product representations in fast fashion online stores might be able to overcome this problem.</p><p>Another proposition in the current study is that mental imagery processing is an important antecedent in the value-creation process. Although the mental imagery evoked generally enhances consumer shopping experiences, the model also confirms that each value component can be clearly delineated as a specific type of value, with each playing its own role in creating value during the shopping experience. With regard to intrinsic benefits, mental imagery stimulates an appreciation of aesthetics, in addition to a playful shopping experience. This result suggests that mental imagery enriches sensory information and makes products appear extra attractive to consumers in fast fashion online stores. In fact, the current results indicate that online stores are capable of providing a convincing amount of intrinsic value when they include dynamic interactive representations that arouse mental imagery. The results further suggest that mental imagery offers extrinsic benefits to varying degrees. The arousal of mental images of product interaction enhances observed service performance. In other words, enhances the extent to which online retailers respond promptly and capably to consumer needs throughout the entire shopping process (service excellence). In the same way, albeit to a far lesser extent, mental imagery improves perceived consumer return on investment.</p><p>Consumers use mental imagery as part of a problem-solving approach, although far less extensive than as part of aesthetics and enjoyment. As demonstrated by the results of this study, shoppers who perceive that an online store provides interactive virtual cues that elicit mental imagery feel rewarded by the fun and attractiveness of these cues, as well as by the excellence and efficiency of the shopping experience. In other words, mental imagery apparently eases the constraints associated with the lack of physical examination, thus generating a holistic valuable experience (as suggested by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Holbrook, 1999)</ref>. The results of the current study is in line with findings in existing literature concerning the importance of perceived substitutability (i.e., to compensate for the lack of sensory inputs) as a decisive factor in online shopping experiences <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Dennis, Jayawardhena, and Papamatthaiou 2010)</ref>.</p><p>Re-patronage intentions are positively affected by three dimensions of experiential value.</p><p>Interestingly, two out of three important dimensions, playfulness and consumer return on investment, have to do with the participative role of the consumer (active value). Consumers are likely to pay repeat visits to online stores that offer shopping experiences that involve enhanced collaboration through some type of virtual and mental manipulation of objects or experiences. Online stores should therefore activate and engage consumers in the process of online value creation rather than considering them as passive recipients of brand identities projected by marketers. Contrary to expectations, perceived service excellence is a negative predictor of re-patronage intention. The existing literature apparently offers no explanation for this negative relationship. We argue that there might be an indication of collinearity, although not according to conventional tests. In the presence of collinearity, the estimate of service excellence's impact on re-patronage intention while controlling for others might be less precise <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Grewal, Cote, and Baumgartner 2004)</ref>. Any suggestion of a negative relationship must therefore remain exploratory pending further research. We suggest that there might be two separate mechanisms at stake when assessing service excellence. To be more precise, consumers may either appreciate service excellence due to hedonic features (excellent service because it provides me with enjoyment, fun, escapism) or due to utilitarian features (excellent service because it is fast and efficient). Future research that disentangles the hedonic and utilitarian dimensions of (perceived) service excellence might help explaining our finding.</p><p>Overall, the results of this study are consistent with the findings of other studies, which have reported that an enhanced experience provided by interactive technologies results in more favorable product evaluations than static product representations <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Li, Daugherty, and Biocca 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kim and Forsythe 2010)</ref>. This study adds that mental imagery processing aroused by image interactivity is an important underlying source of online experiential value perceptions. Results indicate that online interactive product experiences stimulate consumers' thoughts and provide multiple consumer benefits more than static images do.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Managerial implications</head><p>In addition to the suggested theoretical contributions, this study offers several managerial implications. The results show that, despite the inability to make 'real' contact with the products, all sources of consumer value are pivotal in the context of fast fashion online shopping. The incorporation of dynamic product representations in the online store, thereby arousing mental images of product interaction, can enable, support, and direct consumers in the creation of extensive value. This suggests that the pool of online consumers has considerable potential for expansion, because a holistic and thereby more compelling shopping experience may appeal to a new group of consumers. Existing evidence <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Scarpi 2012)</ref> suggests that hedonically oriented consumers are more profitable than utilitarian consumers are. Online retailers should therefore represent their products in such a way as to exploit their full experiential potential, thus appealing to hedonic consumers. Nevertheless, consumer return on investment remains an important predictor of re-patronage intention.</p><p>Finding the right balance between the two extremes is an important challenge for both academics and practitioners.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Limitations and future research</head><p>The present research is subject to several limitations that future researchers should consider. First, this study was limited to members of Gen Y. Individuals in this age group (18-35 years) differ from older individuals (e.g., Generation X ) in terms of their experiences or proficiency in using the dynamic mix-and-match feature. Caution is therefore advised when generalizing the proposed model to other age groups.</p><p>Second, the study was limited to a single product category (i.e., fast fashion), thus further constraining the generalizability of the results. The number of product categories should therefore be extended, with the goal of replicating the findings across different product categories. Moreover, in this study, virtual experiences were provided for apparel, whose dominant attributes have to do with experiences that are difficult to digitize (e.g., texture, fit, and feel). This type of experiential attributes might strongly invite consumers to imagine product trials. The potential to provoke mental imagery might be less important for products that are dominated by searchable attributes or digitizable experiential characteristics (e.g., books and USB sticks), as sensory information is less important for evaluating these products <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Nelson 1974)</ref>.</p><p>Third, the almost relentless stream of technological innovations provides online retailers with the opportunity to integrate a wide range of tools and features for showcasing their products (e.g., extensive zoom, video, 3D applications, augmented reality). The current study examines only one specific feature (i.e., mix-and-match technology). Future research might benefit from including other dynamic tools, thus further developing knowledge regarding the effect of various dynamic cues incorporated into online stores.</p><p>In addition, this study examines the effects of virtual product representation cues on only a few constructs that figure into re-patronage decisions. Additional competing models could be tested. Future studies should therefore investigate whether and how product representations and mental imagery might influence perceived ownership, frustration, satisfaction, or loyalty <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Kamleitner 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Valvi and Fragkos 2012)</ref>. Furthermore, an additional construct of interest could be telepresence. This concept refers to the illusion of 'being there' in a mediated environment <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Kim and Biocca 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Steuer 1992)</ref>. The current study focuses on mental images of experiential contact with products rather than on the feeling of being in a world created by the computer (as is the case with telepresence). However, at the same time it has been suggested that an authentic representation of the direct (in-store) experience has more relevance to e-retailing than does telepresence <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Algharabat and Dennis 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Merrilees 2005)</ref>.</p><p>That is to say, whereas telepresence reflects the illusion and transportation to other places, authencity refers to the extent to which virtual objects are perceived as actual objects in a sensory way in computer-mediated environments <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Algharabat and Dennis 2010)</ref>. Future research should therefore also explore the perceived authenticity of the product visualization.</p><p>To conclude, further research, both in theoretical and methodological directions, should reinforce the idea that research on perceived value can broaden the vision and understanding of e-retailing as a multifaceted consuming experience. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX A. Experimental Conditions</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Experiential value construct based on<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Holbrook (1999)</ref> and<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Mathwick et al. (2001)</ref> </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Proposed research model.</figDesc><graphic coords="14,70.85,70.85,456.30,273.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">(1)</ref> 'The website I just saw included dynamic representations of apparel,' and (2) 'The website I just saw included animated representations of apparel.' Mental imagery processing was measured using the scale that<ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Schlosser (2003)</ref> developed to assess the degree of imagery evoked by a specific communication, as opposed to a person's ability to engage in imagery. This scale incorporated the elaboration and vividness dimension of mental imagery<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Babin and Burns 1998</ref>) into a one-dimensional measure (explaining 65% of the variance). Four items measured the activation of stored information in the production of mental images beyond what is provided by the stimulus and likewise, how vivid these evoked images were. In other words, the scale assessed the extent to which one embellished the mental representation of a stimulus. Mental imagery itself was not manipulated, as participants were not specifically instructed to imagine during the shopping task. Only the natural occurrence of imagery processes was measured.Experiential value perceptions were measured using validated items from the EVS developed byMathwick and colleagues (2001)  to indicate four dimensions of consumer experiential value: aesthetics, playfulness, consumer return on investment, and service excellence. The EVS measures the four dimensions by exploring seven factors: visual appeal, entertainment, escapism, enjoyment, efficiency, excellence, and economic value.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Structural equation modeling was performed in order to identify overall relationships among the constructs. All examined goodness-of-fit indices are satisfactory ( MLMV χ 2 (279) = 754.61, p &lt; .001, CFI = .94, TLI = .93, RMSEA = .051), indicating that the proposed model describes the data well. The results also provide support for eight out of nine hypothesized relationships and the model explains 68% of the variance in re-patronage intention, thereby reinforcing confirmation of the conceptual model. The standardized estimated structural model is presented in Figure 3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Results for the structural model.</figDesc><graphic coords="21,70.85,360.63,459.65,287.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure A.1 STATIC VERSION OF THE ONLINE STORE</figDesc><graphic coords="32,70.85,138.46,453.60,279.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="33,70.85,122.59,453.60,294.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>This test was performed for one pair of factors at a time (15 pairs) so that a non-significant value for one pair of factors would not be undetectable when testing simultaneously with several pairs having significant values.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			
			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors would like to thank the anonymous reviewers for their valuable suggestions and comments to improve the quality of the manuscript.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX B. Measurement items</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using Authentic 3D Product Visualisation for an Electrical Online Retailer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Algharabat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dennis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Customer Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="115" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural Equation Modeling in Practice: A Review and Recommended Two-Step Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Gerbing</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="423" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Anema</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>De Haan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gebuis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Dijkerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Thinking about Touch Facilitates Tactile but Not Auditory Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">218</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="373" to="380" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atmospheric Affect as a Tool for Creating Value and Gaining Share of Customer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Babin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Attaway</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Work And/or Fun: Measuring Hedonic and Utilitarian Shopping Value</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Babin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Darden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Griffin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Consumer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="644" to="656" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of Print Ad Pictures and Copy Containing Instructions to Imagine on Mental Imagery That Mediates Attitudes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Babin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Burns</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Advertising</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Modified Scale for the Measurement of Communication-Evoked Mental Imagery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Babin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Burns</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychology and Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="261" to="278" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Generation and Consequences of Communication-Evoked Imagery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Bone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ellen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Consumer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Operation of Visual Imagery as a Mediator of Advertising Effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Burns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Biswas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Babin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Advertising</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research Note: E-Store Image, Perceived Value and Perceived Risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tseng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="864" to="870" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hedonic and Utilitarian Motivations for Online Retail Shopping Behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Childers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Carr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Peck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Carson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Retailing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="535" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Memory for the Visual and Verbal Components of Print Advertisements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Childers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Heckler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Houston</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychology and Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="149" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generation Y: Evidences from the Fast-Fashion Market and Implications for Targeting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Colucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Scarpi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Theory and Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cause-Related Marketing: How Generation Y Responds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Trent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Matiru</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Retail &amp; Distribution Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antecedents of Internet Shopping Intentions and the Moderating Effects of Substitutability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dennis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jayawardhena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Papamatthaiou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Review of Retail, Distribution and Consumer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="430" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of Image Interactivity Technology on Consumer Responses toward the Online Retailer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fiore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Interactive Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="53" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">For Fun and Profit: Hedonic Value from Image Interactivity and Responses toward an Online Store</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fiore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychology &amp; Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="669" to="694" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating Structural Equation Models with Unobservable Variables and Measurement Error</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Claes</forename><surname>Fornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Larcker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Value Dimensions, Perceived Value, Satisfaction and Loyalty: An Investigation of University Students</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Gallarza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Saura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Travel Behaviour. Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="437" to="452" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multicollinearity and Measurement Error in Structural Equation Models: Implications for Theory Testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Grewal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cote</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Baumgartner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Marketing Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="519" to="529" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Experiential Aspects of Consumption -Consumer Fantasies, Feelings, and Fun</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Holbrook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hirschman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Consumer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="132" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduction to Consumer Value</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Holbrook</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Consumer Value: A Framework for Analysis and Research</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Holbrook</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Chapman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigating the Influence of the Functional Mechanisms of Online Product Presentations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Benbasat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Systems Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="454" to="470" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">When Imagery Influences Spending Decisions: The Role of Ownership Simulations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kamleitner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Zeitschrift Für Psychologie/Journal of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">219</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="237" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adoption of Virtual Try-on Technology for Online Apparel Shopping</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Forsythe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Interactive Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adoption of Dynamic Product Imagery for Online Shopping: Does Age Matter?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Forsythe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Review of Retail, Distribution and Consumer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="467" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Telepresence via Television: Two Dimensions of Telepresence May Have Different Connections to Memory and Persuasion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Biocca</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computer-Mediated Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="0" to="0" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Creating Virtual Product Experiences: The Role of Telepresence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Interactive Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neural Foundations of Imagery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kosslyn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ganis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Reviews. Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="635" to="642" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gender Differences in Sources of Shopping Enjoyment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kotzé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>North</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stols</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Venter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Consumer Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="416" to="424" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Bio-Informational Theory of Emotional Imagery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychophysiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="495" to="512" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consumer Processing of Virtual Experience in E-Commerce: A Test of an Integrated Framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers in Human Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2134" to="2142" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Designing Persuasive Destination Websites: A Mental Imagery Processing Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Gretzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1270" to="1280" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Role of Virtual Experience in Consumer Learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Daugherty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Biocca</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Consumer Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="395" to="407" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Value in Business Markets: What Do We Know?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lindgreen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wynstra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Where Are We Going? Industrial Marketing Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="732" to="748" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Role of Imagery in Information Processing: Review and Extensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Macinnis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Consumer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="473" to="491" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experiential Value: Conceptualization, Measurement and Application in the Catalog and Internet Shopping Environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mathwick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Malhotra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rigdon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Retailing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multichannel Retailing: Profiling the Multichannel Shopper</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mcgoldrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Review of Retail, Distribution and Consumer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="158" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emotional Brand Associations: A New KPI for E-Retailers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Merrilees</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Internet Marketing and Advertising</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="206" to="218" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advertising as Information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Political Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">729</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Value as Excellence in the Consumption Experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Oliver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Consumer Value</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Morris</forename><surname>Holbrook</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Routledge</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Imaging and Analyzing in Response to New Product Advertising</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Oliver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Advertising</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effects of Utilitarian and Hedonic Online Shopping Value on Consumer Preference and Intentions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Overby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10-11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1160" to="1166" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Impact of Technology on the Quality-Value-Loyalty Chain: A Research Agenda</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Parasuraman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Grewal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="168" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cognitive, Affective and Conative Responses to Visual Simulation: The Effects of Rotation in Online Product Presentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Stoel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lennon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Consumer Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evoking the Imagination as a Strategy of Influence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Petrova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Cialdini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Consumer Psychology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Haugtvedt</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Herr</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Kardes</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Erlbaum</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="505" to="523" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">E-Commerce Success Criteria: Determining Which Criteria Count Most</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ramanathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electronic Commerce Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="208" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Concept of Perceived Value: A Systematic Review of the Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sánchez-Fernández</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Á</forename><surname>Iniesta-Bonillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Marketing Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="427" to="451" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Work and Fun on the Internet: The Effects of Utilitarianism and Hedonism Online</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Scarpi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Interactive Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experiencing Products in the Virtual World: The Role of Goal and Imagery in Influencing Attitudes versus Purchase Intentions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Schlosser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Consumer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="198" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of Consumer Psychographics and Store Characteristics in Influencing Shopping Value and Store Switching</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Shukla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Babin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Consumer Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="194" to="203" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Customer Value Creation: A Practical Framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Colgate</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Theory and Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrating Information from Advertising and Trial: Processes and Effects on Consumer Response to Product Information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="204" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Computational Process Model of Evaluation Based on the Cognitive Structuring of Episodic Knowledge</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">NA-Advances in Consumer Research</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Abor</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Association for Consumer Research</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">09</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="136" to="143" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Use of Lisrel in Validating Marketing Constructs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E M</forename><surname>Steenkamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van Trijp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Research in Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="283" to="299" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defining Virtual Reality: Dimensions Determining Telepresence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Steuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Looking at Gen Y Shopping Preferences and Intentions: Exploring the Role of Experience and Apparel Involvement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heitmeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Consumer Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="295" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fashion Involvement and Experiential Value: Gen Y Retail Apparel Patronage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heitmeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Review of Retail, Distribution and Consumer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="459" to="483" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consumer Perceived Value: The Development of a Multiple Item Scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sweeney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Soutar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Retailing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="220" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effects of Information Processing Mode on Consumers&apos; Responses to Comparative Advertising</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Consumer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="530" to="540" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Valvi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fragkos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Critical Review of the E-Loyalty Literature: A Purchase-Centred Framework. Electronic Commerce Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="378" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Willems</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Differentiation Strategy in Retailing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hasselt</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Universiteit Hasselt &amp; Vrije Universiteit Brussel</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Imaginal and Emotional Experiences in Pleasure-Oriented IT Usage: A Hedonic Consumption Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Holsapple</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information &amp; Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="80" to="92" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consumer Perceptions of Price, Quality, and Value -a Means-End Model and Synthesis of Evidence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Zeithaml</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Case Study of Online Retailing Fast Fashion Industy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhenxiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Lijie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of E-Education, E-Business, E-Management and E-Learning</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">89</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The way the web site displays its products is attractive 5</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">I like the way the web site looks 4.92 1.38 1-7 Entertainment value</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">90</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The enthusiasm of the web site is catching</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="51" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>it picks me up 3.94 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The web site doesn&apos;t just sell products</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>it entertains me 3.52</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Shopping from the web site &quot;gets me away from it all&quot; 3.05 1</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="55" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Shopping from the web site makes me feel like I am in another world</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="89" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">I get so involved when I shop from the website that I forget everything</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">I enjoy shopping from the web site for its own sake, not just for the items I may have purchased</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">I shop from the web site for the pure enjoyment of it</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">96</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Overall, I am happy with the web site prices 5</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">43</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">When I think of the web site, I think of excellence 3.20 1</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="25" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">I think of the web site as an expert in the merchandise it offers 3.60 1.35 1-7 Re-patronage intention</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">88</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">I will probably spend more time than planned in the virtual store 3.55 1</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">If I am looking for certain products in the future, this virtual store is one of the first stores I am going to visit 3.27 1.62 1-7 Playfulness to re-patronage intention</title>
		<idno>046-.055</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Consumer return on investment; Model fit indices</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Service excellence to re-patronage intention. MLMV χ 2 (279) = 754.61, p &lt;.001, CFI=.94, TLI =.93, RMSEA = .051, 90% C.I = .</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
