<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">PARTIAL LEAST SQUARE APPROACH TO SECOND ORDER FACTOR IN BEHAVIOURAL STUDY OF ACCOUNTING INFORMATION SYSTEM</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Mohd</forename><surname>Tarmizi</surname></persName>
							<email>tarmizi644@bdrmelaka.uitm.edu.my</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Accountancy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Accounting Research Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Universiti Teknologi Mara</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="MY">Malaysia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Universiti Teknologi MARA (Melaka) Malaysia*</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Saiyidi</forename><surname>Mat</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">PARTIAL LEAST SQUARE APPROACH TO SECOND ORDER FACTOR IN BEHAVIOURAL STUDY OF ACCOUNTING INFORMATION SYSTEM</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1051/,00032(2017)</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T22:23+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Second-order factor</term>
					<term>partial least square</term>
					<term>PLS</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Theories are developed to explain an observed phenomenon in an effort to understand why and how things happen. Theories thus, use latent variables to estimate conceptual parameters. The level of abstraction depends, partly on the complexity of the theoretical model explaining the phenomenon. The conjugation of directly-measured variables leads to a formation of a firstorder factor. A combination of theoretical underpinnings supporting an existence of a higherorder components, and statistical evidence pointing to such presence adds advantage for the researchers to investigate a phenomenon both at an aggregated and disjointed dimensions. As partial least square (PLS) gains its tractions in theory development, behavioural accounting discipline in general should exploit the flexibility of PLS to work with the higher-order factors. However, technical guides are scarcely available. Therefore, this article presents a PLS approach to validate a higher-order factor on a statistical ground using accounting information system dataset.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Partial least square (PLS) which was pioneered by <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Wold (1985)</ref>, lends its relevance in the theory building. This helps researchers to explain an observed phenomenon into components that can be understood, hence acted upon. Although theories are designed to simplify explanations as why and how things happen, the level of abstractions at which the components in a theoretical model are represented can render the model too complex to evaluate or measure with relatively precision. In situations where variables are not directly measured, the researchers approximate the components that make up building blocks of a theory. The components, referred as latent variables (LVs) or factors are represented by a conjugations of related indicators. As shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, xi and xj are LVs which compose of their respective blocks of indicators x1, x2,…, x6. This level of abstraction known as first-order factor.</p><p>In some circumstances however, the researchers need understand the observed phenomenon at a higher level. For example, perceived behavioural control (PBC) in theory of planned behaviour by <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ajzen (1991)</ref> is conceded as two LVs, namely perceived self-efficacy (efficacy) and perceived controllability (control), at its lower level and a single factor (i.e., PBC) at a higher-order (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ajzen, 2002)</ref>. This higher-order component or also referred as a second-order factor is represented by xa in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. At this level, xi and xj form the base values that are used to form xa. As LVs can be measured at any level of abstraction <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Hair, Black, Babin, &amp; Anderson, 2010)</ref>, a higher-order LV represents factors that apparently distinct, yet related, lower-order latent variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Chen, Sousa, &amp; West, 2005)</ref>. The use of a higher-order in a structural equation modelling (SEM), particularly covariance-based SEM, results in more a parsimonious model.</p><p>For interpretative purposes, with sound theoretical backings and sufficient statistical parameters to support an aggregation of the first-order to higher-order factors, the use of second-order factor can provide a new dimension for the researchers to examine the phenomenon of interest. In this article, we use theory of planned behaviour to illustrate how PBC are populated into a single second-order factor which forms a basis for other statistical tests within the context of accounting information system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theory of Planned Behaviour</head><p>Theory of planned behaviour (TPB) is a widely-used theory used to explain behaviour in many disciplines. TPB consists of five components where the outcome variable is actual behaviour (behaviour) that can be predicted directly by intention and perceived behaviour control (PBC). Intention is further affected by attitude, subjective norm, and PBC. As mentioned earlier, PBC is a higher-order factor which is derived from a conjugation of efficacy and control. The relationship of these components is illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">x1 x 2 x 3 x i x j x 4 x 5 x 6</formula><p>x a</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Item level (directly measured variables)</head><p>First-order level Second-order level</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 2. Theory of planned behaviour</head><p>The focus of this article is to illustrate how PBC can be unitarily designed at a higher-order level from two lower-order constructs. Therefore, discussion on the theoretical aspect of each component is not demonstrated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODOLOGY</head><p>A total of 387 responses received from middle managers from regional industrial estate across Malaysia peninsular. This data are used to illustrate PLS to second-order factor. The survey instrument was designed to approximate the respondent's predispositions toward dysfunctional behaviour related to the use of firm's accounting information system. Three main components of theory of planned behaviour (intention, attitude, and subjective norm) were measured using items adapted from prior work. Perceived behaviour control on the other hand, was measured using its lower-order components, efficacy and control, based on five items. All items were put on a 7-point Likert scale. WarpPLS 5.0 was later used to build and test the model with the firs-order and second-order factors. The steps to validate the measurement model are detailed in the following section.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>First-Order Component Validation</head><p>Theoretically, an item is said to have sufficient convergent validity when the item measures a latent variable (LV) or factor for which it is designed for. From statistical point of view, this usually means items having high loading (&gt; .50) on their parent factor <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Hair et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Kline, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Schumacker &amp; Lomax, 2012)</ref> and crossload low on other factors give an indication of good convergent validity. The loadings should also be statistical significant as p-values are used as validation parameters in a confirmatory factor analysis. Additionally, average variance extracted (AVE) for each LV should exceed a minimum threshold of .50 <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Hair et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Urbach &amp; Ahlemann, 2010)</ref>, and a minimum composite reliability (CR) of the construct has to be at .70.</p><p>In order to assess discriminant validity of a construct, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Fornell and Larcker (1981)</ref> suggest that, square-root of AVE of a construct has to be higher than the construct's correlations with other constructs. In addition, variance inflation factor (VIF), a measure of collinearity, is to remain below 5.0, although 3.30 is a normally practiced as a stringent threshold.</p><p>The result of the model with the first-order factor shows that the criteria for factor loadings, crossloadings, AVE, CR and multicollinearity VIF test were met. This is summarised in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>. Table 2 also shows EFFICACY and CONTROL correlation are relatively highly correlated (.81). This is unsurprising given that these LVs are the lower-order factors of PBC. Although they are highly correlated, variance inflation factor (VIF) indicates that these LVs are discernable into two separate constructs. This is consistent with the approach by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Greene and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">D'Arcy (2010), and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Djajadikerta, Mat Roni, and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Trireksani (2015)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Second-Order Component Validation</head><p>The initial stage produces parameter estimates for the components and also computes their factor scores. The factor score for EFFICACY and CONTROL were then used as the scores to compute the higher-order PBC. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Hair, Black, Babin, Anderson, and Tatham (2006)</ref> suggest that a higher-order construct to be assessed in a similar manner as in the lower-order construct structure. Therefore, reliability, discriminant and convergent validity were checked again against acceptable threshold values.</p><p>Outputs from this stage show that EFFICACY and CONTROL had significant loading on PBC (loading = .95, p &lt; .001). Further, AVE of PBC was .90. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3further</ref> supports discriminant validity of PBC with the square-root of AVE that was higher than the maximum shared variance among the constructs. Other parameter estimates for ATT, SN, and INTENT were all satisfactory. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSION</head><p>The flexibility in partial least square (PLS) allows researchers to advance our knowledge to illuminate patterns in an apparently chaotic phenomenon. This flexibility also provides us lenses to look at a theory at different level of aggregation which gives us a broad understanding of an observed phenomenon.</p><p>As shown in the article, perceived behaviour control (PBC) from theory of planned behaviour (TPB) was theoretically vindicated as unitary at a higher-order of abstraction which was a result of a conjugation of two distinct latent variables. Using dataset in behavioural study in accounting information system (AIS), the theoretical argument was confirmed through statistical validations with PLS. When there is a sound theoretical underpinning supporting the existence of lower-and higher-order factors, researchers are encouraged to validate the connotation with statistical evidence. Having examining the models at both levels can enhance discussions and contribute to the pool of existing knowledge.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1.Reflective first-and second-order factors</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>summarises the number of items used to measure each TPB component. WarpPLS 5.0 was later used to build and test the model with the firs-order second-order factors. The steps to validate the measurement model are detailed in the following section.</figDesc><table><row><cell>DOI: 10.1051/</cell></row></table><note><p>*Corresponding author's email: tarmizi644@bdrmelaka.uitm.edu.my</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Item measure for construct</figDesc><table><row><cell>Construct/Factor</cell><cell>N items</cell><cell>References</cell></row><row><cell>Intention (INTENT)</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>Chatterjee (2008)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Venkatesh, Morris, Gordon, and Davis (2003)</cell></row><row><cell>Attitude (ATT)</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>Chatterjee (2008)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Venkatesh et al. (2003)</cell></row><row><cell>Subjective norm (SN)</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>Ajzen (1991)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Chatterjee (2008)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Venkatesh et al. (2003)</cell></row><row><cell>Self-efficacy</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>Thompson, Higgins, and Howell (1991)</cell></row><row><cell>(EFFICACY)</cell><cell></cell><cell>Venkatesh et al. (2003)</cell></row><row><cell>Controllability</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>Ajzen (1991)</cell></row><row><cell>(CONTROL)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Construct correlation matrix and average variance extracted (AVE) for first-order factor</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>ATT</cell><cell>SN</cell><cell>EFFICACY</cell><cell>CONTROL</cell><cell cols="2">INTENT VIF</cell></row><row><cell>ATT</cell><cell>(.975)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>3.070</cell></row><row><cell>SN</cell><cell>.772</cell><cell>(.954)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>3.291</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">EFFICACY .642</cell><cell>.681</cell><cell>(.980)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>3.595</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">CONTROL .574</cell><cell>.636</cell><cell>.806</cell><cell>(.872)</cell><cell></cell><cell>2.996</cell></row><row><cell>INTENT</cell><cell>.770</cell><cell>.772</cell><cell>.711</cell><cell>.643</cell><cell>(.924)</cell><cell>3.433</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Square-root of AVE is in brackets ( )on the diagonal</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">VIF = Variance inflation factor</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Construct correlation matrix and average variance extracted (AVE) for second-order factor</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>ATT</cell><cell>SN</cell><cell>PBC</cell><cell cols="2">INTENT VIF</cell></row><row><cell>ATT</cell><cell>(.975)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>3.058</cell></row><row><cell>SN</cell><cell>.772</cell><cell>(.954)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>3.291</cell></row><row><cell>PBC</cell><cell>.640</cell><cell>.693</cell><cell>(.950)</cell><cell></cell><cell>2.273</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">INTENT .770</cell><cell>.772</cell><cell>.712</cell><cell>(.924)</cell><cell>3.406</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>© The Authors, published by EDP Sciences. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>SHS Web of Conferences 36 shsconf/201</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The theory of planned behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ajzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0749-5978(91)90020-t</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="211" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceived Behavioral Control, Self-Efficacy, Locus of Control, and the Theory of Planned Behavior1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ajzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1559-1816.2002.tb00236.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="665" to="683" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chatterjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Unethical behavior using information technology</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>United States --Washington</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ABI/INFORM Complete</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Washington State University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Ph.D. 3370378. ProQuest Central. ProQuest Dissertations &amp; Theses (PQDT) database</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Teacher&apos;s Corner: Testing Measurement Invariance of Second-Order Factor Models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Sousa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1207/s15328007sem1203_7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="471" to="492" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dysfunctional information system behaviors are not all created the same: Challenges to the generalizability of securitybased research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Djajadikerta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mat Roni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Trireksani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.im.2015.07.008</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.im.2015.07.008" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information &amp; Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1012" to="1024" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating structural equation models with unobservable variables and measurement error</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Larcker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">39</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>JMR</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Assessing the impact of security culture and the employee-organisation relationship on IS security compliance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Greene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Arcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010-06">2010. June 2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="17" />
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Paper presented at the 5th Annual Symposium on Information Assurance 2010</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Black</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Babin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Multivariate data analysis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Upper Saddle River, NJ, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall, Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>7 ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Black</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Babin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Tatham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Multivariate data analysis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New Jersey</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Pearson Prentice Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>6 ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principles and Practice of Structural Equation Modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Guilford Publications</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Third Edition (3 ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Schumacker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lomax</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">A Beginner&apos;s Guide to Structural Equation Modeling : Third Edition</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hoboken</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Taylor and Francis</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3 ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Personal computing: Toward a conceptual model of utilization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Higgins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Howell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MIS Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural Equation Modeling in Information Systems Research Using Partial Least Squares</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Urbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ahlemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Information Technology Theory and Application</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Venkatesh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Gordon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">User Acceptance of Information Technology: Toward a Unified View</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="425" to="478" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Partial least square</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Encyclopedia of statistical sciences</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kotz</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="581" to="591" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
