<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">An Analysis of Technology Acceptance Model with Extensions in Affective Components and Anxiety for Village Financial System (Siskeudes) A Case Study in Tangerang District, Indonesia</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Roby</forename><surname>Syaiful Ubed</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Politeknik Keuangan Negara STAN</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Gede</forename><surname>Agus</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Politeknik Keuangan Negara STAN</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ambang</forename><surname>Aries</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Politeknik Keuangan Negara STAN</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">An Analysis of Technology Acceptance Model with Extensions in Affective Components and Anxiety for Village Financial System (Siskeudes) A Case Study in Tangerang District, Indonesia</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T22:23+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Siskeudes</term>
					<term>TAM</term>
					<term>Anxiety</term>
					<term>Affect</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The purpose of this study is to measure the predictors affecting the acceptance of a new system, Siskeudes, intended to assist villages to administer village fund. It was designed by State Development Audit Agency (BPKP) to be applied in Indonesian villages in 2016. Technology Acceptance Model (TAM) used in this research consisted of Perceived of Usefulness (PU) and Perceived Ease of Use (PEU) as direct variables affecting Intention of Use (IU). In addition, two extensions were added to the model; Computer Anxiety (ANX) and Affect (AFF). From 246 questionnaires distributed to all Siskeudes operators in all villages in Tangeran District, 187 were fit for research purpose. To describe the relationship pattern between latent constructs and observed variables, Structural Equation Modelling (SEM) was used. The significant findings showed that the technology anxiety of operators influenced their perceptions on the usefulness of Siskeudes negatively, whereas operators' positive perception on Siskeudes influenced their perception on Siskeudes ease of use positively. Furthermore, both Siskeudes usefulness and ease of use affected their intention to use positively. Likewise, PEU affected PU positively. One implication of the findings is that gratifying work environments are needed to enhance Computer Affect (AFF). Minimizing Anxiety (ANX) through intensive training for operators is another significance of the findings.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>The Revised State Budget 2015 accommodated the budget for villages for about 3 percent from total budget transferred for regional government (Government Regulation (PP) number 60/2014 jo PP 22/2015). Due to the significant amount of budget, 20,8 trillion rupiahs, transferred to villages across Indonesia, the accountability and transparency problems predicted by Anti-Corruption Commission (KPK) through its financial report recommendation for State Development Audit Agency (BPKP) and Ministry of Home Affair (Kemendagri) should be anticipated by creating Village Financial System <ref type="bibr">(KPK, 2015)</ref>.</p><p>Therefore, memorandum of understanding between BPKP and Kemendagri, MoU-16/K/ D4/2015, was designed to ensure the implementation of Good Village Governance focusing on the way that a village administrative can manage its budget accountably from planning, implementation, administration, reporting, and controlling <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Novianto, 2016)</ref>. Based on the MoU and Ministry of Home Affair Regulation number 113, 2014, BPKP designed a standalone application called Siskeudes that was launched on July 13, 2015.</p><p>Siskeudes is a Microsoft Access-based application enabling Villages to create financial outputs such as Village Medium-Term Development Plan (RPJM), Village Government Work Plan (RKP), Village Budget Implementation Report, Village Asset Report, and Compilation Report <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Novianto, 2016)</ref>. The aim of the application is to assist Village administrations to create financial reports and administrations easier.</p><p>Previous research of user acceptance confirmed that computer proficiency is an important factor influencing the user's intention to use the system <ref type="bibr">(Gary et.al., 2003)</ref>. In line research also found that attitude towards system is prominently affected by several components, two of them are computer anxiety and computer liking (Al <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Khaldi &amp; Al Jabri, 1997)</ref>. Computer Anxiety (ANX) refers to fear when user use certain computer system or application. Prior studies show that computer anxiety may emerge when dealing with computer system, mainly when firstly interacting with the system <ref type="bibr">(Gary et.al., 2003)</ref>. Meanwhile, Computer Affect (AFF) refers to the feeling related to the level of computer is liked <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Saade &amp; Kira, 2006)</ref>.</p><p>In the last few decades, several theories have been developed to explain technology acceptance and its implementation. One of the model proposed by Davis, Technology Acceptance Model (TAM), became a foremost model in examining variables influencing users' acceptance of the new technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Nikola &amp; Andrina, 2014)</ref>. The TAM assumes the contribution of two variables, Perceived Ease of Use (PEU) and Perceived of Usefulness (PU), to predict latent system implementation <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Nikola &amp; Andrina, 2014)</ref>. Perceived Ease of Use (PEU) can be defined as users' perception that the implementation of the technology will be effortless. Meanwhile, Perceived of Useful (PU) refers to users' perception that by implementing the system, the users can enhance their job performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Davis, 1989)</ref>.</p><p>Investigation of Siskeudes' user acceptance by examining its factors, Perceived of Useful (PU) and Perceived Ease of Use (PEU), and by exploring its extensions, Computer Anxiety (ANX) and Computer Affect (AFF), need to be performed to acquire information on what factors determine the most and how to increase the user' intention to use the system. The purpose of this study is to measure the factors influencing the acceptance of the users related to a new system implemented in all over Indonesian villages, Siskeudes by means of the established model conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Davis (1989</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Davis ( , 1993</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Davis ( , and 1996) )</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Saade &amp; Kira (2006)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.</head><p>Literature Review</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Technology Acceptance Model (TAM)</head><p>TAM was first designed to assess the prospective of the IBM's market for its PC's based applications in the mid-1980s <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Davis, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Davis, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Davis &amp; Venkatesh, 1996)</ref>. It was developed to comprehend the association of external stimulus to its user acceptance and actual use in a workplace. External stimulus consists of two variables, perceived usefulness (PU) and perceived ease of use (PEU) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Davis, 1989)</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Perceived Usefulness (PU)</head><p>Perceived usefulness is described as "the degree to which a user believes that using certain system would increase his or her job productivity." Based on organizational perspective, people are generally motivated for high performance by providing increased compensations, incentives, upgrades, and other rewards <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Pfeffer, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schein, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Vroom, 1964)</ref>. The high perceived usefulness system will be accepted positively by the user because of the positive belief he/she has that the system used will enhance his or her working performance. Accordingly, the first hypothesis is as follows: Hypothesis 1: Perceived Usefulness is related to Intention to Use of Siskeudes Users</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Perceived Ease of Use (PEU)</head><p>On the contrary, perceived ease of use is related to "the users' degree of beliefs that by means of a certain system, they would require less effort to operate." This comes from the meaning of "ease", which is autonomy from difficulty or countless effort <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Davis, 1989)</ref>. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Radner &amp; Rothschild (1975)</ref>, effort is a reserve that a person may assign to the numerous accomplishments for which he or she is in charge. The easier the operations of a system, the higher the acceptance by the user <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Davis, 1989)</ref>. Furthermore, perceived ease of use has a causal effect with perceived of usefulness <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Davis, 1993)</ref>. Therefore, the second and third hypotheses are made as follows: Hypothesis 2: Perceived Ease of Use is connected with Intention to Use of Siskeudes Users Hypothesis 3: Perceived Ease of Use is related to Perceived Usefulness</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Intention to Use (IU)</head><p>Instead of using attitude as a variable in the first model of TAM, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Davis &amp; Venkatesh (1996)</ref> proposed the updated TAM that uses behavioral intention or intention to use as replacement.</p><p>They suggested that the attitude did not fully mediate variables perceived usefulness and perceived ease of use. Nevertheless, the use of intention to use in the latter TAM model obviously depicts the direct influence of perceived usefulness and perceived of use.</p><p>In this study, the researchers decided to use the revised model of TAM that differentiates this study with what have completed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Saade &amp; Kira (2006)</ref>. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Davis &amp; Venkatesh(1996)</ref>, intention to use (IU) can be measured by users' attitude concerning adopting new system that is determined by both perceived ease of use (PEU) and perceived usefulness (PU). In addition, Intention to Use is the most significant variable predicting actual usage of system. The revised TAM model can be described in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.">Affect (AFF)</head><p>Affect is one of extensions adapted from <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Saade &amp; Kira (2006)</ref> to more depict what factors correlate to perceived usefulness and perceived ease of use. <ref type="bibr">Lee et.al. (2003)</ref>, found that there are various researches related with extensions of TAM, however, affect positively correlates with the behavior strongly <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Triandis, 1980)</ref>.</p><p>Cognitive, affective, behavioral, and perceived control are four dimensions of the term affect.</p><p>The cognitive component emphasizes on belief, for instance, the belief of user related to the significant rise of output caused by the use of certain system or technology. The affective component is the reaction associated to the preference of new system or technology. The behavioral component can be defined as users' attitude linked to the true activities or aims of the users in relations to the new system or technology. The last component, perceived control, concerns about the feeling of ease or difficulty of carrying out a specific behavior (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Davis, Baggozi &amp; Warshaw, 1992)</ref>.</p><p>The term affective is related to individual's positive and negative perceptions such as delight, happiness, unhappiness, and aversion <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Triandis, 1980)</ref>. The earlier study exposed that there is a strong relationship between affective component and behavior. Positive affect of a learning tool supported students to acquisition of positive involvement, information, and selfefficacy related to practice, while negative affect provoked students to avoid the learning tool <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Arkkelin, 2003)</ref>.</p><p>Based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Saade &amp; Kira (2006)</ref>, there is positive correlation between affect and perceived usefulness. In addition, there is positive association between affect and perceived ease of use. Thus, the fourth and fifth hypotheses are built as follows: Hypothesis 4: Affect is related positively to Perceived Usefulness Hypothesis 5: Affect is related positively to Perceived Ease of Use</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.">Anxiety (ANX)</head><p>In addition to affect, anxiety (ANX) is added as an external predictor on TAM. The reason to add anxiety as an external predictor is due to its significant effect to perceived usefulness and perceived of use <ref type="bibr">(Montazemi et.al., 2015)</ref>.</p><p>Technology anxiety is defined in numerous standpoints. Some scholars described technology anxiety as a state of mind of being dreadful or uneasy when using or in view of the use of new technology such as computer. According to <ref type="bibr">Brosnan (1998)</ref>, variables affecting the acceptance to the new technology, such as computer, are success or failure experience of using hardware or software, and present jobs related to the computer including new computer applications. The researchers have forecasted the factors such as age, gender, ethnicity, previous computer experience, mathematics anxiety, self-efficacy, learning styles, and computer attitude as factors affecting the technology and computer anxiety <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Saade &amp; Kira, 2006)</ref>.</p><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Saade &amp; Kira, (2006)</ref>, there is negative correlation between anxiety and perceived usefulness. Moreover, there is also negative correlation between anxiety and perceived ease of use. Therefore, the sixth and seventh hypotheses are created as follows: Hypothesis 6: Anxiety is related negatively to Perceived Usefulness Hypothesis 7: Anxiety is related negatively to Perceived Ease of Use</p><p>Based on the theory above and considering that AFF and ANX may influence PU and PEU and that this impact varies depending on the characteristics of the new technology used (in the present case, the new technology is Siskeudes) and the context it is used, we hypothesized as described in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Research Methodology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Sample</head><p>The research was conducted in Tangerang district since all its 246 villages have completely implemented Siskeudes since 2015. To obtain better understanding of the operators' acceptance on the Siskeudes, random sampling is applied in this study. By using Isaac and Michael calculation to determine the sample of this research (Sugiyono, 2013), the number of sample collected is 151 respondents with 5% margin of error. The respondents in this study are the operators who use Siskeudes most in the villages.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Procedures</head><p>To estimate the relationship among multiple variables and describe the relationship pattern between latent constructs and indicators/observed variables, Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) was utilized. SEM, which is often employed to analyze human behavior in society, combines regression and confirmatory factor analysis as well as path analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Schumacker and Lomax, 2010)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Schumacker and Lomax (2010)</ref> mentioned that a regression consists only of a dependent variable which is predicted by one or more independent variables, while path model permits multiple dependent and independent variables. Whereas, confirmatory factor analysis contains observed variables hypothesized to measure one or more latent constructs.</p><p>Before analyzing the data, it is necessary to test the statistical assumptions including normality data, heteroscedasticity, and multicollinearity. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Sudarmanto (2005)</ref> argued that meeting those statistical assumptions are important to avoid bias statistical estimation and inference. Alternatively, when the statistical assumptions in this study are unable to meet, Partial Least Squares (PLS) will be utilized since PLS is a less restrictive modelling analysis in terms of Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. Questionnaire items modified from <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Saade and Kira (2006)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Davis (1989</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Davis ( , 1993</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Davis ( , and 1996) )</ref> Construct Item Measure Perceived Usefulness (PU)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PU1</head><p>Making financial report would be easier using Siskeudes. PU2</p><p>Using Siskeudes improves the quality of the financial report.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PU3</head><p>Using Siskeudes enables me to accomplish tasks more quickly. PU4</p><p>Overall, Siskeudes is useful to support my job.</p><p>Perceived Ease of Use (PEU)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PEU1</head><p>Learning to operate Siskeudes will be easy for me. PEU2</p><p>To become skillful at using Siskeudes will be easy for me. PEU3 I make many errors when using Siskeudes. PEU4</p><p>Overall, Siskeudes is easy to use. Intention to Use (IU)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IU1</head><p>Assuming I had access to Siskeudes, I intend to use it IU2</p><p>Given that I had access to Siskeudes, I predict that I would use it.</p><p>Affect distribution assumptions <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Sellin, 1995)</ref>. Furthermore, he also mentioned that PLS is a variancebased approach to predict and confirm the model with large and complex path model, weak underlying theory or small data <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Wold &amp; Noonan, 1982)</ref>. To compute the data, Microsoft Excel and SmartPLS were exploited in this study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Questionnaires</head><p>Questionnaires were modified based on the studies conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Saade and Kira (2006)</ref>, modification and extensions from <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Davis (1989</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Davis ( , 1993</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Davis ( , and 1996))</ref>. All questionnaire items, to measure variables PU, PEU, AFF, ANX, and IU, will be designed based on the 5-Likert scale ranging from 1 (strongly disagree) to 5 (strongly agree). All constructs and questionnaire items in this study are listed in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Results</head><p>R square and T statistics of path coefficient were measured to evaluate inner model of the constructs. R square and T statistics are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>. From Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>, the construct IU is described by its indicators at 43,6%. The construct IU is described by other constructs, PEU and PU at 43,6%. The next construct, PU is described by other constructs, PEU, ANX and AFF at 36,1%. The last construct of the model, PEU is described by other constructs ANX and AFF at 10,2%.  The last inner model evaluation is measurement of T statistics of the path coefficient. The T statistics shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> are all higher than 1.96 except for coefficient from AFF to PU (1,461) and coefficient from ANX to PEU (1,127). In addition, the P value for both path coefficients are also not significant (P value &gt; 0,05). The P value for path coefficient from AFF to PU is 0,145 (P value &gt; 0,05), and P value for path coefficient from ANX to PEU is 0,260 (P value &gt; 0,05).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Discussion</head><p>Hypothesis testing was created by using Partial Least Squares (PLS) analysis. Null hypothesis (Ho) is determined as the absence of relationship between exogenous variable and endogenous variable. Meanwhile, alternative hypothesis (Ha) is determined by the existence of relationship between exogenous variable and endogenous variable.</p><p>The decision was made based on the alpha score. If the alpha score is less than 0,05, Ho will be rejected and Ha will be accepted. On the contrary, if the alpha score is higher than 0,05, Ho will be accepted and Ha will be rejected. That Ha is accepted means that exogenous variable affects endogenous variable. On the opposite, exogenous variable does not affect endogenous variable. In addition, T-test will be conducted to measure the significance level of the relationship between exogenous variable and endogenous variable. The outer loadings should be more than 0.7, therefore PEU→PEU3, AFF→AFF1, AFF→AFF4, IU→IU1, IU→IU2, and IU→IU5 should be removed. Thus the revised model becomes a model as shown in Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>. The next discussion will be based on Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> and Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref>.</p><p>Based on the result, the traditional TAM, relationship between PEU, PU and IU are supported in this study. Furthermore, Siskeudes' easiness to use is the strongest predictor of intention to use in this study. Additionally, this study also confirms <ref type="bibr">Saade and Kira's paper (2006)</ref> which argued that individual's positive perception explained perceived ease of use of application positively and computer's anxiety negatively influenced individual's perceived usefulness.</p><p>Regarding the relationship between PU and IU, this study is in line with <ref type="bibr">Davis and Venkatesh's finding (1996)</ref> which mentioned that PU is one of variables affecting IU. There are many factors affecting the acceptance of new technology, one of those is the belief of people that the new technology will make their jobs getting easier <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Davis, 1989)</ref>. The same results were showed by previous researches such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Davis and Venkatesh (2004)</ref>, as well as <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Venkatesh, et al. (2003)</ref>. They stated that the operators' perception that Siskeudes will enhance their jobs affects their intention to use the application. Accordingly, PEU predicts IU positively showing the same results acquired by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Davis (1989</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Davis ( , 1993</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Davis ( , and 1996))</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Davis and Venkatesh (2004)</ref>, and; <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Saade and Kira (2006)</ref>. When the operators perceive that Siskeudes is user friendly, they intend to use the application more since operating Siskeudes needs less effort. Related to third hypothesis, the path analysis in this study confirms that PEU is significantly and positively affect PU. The result strengthens previous researches, such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Sharp (2007)</ref> which indicated that PEU directly influences PU. Moreover, other findings such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Davis (1989</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Davis ( , 1993</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Davis ( , and 1996) )</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Davis and Venkatesh (2004)</ref> also enhances the finding. The respondents' perception about the ease of using Siskeudes has direct affect to their perception related to the belief that they can increase their job performanceby means of Siskeudes.</p><p>The regression analysis in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4</ref> showed that there is a positive and significant relationship between positive feeling on using computer and PEU of Siskeudes at 5 percent significant level. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Isen (2008)</ref> mentioned that when people are in good mood, they will experience positive thoughts which will assist their brain to process. In other words, positive feeling plays a beneficial role in the perception of people related to user friendliness of a system. Furthermore, people with positive emotion toward certain system revealed more clarity and better information absorption and integration when solving problems or facing challenges, thus, resulting in better adoption of the system <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Djamasbi et al., 2010)</ref>. It can be concluded that affect influences perceived ease of use of Siskeudes significantly. In addition, the research showed that computer anxiety negatively influenced perceived usefulness of Siskeudes which supported hypothesis 6. It is in line with the study of <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Webster (1989)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Igbaria &amp; Chakrabarti (1990)</ref> which found that people feeling uncomfortable with the computer were more likely to produce undesirable results and eventually unable to enjoy working with the application. It is suggested that reducing computer anxiety could be important to increase users' perception about Siskeudes, mainly the usefulness and probability of using it. Furthermore, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Igbaria and Parasuraman (1989)</ref> reported that training is beneficial to increase individual's knowledge and skill on computers and Siskeudes which can ease people's anxiety.</p><p>Conversely, hypotheses 4 and 7 are not supported in this study. Possible explanation related to the insignificant result of affect and perceived usefulness is related to the rigidity of the application from the point of view of operators. Since Siskeudes is designed to assist village administrations to make financial reports which is quite inflexible to add, or revise types of activities, there may have been little alternative to operate Siskeudes in a creative way. In that way, Siskeudes is unable to capture the users' creativity which perhaps made the users question the usefulness of the application <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Djamasbi et al., 2010)</ref>. Thus, future research is needed to study the effect of inflexibility on perceived usefulness of application. Furthermore, computer anxiety, as shown in the finding part, has no relationship with Siskeudes' ease of use. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Cascio &amp; Montealegre (2016)</ref> verified that people who felt capable of learning to use or using new application tended to feel comfortable when the new application was introduced, thus, reduced the effect of anxiety on user friendliness of system. Moreover, experienced people have better self-eficacy and less computer anxiety <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Decker, 1999)</ref>. Based on the demographic characteristics of Siskeudes operators, on average, they have sufficient six years of computer experience. It can be concluded that the impact of anxiety on perceived ease of use is not significant due to the cancelling out effect of computer experience.</p><p>Based on the discussion above, this study proposes the revised version of the model as listed in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4</ref>. The pathways from AFF to PEU and ANX to PEU are removed due to insignificant results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Conclusion</head><p>Five proposed hypotheses about the operators' intention to use Siskeudes were verified in this study. Perceived of Usefulness (PU) correlated positively with Intention to Use (IU). Perceived Ease of Use (PEU) associated positively with PU and IU. Whereas, Computer Affect (AFF) connected positively to PEU and Computer Anxiety (ANX) linked to PU negatively. On the contrary, two proposed hypotheses are unable to be confirmed in this study. ANX could not be associated negatively to PEU and AFF was not related positively to PU.</p><p>Due to the findings, revised version of the model (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4</ref>) was introduced. The revised model of TAM with extensions modified model suggested by <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Saade &amp; Kira (2006)</ref>, and reconfirmed the latest TAM model developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Davis &amp; Venkatesh (1996)</ref>. However, when considering the calculated results, the research is still far-off from the conclusion. This study was conducted only in Tangerang district, thus, to provide better conclusion on the acceptance of Siskeudes, further study with larger coverage needs to be carried out. Furthermore, Siskeudes is still in development with continuous improvements by the developer when the study was conducted which makes the conclusion in this study need to be reconfirmed.</p><p>Future research related the Siskeudes inflexibility which may influence the PU should be generated.</p><p>Moreover, the study linked to the computer experience which probably reduce the level of ANX should also conducted in the future to improve the revised model of TAM with extensions of AFF and ANX.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Technology Acceptance Model<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Davis &amp; Venkatesh, 1996)</ref> </figDesc><graphic coords="3,200.25,87.55,203.00,87.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Technology Acceptance Model with Extensions<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Davis &amp; Venkatesh, 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Saade &amp; Kira, 2006)</ref> </figDesc><graphic coords="5,157.00,82.60,281.34,123.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Revised Version of the Model</figDesc><graphic coords="9,114.18,532.98,378.89,180.45" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>R Square</figDesc><table /><note><p><p>Advances in Economics,</p>Business and Management Research, volume 36   </p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note><p>T Statistics of Path Coefficients Figure 3. Path Diagram with Coefficient and P-value</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Compilation of Proposed Hypothesis</figDesc><table><row><cell>Hyp</cell><cell>P-value</cell><cell>Details</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>0,000</cell><cell>PU has significantly positive correlation with IU</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>0,000</cell><cell>PEU has significantly positive correlation with IU</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>0,000</cell><cell>PEU has significantly positive correlation with PU</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>0,167</cell><cell>AFF has insignificantly positive correlation with PU</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>0,003</cell><cell>AFF has significantly positive correlation with PEU</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>0,013</cell><cell>ANX has significantly negative correlation with PU</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>0,295</cell><cell>ANX has insignificantly negative correlation with PEU</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Relationship of Attitudes to Computer Utilization: New Evidence from a Developing Nation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Al</forename><surname>Khaldi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Al</forename><surname>Jabri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers in Human Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Putting Prometheus&apos; feet to the fire: Student evaluations of Prometheus in relation to their attitudes towards and experience with computers, computer self-efficacy and preferred learning style</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Arkkelin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Syllabus2003 Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development and test of a theory of technological learning and usage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Baggozi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Warshaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Human Relations</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="659" to="686" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Technophobia: The psychological impact of information technology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brosnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How Technology Is Changing Work and Organizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Cascio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Montealegre</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Organizational Psychology and Organizational Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="349" to="375" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceived Usefulness, Perceived Ease of Use, and User Acceptance of Information Technology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MIS Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="319" to="340" />
			<date type="published" when="1989-09">1989. Sep., 1989</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Management Information Systems Research Center, University of Minnesota</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">User Acceptance of Information Technology: User Characteristics, User Perceptions, and Behavioral Impacts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal Man-Machine Study</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="475" to="487" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A critical assessment of potential measurement biases in the technology acceptance model : three experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Venkatesh</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int . J . Human -Computer Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward preprototype user acceptance testing of new information systems: implications for software project management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Venkatesh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Technical education transfer: perceptions of employee computer technology self-efficacy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Decker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers in Human Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="172" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Affect and acceptance: Examining the effects of positive mood on the technology acceptance model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Djamasbi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Strong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dishaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Decision Support Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="383" to="394" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computer Playfulness and Anxiety: Positive and Negative Mediators of the System Experience Effect on Perceived Ease of Use</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gary</forename><surname>Hackbarth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Varun</forename><surname>Grover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mun</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information and Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computer anxiety and attitudes towards microcomputer use</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Igbaria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chakrabarti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behaviour &amp; Information Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="241" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A path analytic study of individual characteristics, computer anxiety and attitudes toward microcomputers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Igbaria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Parasuraman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="373" to="388" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some Ways in which Positive Affect Influences Decision Making and Problem Saving</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Isen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>60/2014 jo PP 22/2015</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">regarding Village Fund which sourced from State Budget</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Guilford, Press New. Government Regulation</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Handbook of Emotions</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kementerian</forename><surname>Perindustrian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.kemenperin.go.id/artikel/8161/Kualitas-Tenaga-Kerja-RI-RendahKPK" />
		<title level="m">Rekomendasi KPK kepada BPKP dan Kemendagri dalam Rapat Dengar Pendapat Komisi XI DPR</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Empirical Study of Factors Affecting Software Package Selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kozar</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kai</forename><surname>Larsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Technology Acceptance Model: Past, Present, and Future</title>
		<title level="s">Communications of the Association for Information Systems</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cameron</forename><surname>Montazemi</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">2003. 1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="105" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factors affecting Adoption of Online Banking: A Metaanalytic Structural Equation Modeling Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Saremi</forename><surname>Montazemi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Information and Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="210" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Technology Acceptance Model: A Literature Review from 1986 to 2013</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nikola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Andrina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10209-014-0348-1</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Verlag Berlin Heidelberg</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Pengawalan Akuntabilitas Pengelolaan Keuangan Desa melalui Penerapan Aplikasi Keuangan Desa (Siskeudes)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Iskandar</forename><surname>Novianto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Presentasi pada PKN STAN tanggal 14 Maret</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Organizations and Organization Theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pfeffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
			<pubPlace>Pitman, Boston, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the Allocation of Effort</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Radner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rothschild</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="358" to="376" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Emotional State of Technology Acceptance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kira</forename><surname>Saade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Issues in Informing Science and Information Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Organizational Psychology, third edition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Schumacker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lomax</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">A beginner&apos;s guide to structural equation modeling 3rd edition</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Psychology Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Partial least squares modeling in research on educational achievement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sellin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="256" to="267" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Reflections on educational achievement</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development, extension, and application: a review of the technology acceptance model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Sharp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Syst. Educ. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analisis Regresi Linear Ganda dengan SPSS</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sudarmanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Cara Mudah Menyusun: Skripsi, Tesis, dan Disertasi</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Bandung</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Alfabeta</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nebraska symposium on motivation, 1979: Beliefs, attitudes, and values</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Triandis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="259" />
			<pubPlace>Lincoln, NE</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Values, attitudes and interpersonal behavior</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Work and Motivation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Vroom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1964">1964</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">User acceptance of information technology: Toward a unified view</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Venkatesh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MIS Quart</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Playfulness and computers at work, unpublished PhD Dissertation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Webster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>New York University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PLS path modeling with indirectly observed variables: a comparison of alternative estimates for the latent variable</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Noonan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Systems under indirect observation</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">II</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="94" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
