<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Causal Discovery Toolbox: Uncovering causal relationships in Python</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Diviyan</forename><surname>Kalainathan</surname></persName>
							<email>diviyan@fentech.ai</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Olivier</forename><surname>Goudet</surname></persName>
							<email>olivier.goudet@univ-angers.fr</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ritik</forename><surname>Dutta</surname></persName>
							<email>dutta.ritik@iitgn.ac.in</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">FenTech</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">TAU, LRI</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INRIA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Université Paris-Sud</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>20 Rue Raymond Aron</addrLine>
									<postCode>75013</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">LERIA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Université d&apos;Angers</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2 boulevard Lavoisier</addrLine>
									<postCode>49045</postCode>
									<settlement>Angers</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">IIT Gandhinagar</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>382355</postCode>
									<settlement>Gandhinagar</settlement>
									<region>Gujarat</region>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Univ. Paris-Saclay</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Causal Discovery Toolbox: Uncovering causal relationships in Python</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Submitted 3/19; Revised 11/19;</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T18:21+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Causal Discovery</term>
					<term>Graph recovery</term>
					<term>open source</term>
					<term>constraint-based methods</term>
					<term>score-based methods</term>
					<term>pairwise causality</term>
					<term>Markov blanket</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper presents a new open source Python framework for causal discovery from observational data and domain background knowledge, aimed at causal graph and causal mechanism modeling. The Cdt package implements an end-to-end approach, recovering the direct dependencies (the skeleton of the causal graph) and the causal relationships between variables. It includes algorithms from the 'Bnlearn' (Scutari, 2018) and 'Pcalg' <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Kalisch et al., 2018)</ref> packages, together with algorithms for pairwise causal discovery such as ANM (Hoyer et al.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Causal modeling is key to understand physical or artificial phenomena and to guide interventions. Most softwares for causal discovery have been developed in the R programming language <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Kalisch et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Scutari, 2018)</ref>, and a few causal discovery algorithms are available in Python e.g. RCC <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Lopez-Paz et al., 2015)</ref>, CGNN <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Goudet et al., 2018)</ref> and SAM <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Kalainathan et al., 2019)</ref>, while Python supports many current machine learning frameworks such as PyTorch <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Paszke et al., 2017)</ref>.</p><p>The Causal Discovery Toolbox (Cdt) is an open-source Python package concerned with observational causal discovery, aimed at learning both the causal graph and the associated causal mechanisms from samples of the joint probability distribution of the data. Cdt includes many state-of-the-art causal modeling algorithms (some of which are imported from R), that supports GPU hardware acceleration and automatic hardware detection. A main goal of Cdt is to provide the users with guidance towards end-to-end experiments, by including scoring metrics, and standard benchmark data sets such as the "Sachs" data set <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Sachs et al., 2005)</ref>.</p><p>Compared to other causal discovery packages, Cdt unifies pairwise and score-based multi-variate approaches within a single package, implementing an step-by-step pipeline approach (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). Cdt also provides an intuitive approach for including R-based algorithms, facilitating the task of extending the toolkit with additional R packages. The package revolves around the usage of networkx.Graph classes, mainly for recovering (un)directed graphs from observational data. Cdt currently includes 17 algorithms for graph skeleton identification: 7 methods based on independence tests, and 10 methods aimed at directly recovering the skeleton graph. It further includes 20 algorithms aimed at causal directed graph prediction, including 11 graphical and 9 pairwise approaches.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Original contributions of the package</head><p>The causal pairwise setting considers a pair of variables and aims to determine the causal relationship between both variables. This setting implicitly assumes that both variables are already conditioned on other covariates, or readjusted with a propensity score <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Rosenbaum and Rubin, 1983)</ref>, and that the remaining latent covariates have little or no influence and can be considered as "noise". The pairwise setting is also relevant to complete a partially directed graph resulting from other causal discovery methods. In the 2010s, the pairwise setting was investigated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Hoyer et al. (2009)</ref> among others, who proposed the Additive Noise Model (ANM). Later on, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Guyon (2013)</ref> on Cause-Effect pair (CEP) problems; CEP formulates bivariate causal identification as a supervised machine learning task, where a classifier is trained from examples (A i , B i , i ), where the variable pair (A i , B i ) is represented by samples of their joint distribution and label i indicates the type of causal relationship between both variables (independent,</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">A i → B i , B i → A i ).</formula><p>Cdt is one the few packages to include causal pairwise discovery algorithms. These algorithms, mostly implemented using Python or Matlab are often left unmaintained. Therefore, many algorithms that are known to be quite efficient (such as Jarfo (Fonollosa, 2019), first and first in the cause-effect pairs challenges, coded in Python 2.7) are outdated and require a substantial amount of work to fix and update. Cdt implements 9 pairwise algorithms, all coded in Python, 5 of them being new implementations (NCC, GNN, CDS, RECI and a baseline method based on regression error).</p><p>The graph setting, extensively studied in the literature, is supported by many packages. Bayesian approaches rely either on conditional independence tests named constraintbased methods, such as PC or FCI <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Spirtes et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Strobl et al., 2017)</ref>, or on scorebased methods, involving finding the graph that maximizes a likelihood score through graph search heuristics, like GES <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Chickering, 2002)</ref> or CAM <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Bühlmann et al., 2014)</ref>. Other approaches leverage the Generative Network setting, such as CGNN or SAM <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Goudet et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Kalainathan et al., 2019)</ref>. Graph setting methods output either a directed acyclic graph or a partially directed acyclic graph. Most approaches in the graph setting are imported from R packages, with the exception of CGNN and SAM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Comparison with other packages</head><p>To our best knowledge, Causality and Py-Causal are the only alternatives to Cdt for causal discovery in Python. However, the only overlap with Cdt concerns the PC-algorithm, common to Py-Causal and Cdt. Akin to Cdt, Py-Causal is a wrapper package but around the Tetrad Java package. Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> compares the runtimes of the two PC implementations on synthetic graphs with of varying size, connectivity, and number of data points, showing a constant gap in with respect to the number of data points and connectivity of the graph. This gap is due to the creation of the subprocess and the data transfer, that are not taken into account in the PyCausal execution runtime. The gap with respect to the number of nodes is due to different implementations and computational complexity. Further effort will be devoted to imposing the efficiency of our Python-Numba implementation of PC. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Implementation and utilities</head><p>R integration. As said, the Cdt package integrate 10 algorithms coded in R and 17 coded in Python. The Cdt package integrates all of them, using Wrapper functions in Python to enable the user to launch any R script and to control its arguments; the R scripts are executed in a temporary folder with a subprocess to avoid the limitations of the Python GIL. The results are retrieved through output files back into the main Python process. The whole procedure is modular and allows contributors to easily add new R functions to the package.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sustainability and deployment.</head><p>In order for the package to be easily extended, fostering the integration of further community contributions, special care is given to the quality of tests. Specifically, a Continuous Integration tool added to the git repository, allows to sequentially execute tests on new commits and pull request: i) Test all functionalities of the new version on the package on toy data sets; ii) Build docker images and push them to hub.docker.com ; iii) Push the new version on pypi ; iv) Update the documentation website. This procedure also allows to test the proper functioning of the package with its dependencies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion and future developments</head><p>The Causal Discovery Toolbox (Cdt) package allows Python users to apply many causal discovery or graph modeling algorithms on observational data. It is already used in research projects, such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Yale et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Kalainathan et al., 2019)</ref>. As the output graphs are networkx.Graph classes, these are easily exportable into various formats for visualization softwares, using e.g. Graphviz or Gephi. At the package import, tests are realized to pinpoint the configuration of the user: availability of GPUs and R packages and number of CPUs on the host machine.</p><p>The package promotes an end-to-end, step-by-step approach: the undirected graph (bivariate dependencies) is first identified, before applying causal discovery algorithms; the latter are constrained from the undirected graph, with significant computational gains.</p><p>Future extensions of the package include: i) reimplementing the R algorithms in Python -Numba and reimplement the Pytorch algorithms in Chainer to drop all heavy dependencies and to integrate Cdt in the Python community with a Numpy-API ; ii) developing GPUcompliant implementation of new algorithms; iii) handling interventional data and timeseries data (e.g. for neuroimaging and weather forecast). In the longer term, our priority is to provide the user with tests to whether the standard assumptions (e.g. causal sufficiency assumption) hold and assess the risk of applying methods out of their intended scope.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: The Cdt causal modeling package: General pipeline</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure Runtimes of implementations of PC on various graphs</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CAM: Causal additive models, highdimensional order search and penalized regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Bühlmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonas</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Ernest</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Annals of Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal structure identification with greedy search</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Maxwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chickering</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of machine learning research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="507" to="554" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-11">Nov. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conditional distribution variability measures for causality detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>José</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Fonollosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Cause Effect Pairs in Machine Learning</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning functional causal models with generative neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Olivier</forename><surname>Goudet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Diviyan</forename><surname>Kalainathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Philippe</forename><surname>Caillou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Isabelle</forename><surname>Guyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Lopez-Paz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michele</forename><surname>Sebag</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Explainable and Interpretable Models in Computer Vision and Machine Learning</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Chalearn cause effect pairs challenge</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Isabelle</forename><surname>Guyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.causality.inf.ethz.ch/cause-effect.php" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear causal discovery with additive noise models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Patrik</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Hoyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dominik</forename><surname>Janzing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Joris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonas</forename><surname>Mooij</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bernhard</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Schölkopf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="689" to="696" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural agnostic modeling: Adversarial learning of causal graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Diviyan</forename><surname>Kalainathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Olivier</forename><surname>Goudet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Isabelle</forename><surname>Guyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Lopez-Paz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michèle</forename><surname>Sebag</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ArXiv</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Package &apos;pcalg&apos;</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Markus</forename><surname>Kalisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alain</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/pcalg/index.html" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a learning theory of cause-effect inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Lopez-Paz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Krikamol</forename><surname>Muandet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bernhard</forename><surname>Schölkopf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ilya O Tolstikhin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ICML</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1452" to="1461" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Automatic differentiation in PyTorch</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Adam</forename><surname>Paszke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sam</forename><surname>Gross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Soumith</forename><surname>Chintala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://pytorch.org/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The central role of the propensity score in observational studies for causal effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Paul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Donald</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Rosenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causal protein-signaling networks derived from multiparameter single-cell data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Karen</forename><surname>Sachs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Omar</forename><surname>Perez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dana</forename><surname>Pe'er</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Douglas</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lauffenburger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Garry</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nolan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">308</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5721</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="523" to="529" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Package &apos;bnlearn</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Marco</forename><surname>Scutari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.bnlearn.com/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Causation, prediction, and search</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Spirtes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Clark</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Glymour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Scheines</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>MIT press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Approximate kernel-based conditional independence tests for fast non-parametric causal discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eric</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Strobl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kun</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shyam</forename><surname>Visweswaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Privacy preserving synthetic health data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><surname>Yale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Saloni</forename><surname>Dash</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ritik</forename><surname>Dutta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Isabelle</forename><surname>Guyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Adrien</forename><surname>Pavao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kristin</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ESANN</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
