<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Principal Transformational Leadership, Job Satisfaction and Work Motivation on the Performance of Elementary School Teachers in Halong District</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Normaini</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master in Educational Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Sulaiman</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master in Educational Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Principal Transformational Leadership, Job Satisfaction and Work Motivation on the Performance of Elementary School Teachers in Halong District</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-39</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T21:23+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Transformational Leadership</term>
					<term>Satisfaction</term>
					<term>Motivation</term>
					<term>Performance</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The main key in improving the quality of education is the optimization of human resources, namely teachers. Teacher performance is one of the factors determinant of the success of any educational effort, but there are other factors such as the principal's transformational leadership, job satisfaction and work motivation. Therefore, this study aims to examine the effect of: principal's transformational leadership on teacher performance; satisfaction with teacher performance; motivation on teacher performance; the principal's transformational leadership on job satisfaction, the principal's transformational leadership on work motivation; the principal's transformational leadership on performance through job satisfaction; and principal transformational leadership on teacher performance through work motivation. The population of this study was 180 teachers in 22 schools with a research sample of 124 teachers using proportional random sampling technique. The data in this study was collected using instruments consisting of principals' transformational leadership (30 items), job satisfaction (20 items), work motivation (27 items) which had been tested for validity and reliability. Meanwhile, teacher performance uses teacher documentation. The researchers analyzed the data by using path analysis. The results of the study showed that there was an effect of the principal's transformational leadership on teacher performance, job satisfaction on teacher performance, motivation on teacher performance, principal's transformational leadership on job satisfaction, principal's transformational leadership on work motivation, job satisfaction was an intermediary for the influence of principal's transformational leadership on teacher performance and work motivation is an intermediary of the influence of the principal's transformational leadership on teacher performance.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Indonesia faces the challenges of national competition in the global era that demands an increase in the quality and productivity of educated human beings <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Supardi, 2013)</ref>. Based on this statement, an effort to be done for improving the quality of human resources is education. As a determining factor for the success of development, the quality of human resources is improved through various educational programs that are carried out systematically and directed based on interests that refer to the progress of science and technology and are based on faith and devotion. Education is included in the most significant component in human existence, and it has become a requirement in order to accomplish the desired goals and objectives. As a result, in accordance with the mission of the 1945 Constitution, the government pursues education spanning from basic to higher education to educate the nation's life. The purpose of education must be rooted in the Indonesian nation's culture and in accordance with the state's foundations, as stated in Law No. 20 of 2003 concerning the national education system, Chapter 1 article 1 paragraph <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>, which states: "National Education is education rooted in the Indonesian nation's culture and based on the 1945 Constitution." This statement implies that all aspects contained in the national education system will reflect activities inspired by Pancasila and the 1945 Constitution and rooted in the culture of the Indonesian nation. Schools are a means for people to get education. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Moeheriono (2012)</ref> argues that schools in general are a small community that is a vehicle for student development where the activities in it are service processes. Schools prepare students to acquire knowledge, skills, character, increase their devotion to God Almighty so that they are able to equip themselves towards higher education as a provision for life in society. The main key in improving the quality of education is the optimization of human resources, especially teachers. To achieve the success of education in school organizations is charged with the quality of the competence of teachers as teachers who are directly responsible for student achievement. This is in accordance with Law Number 14 of 2005 concerning Teachers and Lecturers stating that teachers are professional educators with the main task of educating, teaching, guiding, directing, training, assessing, and evaluating students in early childhood education through formal education, education elementary, and secondary education. Teachers, as education specialists, are expected to be able to demonstrate their knowledge in order to improve educational quality. Because instructors are intimately involved in the learning process at school, this is the case. Teachers must be qualified and professional in order for the learning process to be of good quality. Professional instructors have specialized skills and knowledge in the field of education, allowing them to perform their duties and functions as teachers to the best of their ability <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Dessler, 2013)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Teacher Performance</head><p>Teacher performance is the ability of a teacher to carry out learning tasks at school and is responsible for students who are under his guidance by increasing student achievement or learning outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Supardi, 2013)</ref>. Therefore, teacher performance can be interpreted as a condition that shows the ability of a teacher in carrying out his duties at school and describes the existence of learning activities in order to be able to guide and educate students in achieving optimal achievement and learning outcomes. In an effort to create a professional teacher performance, the government has made regulations for the requirements to become a teacher. Article 8 of Law Number 14 of 2005 concerning teachers and lecturers states that teachers are required to have academic qualifications, competencies, educator certificates, physically and mentally healthy, and have the ability to realize national education goals. Furthermore, Article 10 paragraph 1 explains that teachers as professionals in education must have 4 competencies, namely (1) pedagogic competence, (2) personality competence, (3) social competence and (4) professional competence. Another article is article 11, paragraph <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> states that educator certificates as referred to in article 8 are given to teachers who already have the requirements for the 4 competencies mentioned above and in Chapter IV article 20 (a) regarding teachers and lecturers it is stated that the standard of teacher work performance in implementing In their professional duties, teachers are obliged to plan lessons, carry out quality learning processes and assess and evaluate learning outcomes. The main task of the teacher which is realized in teaching and learning activities is a form of teacher performance. Teacher performance is crucial for schools because it may help them achieve their objectives. The quality and amount of output, as well as work dependability, are all factors in teacher success. Teachers with a high level of performance can also generate excellent work. It is hoped that the school organization's and educational goals may be met thanks to the excellent level of performance displayed by instructors. On the other hand, if working instructors do not perform well enough to generate good work, the school organization's goals will be difficult, if not impossible, to attain.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Transformational Leadership</head><p>Teacher performance is influenced by a variety of factors, one of which is the principal's leadership. The principal's leadership is critical since it is the leader who will motivate and steer the instructors toward the achievement of the goals. This is not a simple task because the leader must understand the behavior of various teachers. According to Davis and Thomas <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Suriansyah, 2015)</ref>, the critical role of transformational leadership in building teacher professionalism necessitates a shift in focus away from administrative coaching and toward professional coaching with a focus on enhancing teacher performance in schools. Transformational leadership is a leadership model for a leader who tends to motivate subordinates to work better and place more emphasis on behavior to help transformation between individuals and organizations <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Kardata, Mahrita, &amp; Aslamiah, 2018)</ref>. This model is also very helpful for organizations from leaders to subordinates so that they are able to achieve organizational goals and can continue to make improvements. Transformational leadership is expected to encourage increased work for teachers, because good performance will be able to support the achievement of educational goals and objectives. Transformational leadership is able to empower all school resources to achieve goals. Transformational leadership has professional abilities, namely: personality, basic skills, experience, training and professional knowledge, as well as administrative and supervisory competencies. The principal's transformational leadership is believed to lead to superior performance in organizations that are facing demands for renewal and change. Bass and Avolio in their theory state that a leader can transform his subordinates through four ways called the Four I (4Is): 1) Idealized influence (charisma), 2) Intellectual stimulation, 3) Individualized consideration, 4) Inspiration motivation <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Suriansyah and Aslamiah, 2012 )</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Job Satisfaction</head><p>In addition to principal leadership factors, teacher job satisfaction also affects teacher performance. Teachers as social beings expect satisfaction in work. Satisfaction of teachers working like teachers can be accepted and appreciated by fellow teachers, teachers will also be happier when able to accept and help other teachers <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Wahjosumidjo, 2013)</ref> . Job satisfaction of a teacher is basically an individual thing, each individual has a different level of job satisfaction according to his wishes and the value system he adheres to. The satisfaction felt by the teacher is a comparison of what has been received from the results he has done with what he expected. Job satisfaction reflects a person's feelings towards his work which can be seen from the teacher's attitude towards work and everything in his work environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Effect of Principal Transformational Leadership, Job Satisfaction and Work Motivation on the Performance of Elementary School Teachers in Halong District</head><p>Luthans <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Danim, 2014)</ref> states that job satisfaction is a happy emotional state or positive emotion that comes from evaluating one's job or work experience. The more aspects of the job that match the wishes and value system of the individual, the higher level satisfaction which obtained. Thereby also on the contrary, the more the more aspects of the job that are not in accordance with the wishes and value system of the individual, the lower the level of satisfaction obtained. Job satisfaction can be viewed from two sides, from the teacher's side, job satisfaction will create a pleasant feeling in work, whereas from side organization, satisfaction work will improve performance in advancing organizational goals, such as teacher loyalty to the workplace, attitudes and behavior in work <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Suwatno &amp; Priansa, 2013)</ref>. Therefore, a teacher's job satisfaction can be closely related to the results of teacher performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Work motivation</head><p>Motivation is significant and it might be the source, conduit, or supporter of a person's behavior, causing them to work hard and enthusiastically to attain the best outcomes possible. The necessity of motivating instructors in an educational setting forces educational institutions to consider how to do so effectively. Motivation may be defined as a desire to engage in a certain activity. As a result, it can be claimed that all teachers at work have a reason for doing what they do. Teacher motivation in carrying out the task is very important for the smooth and successful teaching and learning process and in order to realize educational goals as expected. Without high work motivation in doing Duty, no will possible destination education can be achieved properly. Teachers as implementers of the mandate of the Republic of Indonesia Law No. 20 of 2003 concerning the national education system, teachers should have motivation which tall in work with direct all the expertise that is in him for the smooth implementation of the learning process and the achievement of educational goals. Teacher motivation in work should be seen from high persistence because teachers have the responsibility to provide education and knowledge to their students, teachers have will and enjoyment which deep to profession done, and are enthusiastic about getting the job done. Teachers must have a high sense of responsibility for their work, such as working hard and optimistically in carrying out their work and being able to overcome problems that occur in carrying out their duties.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHOD</head><p>This study aims to examine direct and indirect relationships between variables:influence transformational leadership of the principal on teacher performance; job satisfaction on teacher performance; motivation on teacher performance; the principal's transformational leadership on job satisfaction, the principal's transformational leadership on work motivation; the principal's transformational leadership on performance through job satisfaction; Principal transformational leadership on teacher performance through work motivation. The participants in this study were all 180 Halong District primary school teachers. Proportional random sampling was utilized as the sample method. The cronbach alpha formula was used to determine the number of samples, which totaled 124 instructors. The principal's transformational leadership (idealized Influence, Inspirational motivation, Intellectual stimulation, individual consideration), job satisfaction (intrinsic factors, extrinsic factors), and work motivation (motivational factors and maintenance factors) were all assessed using a questionnaire, while teacher performance was assessed using documentation from teachers. The information is gathered using a Likert scale that has been correlation checked for validity and reliability. By first performing the normality test, linearity test, and multicollinearity tests, the data was investigated using path analysis to identify the direct and indirect correlations between variables. In accordance with the conceptual model, the analysis used path analysis to answer the seven research hypotheses, namely: H 1 : there is a direct influence between the principal's transformational leadership on teacher performance; H 2 : there is a direct influence between job satisfaction and teacher performance; H 3 : there is a direct effect of work motivation on teacher performance; H 4 : there is a direct influence between the principal's transformational leadership on job satisfaction; H 5 : there is a direct influence between the principal's transformational leadership on work motivation; H 6 : there is no influence of the principal's transformational leadership through job satisfaction on teacher performance; and H 7 : there is an indirect effect of the principal's transformational leadership through work motivation on teacher performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1. Conceptual Relationship Model among variables</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head><p>Based on the findings of SPSS-assisted data, the coefficients of direct and indirect influence were found as described in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.  Based on Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>, the acceptance of the hypothesis in this study can be seen in Tables <ref type="table">2</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_1">3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 2. Summary of Hypothesis Testing Decisions H 1, H 2, H 3, H 4, H 5</head><p>Hypothesis p Decision H1: there is a positive and significant influence on the principal's transformational leadership on teacher performance; 0.000 Accept H2: there is a positive and significant influence on job satisfaction on teacher performance; 0.000 Accept H3: there is a positive and significant effect of work motivation on teacher performance 0.000 Accept H4: there is a positive and significant effect of the principal's transformational leadership on job satisfaction ; 0.000 Accept H5: there is a positive and significant effect of the principal's transformational leadership on motivation 0.000 Accept The results of the path analysis as can be seen in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> are used to answer the seven research hypotheses that have been formulated whose decisions are given in Table <ref type="table">2</ref> and Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">3</ref>. Table <ref type="table">2</ref> is a summary of the decisions H 1 , H 2 , H 3 , H 4 , and H 5 with a significance value criterion of less than 0.05, then the hypothesis is accepted. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">3</ref> is a summary of the decisions for testing the hypotheses H 6 and H 7 with the provisions of the Sobel test calculation that, if T count is greater than T table <ref type="bibr">(1.980)</ref>, then the hypothesis is accepted.</p><p>Based on the results of the analysis in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1,</ref><ref type="table">2</ref>, and 3, this study found a relationship between variables which can be explained as follows.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. The Direct Effect of Principal Transformational Leadership on Teacher Performance</head><p>The results of this study indicate that the principal's transformational leadership directly influences teacher performance by 0.649. This identifies that in order to improve teacher performance, it can be done by increasing the quality of the principal's transformational leadership. The leadership factor has a very important role in improving performance because effective leadership has a positive influence on the efforts of all teachers in achieving organizational goals.</p><p>Transformational leadership according to Bass (Usman, 2013) defines transformational leadership based on the influence of leaders with followers or subordinates. Transformational leadership is able to make followers feel confident, admire, loyal and honor leader, as well as have high commitment and motivation to achieve and perform higher. The element of transformational leadership of the head is the influence he has and the ability to use that influence and the consequences of that influence for the people who want to be influenced, namely teachers, employees, and other school members. Based on indicator study realized through theory Bass and Avolio <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Suriansyah, 2012)</ref> suggests that the transformational process can be seen from a number of leadership behavior patterns such as attribute charisma, idealized influence (inspirational communication), inspirational motivation (motivating by providing inspiration), intellectual stimulation and individual consideration (sensitivity).</p><p>The results of this study strengthen previous research, namely Monoyasa, Sularso, &amp; Prihatini (2017); Shafie (2016); Nurhayati &amp; Sudarsyah (2021); Rando and Mokalu (2021); Banurea and Marpuang (2019) whose research results state that transformational leadership has an effect on performance. Based on some of the results of the research above, it shows that transformational leadership is able to mobilize all existing resources in schools so that they can be empowered to be used optimally in order to achieve the goals that have been set. The current high and low performance of teachers depends on how ability head school in influence behavior teacher in carrying out the task.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. The Direct Effect of Teacher Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance</head><p>The results of this study indicate that teacher job satisfaction has a direct effect on teacher performance by 0.310. This illustrates that to improve teacher performance, it can be done by providing satisfaction for teachers at work. This study found that teacher</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Effect of Principal Transformational Leadership, Job Satisfaction and Work Motivation on the Performance of Elementary School Teachers in Halong District</head><p>performance was high due to the fulfillment of aspects in job satisfaction such as the work that was occupied in accordance with the wishes and ideals, the current income can meet the needs of life, the atmosphere in working with the principal feels like family, the influence with the principal is felt very cooperative, help each other in solving problems, there is convenience to get help from coworkers and influence with coworkers is very pleasant. Job satisfaction is a set of feelings whether or not the job is fun. A person who works in an organization brings with him a set of wants, needs, desires, and past experiences that coalesce to form job expectations. Job satisfaction shows the match between one's expectations that arise and the rewards provided by the job <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Sedarmayanti, 2018)</ref> . Stoner and Freeman's research <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Priansa, 2014)</ref> shows that job satisfaction shows a match between the expectations that arise with the rewards provided by the job, so that job satisfaction is also related to performance. Job satisfaction is a set of feelings whether or not the job is fun. A person who works in an organization brings with him a set of wants, needs, desires, and past experiences that coalesce to form performance.</p><p>The results of this study corroborate <ref type="bibr">Baron 's (2014)</ref>  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Influence Direct Motivation Work to Performance Teacher</head><p>According to the findings, work motivation has a direct effect on teacher performance of 0.479. This conclusion is logical since work motivation has a significant impact on the performance of instructors who are owned by and underpin the perpetrators. Motivation work is the encouragement that exists in a self-teacher as a result of the existence of influence that originated neither inside herself nor from the outside. The higher the motivation level, the better. Of course, the instructor's work for the work received will have an influence on the completion of the tasks completed by the teacher, resulting in good job performance. Work on motivation that is tall capable of supporting variety change and has a major impact on teacher performance. Indicators of measuring work motivation variables in this study refer to Abraham Maslow's hierarchy of needs theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Arifin, 2014)</ref> covering needs physiological needs, the need for security (safety needs), social needs (affiliation needs), the need for esteem (esteem needs), self-actualization needs. The importance of studying the effect of work motivation on teacher performance in research this based on theory Robbins (2012) stating that teacher against strong motivation will do the work seriously or work hard so that performance continues increase.</p><p>The results of this study support previous research, namely <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Bienstock &amp; Marker (2015)</ref> concluding that work motivation has a positive and significant effect to performance teacher. Thing this prove that motivation work tall one could give contribution significant to enhancement performance teachers. Other studies that can prove that work motivation has a positive and significant effect on employee performance are the results of Hasturmadi's research (2018); Wahyudi (2019); <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Barnawi (2014)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Theodora (2015)</ref> whose research results prove that work motivation has a positive and significant effect on employee performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. The Direct Effect of Principal Transformational Leadership on Teacher Job Satisfaction</head><p>Based on the interpretation of the hypothesis test, it can be seen that there is a direct influence of leadership transformational head school on teacher job satisfaction that is equal to 0.569. This illustrates that the transformational leadership that has been carried out has a positive effect on teacher satisfaction at work. According to Schemerhorn <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Anoraga, 2018)</ref> high and low satisfaction work also caused by a number of aspect, like profession that myself, supervisor (supervision), friend worker, promotion, as well as wages or wages. Satisfaction Work can also be influenced by several factors, such as compensation policies, job security, working conditions, influence with superiors, promotion and career development, leadership style, working in teams, and the employees themselves <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Dessler, 2013)</ref>. The role of transformational leadership in increasing teacher job satisfaction can be seen from the role of leadership in an organization. In this case the principal can provide opportunities for teachers to solve problems together; provide direction so that teachers can prioritize the implementation of tasks over other matters and complete their work on time; determine the solution to the problem at hand, and be able to provide examples or demonstrate the tasks that must be done. According to Colquit, LePine , and Wesson <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Getol, 2012)</ref> which states that one of the factors that increase job satisfaction is the transformational leadership factor. because with leader which capable push, provide motivation, a positive stimulus for teachers to make the teacher feel comfortable and satisfied at work or in other words supervision satisfaction, which means workers' feelings about superiors they. This research strengthens the previous research, namely <ref type="bibr">Dewi's research (2013)</ref>; Anoraga (2018); Anggraeni (2013); Dewi &amp; Subudi (2015); Ritawati (2013) who concludes that there is an influence of transformational leadership on job satisfaction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. Influence Direct Transformational Leadership Head School To Motivation Work teacher</head><p>The results of this study indicate that there are the direct effect of transformational leadership on teacher motivation is 0.619. The principal acts as a motivator both to subordinates and the surrounding environment. In addition, a leader must have inspirational motivation (inspirational motivation) where the leader has time for communicate to employee and could provide motivation to </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F. Indirect Effect of Principal Transformational Leadership through Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance</head><p>This study shows the indirect effect of transformational leadership through job satisfaction on teacher performance of 0.176. Good transformational leadership is able to create comfortable working conditions and be able to fulfill the desires of their subordinates so that subordinates will feel satisfaction at work and feel satisfaction with the leadership applied so that they strive to achieve higher and quality work performance in return for perceived job satisfaction. According to Bass <ref type="bibr">(Kardata et.al, 2018)</ref> said that making job satisfaction on the way to align the desires of the leadership to the desires and needs of teachers in achieving learning goals, namely student achievement and this can only be done on learning leadership. This is in accordance with Herzberg's opinion <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Suriansyah, 2013)</ref>  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G. There is an Indirect Effect of Principal Transformational Leadership through Work Motivation on Teacher Performance</head><p>This study shows that there is an indirect effect of transformational leadership through work motivation on teacher performance of 0.296. This proves good transformational leadership. This will encourage or motivate all teachers to be more active in their work and feel valued so that they will work optimally and ultimately the teacher's performance will increase. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Wahjosumidjo (2013 )</ref>, the capacity to encourage his employees is one of the most crucial skills a transformative leader must possess. The head of the school serves as a motivator for the subordinates and the surrounding environment. Because leadership serves as a role model and draws attention from subordinates, transformational leadership has a significant impact on boosting performance. Ideas, aspirations, and efforts will arise in terms of accomplishment motivation in order to carry out activities successfully and efficiently. A teacher must be able to improve himself as well as work motivation that is balanced in order to achieve high professional performance. The results of the study strengthen the research of Kardata, Mahrita &amp; Aslamiah (2018) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kusrini (2018)</ref> which states that work motivation in strengthening the influence of transformational leadership on teacher performance. Other research results; Bana (2016); Sujana &amp; Ardana (2020); Prayudi (2020); Anam (2020) research results state that work motivation mediates the influence of transformational leadership on employee performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Based on the results of data analysis and discussion as described above, it is concluded that there is a significant direct influence on the principal's transformational leadership, satisfaction work and work motivation on teacher performance. In addition, there is a significant indirect effect of principal transformational leadership through job satisfaction on teacher performance and there is an indirect effect transformational leadership of school principals through work motivation on teacher performance. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Effect of</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>The</head><label></label><figDesc>Effect of Principal Transformational Leadership, Job Satisfaction and Work Motivation on the Performance of Elementary School Teachers in Halong District</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .The</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Results of the analysis of the influence among variables</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Principal Transformational Leadership, Job Satisfaction and Work Motivation on the Performance of Elementary School Teachers in Halong District The Effect of Principal Transformational Leadership, Job Satisfaction and Work Motivation on the Performance of Elementary School Teachers in Halong District The Effect of Principal Transformational Leadership, Job Satisfaction and Work Motivation on the Performance of Elementary School Teachers in Halong District</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 : Summary of Pathway Analysis Results</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Substructural 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Transformational Leadership, Job Satisfaction, Work Motivation on Teacher Performance</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Path Coefficient</cell><cell>T</cell><cell>p</cell></row><row><cell>Transformational leadership</cell><cell>0.649</cell><cell>9,004</cell><cell>0.000</cell></row><row><cell>Job satisfaction</cell><cell>0.310</cell><cell>7,095</cell><cell>0.001</cell></row><row><cell>Work motivation</cell><cell>0.479</cell><cell>4,439</cell><cell>0.000</cell></row><row><cell>Substructural 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Transformational Leadership on Job Satisfaction</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Path Coefficient</cell><cell>T</cell><cell>p</cell></row><row><cell>Transformational leadership</cell><cell>0.569</cell><cell>40.528</cell><cell>0.000</cell></row><row><cell>Substructural 3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Transformational Leadership on Work Motivation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Path Coefficient</cell><cell>T</cell><cell>P</cell></row><row><cell>Transformational leadership</cell><cell>0.619</cell><cell>38,145</cell><cell>0.019</cell></row></table><note><p>At state elementary schools in Halong District. The influence between variables is formulated into a path analysis model, both direct and indirect.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 3 . Summary of Hypothesis Testing Decisions H 6 and H 7</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Hypothesis</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>research study and<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Indrawati (2013)</ref> in which both studies concluded that job satisfaction will affect performance. The results of this study are in line with Hapsari's research (2020); Wahyudi &amp; Tupti (2019); Arifin, Barlian &amp; Hidayat (2018); Juniantara &amp; Riana (2015) concluded that job satisfaction is a predictor of performance, because job satisfaction has a moderate correlation with performance.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>The Effect of Principal Transformational Leadership, Job Satisfaction and Work Motivation on the Performance of Elementary School Teachers in Halong District subordinates</head><label></label><figDesc>to do their job to the maximum. According to<ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Wahjosumidjo (2013)</ref>, one of the important competencies that must be possessed by a transformational leader is the ability to motivate his subordinates. Leaders also motivate teachers to improve the competence and careers of teachers by providing opportunities for teachers to take part in various trainings or trainings develop education more tall. Leader with His sincerity motivates teachers to work at a minimum of reinforcement and praise fairly and equitably and most importantly a leader is always open in every criticism and suggestion or in dealing with any existing problems. Against the attitude and nature of the leadership will certainly make the motivation of the teacher becomes tall. Several studies that are in line with the influence of leadership on motivation are Kumalasari (2019);</figDesc><table><row><cell>Dharmawan (2020); Ruslan (2019); Yanti</cell></row><row><cell>(2019); stated that the principal's transformational leadership had a positive effect on teacher work motivation. This study also</cell></row><row><cell>strengthens previous research, namely the research of Savitri (2014); Tucunan (2014); Nurhuda, Sardjono &amp; (2020)</cell></row><row><cell>who stated that transformational leadership affects employee work motivation.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>which says that job satisfaction and job dissatisfaction are two different things. Herzberg categorizes conditions that impact a person's job satisfaction into two categories: statisticians and disstatisfiers. Group statisfiers are also known as intrinsic factors, job content, and motivators. Extrinsic factor, employment context, and hygiene factor are some words used to describe the disstatisfiers group. Work performance, responsibilities, the work itself, knowledge and introduction to work, and self-development are all variables or circumstances that have been demonstrated to be sources of happiness. Disstatisfiers are elements that have been demonstrated to cause unhappiness in the workplace, such as corporate policies and administration, supervisory practices, pay, interpersonal effects, and working environment. This research reinforces Riadi's research study (2017) ; Ermsari (2018); Gani (2020); which states that the transformational leadership variable can be through the intervening variable, namely job satisfaction in influencing the level of teacher performance. This is also in line with the research results of Pambudi, Mukzam &amp; Nurtjahjono (2016);<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alam &amp; Monica (2015)</ref> stating that job satisfaction can be a mediator of transformational leadership on employee performance.</figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Leadership Style and Work Motivation on Employee Performance With Job Satisfaction as an Intervening Variable</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Alam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Monica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Management and Business</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="242" to="265" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The effect of transformational leadership on employee performance with motivation as an intervening variable</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Anam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020. 2020</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Maulana Malik Ibrahim State Islamic University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>PhD Diss</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of transformational leadership on employee job satisfaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Anggraeni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Santosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Tec</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic &amp; Business Dynamics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Occupational Psychology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Anoraga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>PT Rineka Cipta</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Motivation, Achievement, and Job Satisfaction on Employee Performance at Sumbersari Public Health Center, Rowokangkung District, Lumajang Regency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Arifin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Barlian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Hidayat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings Progress Conference</title>
		<meeting>Progress Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018. 2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="480" to="487" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Arifin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Ethics and the Educational Profession. Yogyakarta: Ar-ruzz Media</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Transformational Leadership and Physical Work Environment on Employee Performance With Work Motivation as a Mediating Variable (Study on Regional Drinking Water Company (Pdam), Kendari City)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bana</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Business and Management Urnal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Teacher Perceptions About Transformational Leadership Of Madrasah Head With Teacher Performance At The Madrasah Tsanawiyah Negeri Kabanjahe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Banurea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Marpaung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Almufida: Journal of Islamic Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The influence of empowerment and motivation on employee performance (study on employees of CV. Catur Perkasa Manunggal)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Barnawi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Brawijaya University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Doctoral dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Job Satisfaction and Teachers Performance An Emperical Study at Higher Learning Institution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">&amp;</forename><surname>Baron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Psychological Research. A Review. International</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="200" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transformational leadership and employee performance: The role of identification, engagement and proactive personality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">&amp;</forename><surname>Bienstock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Marker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.Ijhm.2018.06.014</idno>
		<ptr target="Https://Doi.Org/10.1016/j.Ijhm.2018.06.014" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Hospitality Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Leadership Motivation and Group Effectiveness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Danim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Rineka Cipta</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Relationship between Principal Transformational Leadership, School Climate and Motivation on Teacher Performance through Work Motivation of State Elementary School Teachers in Banjarmasin City</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Dharmawan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="Http://Digilib.Ulm.Ac.Id/Archive/Digital/Catalogue.Php?Page=1&amp;key=kepemimanan" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Human Resource Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dessler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>PT Index Gramedia Group</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Transformational Leadership on Job Satisfaction and Turnover Intention in CV</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nknc</forename><surname>Dewi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Subudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gita Karya Persada Denpasar. E-Journal of Unud Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4219" to="4244" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The influence of transformational leadership style on employee job satisfaction and organizational commitment at PT. KPM</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Dewi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Management, Business Strategy, And Entrepreneurship</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="116" to="125" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Influence of Leadership Style, Work Commitment, Job Satisfaction and Motivation on State Mandrasah Aliyah</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ermsari</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">Teachers in Banjarmasin City. ..(Online PDF</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<ptr target="Workhttp://Digilib.Ulm.Ac.Id/Archive/Digital/Catalogue.=satisfaction-work" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Transformational Leadership Style and Job Satisfaction on Employee Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celebes Equilibrum Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Getol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Good Leadership vs Bad Leadership. Jakarta: Elex Media</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Kindergarten Principals Transformational Leadership, Job Satisfaction, and Work Spirit on Kindergarten Teacher Performance in the Rainbow Gugus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Usa</forename><surname>Hapsari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="Http://Digilib.Ulm.Ac.Id/Archive/Digital/Catalogue.Php?Page=1&amp;key=kinerja" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Banjar Masin Selatan District</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Transformational Leadership, Motivation, Compensation and Job Satisfaction on Work Performance of Employees in Jumantono District, Karangayar Regency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hasturmadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Slamet Riyadi Faculty of Surakarta</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Journal of the Slamet Riyadi Faculty of Surakarta</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of job satisfaction on employee performance and customer satisfaction at a private hospital in Denpasar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Indrawati</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Indrawati, AD</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 2013. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="142" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Journal of Management</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of motivation and job satisfaction on the performance of cooperative employees in Denpasar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Juniantara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Riana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economics and Business</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="611" to="628" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Udayana University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Relationship Between Transformational Leadership And Work Motivation With The Teacher&apos;s Performance Of Public Elementary School In South Banjarmasin District, Indonesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kardata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mahrita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aslamiah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Education Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Principal Transformational Leadership on Teacher Work Motivation at the Integrated Islamic Elementary School (SDIT) Bina Amal Semarang</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kumalasari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Managerial-Journal of Management Science Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Relationship Between Perceptions of Transformational Leadership Style, Work Climate and Work Motivation on the Performance of State Senior High School Teachers in Banjarmasin City</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kusrini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Scientific Development and Research (IJSDR)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">142</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018. 1901023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Competency-Based Performance Measurement. Jakarta: Raja Grafindo Persada</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Moeheriono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Principal&apos;s Transformational Leadership Style on Elementary School Teacher Performance with Teacher Motivation and Innovation as Intervening Variables at the Administrative City of Jember. relation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Monoyasa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sularso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Prihatini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JOURNAL OF ECONOMICS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="335" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quality Assurance of Transformational Leadership in Education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nurhayati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sudarsyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Research of Educational Administration and Management</title>
		<meeting>the 4th International Conference on Research of Educational Administration and Management</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">526</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="80" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Transformational Leadership Style, Work Discipline, Work Environment on Employee Motivation and Performance at Anwar Medika Hospital Jl</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nurhuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sardjono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Purnamasari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Raya Bypass Krian Km. 33 Balongbendo-Sidoarjo. IqtishadE</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">2622-6367</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2020. 2019</date>
			<publisher>ONLINE)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Transformational Leadership Style on Employee Performance Through Employee Job Satisfaction as a Mediation Variable (Study on Employees of PT Telkom Indonesia Witel Jatim Selatan Malang)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Pambudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mukzam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Nurtjahjono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ge</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Administration (JAB)|Vol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016-10-01">2016. 1 October 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Transformational Leadership Style on Employee Performance With Work Motivation as an Intervening Variable (Study on Employees at Binjai City Development)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Prayudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Teacher Performance and Professionalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Priansa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Alphabeta</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Bandung</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The correlation between transformational leadership factors, work commitment and job satisfaction on the performance of mathematics teachers at SMAN 12 Samarinda</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Riadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Administration Quality</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">2355-0333</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="216" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2017. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>e-ISS</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Transformational Leadership and Organizational Culture on Job Satisfaction and Employee Performance of PT. Jamsostek (Persero) Surabaya Branch. die</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ritawati</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economics and Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Organizational Behavior (First)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Robbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Salemba Empat</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Effect of Leadership and Teacher Satisfaction on Teacher Performance with Work Motivation as a Mediation (study at SMAN Se Tanah Bumbu District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ruslan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="Http://Digilib.Ulm.Ac.Id/Archive/Digital/Catalogue.Php?Page=1&amp;key=KepemiMpinan" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of transformational leadership style on the work motivation of nurses in inpatient installations (IRNA) ii RSUD dr. Poor Saiful Anwar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Savitri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PSIKOVIDYA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Human Resource Management, Bureaucratic Reform and Civil Service Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sedarmayanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>PT Refika Aditama</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Bandung</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influence of transformational leadership on employees innovative work behavior in sustainable organizations: Test of mediation and moderation processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shafie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/su11061594</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3390/su11061594" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sustainability (Switzerland)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Role of Work Motivation Mediates the Effect of Transformational Leadership on Employee Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Npasp</forename><surname>Sujana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ardana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">E-Journal of Management Udayana University</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020. 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Teacher performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Supardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Rajawali Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Towards Effective Principals from Theoretical To Practical</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Suriansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aslamiah</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>House of Knowledge</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Solo</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Principals, Teachers, Parents and Community Leadership Strategies in Shaping Student Character</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Suriansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Horizon</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Educational Profession &quot;Perfective Professional Teacher. Depok: PT. Raja Grafindo Persada</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Suriansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Priansa</forename><surname>Suwatno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Human Resource Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Alphabeta</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Bandung</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of work motivation on the performance of employees of PT. Prosperous Motor Glorious</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Theodora</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Agora</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="195" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Transformational Leadership on Employee Motivation and Performance (Case Study at PT</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tucunan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Supartha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Juniantara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Iw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Riana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pandawa. E-Jurnal of Economics and Business</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="533" to="550" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Udayana University</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning Leadership Strategy Welcoming Curriculum implementation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Usman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Education Horizon. No</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">XXXI</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principal Leadership: A Theoretical Review and Its Problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wahjosumidjo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Rajawali Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Yogyakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Organizational Culture, Motivation and Job Satisfaction on Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wahyudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Tupti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific Journal of Masters in Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Effect of Discipline and Motivation on Employee Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wahyudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://ojspustek.org/index.php/SJR/issue/view/8" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Principal Leadership, Job Satisfaction and Motivation on Teachers at SMPN Kurau District. (Online PDF)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">There is an Open Access article, distributed under the term of the Creative Commons Attribution -Non Commercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>which permits remixing, adapting and building upon the work for non-commercial use, provided the original work is properly cited</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
