<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Use of Structural Equation Models in Interpreting Regression Equations Including Suppressor and Enhancer Variables</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mcfatter</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Denver</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Use of Structural Equation Models in Interpreting Regression Equations Including Suppressor and Enhancer Variables</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T17:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>It is shown that the usual interpretation of "suppressor" effects in a multiple regression equation assumes that the correlations among variables have been generated by a particular structural (causal) model, namely, Conger's (1974)  two-factor model. A distinction is drawn between the technical definition of "suppression," which is more fittingly labelled enhancement, and suppression as the appropriate interpretation of a regression equation exhibiting enhancement when that equation has been gen- erated by the two-factor model. It is demonstrated that a number of models can generate enhancement but cannot sensibly be interpreted in terms of the measuring, removing, or suppressing of irrelevant or invalid variance. How a regression equation is interpreted thus depends critically on the structural model deemed appropriate.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The occurrence of what has loosely been termed &amp;dquo;suppression&amp;dquo; is frequently a source of dismay and/or confusion among researchers using some form of regression analysis to analyze their data. It has been called &amp;dquo;quasi-paradoxical,&amp;dquo; &amp;dquo;ambiguous,&amp;dquo; &amp;dquo;uninterpretable,&amp;dquo; and probably other more colorful names as well. This paper will show that the usual interpretation of &amp;dquo;suppressor&amp;dquo; effects in the simple two-predictor case implicitly assumes a unique causal model-namely, the two-factor model explicated by Conger <ref type="bibr">(1974)</ref> and discussed below as Model I; however, the pattern of rela- tionships among correlations and regression weights which are used to technically define and diagnose &amp;dquo;suppression&amp;dquo; can be generated by a large number of causal structures for which the notion of suppression as the measuring, removing, or subtracting of irrelevant variance is inappropriate and misleading. Thus, the interpretation of any obtained &amp;dquo;suppressor&amp;dquo; effects (and, in fact, any regression equation) depends critically upon the causal structural model that is at least implicitly assumed to un- derlie the data. In most cases, successful interpretation of the regression situation involves estimating and interpreting the parameters of this structural model (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Duncan, 1975;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Heise, 1975;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">or Johnston, 1972,</ref> for introductory treatments).</p><p>It will be very helpful in the following discussion to distinguish between the technical definition of &amp;dquo;suppression&amp;dquo; (provided by several authors, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Cohen &amp; Cohen, 1975;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Conger, 1974)</ref>, referring to a pattern of relationships among correlations and regression weights, and the way variables operate in the particular causal model which is usually assumed in discussions of suppression. For reasons which should become apparent, all variables which conform to the more general technical criteria will be called enhancers, while the terms suppressors and suppression will be reserved for those particular enhancers which also conform to the two-factor model. Much of the difficulty in interpreting &amp;dquo;sup-pressor&amp;dquo; effects stems from the failure to make this distinction or to consider alternative models which might give rise to what will be called enhancement phenomena.</p><p>This paper will explore some of the variety of models which can and cannot lead to enhancement in the simple two-predictor case and, in so doing, will attempt to clarify how the occurrence of en- hancement can be helpful in interpreting a regression equation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Three Types of Enhancement</head><p>There are a number of slightly varying technical definitions of &amp;dquo;suppression&amp;dquo; (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Cohen &amp; Cohen, 1975;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Conger, 1974;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Darlington, 1968;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Lord &amp; Novick, 1968</ref>); however, the variations are rela- tively minor and in no way affect the argument of this paper. Since Conger's <ref type="bibr">(1974)</ref> definition is the most general, it will be used for the definition of enhancer variables: An ... [enhancer] variable is defined to be a variable which increases the predictive validity of another variable (or set of variables) by its inclusion in a regression equation. This variable is an ...</p><p>[enhancer] only for those variables whose regression weights are increased. (pp. <ref type="bibr">[36]</ref><ref type="bibr">[37]</ref> In the two-predictor case, let Xo be the criterion with predictors X, and X2, reflected if necessary so as to make all correlations with Xo positive. If X2 is arbitrarily designated as an enhancer, the above definition holds in the population if and only if the following condition holds: where {301 2 its the standardized regression coefficient for X, and Q., is the correlation between Xo and X,. Henceforth, {301 2 and {302 will be abbreviated as (30, and P02. There are three distinct types of enhancement which can be derived from Condition 1 by substituting the equation for {301o</p><p>into Condition 1:</p><p>The defining characteristics of the three varieties are summarized below, following <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Cohen and Cohen (1975)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Classical Enhancement</head><p>If 602 = 0 and Qo~ and 612 are greater than zero, then (30, &gt; Qo,, satisfying Condition 1; and classical enhancement is said to obtain. Notice that under classical enhancement, (J02 is negative even though e02 is zero, since Downloaded from the Digital Conservancy at the University of Minnesota, <ref type="url" target="http://purl.umn.edu/93227">http://purl.umn.edu/93227</ref>. May be reproduced with no cost by students and faculty for academic use. Non-academic reproduction requires payment of royalties through the Copyright Clearance Center, <ref type="url" target="http://www.copyright.com/">http://www.copyright.com/</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Net Enhancement</head><p>When all correlations are positive and yet /3oz is negative (implying that Q02 -QOIQ12 &lt; 0), then again, <ref type="bibr">(30,</ref><ref type="bibr">&gt; Qol,</ref><ref type="bibr"></ref> satisfying Condition 1; and net enhancement is said to obtain.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cooperative Enhancement</head><p>When Qoi and Q02 are both positive and yet Q12 is negative, then once again, (30, &gt; Qo,, satisfying Condition 1; and cooperative enhancement is said to obtain. Notice that under cooperative en- hancement, both (30, and (302 must be positive.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Interpretation of Enhancement</head><p>Lord and Novick's (1968) account of suppression expresses implicitly the model usually applied in interpreting enhancement phenomena. They write, &amp;dquo;In effect, they [suppressor variables] represent some aspect of the predictor variables that is not related to the criterion but that functions to 'suppress' or subtract out this invalid component and thus to make the original predictor more valid&amp;dquo; (pp. <ref type="bibr">[271]</ref><ref type="bibr">[272]</ref>. Notice that in this account, variation in a predictor, say X,, is presumed to arise from two sources-one relevant to the criterion and the other irrelevant or invalid. Furthermore, variation in the suppressor, X2, arises mainly from that source which is irrelevant to the criterion; thus, ~2 con- tributes indirectly to prediction by removing or suppressing the irrelevant variation in X,.</p><p>Conger (1974) expresses this two-factor suppression model formally and shows how variation in the parameters of the model lead to the three types of enhancement defined above. What he and others fail to point out is that although enhancement phenomena which are generated by the two-fac- tor model can be sensibly interpreted in terms of the suppression of irrelevant or invalid variance, there are a number of other models which can be expected to generate data which exhibit all three kinds of enhancement but which cannot be interpreted in terms of suppression or even relevant and irrelevant variance. Moreover, there is nothing about enhancement in general, or one of the three types in particular, which invariably signals some underlying structure. This fact can be made more apparent by examining Conger's two-factor model as well as some other models which can give rise to enhancement, but it is important to understand at the outset the rationale and strategy for examining how differing structural equation (causal) models can generate the same multiple regression equation and that the interpretation of the regression equation depends critically upon which model is believed to be appropriate. Briefly, it is well known that simply knowing the correlation matrix (and hence the regression co- efficients) among three variables-Xo, X,, and X2-is not sufficient to allow inference of the causal relationships among the variables. Correlations and regression coefficients are, in this sense, causally uninformative. If, however, one is willing to postulate or hypothesize a causal model in the form of a set of structural equations, each of which represents a causal rather than a mere empirical asso- ciation, that model can then be shown to impose a very definite structure on the correlation (or co- variance) matrix of variables in the model. If this structure is restrictive enough, it will be possible to estimate the parameters of the model from the values in the correlation matrix. However, a large number of models will always be consistent with the actual values in the correlation matrix and the re- gression equation derived from it, so that how the regression equation is interpreted depends on which model is deemed appropriate.</p><p>Since enhancement has been defined above in terms of patterns in the correlation matrix, our strategy will be to postulate some structural models along with content examples to see the kinds of models which can and cannot generate enhancement and how they might be interpreted.</p><p>Model I-The Two-Factor Model</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> shows Conger's two-factor model, but in the form of a path diagram. T and S are un- correlated latent variables which are measured by Xo, X,, and X2 with measurement errors eo, e i, and e2, respectively, where E(e,) = E(e,e,) = 0; i, j = 0, 1, 2; and i =1= j. The observed criterion, Xo, is assumed to measure only T, while Xi and X2 measure both T and S. T and S are assumed to be uncorrelated with each other; hence Xo and S are uncorrelated. It will be assumed, for convenience, that all variables including S and T have been standardized to mean and variance of 0 and 1.1 The structural equations which correspond to Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> are Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> Path diagram for Model I 'Standardizing all variables except measurement errors and disturbance terms will be done routinely throughout this paper. It simplifies the algebra considerably, but does not affect the fundamental arguments made. The a's and b's represent structural parameters and have the properties of orthogonal factor loadings or standardized regression coefficients in Equation Set 5. If the factor model of Equation Set 5 is assumed, the unique entries in the correlation matrix of the observed variables ~0,~1, and X are Maintaining the earlier convention requiring eo, and eo2 to be positive, the direction of T is chosen so as to make ao, and hence a i, positive. It should be clear from an examination of the cor- relation matrix that classical enhancement occurs only when a2 = 0 and b,b2 &gt; 0. In Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> this simply means there is no arrow connecting T to X2.</p><p>Conger (1974) analyzes the other two types of enhancement from the standpoint of the two-factor model to show that net enhancement will occur whenever a2 &lt; al (aia2+ bib2); and cooperative en- hancement, whenever a,a2 + b,b2 &lt; 0, which implies that b, and b2 are of opposite sign. Example. Most discussions of suppression supply an example similar to Darlington's (1968):</p><p>A typical example in which prediction is improved by [suppression] ... might be a situation in which a test of reading speed is used in conjunction with a speeded history achievement test to predict some external criterion of knowledge of history. Since the history test is contaminated by reading speed, assigning a negative weight to the reading speed test would help to correct for the disadvantage suffered by a student with low reading speed who is competing with faster readers. (p. 163) In Darlington's example, T and S become, respectively, the latent variables true knowledge of history and true reading speed; and Xo, X 1, and XZ are, respectively, &amp;dquo;some external criterion of knowledge of history,&amp;dquo; history achievement score, and reading speed score. The &amp;dquo;contamination&amp;dquo; Darlington refers to is represented by the arrow from S to Xi in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> or the structural parameter, b,, in Equation Set 5. While the specification of no correlation between T and S is somewhat questionable in Darling- ton's example, it appears that the basic structure is that of Conger's two-factor model. It should also be apparent that the notion that enhancers can remove or suppress irrelevant vari- ance is quite consistent with the two-factor model. That is, variation in S has no effect whatever on T or Xo and is therefore a source of variation in Xi which is irrelevant to T or Xo. Consequently, a negative regression weight attached to X2.may be thought of as removing or suppressing irrelevant variance in X,. There are, however, structural models other than the two-factor model which can give rise to enhancement, but for which the notions of irrelevant variance and suppression are inappropriate.</p><p>Model II-Enhancers that Do Not Suppress Another example may prove helpful in thinking about situations where interpreting en- hancement as suppression will be quite misleading.</p><p>Example. Suppose one were interested in predicting the number of errors made by assembly-line workers as a function of IQ and Intolerance of Boredom scores. Let Xo be number of errors, Xi be Intolerance of Boredom score, and X2 be IQ score. If one obtained sample correlations of roi = .3535, ro2 = 0, and r12 = .707; noted that this was a case of classical enhancement; and relied on the usual discussions of suppression, one might be tempted to conclude that IQ was totally irre- levant to the number of assembly-line errors made, but did measure precisely that aspect of In- tolerance of Boredom which is also irrelevant to the number of errors made. This is the interpretation one would make were the two-factor model the structure underlying these variables. The conclusion does not seem to lead to much insight in this situation, however; and the frus- tration generated by attempting to interpret cases of enhancement like this as suppression no doubt contributes to a good deal of the confusion and reluctance in interpreting so-called suppression effects. Model II. Consider the simple case in which no measurement error is allowed; subsequently, this constraint will be relaxed. Suppose that Xo, Xi, andX2 (all measured without error) are causally reiated in the popuiation as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>. The structural equations which correspond to Model II are (again assuming Xo, X,, and X2 are all standardized): where u and v are stochastic disturbance terms representing all sources of variation not otherwise in- cluded in the model with E(u) = E(v) = E(uv) = 0. The population correlation matrix generated by the structure represented in Equation Set 7 is Notice first that all the variance in X, is causally relevant to Xo and that all the variance in X2 is causally relevant to both Xo and X,. Nonetheless, it is easy to show that all three kinds of en- hancement can occur in this model. Classical Enhancement. Fixing e02 = 0 requires that b3 = -blb2, while en &gt; 0 implies b2 &gt; 0. Substituting these conditions into the equation for Q., yields poi = b,(1 -~2~). Since it is desired that pot &gt; 0, then bl &gt; 0. Thus, when b, and b2 are positive and b3 = -b,b2, classical enhancement will ob- tain. For example, let b, = b2 =.707 and b3 = -.50. The population correlations are then the same as those in our example above, Qo, = .3535, e02 = 0, and 512 = .707. Notice that although the correlation between Xo and X2 is zero, the standardized regression weight for X2 will be equal to b3, which is negative. Moreover, there is no sense in which X2 can be said to be subtracting or suppressing irrelevant or invalid variance in Xi. The negative weight forX2 simply represents the fact that ~2 in this model has a direct negative effect on Xo, despite its exactly compensating positive influence on Xo through XI.</p><p>If Model II is adopted in interpreting the above example, one does not attempt to sort out some elusive aspect of Intolerance of Boredom that is related to number of errors but not IQ. Instead one concludes that IQ does, as might be expected, negatively influence the number of errors; however, that influence is exactly compensated for by the positive influence of IQ through Intolerance of Bore- dom on the number of errors made. Given the substantive nature of the example, this conclusion seems more appropriate, although this appropriateness clearly rests both on prior beliefs about what reasonable relationships among the three variables would be and on the inability to construct mean- ingful latent variables in the two-factor model.</p><p>It is important to realize that in the foregoing, no objective criteria have been suggested for de- ciding between Model I and Model II. Both models could conceivably have generated the correlation matrix which produced classical enhancement. In general, it will always be the case that several al- ternative models will describe one's data equally well, and considerations above and beyond the data itself must be used to decide among them. The crucial point is that the models are very different, and yet both can generate all three kinds of enhancement. They are not superficially different yet formally equivalent ways of saying the same thing. The two models are fundamentally different; and if Model II is the &amp;dquo;correct&amp;dquo; model, then it is nonsensical to interpret the obtained enhancer effect as sup- pressing invalid or irrelevant variance as one might do if Model I were appropriate.</p><p>Net and Cooperative Enhancement. Consideration of Equation Set 8 shows that both net and cooperative enhancement can also occur when Model II is assumed. A little algebra reveals that the requirements for net enhancement are that -b,b2 &lt; b3 &lt; 0 and b,, b2 &lt; 0, while those for cooperative enhancement are that -b,b2 &lt; b3 &lt; -bl/b2, where b2 &lt; 0 and bI, b3 &gt; 0. It has been assumed so far in Model II that Xo, Xl, andX2 are measured without error. Allowing measurement error into the model complicates the analysis a bit but does not change the fun- damental conclusions about the possibility of enhancement. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">3</ref> shows how Model II is changed when Xo, X,, and X2 are presumed to be fallible measures of three latent (true) variables, T, S, and R, respectively. Again, for convenience, all variables including T, S, and R are assumed standardized. It is apparent from Equation Set 12 that the requirements for classical and cooperative en- hancement in Model III are the same as for Model II. Some algebra shows that net enhancement will occur in Model III when and b,, b2 &lt; 0. Since the conditions for enhancement in Model III are not substantially different from those of Model II, the interpretation of the two cases is similar. Clearly, the presence or absence of measurement error in a set of variables does not in general affect whether it is reasonable to think about enhancer effects as removing or subtracting irrelevant variance.</p><p>There are a number of possible sfructural models in the two-predictor case, other than the ones discussed so far, which are capable of generating enhancement phenomena. For example, a slight change can be made in the two-factor Model I, and T can be allowed to be influenced by S. This would amount to adding an arrow from S to T and a disturbance to T in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> and/or simply add- ing another equation, T = cS + u, to the system of Equation Set 5.</p><p>It can be shown in the same way as has been shown in Models I to III that all three kinds of en- hancement can occur in this revised Model I. However, if T is allowed to be influenced by S, then S is not an irrelevant or invalid component of T and X,; and once again, it becomes impossible to inter- pret enhancement as the suppression of irrelevant variance.</p><p>These considerations should make it plain that it is only under a very special set of circumstances that enhancement can meaningfully be interpreted as having anything to do with irrelevant or invalid variance, and this conclusion holds a fortiori in the case of more than two predictors. Despite the fact that the presence of enhancement could not help us decide among the foregoing models, its occur- rence is not useless information; for there are models which cannot lead to enhancement and could thus be rejected when evidence of enhancement is found. To see this, consider Model IV in  It is impossible for any form of enhancement to occur in this model. It is easiest to show this for all kinds of enhancement by using the necessary and sufficient Condition 1, where the directions of X, and X2 are always chosen so as to make Qol and Q02 positive. From this con- dition we have that Since the quantity in brackets is always positive and less than 1 and (ac + bo)bl is always positive and less than 1, the inequality can never hold and enhancement cannot occur.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>The foregoing analysis may be considered as an argument to the effect that the numbers ob- tained by calculating regression and correlation coefficients are substantively uninterpretable apart from at least an implicit structural model. A negative regression weight for X2 means very different things, depending on whether Model I, II, or some other model is appropriate. Consequently, it is often more informative to specify explicitly a structural model and to attempt to estimate its parameters. Note that while we have analyzed how various structural models can or cannot generate a par- ticular pattern of correlations and regression weights (i.e., enhancement), the same kind of analysis could be applied to any pattern of obtained coefficients.</p><p>It sometimes happens that it is impossible to estimate the parameters of the structural model be- lieved to underlie the observed data because there is not enough information in the observed co- variances among variables to provide unique estimates of all the structural parameters. When this is the case, the model is said to be underidentified. All of the models examined except Model II fall into this category. This fact, however, suggests the possibility of a situation in which the simple knowledge that enhancement was occurring could be helpful information despite the multiplicity of </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Downloaded from the Digital Conservancy at the University of Minnesota, http://purl.umn.edu/93227. May be reproduced with no cost by students and faculty for academic use. Non-academic reproduction requires payment of royalties through the Copyright Clearance Center, http://www.copyright.com/</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Downloaded from the Digital Conservancy at the University of Minnesota, http://purl.umn.edu/93227. May be reproduced with no cost by students and faculty for academic use. Non-academic reproduction requires payment of royalties through the Copyright Clearance Center, http://www.copyright.com/</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2 Path diagram for Model II</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Downloaded from the Digital Conservancy at the University of Minnesota, http://purl.umn.edu/93227. May be reproduced with no cost by students and faculty for academic use. Non-academic reproduction requires payment of royalties through the Copyright Clearance Center, http://www.copyright.com/</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Downloaded</head><label></label><figDesc>from the Digital Conservancy at the University of Minnesota, http://purl.umn.edu/93227. May be reproduced with no cost by students and faculty for academic use. Non-academic reproduction requires payment of royalties through the Copyright Clearance Center, http://www.copyright.com/ Model ill-Including Measurement Error</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3 Path diagram for Model III</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 4.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>F igure 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Path diagram for Model IV Downloaded from the Digital Conservancy at the University of Minnesota, http://purl.umn.edu/93227. May be reproduced with no cost by students and faculty for academic use. Non-academic reproduction requires payment of royalties through the Copyright Clearance Center, http://www.copyright.com/</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Downloaded from the Digital Conservancy at the University of Minnesota, http://purl.umn.edu/93227. May be reproduced with no cost by students and faculty for academic use. Non-academic reproduction requires payment of royalties through the Copyright Clearance Center, http://www.copyright.com/</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Downloaded from the Digital Conservancy at the University of Minnesota, http://purl.umn.edu/93227. May be reproduced with no cost by students and faculty for academic use. Non-academic reproduction requires payment of royalties through the Copyright Clearance Center, http://www.copyright.com/</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>The author wishes to thank <rs type="person">Harry F. Gollob</rs> and <rs type="person">Betty B. Rossman</rs> for their helpful comments on an earlier draft of this paper.</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>where eo, ei, and e2 are measurement errors with E(ei) = E(e,e,) = 0, ij = 0, 1, 2; and i ~ j. The dis- turbances-u and v-have zero means and are uncorrelated with each other and the errors of mea- surement. Solving Equation Set 9 to eliminate T and S yields</p><p>The population correlation between Xo and X, from this model is Qol = ao [aib2 (b,b2 + b3) + a,b 10,2]. Since Sand R are standardized, we have from the last equation in Equation Set 9 that av2 =1 1 -b22. Thus the equation for Q., may be written The population correlations amongXo, X,, and X2 are A comparison of the correlations in Equation Set 12 with those in Equation Set 8 reveals the effect of measurement error on the observable correlations. If there is no measurement error, all a's equal unity and the correlations in Equation Set 12 become precisely those of the error-free model.</p><p>The direction of the latent variables can always be chosen so as to make ao, a,, and a2 positive; and since all variables except the disturbances and measurement errors are standardized, ao, al, and a2 2 are equal to the square roots of the reliabilities of Xo, Xi, and X2. Thus, the correlation matrix for Model III will be exactly the same as that for Model II except that each correlation is attenuated due to the presence of measurement error. This model is similar in some respects to Model I and the revised Model I mentioned earlier. The structural equations of the model are with E(u) = E(e,) = 0 and all covariances among measurement errors and the disturbance equal to zero. Solving Equation Set 14 to end up with only observables on the left side, we have</p><p>The population correlations amongXo, Xi, andX2 that would be generated by Model IV are Downloaded from the Digital Conservancy at the University of Minnesota, <ref type="url" target="http://purl.umn.edu/93227">http://purl.umn.edu/93227</ref>. May be reproduced with no cost by students and faculty for academic use. Non-academic reproduction requires payment of royalties through the Copyright Clearance Center, <ref type="url" target="http://www.copyright.com/">http://www.copyright.com/</ref> models that could generate it. Model IV, like Models I and III, is underidentified as it stands. The fact that it can be shown to disallow any kind of enhancement indicates, however, that even under- identified models may sometimes be profitably examined in light of one's data. If, for example, one had reason to believe that either a structure like Model I (or the revised Model I mentioned earlier or</p><p>Model IV) underlay one's data, then the occurrence of enhancement (over and above what might be attributed to sampling fluctuations) could allow one to reject the latter model. The situations in which the general concept of enhancement could be helpful in this manner would perhaps be rather rare; nonetheless, with underidentified models, any help at all is unusual.</p><p>Author's Address </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Applied multiple regression/correlation analysis for the behavioral sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<publisher>Halsted Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A revised definition for suppressor variables: A guide to their identification and interpretation. Educational and Psychological Measurement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Conger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="46" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple regression in psychological research and practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Darlington</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="182" />
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to structural equation models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Duncan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Causal analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Heise</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<publisher>Wiley-Interscience</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Johnston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Econometric methods</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Statistical theories of mental test scores</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lord</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Novick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Reading, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
