<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Springer Texts in Statistics</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Ralph</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Mueller</surname></persName>
							<email>rmueller@gwis2.circ.gwu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">George</forename><surname>Casella</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><surname>Fienberg</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ingram</forename><surname>Olkin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Francine</forename><surname>Mcneill</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Educational Leadership Graduate School of Education and Human Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The George Washington University Washington</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20052</postCode>
									<region>DC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Statistics Carnegie</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Biometrics Unit Cornell University Ithaca</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>14853-7801</postCode>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Statistics Stanford University Stanford</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Mellon University Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>175 Fifth Avenue</addrLine>
									<postCode>15213-3890 94305 10010</postCode>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>PA CA NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Typeset by Asco Trade Typesetting Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>9 8 7 6 5 4 3 2</addrLine>
									<settlement>Hong Kong</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Springer Texts in Statistics</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">DOl:10.1007/978-1-4612-3974-1e-ISBN:978-1-4612-3974-1</idno>
					<note type="submission">Alfred: Elements of Statistics for the Life and Social Sciences Berger: An Introduction to Probability and Stochastic Processes Blom: Probability and Statistics: Theory and Applications Brockwell and Davis: An Introduction to Times Series and Forecasting</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T17:39+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Probability Theory: Independence</term>
					<term>Interchangeability</term>
					<term>Martingales</term>
					<term>Third Edition Christensen: Plane Answers to Complex Questions: The Theory of Linear Models</term>
					<term>Second Edition</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>On the cover: The artwork is based on an illustration of the basic matrices for structural equation models.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Library of Congress</head><p>Cataloging-in-Publication Data Mueller, Ralph O. Basic principles of structural equation modeling: an introduction to LISREL and EQS/Ralph O. Mueller. p. cm.-(Springer texts in statistics) Includes bibliographical references (pp. 216-221) and index.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>To <ref type="bibr">Mama and Papa;</ref> to Dan, Paula; and to Rob: My family of choice</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Preface</head><p>During the last two decades, structural equation modeling (SEM) has emerged as a powerful multivariate data analysis tool in social science research settings, especially in the fields of sociology, psychology, and education. Although its roots can be traced back to the first half of this century, when <ref type="bibr">Spearman (1904)</ref> developed factor analysis and Wright <ref type="bibr">(1934)</ref> introduced path analysis, it was not until the 1970s that the works by Karl Joreskog and his associates (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Joreskog, 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr">Joreskog and Van Thillo, 1973)</ref> began to make general SEM techniques accessible to the social and behavioral science research communities. Today, with the development and increasing availability of SEM computer programs, SEM has become a well-established and respected data analysis method, incorporating many of the traditional analysis techniques as special cases. State-of-the-art SEM software packages such as LISREL <ref type="bibr">(Joreskog and Sorbom, 1993a,b)</ref> and EQS <ref type="bibr">(Bentler, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr">Bentler and Wu, 1993)</ref> handle a variety of ordinary least squares regression designs as well as complex structural equation models involving variables with arbitrary distributions.</p><p>Unfortunately, many students and researchers hesitate to use SEM methods, perhaps due to the somewhat complex underlying statistical representation and theory. In my opinion, social science students and researchers can benefit greatly from acquiring knowledge and skills in SEM since the methods-applied appropriately-can provide a bridge between the theoretical and empirical aspects of behavioral research. That is, interpretations of SEM analyses can assist in understanding aspects of social and behavioral phenomena if (a) a "good" initial model is conceptualized based on a sound underlying substantive theory; (b) appropriate data are collected to estimate the unknown population parameters; (c) the fit of those data to the a priori hypothesized model is assessed; and (d) if theoretically justified, the initial model is modified appropriately should evidence of lack-of-fit and model misspecification arise. Structural equation modeling thus should be understood as a research process, not as a mere statistical technique. Preface Many social science graduate programs now offer introductions to SEM within their quantitative methods course sequences. Several currently available textbooks (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Blalock, 1964;</ref><ref type="bibr">Bollen, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr">Duncan, 1975;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hayduk, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kenny, 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr">Loehlin, 1992)</ref> reflect the rapidly increasing interest and advances in SEM methods. However, most treatments of SEM are either outdated and do not provide information on recent statistical advances and modern computer software, or they are of an advanced nature, sometimes making the initial study of SEM techniques unattractive and cumbersome to potential users. The present book was written to bridge this gap by addressing former deficiencies in a readily accessible introductory text.</p><p>The foci of the book are basic concepts and applications of SEM within the social and behavioral sciences. As such, students in any of the social and behavioral sciences with a background equivalent to a standard two-quarter or two-semester sequence in quantitative research methods (general ANOV A and linear regression models and basic concepts in applied measurement) should encounter no difficulties in mastering the content of this book. The minimal knowledge of matrix algebra that is required to understand the basic statistical foundations of SEM may be reviewed in this text (Appendix C) or acquired from any elementary linear algebra textbook. The exercises and selected references at the end of each chapter serve to test and strengthen the understanding of presented topics and provide the reader with a starting point into the current literature on SEM and related topics.</p><p>Central to the book is the development of SEM techniques by sequentially presenting linear regression and recursive path analysis, confirmatory factor analysis, and more general structural equation models. To illustrate statistical concepts and techniques, I have chosen to use the computer programs LISREL <ref type="bibr">(Joreskog and Sorbom, 1993a,b)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">EQS (Bentler, 1993)</ref> to analyze data from selected research in the fields of sociology and counseling psychology. The book can be used as an introduction to the LISREL and EQS programs themselves, although certainly it is not intended to be a substitute for the program manuals <ref type="bibr">(LISREL: Joreskog &amp; Sorbom, 1993a,b;</ref><ref type="bibr">EQS: Bentler, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr">Bentler and Wu, 1993)</ref>. While other computer programs could have been utilized <ref type="bibr">[e.g., Steiger's (1989</ref><ref type="bibr">) EzPATH, MuthCn's (1988)</ref> LISCOMP, or SAS's PROC CALIS (SAS Institute Inc., 1990)], the choice of introducing LISREL and EQS was based on my perception that they are the most widely used, known, and accepted structural equation programs to date.</p><p>The notation used to present statistical concepts is consistent with that in other treatments of <ref type="bibr">SEM (e.g., Bollen, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hayduk, 1987)</ref> and follows the Joreskog-Keesling-Wiley approach to represent systems of structural equations (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Joreskog, 1973</ref><ref type="bibr">Joreskog, , 1977;;</ref><ref type="bibr">Joreskog and Sorbom, 1993a;</ref><ref type="bibr">Keesling, 1972;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wiley, 1973)</ref>. Since all versions of LISREL are based on this approach, the program's matrix-based syntax is easily explained and understood once some underlying statistical theory has been introduced. However, the LISREL package also features an alternative command language, SIMPLIS (Joreskog Preface IX and Sorbom, 1993b), which allows the researcher to analyze structural equation models without fully understanding and using matrix representations.</p><p>While LISREL examples throughout the chapters use the matrix-based syntax to illustrate the statistical foundation and representation of SEM, their equivalents using SIMPLIS are explained in Appendix A.</p><p>The EQS language, on the other hand, is built around the Bentler-Weeks model <ref type="bibr">(e.g., Bentler, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr">Bentler and</ref><ref type="bibr">Weeks, 1979, 1980)</ref>; this alternative way to represent structural equation systems is not used in this book. Like SIMPLIS, the EQS syntax does not involve matrix specifications and, hence, knowledge of the matrix form of the Bentler-Weeks model is not required to understand and use the EQS program. The package's MS Windows version <ref type="bibr">(Bentler and Wu, 1993)</ref> includes the BuilLEQS option that allows the analyst to create an EQS input file without actually having to write the input program but, instead, by "clicking" on certain options within various dialogue boxes. I feel that knowledge of the program's syntax for model specification is of overall educational value and, thus, discuss actual input files rather than emphasizing the Build_EQS option.</p><p>Initially, any SEM programming language that does not depend on an understanding of the matrix representation of structural equation models might seem easier than a traditional matrix-based syntax. To acquire an "aesthetic" appreciation of SEM, however, it is necessary to grasp some of the underlying statistical principles and formulations-be it via the approach used here or the one proposed in the Bentler-Weeks model. Getting acquainted with the syntax of the matrixand nonmatrix-based command languages of LISREL and EQS will aid in this endeavor.</p><p>In summary, this book was written with four goals in mind: (1) to help users of contemporary social science research methods gain an understanding and appreciation of the main goals and advantages of "doing" SEM; (2) to explicate some of the fundamental statistical theory that underlies SEM;</p><p>(3) to illustrate the use of the software packages LISREL and EQS in the analysis of basic recursive structural equation models; and, most importantly, (4) to stimulate the reader's curiosity to consult more advanced treatments of SEM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Organization and Historical Perspective</head><p>The book contains three chapters, largely reflecting the historical development of what is known now as the general area of SEM: from a discussion of classical path analysis (Chapter 1) and an introduction to confirmatory factor analysis (Chapter 2) to an exploration of basic analyses of more general structural equation models (Chapter 3). In addition, the book contains five appendices: Appendix A presents all LISREL examples from the chapters in the SIMPLIS command language and serves as an introduction to this x Preface alternative LISREL syntax. Appendix B briefly reviews the statistical concepts of distributional location, dispersion, and variable association mainly to explain some of the notation used in this book; some elementary concepts of matrix algebra are presented in Appendix C. Finally, Appendices D and E contain coding information and summary statistics for all variables used in the LISREL and EQS example analyses.</p><p>Chapter 1 introduces the language and notation of SEM through a discussion of classical recursive path analysis. Most modern treatments trace the beginnings of SEM to the development of path analysis by Sewall Wright during the 1920s and 1930s <ref type="bibr">(Wright, 1921</ref><ref type="bibr">(Wright, , 1934))</ref>. However, it took almost half a century before the method was introduced to the social sciences with articles by <ref type="bibr">Duncan (1966)</ref> in sociology, <ref type="bibr">Werts and Linn (1970)</ref> in psychology, and <ref type="bibr">Anderson and Evans (1974)</ref> in education, among others. Early path analyses were simply ordinary least squares (OLS) regression applications to sets of variables that were structurally related. In many ways, SEM techniques still can be seen as nothing more than the analysis of simultaneous regression equations. In fact, if the statistical assumptions underlying linear regression are met, standard OLS estimation~as available in computer programs such as SPSS, SAS, or BMDP~can be used to estimate the parameters in some structural equation models.</p><p>Throughout the review of univariate simple and multiple linear regression in Chapter 1, standard regression notation is replaced by that commonly used in SEM (the Joreskog-Keesling-Wiley notation system), providing an easy transition into the basic concepts of SEM. The introduction of path diagrams and structural equations leads to the First Law of Path Analysis, which allows for the decomposition of covariances between any two variables in a recursive path model. In turn, such decompositions lead to the definitions of the direct, indirect, and total effects among structurally ordered variables within a specific model. Finally, a discussion and demonstration of the identification problem in recursive path models is included to sensitize the reader to a complex issue that demands attention before SEM analyses can be conducted. Throughout the chapter, theoretical concepts are illustrated by annotated LISREL and EQS analyses of a data set taken from the sociological literature.</p><p>In Chapter 2, the inclusion of latent, unobserved variables in structural equation models is introduced from a confirmatory factor analysis (CF A) perspective. Based on Spearman's (1904) discovery of exploratory factor analysis (EFA), several individuals (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Joreskog, 1967</ref><ref type="bibr">Joreskog, , 1969;;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lawley, 1940</ref><ref type="bibr">Lawley, , 1967;;</ref><ref type="bibr">Thurstone, 1947)</ref> advanced the statistical theory to represent relationships among observed variables in terms of a smaller number of underlying theoretical constructs, that is, latent variables. It was not until the mid-1950s that a formal distinction was made between EF A and CF A: While the former method is used to search data for an underlying structure, the latter technique is utilized to confirm (strictly speaking, disconfirm) an a priori hypothesized, theory-derived structure with collected data. In this text, only CF A Preface Xl models are discussed; books by <ref type="bibr">Gorsuch (1983)</ref>, <ref type="bibr">Mulaik (1972</ref><ref type="bibr">), or McDonald (1985)</ref> can be consulted for detailed introductions to EF A.</p><p>Based on the assumption that most measured variables are imperfect indicators of certain underlying, latent constructs or factors, CF A allows the researcher to cluster observed variables in certain prespecified, theory-driven ways, that is, to specify a priori the latent construct(s) that the observed variables are intended to measure. After estimating the factor loadings (structural coefficients in the regressions of observed on the latent variables) from a variance/covariance matrix of the observed variables, the investigator can and should assess whether or not the collected data "fit" the hypothesized factor structure. Since several issues surrounding the question of how best to assess data-model fit still are unresolved and current answers remain controversial, a detailed discussion of some of the currently utilized data-model fit indices is presented in Chapter 2. The different approaches to data-model fit, as well as other concepts introduced in Chapter 2 (e.g., model modification), are illustrated by (a) an extended analysis of the data set introduced in Chapter 1, and (b) a LISREL and EQS CF A to assess the validity and reliability of a behavior assessment instrument taken from the counseling psychology literature.</p><p>Finally, Chapter 3 treats the most general recursive structural equation model presented in this book. The conceptual integration of the classical path analysis model (Chapter 1) and the CFA model (Chapter 2) is used to develop the general structure. During the 1970s, several researchers (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Keesling, 1972;</ref><ref type="bibr">Joreskog, 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wiley, 1973)</ref> succeeded in developing the statistical theory and computational procedures for combining path analysis and CF A into a single statistical framework. The various versions of LISREL, developed by Joreskog and associates dating back to 1970, continuously incorporated up-to-date statistical advances in SEM. Similarly, EQS <ref type="bibr">(Bentler, 1993)</ref> is regarded as one of the most sophisticated and respected software packages for the analysis of a wide variety of structural equation models, including path analytical, CF A, and more general models. In addition, its MS Windows version <ref type="bibr">(Bentler and Wu, 1993)</ref> includes many exploratory data analytical tools, such as outlier analysis and other descriptive statistics with various plot options, in addition to inferential techniques, such as dependent and independent t-tests, regression, and ANOYA.</p><p>After discussing the specification and identification of general structural equation models that involve latent variables in Chapter 3, the estimation of direct, indirect, and total effect components introduced in Chapter 1 is simplified by introducing a matrix algorithm to estimate the various effect components. Also, two of the most common iterative methods for estimating parameters in general structural equation models are discussed: maximum likelihood <ref type="bibr">(Joreskog, 1969</ref><ref type="bibr">(Joreskog, , 1970</ref>; among others) and generalized least squares <ref type="bibr">(Goldberger, 1971;</ref><ref type="bibr">Joreskog and Goldberger, 1972)</ref>. While these techniques have important advantages over more traditional methods such as OLS, both methods still depend on the multivariate normality assumption; for Xll Preface data from nonnormal distributions, <ref type="bibr">Browne's (1982</ref><ref type="bibr">Browne's ( , 1984) )</ref> asymptotically distribution free (ADF) estimators can be obtained from both the LISREL and EQS packages. Following the organization of previous chapters, the concepts presented in Chapter 3 are illustrated with LISREL and EQS analyses of extensions of the models introduced in Chapters 1 and 2 [a demonstration of the ADF method is omitted since it would require either the use of PRELlS <ref type="bibr">(Joreskog and Sorbom, 1993c)</ref> or an analysis of raw datal</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A Brief Comment on Causality1</head><p>It is only natural that the growing attention paid to structural equation modeling-called by some causal modeling-has led to a number of criticisms. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baumrind (1983</ref><ref type="bibr">), Cliff (1983</ref><ref type="bibr">), Freedman (1987</ref><ref type="bibr">), and Ling (1983)</ref>, for example, all presented very insightful perspectives on the dangers associated with utilizing SEM for understanding social science phenomena. Often, however, the reader of such critical views might not recognize immediately which step in the SEM process is being challenged: (a) model conceptualization and specification, (b) identification, (c) parameter estimation, (d) data-model fit assessment, or (e) model modification. Whereas steps (b), (c), and (d) might raise certain statistical questions, steps (a) and (e) are based mostly on some key philosophical assumptions and/or substantive considerations. <ref type="bibr">Duncan (1975)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Wolfle (1985)</ref> pointed to the importance and implication of this differentiation: 'The study of structural equation models can be divided into two parts: the easy part and the hard part" <ref type="bibr">(Duncan, 1975, p. 149)</ref>. "The easy part is mathematical. The hard part is constructing causal models that are consistent with sound theory. In short, causal models are no better than the ideas that go into them" <ref type="bibr">(Wolfle, 1985, p. 385)</ref>. Using this conceptualization, the present book may be seen as an introduction to the "easy" part of SEM. Mastering the "hard" part requires knowledge and understanding of the theoretical, substantive, and philosophical underpinnings of the particular research question(s) as well as an appreciation for the goals and limitations of social science research methodology in general.</p><p>One of the most controversial philosophical issues surrounding SEM is the role and interpretation of the concept of causality. A review of major paradigm shifts in the philosophy of science since the British empiricists reveals that "causality" repeatedly has been in and out of favor with philosophers and researchers in the natural and social sciences (see <ref type="bibr">Mulaik, 1987, and references therein)</ref>. For example, while some contemporary methodologists suggest that "causal explanation is the ultimate aim of science" <ref type="bibr">(Shaffer, 1992, p.</ref> x; italics added), others insist that "it would be very healthy if more researchers abandon thinking of and using terms such as cause and 1 The comments in this section are taken largely from those expressed in <ref type="bibr">Mueller and Dupuy (1992)</ref>. The contributions by Paula Dupuy are greatly appreciated and hereby acknowledged.  effect" <ref type="bibr">(M uthen, 1992, p. 82)</ref>. It seems that this controversy can be explained partially by the arduous challenge facing the applied researcher of translating philosophical concepts into scientific methodologies: The difficult task is using the common-sense notion of causality as a way to explain human experience and finding ways to operationalize the concept for rigorous and meaningful scientific research.</p><p>In my view, some of the main criticisms leveled against SEM are closely linked to the particular conceptualizations, definitions, and uses of the concept of causality. While most contemporary operational definitions of causality overlap at least partially, there are differences among them that could have significant impacts on the model conceptualization and interpretation phases of the SEM process. For example, some contributors make the epistemological assumption that nonexperimental research can generate causal inferences <ref type="bibr">(e.g., Glymour et al., 1987)</ref>, whereas the motto "no causation without manipulation" <ref type="bibr">(Holland, 1986, p. 959)</ref> implies the inappropriateness of causal modeling in a nonexperimental research setting. Also, researchers disagree on requiring time precedence as a necessary condition for causality: For example, while <ref type="bibr">Kenny (1979)</ref> saw cause and effect ordered by time, <ref type="bibr">Marini and Singer (1988)</ref> argued that temporal order is not necessary for cause-effect relationships to exist. If time precedence is seen as a necessary condition for causality, only recursive models (models that do not include bidirectional causal relations) are valid. However, if the cause does not need to precede the effect in time, nonrecursive models can be specified (for a classic example, see <ref type="bibr">Duncan et al., 1968)</ref>. Finally, differences in causality definitions seem to contribute to the discussion over the appropriateness of SEM in exploratory versus confirmatory research modes. Whereas Glymour et al. <ref type="bibr">(1987)</ref> claimed to have methods that discover causal structures, Bollen (1989) sought "only" to reject a priori specified models. This difference is basically an epistemological one that can be reconciled only by considering their different sets of causality assumptions.</p><p>In conclusion, many experts have explored and sought to clarify the role of causality in scientific research in general and SEM in particular. In this book, I do not attempt to add to these discussions in any meaningful way (except, perhaps, by expressing and explaining at various points throughout the book that SEM should not be seen as an exploratory data analysis tool). On the contrary, I admit to somewhat avoiding the issue of causality by using the seemingly more neutral term structural-instead of causal-when describing relationships among variables that are more than just correlational in nature (in doing so, however, note that it remains difficult to escape the implicit underlying notion of causality). Thus, the following pages deal mainly with an introduction to the "easy" part of SEM, leaving an explanation of the "hard" part to philosophers and other experts. Below, the interested reader is referred to a number of sources that should provide a good entry point into the literature dealing with the philosophical issues surrounding the concept of causality within SEM. No difficulties should be encountered in covering the content of the book in a one-quarter or one-semester course. When considerably less time is available and/or coverage of the main topics is sought purely from a nontechnical perspective (i.e., when no coverage of basic-but matrix-based-concepts underlying SEM is planned), it is possible to focus mostly on the nonmatrixbased SIMPLIS and EQS illustrations since the examples are relatively selfcontained. The more technical parts of the book then serve as a resource for future reference and self-study.</p><p>It seems helpful to students to supplement a text such as this with additional readings from the applied research literature that use SEM techniques for data analysis. The LISREL and EQS manuals are good resources for additional examples and, at the very least,• should be made available to students for the duration of the course for reference purposes and specific program information. Also, students should be encouraged to consult the more philosophical treatments of SEM (some of which are listed below), in particular those dealing with the role of causality in SEM.</p><p>I should mention explicitly that this book does not cover certain topics that are, in my opinion, of a somewhat advanced nature and do not need to be part of a first exposure to SEM data analysis. Analyses of nonrecursive models, multigroup designs, second-order CF As, mean structures, and ways of dealing with missing data are not covered here; instead, the reader is referred to more advanced sources such as Bollen (1989). Further, I treat all variables used in the examples as continuous when, in fact, strictly speaking, some are measured on an ordinal scale only [for a detailed discussion on the analysis of ordinal data, consult the manuals accompanying the <ref type="bibr">PRELIS and LISCOMP programs (J6reskog and S6rbom, 1993c;</ref><ref type="bibr">Muthen, 1988, respectively)</ref>].</p><p>Of course, I must take responsibility for any errors that are present in the pages to follow. I invite you to contact me if you discover such errors or if you have other comments that could be of value for possible revisions or future editions of the book.</p><p>Preface xv an anonymous reviewer for their in-depth and constructive critiques, and Karl Joreskog for a personal account of the history of SEM that inspired me greatly. Scientific Software, Inc., and BMDP Statistical Software, Inc., are acknowledged for providing review copies of the LISREL and EQS packages. Of course, Martin Gilchrist, Senior Editor at Springer-Verlag, and Elise Oranges, copyeditor and Director of Publishing Network, deserve much credit for the final product.</p><p>Washington, DC R.O. MUELLER</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recommended Readings</head><p>For acquiring a historical perspective on SEM, the following two references might be helpful:  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Preface</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>X1I1</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 1.2 Selected LISREL Output from the Analysis of the Model in Figure 1.2 EQS Input File for the Model in Figure 1.5 Selected EQS Output from the Analysis of the Model in Figure 1.5 LISREL Input File for the Model in Figure 1.6 Selected LISREL Output from the Analysis of the Model in Figure 1.6 EQS Input File for the Model in Figure 1.8 Selected EQS Output from the Analysis of the Model in Figure 1.8 LISREL Input File for the Model in Figure 1.10 Selected LISREL Output from the Analysis of the Model in Figure 1.10 EQS Input File for the Model in Figure 1.10 Selected EQS Output from the Analysis of the Model in Figure 1EQS Output from an Analysis of the Model in Figure 3.6 172 A.1 SIMPLIS Input File for the Simple Linear Regression in Example 1.1 182 A.1(a) Partial SIMPLIS Output from the Simple Linear Regression in Example 1.1</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>Finally, this project depended on the help of many individuals. I thank my former students at The University of Toledo who had to contend with several rough drafts of this book, provided feedback, and kept encouraging me to finish what I had started. Once I felt that the drafts were becoming more presentable, I started to share copies with colleagues whose invaluable input led to the book you see before you. In particular, I thank <rs type="person">Peter Bentler</rs> and</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Specious causal attributions in the social sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Baumrind</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1289" to="1298" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causation issues in structural equation modeling research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bullock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Harlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mulaik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Structural Equation Modeling</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="267" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward a conception of causality applicable to experimentation and causal modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mulaik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Child Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Shafer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Role of Models in Nonexperimental Social Science: Two Debates</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>American Educational Research Association</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
