<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Methodological challenges to confirmatory latent variable models of social vulnerability</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2021-02-13">13 February 2021</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zachary</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Goodman</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-0126-4425</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Miami</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Office 446, Coral Gables</addrLine>
									<postCode>5665 33146-0751</postCode>
									<settlement>Ponce de Leon Blvd</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Caitlin</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stamatis</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Miami</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Office 446, Coral Gables</addrLine>
									<postCode>5665 33146-0751</postCode>
									<settlement>Ponce de Leon Blvd</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Justin</forename><surname>Stoler</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Geography and Regional Studies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Miami</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Coral Gables</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>FL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Public Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Miller School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Miami</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Miami</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Christopher</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Emrich</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">College of Community Innovation and Education</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Central Florida</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Orlando</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Llabre</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Miami</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Office 446, Coral Gables</addrLine>
									<postCode>5665 33146-0751</postCode>
									<settlement>Ponce de Leon Blvd</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Methodological challenges to confirmatory latent variable models of social vulnerability</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2021-02-13">13 February 2021</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11069-021-04563-6</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 13 August 2020 / Accepted: 19 January 2021 /</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T17:32+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Vulnerability</term>
					<term>Measurement</term>
					<term>Evaluation</term>
					<term>Validity</term>
					<term>Social indicators</term>
					<term>Social vulnerability</term>
					<term>SoVI</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Socially vulnerable communities experience disproportionately negative outcomes following natural disasters and underscoring a need for well-validated measures to identify those at risk. However, questions have surfaced regarding the factor structure, internal consistency, and generalizability of social vulnerability measures. A reliance on data-driven techniques, which are susceptible to sample-specific characteristics, has likely exacerbated the difficulty generalizing social vulnerability measures across contexts. This study sought to validate previously published structures of SoVI using confirmatory factor analysis (CFA). We fit CFA models of 28 sociodemographic variables frequently used to calculate a commonly used measure, the social vulnerability index (SoVI), drawn from the American Community Survey across 4162 census tracts in Florida. Confirmatory models generally did not support theory-driven pillars of SoVI that were previously used to study vulnerability in the New York metropolitan area. Modified models and alternative SoVI factor structures also failed to fit the data. Many of the input variables displayed little to no variability, limiting their utility and explanatory power. Taken together, our results highlight the poor generalizability of SoVI across contexts, but raise several important considerations for reliability and validity, as well as issues related to source data and scale. We discuss the implications of these findings for improved theory-driven measurement of social vulnerability.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Extreme events have inspired decades of research on risk and vulnerability, with the goal of identifying communities with the least capacity to prepare for, respond to, and rebound from disasters. Unfortunately, studies suggest that beyond the impact of physical hazard, socially disadvantaged communities face disproportionate risk when exposed to natural disasters <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Laska and Morrow 2006)</ref>. Similar observations underpinned the development of early social vulnerability indices, which utilize variability in sociodemographic data to quantify population vulnerability to loss in the face of an event such as a hurricane (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Clark et al. 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Cutter et al. 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Tapsell et al. 2002)</ref>.</p><p>Although the theoretical links between sociodemographic factors and hazard vulnerability are well established, there remains considerable debate around best practices for measuring social vulnerability <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Beccari 2016)</ref>. Several social vulnerability indices have been proposed to quantify this latent construct, but most are ecological in nature (i.e., measuring vulnerability at various levels of census geography or other units), and few studies have attempted to validate them or otherwise assess their relative utility <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Fekete 2019)</ref>. Decision makers have begun to utilize measures of social vulnerability for resource disaster recovery allocation (New York Times 2020), and nearly 40% of states are planning on using vulnerability measures to prioritize COVID-19 vaccine distribution (NPR 2020; <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schmidt et al 2020)</ref>. Such use of this theoretical contract and its empirical manifestations, although seemingly ethical in nature, may have unknown or unintended consequences. Although these measures may have face validity and are being applied, we still don't know how "good" or "useful" these measures are from a variety of perspectives. Here, utility may take several forms, including ease of construction, internal consistency, robustness, transferability, or explanatory power. Arguably, the best model would perform well on each of these criteria, yet most social vulnerability models have not been rigorously tested.</p><p>Validation studies aimed at understanding the utility of social vulnerability surrogates, variable aggregates, and models/indices remain difficult to undertake for a variety of reasons, including the lack of available point level data on vulnerability and outcome measures, the ecological fallacy created when aggregating outcomes and social vulnerabilities to various levels of geography and the challenges related to using a multivariate characteristic such as social vulnerability to describe univariate outcomes such as total losses, fatalities, slow recovery and the like. Recently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Rufat et al. (2019)</ref> tested the empirical validity of four social vulnerability indices against Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA) claims data from Hurricane Sandy (as a proxy for losses) aggregated to census tracts, with mixed results. The four indices they tested were highly variable in their use of data driven, pillar-based, and expert opinion approaches.</p><p>One of these indices, the social vulnerability index (SoVI) originally developed by Cutter and colleagues <ref type="bibr">(2003)</ref> remains among the most heavily referenced and often utilized for understanding capacity in the face of disaster. SoVI's original formulation-a 42 variable empirical measure of sociodemographic and built environment characteristics of community capacity to prepare for, respond to, and rebound from disaster events-has a long history of utility in both academic settings with more than 4700 citations and applied planning tools <ref type="bibr">(NOAA 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr">Surging Seas 2014)</ref>. Derived as an empirical method to understand, measure, and monitor difference between places, SoVI is the product of well-known individual/community social inequality measures and place inequality measures or those characteristics contributing to the social vulnerability of places. SoVI, the first largescale (county level) composite measure capturing the broad suite of social vulnerability 1 3 characteristics identified through a literature review, has been largely accepted and applied across academic and practical fields of use. SoVI's more recent incarnations (27-29 variables focused only on sociodemographics) have long filled the need to understand lack of capacity to prepare for, respond to, and rebound from environmental threats. However, an important distinction here is that SoVI's original conceptualization centered on building a model based on a retrospective of disaster impacts and outcomes rather than building the most robust model from a psychometric perspective. Although, the SoVI model has become one of the more notable targets for critical review. Most recently, Spielman and colleagues (2020) observed several problems with two measures used to determine a model's utility, construct validity, and internal consistency. <ref type="bibr">Spielman and colleagues (2020)</ref> further argue that SoVI's construction is not consistently robust with respect to traditional psychometric theory. Although the recent criticism is specific to SoVI, it is not clear if any existing social vulnerability measures are generalizable beyond context-specific applications. Rather, these limitations may lie in the approach to measuring and assessing the latent constructs of interest.</p><p>Although the advent of social vulnerability measurement has yielded some important insights in the disaster risk literature, several limitations remain in the ways which researchers have attempted to quantify social vulnerability. On the one hand, the concept is theoretically robust; it has long been appreciated that social factors influence one's experience of hazards and stressors <ref type="bibr">(Turner et al. 2003). Simultaneously, data-driven and pillar-based (i.e., construct-based)</ref> approaches, such as those tested by <ref type="bibr">Rufat and colleagues (2019)</ref>, appear to be limited in their generalizability. This hinders progress toward the ultimate goals of developing portable metrics for understanding who is affected by disasters and mitigating related losses.</p><p>The development of more generalizable social vulnerability indices may benefit from statistical approaches that combine theoretical or conceptual knowledge of vulnerability with empirical confirmation. Data-driven approaches, such as principal component analysis (PCA) and exploratory factor analysis (EFA), are known for their susceptibility to sample-specific characteristics of the data <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Widaman 2018)</ref>. Models informed by theory, such as the pillar-based approach by <ref type="bibr">Rufat and colleagues (2019)</ref>, can help reduce sample specificity and overfitting by imposing constraints consistent with theory. At the same time, purely pillar-based or expert-based models account for theoretical knowledge but minimize nuances in the data pertinent to a given disaster or a given community. Moving forward, this area of research can rely on current confirmatory latent variable approaches that incorporate the best of both worlds.</p><p>Latent variable models can enhance the generalizability of social vulnerability indices. In particular, confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) is a framework that uses theory-guided a priori knowledge to specify a latent construct or constructs hypothesized to underlie the covariation among a set of indicators <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Llabre and Fitzpatrick 2012)</ref>. Applying CFA to social vulnerability indexing would involve specifying indicators, or observed variables, that are presumed to reflect the construct or constructs of interest. CFA can test single factor or multifactor models, and for each factor or latent variable, the indicators reflecting the construct are specified. For example, if theory suggests that a socioeconomic factor is important for social vulnerability indices, we can specify census measures-such as per capita income, percent living below the poverty line, and median house value-as indicators of the latent socioeconomic construct. CFA models partition the variability in an indicator into that which is derived from the latent variable and the residual which contains specific variance and error. The model yields estimate of the loadings associated with each indicator. These loadings represent the correlation between the latent variable and the indicator and provide a measure of the adequacy of the indicator in reflecting the construct <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Kline 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Llabre and Fitzpatrick 2012)</ref>. Further, squared standardized factor loadings provide the proportion of explained variance of the observed variable. Tests of fit between the model specified and the data provide important information about the adequacy of the theory in a given situation, as well as the adequacy of the indicators. Applying a confirmatory measurement modeling approach to social vulnerability indices may provide a deeper understanding of the latent social vulnerability construct. Additionally, this approach may identify additional social characteristics that can best inform policies to decrease disaster vulnerability.</p><p>In the present study, our overarching objective was to apply confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) to evaluate SoVI model construct validity and generalizability following separate natural disasters <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Rufat et al. 2019)</ref>. This study represents a departure from the purely datadriven approaches typically used to quantify social vulnerability by applying a theoretically-based pillars approach to SoVI's raw underlying data. Our overall intent is to leverage the best aspects of prior social vulnerability indices and incrementally create a revised index with stronger empirical validity for our study area, Florida. Our first aim was to fit confirmatory measurement models of each of the five pillars identified by <ref type="bibr">Rufat and colleagues (2019)</ref>, including socioeconomic status, population structure, race and ethnicity, access and needs, and housing structure (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). Assuming we could attain acceptable fit for each measurement model, our second aim was to integrate the individual measurement models into a five-factor model representing the overall SoVI construct and ultimately test its association with FEMA claims data from Hurricane Irma, the fifth costliest hurricane to hit the mainland United States (National Hurricane Center 2018). But, we did not get that far our analysis encountered several obstacles highlighting some of the underlying challenges that have afflicted past attempts to validate social vulnerability indices. This paper focuses on those methodological issues and discusses the implications for generalizable social vulnerability measures with recommendations for future attempts to quantify and validate this construct.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Method</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Data and data screening</head><p>This study analyzed the 28 sociodemographic census variables commonly used as candidates in the computation of SoVI (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>), gathered from the American Community Survey, five-year product (2014-2017) and aggregated to 4,246 Florida census tracts. We could have used alternate spatial units, such as counties or metropolitan statistical areas, but census tracts are the smallest geographic unit for which demographic variables are considered to be statistically reliable <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Spielman et al. 2014)</ref>. Of the initial sample, 84 tracts were excluded due to zero residents, resulting in an effective sample of 4162 tracts.</p><p>In preparation for testing confirmatory factor models, we examined the variability, skewness, kurtosis, and scaling of each SoVI variable before proceeding with further analyses. Low variability indicates a variable that is relatively stable across census tracts. In the extreme case, when there is no variability for a given measure (i.e., the variable was effectively constant), it was impossible to assess the variable's quality as an indicator of a latent construct or relationships to other variables.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">3</head><p>In addition to variability, we also addressed variable scaling, as estimation difficulties can arise when variables have drastically different ranges. We chose to rescale percentage variables by multiplying them by 100, and we divided absolute measures such as per capita income, median house value, and median rent by 1000. Measures of skewness and kurtosis provide information about the extent to which variables meet the normality assumptions required by maximum likelihood estimation. The recommended cut points are ± 3 for skewness and 8 for kurtosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Kline 2016)</ref>.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Statistical analyses</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1">Confirmatory factor analysis</head><p>We conducted a series of confirmatory factor analyses (CFA) with full-information maximum likelihood (FIML) estimation to test the structure of theoretically driven models of social vulnerability. All statistical analyses were conducted in R version 3.6.3, and CFA was conducted via the lavaan package <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Rosseel 2012</ref>). For each model, we explicitly specified which indicators (i.e., variables) served as observed measures of a given latent construct. Measures of model fit allowed us to evaluate how well the theoretically specified model was supported by the data. Each CFA was evaluated for overall model fit and reliability, with model fit evaluated according to the following standard criteria: nonsignificant chi-square test (χ 2 ), root mean square error of approximation (RMSEA) less than .08, standardized root mean square residual (SRMR) less than .06, and comparative fit index (CFI) greater than .95 <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Kline 2016)</ref>. A standardized factor loading (λ) less than .30 suggests the indicator is a weak reflection of the latent construct. We also examined Cronbach's alpha (α), a commonly used metric of internal consistency, for the five measurement models (i.e., for each pillar); α greater than .70 generally indicates acceptable reliability. Indicators which loaded negatively onto a latent variable were reversed (i.e., multiplied by -1) before calculating reliability. Fit indices for CFA models are reported in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>. Standardized and unstandardized factor loadings as well as associated significance tests are reported in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2">Initial single-factor measurement model specification</head><p>To test our first aim, we specified a set of confirmatory single-factor measurement models based on the pillars suggested by Rufat and colleagues (2019) (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). Socioeconomic status was indicated by per capita income, percent living under the poverty line, median house value, percent earning over $200,000 per year, percent working in the service sector, percent working in the extractive sector, percent with less than 12 years of education, and median rent. Population structure was indicated by median age, percent living with a child younger than 5 years or adult older than 65 years, people per housing unit, percent of female-headed households, percent of females employed, percent of population which is female, and percent of married families. Race and ethnicity was indicated by four variables: percent of population which is African American, Hispanic/Latino, Native American, and Asian American. Access and needs was indicated by percent living in a nursing home, percent receiving social security benefits, percentage of population in which English is a second language, percent of population who do not have an automobile, and percent uninsured. Housing structure was indicated by percent of units occupied by renters, percent of vacant houses, and percent living in a mobile home.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.3">Single-factor model respecification</head><p>If specified single-factor models did not fit the data well, we explored modifications to improve fit. While model respecification is an empirically guided step, we sought to make modifications consistent with theory, in line with our overarching aim of increasing the generalizability of the SoVI model. To make modifications, we examined problematic indicators (e.g., low factor loadings) and modification indices suggested by lavaan. Typically, model respecification was done by removing indicators or correlating residual variances between indicators, with the latter modification suggesting that two variables share some relationship above and beyond the covariance explained by the latent variable. In the case of correlating residual variances, it is generally the responsibility of the analyst to interpret the covariance and theorize what external factor might contribute to these associations. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.4">Correlated factor model</head><p>Although we observed that the single-factor models were not a good fit, we tested our second aim by fitting a correlated five-factor model that tested the overall fit of the theoretical SoVI structure. All five of the single-factor models described above were included in a model simultaneously, and latent variables were allowed to correlate. We tested the correlated factor model first using the original single-factor models (i.e., with no modifications). We then tested the model again including the respecifications from the single-factor models to see if this would improve fit. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.5">Alternative models</head><p>To examine alternative factor structures of SoVI variables, we tested several additional models. These included a single-factor model with a broad social vulnerability latent variable indicated by all previously mentioned indicators and a bifactor model which tested both a general and domain-specific latent variable. A single-factor model implies all census variables represent a common, social vulnerability construct rather than representing distinct but related subfactors, as discussed above-this solution would reject the theorybased pillars of past literature. A bifactor model is a combination of the single-factor model and the specific factor models discussed above and implies all census variables represent two constructs: a general social vulnerability latent variable and a domain-specific latent variable (e.g., socioeconomic status).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Data screening</head><p>Many SoVI candidate variables yielded minimal variability across census tracts in Florida; several percentage variables had standard deviations as low as 0.01 (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). Normality was a concern for many of the variables included in SoVI (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>). Skewness ranged from -2.08 (percent of females employed) to 9.95 (percent of population that is Native American), with a median skewness of 1.68 (SD = 2.27). Similarly, kurtosis ranged from -0.06 (percent of married families) to 170.57 (percent Native American), with a median kurtosis of 4.04 (SD = 33.63). Consequently, all variables were transformed logarithmically to resolve complications in model estimation that can arise due to non-normality. Due to a lack of variability and concerningly high skew, three census variables were removed from subsequent analyses: percent working in the extractive sector, percent of the population which is Native American, and percent living in a nursing home.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Single-factor confirmatory factor models</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Socioeconomic status</head><p>The initial CFA demonstrated poor overall fit, although the SRMR was acceptable (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>). Several respecifications based on modification indices were conducted to reach acceptable model fit, and improvements between each respecified model were marginal.</p><p>Residual covariances were added one at a time between the following pairs of census variables, with model fit reassessed after each addition: per capita income and median rent; median house value and percent earning over $200,000; median house value and median rent; per capita income and percent earning over $200,000; per capita income and median house value; and percent unemployed and percent working in the service sector. The final respecification step improved model fit to acceptable cutoffs and produced a reliable latent variable (α = .88). Note that all of these respecifications are data driven and require additional validation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">Population structure</head><p>The initial single-factor model demonstrated very poor fit to the data (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>). A residual covariance between percent of females employed and percent of the population which is female improved fit substantially, although fit was still poor according to standard criteria <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Kline 2016)</ref>. While the addition of a residual covariance between percent of femaleheaded households and percent of married families improved fit, as did the inclusion of a covariance between percent of female-headed households and percent of people per housing unit, attempts to include additional parameters produced negative variances. Consequently, the final model did not achieve acceptable fit indices as demonstrated by marginal reliability (α = .67).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.3">Race and ethnicity</head><p>The indicator representing percent of the population that is Native American was removed due to minimal variability, such that the race and ethnicity factor had only 3 indicators. While factor loadings for a single-factor model with three indicators can be estimated, fit indices cannot be produced because a minimum of four indicators is required in order to test model fit. Consequently, we focused on the factor loadings, which revealed several concerns. The standardized factor loadings of the percent of the population identifying as Asian American (λ = .24) and African American (λ = .18) were low, suggesting that the indicators do not share significant common variance. Additionally, these indicators demonstrated highly skewed and leptokurtic distributions, which persisted after logarithmic transformations. Unsurprisingly, the reliability of the race and ethnicity factor was extremely low (α = .17), which may mirror the transition from historic settlement patterns shaped by racial capitalism to newer, evolving patterns of residential segregation <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Ellis et al. 2018)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.4">Access and needs</head><p>The initial model demonstrated poor fit to the data (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>). Of note, the standardized factor loading of percent receiving social security benefits (λ = -.34) was negative. The inclusion of a covariance between percent uninsured and percent without an automobile improved fit; however, this addition resulted in a low standardized factor loading for percent without an automobile (λ = .25). Removal of percent without an automobile resulted in a model with three indicators, so fit could not be examined. The loading of percent receiving social security benefits remained negative (λ = -.43), and the final model demonstrated low reliability (α = .60).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.5">Housing structure</head><p>As with the race and ethnicity model, the housing structure latent variable only included three indicators, such that model fit could not be tested. While the standardized factor loadings of the housing structure latent variable were moderate ranging from .40 to .49, the reliability of this latent variable was extremely poor (α = .35).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Combined models</head><p>Given that all but one of the single-factor models demonstrated poor fit to the data and/ or low reliability, it was unlikely that a correlated factor model would be tenable. However, in keeping with our second aim, we tested a correlated five-factor model, wherein each of the hypothesized latent variables was estimated simultaneously. As expected, the model demonstrated very poor fit to the data (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>), indicated errors in estimation and produced correlations between factors exceeding 1. Attempting to estimate the correlated factor model using a combination of the modified single-factor models produced similar results. Given these empirical limitations, a correlated factor structure of SoVI was not supported.</p><p>Next, we tested a general single-factor model, wherein every indicator loaded onto one social vulnerability factor. Again, this model demonstrated poor fit (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>), although there were no difficulties in model estimation. Despite removing several indicators with low loadings and the addition of 23 residual covariances, model fit remained poor.</p><p>Finally, we explored a bifactor model, wherein each indicator belonged not only to its previously identified specific factor, but also to a general social vulnerability factor. Factors in bifactor models are required to remain uncorrelated. The bifactor model demonstrated poor fit to the data (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>) and resulted in an estimated factor loading greater than 1, suggesting an improper solution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Discussion</head><p>This study applied confirmatory factor analysis to test the generalizability and construct validity of SoVI, a commonly used measure of social vulnerability and its component input variables. We demonstrated that the previously theorized pillars of social vulnerability, established with indicators drawn from the US Census data, were not well supported in a latent variable framework. Only one of the five pillar models (Socioeconomic Status) achieved acceptable fit, while two others had marginal fit even after significant model respecification that may not generalize to new samples. Our results underscore challenges with the construct validity of SoVI <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Spielman et al. 2020)</ref>, which remain an obstacle to achieving the goal of specifying a widely applicable vulnerability index. At the same time, we also face the reality that social vulnerability to hazards and disasters may be more context-specific than many other public health constructs, and that a generalizable indicator may be unnecessary for locally identifying vulnerable communities and facilitating effective disaster preparedness, response, and recovery efforts. Simply put, space matters, and social vulnerability manifest itself differently across study/impact areas. As many scholars have previously found, a one size fits all approach to social vulnerability may not be achievable <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Cutter and Emrich 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Cutter and Finch 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Tapsell et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Emrich and Cutter 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Tate 2012)</ref>.</p><p>At both the pillar level and the overall SoVI construct level, confirmatory models did not fit the data and showed low reliability, indicating that the SoVI model applied to the New York region following Hurricane Sandy was not portable to a statewide vulnerability analysis in Florida. The establishment of well-fitting confirmatory factor models is the minimum requirement to establishing unidimensional, reliable indices of social vulnerability which can then be examined for generalizability. Results from our study indicated that this minimum requirement is not met for the pillar approach to SoVI put forth by <ref type="bibr">Rufat and colleagues (2019)</ref>, at least not with the proposed set of indicators. The consistently poor fit of our attempted models suggests that the theorized SoVI pillars may not adequately capture latent commonalities between groups of census variables that are thought to measure common vulnerabilities. While the socioeconomic status latent variable did achieve acceptable fit and reliability after considerable modification, this is likely a consequence of overfitting the model. When a model is excessively modified, it will fit the observed data very well; however, the likelihood that such a data-driven model will generalize to new samples is substantially lower than if the theorized model had fit the data well without modification <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Babyak 2004</ref>). This general finding aligns with criticism of the internal consistency and construct validity of SoVI <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Spielman et al. 2020)</ref>, further suggesting that all indicators of social vulnerability may not be applicable to every community. On the other hand, achieving an acceptable model does provide some degree of optimism that at least the socioeconomic dimension of SoVI may be generalizable across contexts.</p><p>While a number of factors likely explain why these models failed to fit the data, one reason stems from properties of the indicator variables, pointing to important considerations for future attempts to fit SoVI models. A critical step in these attempts is an examination of the distribution of each indicator. In our data, several variables were constants or near constants for Florida (e.g., percent working in the extractive sector; percent Native American). Variables with no or low variability do not contribute to covariation and detract from the fit of the model. Moreover, a variable with low to no variance cannot serve as an informative predictor of some outcome, such as hardships during disaster recovery. Finding differences in the variation of indicators across datasets, as is the case when our data are compared to the data on Hurricane Sandy presented by <ref type="bibr">Rufat and colleagues (2019)</ref>, suggests that indicators may be region and disaster specific, limiting the generalizability of social vulnerability models in general and SoVI in this case.</p><p>Given that generalizability is essential for prediction, it seems important to identify a minimum set of indicators that are likely useful across situations and therefore generalizable. To the extent, it is possible to identify a minimum number of indicators that are generalizable, these indicators could serve as anchor items (i.e., items used across all regions and contexts in the assessment of vulnerability to disasters). For each use case, the generalizable anchor items could be combined with specific indicators that are more variable across certain disasters and regions. Multiple group latent variable models represent a promising methodology for pursuing such an approach, as they allow a combination of invariant and region/disaster specific indicators. In order to test the notion of a SoVI that includes a set of fixed generalizable indicators and a subset of specific ones that may vary across disasters or regions, researchers would need data across multiple disasters and regions, all contributing a comparable set of measures.</p><p>Many indicators depend on context for their valence in social vulnerability and may not be theorized to consistently increase or decrease social vulnerability. For example, a greater percent Hispanic may result in greater vulnerability in a less diverse region such as northern Florida, but may buffer households from vulnerability in more diverse places like South Florida, particularly in Florida's most populous county, Miami-Dade, where the majority of the population is Hispanic. Consequently, while Rufat and colleagues' (2019) SoVI pillars made theoretical sense for the New York metropolitan area, Florida's sociodemographic context may present a challenge to constructing them using this set of 27 indicators.</p><p>Other researchers have also raised the possibility that the indicators that are typically combined during social vulnerability analyses might be better used as independent measures, rather than combined in an index <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Fekete 2019)</ref>. Such a formative modeling approach would test common indicators as a proxy for social vulnerability, rather than attempt to directly approximate this latent construct. Either way, this approach requires a "best" set of indicators, which remains elusive throughout the vulnerability case study literature, and certainly no set of indicators has been validated across a region as large and diverse as the US. Given the limitations described earlier, it is possible that the social vulnerability of large, diverse regions cannot be reduced to a small set of generalizable indicators with any meaningful degree of precision that would shape public policy in the planning and response to disasters. It is more likely that a big data approach leveraging a very large set of indicators would improve precision but at greater cost. For local and regional planning purposes, perhaps the local scale is what matters most.</p><p>Variable selection may also be limited by the classic modifiable areal unit problem, i.e., the ecological fallacy that can inadvertently arise when grouping data into regions at different geographic scales <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Openshaw 1984)</ref>. When conceptualizing social vulnerability, the intent is to identify individuals who are at the greatest risk of hardship following a natural disaster. To operationalize this, a predictive model would require individual-level data, which is generally unavailable due to important ethical restrictions on the use of personal identifiable information. In homogenous regions, census tract-level data may approximate individual-level data. But in heterogeneous areas such as Florida, particularly urban areas with severe residential segregation over short distances, the census tract level of analysis may not accurately reflect the individual social vulnerability. Moreover, such levels of analyses may put decision makers at risk of ecological fallacies, in which conclusions based on group-level data are erroneously applied to individuals within that group. Consequently, indices relying on census tract data may provide valuable risk prediction in regions with homogenous and stable populations but may not be specific enough in more dynamic areas.</p><p>A related issue that may account for differences in indicator variability across contexts is that different relative scales are appropriate for different regions with different costs of living. A household income that suggests vulnerability in one area, such as New York City or Miami, may present little risk in nearby rural or suburban areas such as Central Florida. One approach is to normalize indicators that are in absolute scales in order to standardize their meaning across regions. While past studies have used Z-scores as an attempt to address this issue <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Emrich et al. 2020)</ref>, Z-scores computed relative to the overall population still reflect regional heterogeneity. Future studies may consider the use of multilevel models, which would account for effects relative to the group mean (e.g., household income relative to others in Central Florida rather than the country overall). Hierarchical models can improve the accuracy of comparisons by controlling for regional homogeneity and could be further refined to adjust for spatial interaction effects between regions (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Tate 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Dong et al. 2020)</ref>. Hierarchical models also enable the simultaneous modeling of indicators and their interactions across multiple scales, an approach likely to bring new insights to social vulnerability analysis.</p><p>These issues of scale and level of analysis have led others to call for improvements to social vulnerability analysis that differentiate urban and rural places and that conceptually separating social vulnerability at national, community, and individual scales <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Fekete 2019)</ref>. We must acknowledge that Florida is, both empirically and experientially, an unusual place that does not uniformly conform to the theoretical manifestation of social vulnerability. For reasons already noted, Florida's most populated county, Miami-Dade, is so different from the rest of the state that it may bias our attempts to reconstruct the SoVI pillars used by <ref type="bibr">Rufat and colleagues (2019)</ref>. That said, the New York metropolitan area used by Rufat and colleagues is itself a diverse urban area, and if the pillars and indicators were robust enough, we should have experienced fewer modeling challenges.</p><p>Natural hazards require a coordinated response from federal to local scales, and scale matching in disaster response has long been a challenge for environmental policy <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Baker and Refsgaard 2007)</ref>. Ultimately the implementation of disaster response occurs locally, often implemented by federal agencies, but under direction from state and local officials who know their constituencies best. By using a context-driven set of indicators, vulnerability models could be tailored to pinpoint local risk and protective factors. Social vulnerability measures can tell us about differential recovery. SoVI and its input variables are highly utilized in emergency management <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Tierney and Oliver-Smith 2012)</ref> and have proven useful in linking outcomes to underlying sociodemographic in several disaster specific case studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Cutter and Finch 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Domingue and Emrich 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Emrich et al. 2020)</ref>, demonstrating how baseline conditions are influential across the emergency management cycle. From this perspective, we can identify interventions and pathways toward hazard mitigation by setting aside the theoretically wobbly ideal of a single vulnerability model-one that can be broadly applied to different types of disasters at different geographic scales-and instead focusing on the links between variables and outcomes.</p><p>This study faced several important limitations. We tested the portability of a prior analysis of the New York metropolitan area to the state of Florida using a defined set of indicators and pillar design. When our modeling efforts failed, we did not explore other indicators or pillars in the absence of new theory. It is possible that a data-driven reconfiguration of the pillars might have improved our modeling approach, but such an approach would abandon longstanding theory about the drivers of social vulnerability. Further, Florida's peninsular shape, which creates problems for geospatial analysis, may also lead to challenges in underlying data representations, estimations, and variation. Finally, because SoVI and disasters are both place-specific in nature, perhaps a tract-level index computed at the state level should make little empirical sense given the local scales at which processes such as residential segregation operate. Perhaps SoVI's utility as a measure of outcomes would be much more appreciable at smaller scales of analysis such as disaster impact areas or informing city level programs and regional intervention.</p><p>Future research on the development and validation of vulnerability should consider the kind of evidence needed to validate an index across multiple contexts and how a balance of universal and context-specific indicators may be integrated. A social vulnerability index might be reconceptualized using different mixes of theoretical and data-driven approaches to deriving its underlying pillars, and with potentially different indicators and pillars for different scales of analysis, and for different types of disasters. Future social vulnerability measures will likely evolve along with changes in data availability and more robust conceptual and practical ties between vulnerability and outcomes. Ultimately new approaches must strike the balance between theoretical rigor and the reality that-despite the challenges outlined in this paper and others-applications of social vulnerability measures, including SoVI, continue to provide decision makers with empirical, pragmatic measures of a complex concept.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Conclusion</head><p>This study sought to confirm the construct validity of theoretically driven organizations of social vulnerability indices, with the goal of empirically testing the generalizability of SoVI in diverse contexts. The lack of alignment between previous formulations of SoVI and census tract-level data for Florida, as demonstrated in this study, does not support the generalizability of SoVI to other contexts-at least in SoVI's current form. We believe several limitations in the data contributed to the poor psychometric evidence produced from this study. The poor support for the theorized pillars of SoVI and alternative model structures suggest the need to reconsider the input variables and scale of analysis, if the goal is to measure a generalizable construct (or subconstructs) of social vulnerability. This study highlights the challenges inherent in measuring social vulnerability across different geographic settings and types of natural disasters and the need for more robust assessment of confirmatory models.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1 Theoretical correlated factor structure of SoVI</figDesc><graphic coords="5,165.80,57.85,226.80,381.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2 Frequency distributions for all 28 census tract-level SoVI indicators before conducting logarithmic transformations</figDesc><graphic coords="11,49.59,397.95,340.20,192.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Descriptive statistics for each of the SoVI census variables at the census tract level</figDesc><table><row><cell>Kurtosis</cell><cell>10.87</cell><cell>4.26</cell><cell>3.30</cell><cell>29.31</cell><cell>10.04</cell><cell>2.44</cell><cell>60.41</cell><cell>2.36</cell><cell>5.31</cell><cell>0.36</cell><cell>3.83</cell><cell>0.37</cell><cell>1.58</cell><cell>1.78</cell><cell>14.57</cell><cell>-0.06</cell><cell>9.22</cell><cell>3.89</cell><cell>2.19</cell><cell>170.57</cell><cell>44.84</cell><cell>0.60</cell><cell>4.35</cell><cell>6.99</cell><cell>1.08</cell></row><row><cell>Skew</cell><cell>2.59</cell><cell>1.56</cell><cell>1.25</cell><cell>4.05</cell><cell>2.76</cell><cell>0.73</cell><cell>6.56</cell><cell>1.32</cell><cell>1.67</cell><cell>0.75</cell><cell>1.77</cell><cell>0.53</cell><cell>1.06</cell><cell>0.06</cell><cell>-2.08</cell><cell>-0.57</cell><cell>2.44</cell><cell>2.07</cell><cell>1.68</cell><cell>9.95</cell><cell>5.32</cell><cell>0.72</cell><cell>2.04</cell><cell>2.24</cell><cell>0.80</cell></row><row><cell>SD</cell><cell>16,955.50</cell><cell>0.11</cell><cell>0.09</cell><cell>165,567.79</cell><cell>0.07</cell><cell>0.08</cell><cell>0.03</cell><cell>0.09</cell><cell>413.43</cell><cell>10.62</cell><cell>0.13</cell><cell>0.56</cell><cell>0.08</cell><cell>0.06</cell><cell>0.05</cell><cell>0.21</cell><cell>0.03</cell><cell>0.20</cell><cell>0.23</cell><cell>0.01</cell><cell>0.01</cell><cell>0.16</cell><cell>0.13</cell><cell>0.07</cell><cell>0.08</cell></row><row><cell>M</cell><cell>29,065.44</cell><cell>0.16</cell><cell>0.28</cell><cell>205,014.73</cell><cell>0.05</cell><cell>0.20</cell><cell>0.01</cell><cell>0.13</cell><cell>1161.64</cell><cell>43.81</cell><cell>0.27</cell><cell>2.64</cell><cell>0.13</cell><cell>0.48</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.64</cell><cell>0.02</cell><cell>0.15</cell><cell>0.22</cell><cell>&lt; 0.01</cell><cell>&lt; 0.01</cell><cell>0.37</cell><cell>0.11</cell><cell>0.07</cell><cell>0.15</cell></row><row><cell>Variable label</cell><cell>PERCAP</cell><cell>POVTY</cell><cell>UNEMP</cell><cell>MHSEVAL</cell><cell>RICH200K</cell><cell>SERV</cell><cell>EXTRCT</cell><cell>ED12LES</cell><cell>MDGRENT</cell><cell>MEDAGE</cell><cell>AGEDEP</cell><cell>PUNIT</cell><cell>FHH</cell><cell>FEMLBR</cell><cell>FEMALE</cell><cell>MARFAM</cell><cell>ASIAN</cell><cell>BLACK</cell><cell>HISP</cell><cell>NATAM</cell><cell>NURSE</cell><cell>SSBEN</cell><cell>ESL</cell><cell>NOAUTO</cell><cell>UNISURED</cell></row><row><cell>Census variable</cell><cell>Per capita income ($)</cell><cell>Living under poverty line (%)</cell><cell>Unemployed (%)</cell><cell>Median house value ($)</cell><cell>Annual income over $200,000 (%)</cell><cell>Working in service industry (%)</cell><cell>Working extractive industry (%)</cell><cell>Less than 12 years of education (%)</cell><cell>Median rent ($)</cell><cell>Median age of population (#)</cell><cell>Population with age-based dependents (%)</cell><cell>People per housing unit (#)</cell><cell>Female head of households (%)</cell><cell>Female population that is employed (%)</cell><cell>Population that is female (%)</cell><cell>Families that are married (%)</cell><cell>Population that is Asian American (%)</cell><cell>Population that is African American/Black (%)</cell><cell>Population that is Hispanic/Latino (%)</cell><cell>Population that is native American (%)</cell><cell>Residing in nursing homes (%)</cell><cell>Receiving social security benefits (%)</cell><cell>English as a second language (%)</cell><cell>Without automobiles (%)</cell><cell>Uninsured (%)</cell></row><row><cell>Factor</cell><cell>Socioeconomic status</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Population structure</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Race and ethnicity</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Access and needs</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fit indices for single-factor CFA models with subsequent modified models including residual covariances between indicators CFI, comparative fit index; RMSEA, root mean square error approximation; SRMR, standardized root mean residual a Model includes each theorized factor with correlations between factors b Model includes each theorized factor model and a general factor indicated by all SoVI variables c All SoVI variables loading onto a broad, single factor</figDesc><table><row><cell>d Single-factor model with 23 residual covariances included</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Unstandardized and</cell></row><row><cell>standardized factor loadings,</cell></row><row><cell>with associated test statistics, for</cell></row><row><cell>the final single-factor models</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Author contributions All authors made substantial contributions. Funding Zachary T. Goodman is supported by the National Institutes of Health (T32-HL007426).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Availability of data and material</head><p>All data used in this study are publicly available, and analytical code is available upon request.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Compliance with ethical standards</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflicts of interest</head><p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to report.</p><p>Publisher's Note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What you see may not be what you get: a brief, nontechnical introduction to overfitting in regression-type models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Babyak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychosom Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="421" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Institutional development and scale matching in disaster response management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Refsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecol Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="343" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparative analysis of disaster risk, vulnerability and resilience composite indicators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Beccari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/currents.dis.453df025e34b682e9737f95070f9b970</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1371/currents.dis" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Curr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">70</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>453df 025e3 4b682 e9737 f9507 0f9b9</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing the vulnerability of coastal communities to extreme storms: the case of revere</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Moser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ratick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1023/A:1009609710795</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MA., USA. Mitig Adapt Strat Glob Change</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">795</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Surging seas</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Climate Central</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social vulnerability to environmental hazards*</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Cutter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Boruff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Shirley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1540-6237.8402002</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/1540-6237.8402002" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soc Sci Q</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="242" to="261" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moral hazard, social catastrophe: the changing face of vulnerability along the hurricane coasts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Cutter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Emrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Am Acad Political Soc Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">604</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="102" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temporal and spatial changes in social vulnerability to natural hazards</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Cutter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Finch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2301" to="2306" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Revealing the vulnerability of people and places: a case study of Georgetown County, South Carolina</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Cutter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/0004-5608.00219</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Assoc Am Geogr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="713" to="737" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social vulnerability and procedural equity: exploring the distribution of disaster aid across counties in the United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Domingue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Emrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am Rev Public Adm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="897" to="913" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developing a locally adaptive spatial multilevel logistic model to analyze ecological effects on health using individual census records</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Am As Geogr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="739" to="757" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Remaking white residential segregation: metropolitan diversity and neighborhood change in the United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ellis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Holloway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fiorio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Urban Geogr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="519" to="545" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Social vulnerability to climate-sensitive hazards in the Southern United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Emrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Cutter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1175/2011WCAS1092.1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1175/2011WCAS1092.1" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Wea Climate Soc</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="193" to="208" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring social equity in flood recovery funding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Emrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Larson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ Hazards</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="228" to="250" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social vulnerability (re-)assessment in context to natural hazards: review of the usefulness of the spatial indicator approach and investigations of validation demands</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fekete</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s13753-019-0213-1</idno>
		<idno>1375 3-019-0213-1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Disaster Risk Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="220" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principles and practices of structural equation modeling, 4th edn. American Psychological Association</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social vulnerabilities and Hurricane Katrina: an unnatural disaster in New Orleans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Laska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Morrow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4031/002533206787353123</idno>
		<idno>00253 32067 87353 123</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4031/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Marine Technology Society Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">013 e3182 433a3 0 National oceanic and atmospheric administration, office for coastal management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Llabre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/PSY.0b013e3182433a30</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.nhc.noaa.gov/data/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychosom Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="177" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-06">2012. June 2020. 2018. 2018. June 2020</date>
			<publisher>NOAA Office for Coastal Management</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Charleston, SC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Atlantic Hurricane Season</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Will the hardest-hit communities get the coronavirus vaccine?</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/10/30/health/covid-vaccine-racism.html" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">New York Times</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-01-10">2020. 10 Jan 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">California may consider &apos;historical injustice&apos; when allocating COVID-19 vaccine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Npr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2020/12/16/942452184/california-may-consider-historical-injustice-when-allocating-coronavirus-vaccine" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-01">2020. January 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ecological fallacies and the analysis of areal census data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Openshaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1068/a160017</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1068/a160017" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ Plan A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">lavaan: an R package for structural equation modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Rosseel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Stat Softw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How valid are social vulnerability models?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rufat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Emrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Antolini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Am As Geograph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1131" to="1153" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Equitable allocation of Covid-19 vaccines: an analysis of the initial allocation plans of CDC&apos;s jurisdictions with implications for disparate impact monitoring</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Weintraub</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2139/ssrn.3740041</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.3740041" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SSRN Elect J</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patterns and causes of uncertainty in the American community survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Spielman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Folch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nagle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.apgeog.2013.11.002</idno>
		<idno>11.002</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apgeog.2013" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl Geogr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating social vulnerability indicators: criteria and their application to the social vulnerability index</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Spielman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tuccillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Folch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Hazards</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="436" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social vulnerability to natural hazards</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tapsell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mccarthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Faulkner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alexander</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">State of the art report from CapHaz-Net&apos;s WP4 London</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vulnerability to flooding: health and social dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Tapsell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Penning-Rowsell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Tunstall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos Transact Math Phys Eng Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">360</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1511" to="1525" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social vulnerability indices: a comparative assessment using uncertainty and sensitivity analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11069-012-0152-2</idno>
		<idno>1106 9-012-0152-2</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Hazards</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="325" to="347" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social dimensions of disaster recover</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tierney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Oliver-Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Mass Emerg Disasters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A framework for vulnerability analysis in sustainability science</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kasperson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Matson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.1231335100</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1231335100" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8074" to="8079" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On common factor and principal component representations of data: implications for theory and for confirmatory replications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Widaman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10705511.2018.1478730</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Struct Equ Model Multidiscip J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="829" to="847" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
