<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the Complex Landscape of Electric Vehicle Adoption: Understanding Incentives and Overcoming Barriers for Sustainable Transportation in the US</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Farshid</forename><surname>Javadnejad</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Old Dominin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Norfol</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mohammad</forename><surname>Jahanbakh</surname></persName>
							<email>mohammad.jahanbakht@uta.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Texas at Arlington</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Arlington</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Cesar</forename><forename type="middle">Ariel</forename><surname>Pinto</surname></persName>
							<email>cpinto2@albany.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">The University at Albany</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>New York</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Azita</forename><surname>Saeidi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Old Dominin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Norfol</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Old Dominin University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">The University of Texas at Arlington</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">University at Albany</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">State University of New York Azita Saeidi Old Dominin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the Complex Landscape of Electric Vehicle Adoption: Understanding Incentives and Overcoming Barriers for Sustainable Transportation in the US</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.21203/rs.3.rs-3168405/v1</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T20:50+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Eelectric vehicles adoption</term>
					<term>incentives</term>
					<term>barriers</term>
					<term>economic and market</term>
					<term>technical</term>
					<term>policy</term>
					<term>social factors</term>
					<term>and advanced shbone diagram Eelectric vehicles adoption</term>
					<term>incentives</term>
					<term>barriers</term>
					<term>economic and market</term>
					<term>technical</term>
					<term>policy</term>
					<term>social factors</term>
					<term>and advanced fishbone diagram</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The adoption of electric vehicles (EVs) is influenced by a range of incentives and barriers. EVs offer benefits such as reduced emissions and lower costs but face challenges in gaining widespread acceptance. Government subsidies, tax credits, and EV charging infrastructure have played a pivotal role in driving EV adoption, making them more financially attractive and convenient. However, barriers such as high upfront costs, limited driving range, insufficient charging infrastructure, and consumer concerns about battery life and availability have hindered broader uptake. This study presents a novel approach that considers both incentives and barriers to summarize the factors influencing EV development in the US. Through a comprehensive literature review, we explore the various barriers and incentives that affect EV deployment. Using an advanced fishbone diagram, we categorize the factors into economic and market, technical, policy, and social categories, providing a better understanding of their interrelationships. We discuss critical incentives and barriers within each category, offering a detailed analysis of their impact on EV adoption. Additionally, we present the results of a quantitative analysis of selected factors by examining their correlations with EV sales. This research provides a comprehensive understanding of the incentives and barriers to EV development in the US, assisting policymakers and stakeholders in developing effective strategies and initiatives for promoting EV adoption and achieving a cleaner and more sustainable future.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>There is an overwhelming consensus that the escalating amount of carbon emissions has caused global warming. These emissions are generated from diverse sources, with the transportation industry playing a crucial role <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Zhang &amp; Bai, 2021)</ref>. Significantly, vehicular CO2 emissions account for a considerable amount of fossil fuel burning in the atmosphere <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Tahami et al., 2020)</ref>. The expansion of cities and economic development in developing nations has made private automobiles increasingly accessible to citizens <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Babar &amp; Ali, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Ghanbari, 2013)</ref>. The number of registered vehicles in the United States has dramatically expanded from 2003's 23.8 million to 2022's 290.8 million. EVs are widely prescribed as an ecofriendlier alternative to address this expanding problem.</p><p>The US transportation sector accounts for the most significant proportion of greenhouse gas emissions, approximately 29%, out of all sources <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Bibra et al., 2022)</ref>.EVs are highly efficient, surpassing conventional internal combustion engine (ICE) models by two to four times. They reduce reliance on oil-based fuels and can significantly lower greenhouse gas emissions when powered by low-carbon sources. With zero tailpipe emissions, they effectively tackle air pollution <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Bibra et al., 2021)</ref>. Several nations are promoting EVs to fulfill environmental objectives (Fast Facts: U.S. Transportation Sector Greenhouse Gas Emissions, 2021). The International Energy Agency labels the transition to electric cars as essential to reaching global carbon neutrality before 2050. According to the agency, EVs' market share will surge dramatically from 5% to over 60% of total car sales by 2030 <ref type="bibr">(Green Vehicle Guide, 2022)</ref>. In 2021, electric vehicle sales rocketed to 6.6 million units, tripling the amount seen as recent as two years ago and constituting around 9% of the global automobile market. Europe and China have emerged as leaders in the EV revolution, achieving market penetrations of 16% and 14% respectively. In contrast, EVs only make up 4.5% of the American market. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Bouckaert et al., 2021)</ref> Despite the numerous benefits of electric vehicles, various barriers and obstacles have hindered their deployment. In contrast, incentives have been implemented to encourage their adoption. Therefore, evaluating incentives and barriers is crucial to understanding the factors affecting EV development in the US. This study presents a novel approach that considers incentives and obstacles to summarize the factors impacting EV development in the US. Based on a comprehensive literature review, the various barriers and incentives that affect the deployment of electric vehicles have been explored. We utilized an advanced fishbone diagram that offers a more complex explanation system of the phenomenon, providing a better understanding of the interrelated factors that impact EV development. This study aims to contribute to existing knowledge and provide a deeper understanding of the US's incentives and barriers to electric vehicle development.</p><p>Our research offers an essential tool for policymakers, electric vehicle makers, and all other transportation stakeholders. We can exploit our comprehension of the stimuli and roadblocks to electric vehicle progress to formulate a more environmentally friendly and productive transportation system that benefits everyone. This paper is organized as follows: Section 1 describes the methodology used to create a comprehensive model for promoting EV adoption, using an advanced fishbone diagram that captures a broad range of factors and can be applied to different fields; In section 2, a literature review was conducted to identify all influential factors related to the adoption of electric vehicles;In Section 3 we categorized these factors into four main categories: economic and market, technical, policy, and social. We further discussed critical incentives and barriers within each category, providing a detailed analysis of how they can impact the adoption of electric vehicles; and Section 4 focused on the quantitative analysis of influencing factors in the context of electric vehicle (EV) adoption. Through the collection of data for a subset of factors within established categories, this study provided a comprehensive overview of the relationship between these factors and their impact on EV adoption. The analysis employed statistical techniques and visual representations, such as tables, histograms, scatterplots, and correlation coefficients, to gain insights into the significance and interdependencies of these factors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methodology</head><p>Our study utilized a comprehensive methodology to examine the factors influencing the adoption of EVs. We conducted an extensive literature review to identify and categorize the various incentives and barriers associated with EV adoption. These factors were classified into four categories: economic and market, technical, policy, and social. Our study showcases a novel and comprehensive model that promotes the adoption of EVs by simultaneously considering all incentives and barriers. To further analyze the relationships between these factors and EV adoption, we created an advanced fishbone diagram., The diagram's versatility extends beyond EV adoption, making it a valuable tool for decision-making and problem-solving in various industries. For this study, the diagram provides a more detailed and complex explanation system of the phenomenon. Our fishbone diagram presents a comprehensive and detailed analysis of the factors impacting EV adoption. The diagram depicts the leading cause as the fish head, with the upper rib branches and sub-branches representing positive and stimulating factors, while the lower branches symbolize negative and obstructing factors. Furthermore, we conducted a detailed analysis of critical incentives and barriers within each category, shedding light on how these factors can impact the adoption of electric vehicles.</p><p>Collected data provided a comprehensive overview of quantitative information. Moreover, we utilized the Pearson correlation coefficients matrix to quantitatively analyze the relationships between feature variables. Through the analysis of correlation coefficients, we identified key influencing factors and their interdependencies.</p><p>This methodology allowed us to gain a deeper understanding of the factors influencing EV adoption and their impact. It provided a framework for evaluating the relative importance of each factor and their potential effects on EV adoption. The insights gained from this methodology can inform policymakers, industry stakeholders, and researchers in developing effective strategies and initiatives to promote the widespread adoption of EVs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Background</head><p>The research conducted by <ref type="bibr">Wang et al.</ref> found that policy measures, such as financial incentives, information provision, and convenience measures, are positively and significantly related to consumer intentions to adopt EVs. They found that convenience measures were the most critical policy for promoting EV adoption.</p><p>Financial incentives, such as direct subsidies, tax exemptions, and road-tolling exemptions, aim to lower the cost of purchasing and operating EVs. Information provision policy measures aim to provide information about EVs to consumers, such as the price, practicality, reliability, safety, driving range, charging time, battery life, fuel consumption, and environmental performance. Convenience policy measures aim to make it more convenient for consumers to use EVs, such as infrastructure construction, and privileges such as access to high-occupancy vehicle lanes <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Wang et al., 2017)</ref>. The research conducted by Hasan integrated multiple EV attributes, such as cost aspects, range-recharge, policy measures, environmental features, symbolic characteristics, and availability of EV models, to measure their impact on consumers' overall satisfaction with EV use <ref type="bibr">(Hasan, 2021a)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Gong et al.</ref> examined consumer preferences related to EV attributes and government incentives and identified three sets of core attributes that describe EV alternatives: vehicle properties, potential government support schemes, and EV market share. The results showed that consumers are unwilling to pay a large premium for the upfront cost of an EV, they want it to have an affordable purchase price and low operating costs, and they like strong government incentives. The study also found that EV acceptance levels increase with education, employment, and income <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Gong et al., 2020)</ref>. In a survey conducted by Krupa et al. on plug-in hybrid electric vehicles (PHEVs) in the US market, it was found that significant savings on monthly fuel costs, at-home recharge facilities, and a tax rebate of $7000 were the factors that increased consumer comfort level with PHEV technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Krupa et al., 2014)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Wolbertus et al.</ref> discovered that restrictive policies regarding charging infrastructure could negatively impact both the charging behavior of current EV owners and the purchase intentions of current ICE owners <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Wolbertus et al., 2018)</ref>. Adhikari et al. developed a framework for identifying and analyzing barriers to EV adoption classified into five categories: technical, policy, economic, infrastructure, and social, and ranked based on expert opinions <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Adhikari et al., 2020</ref>). Cherchi's research found that the availability of charging infrastructure and parking policies significantly affected purchase intention. The study also found that informational and normative conformity significantly impacted the choice between EVs and conventional vehicles, with informational conformity having a high impact on EV utility, but only when the reported experience was negative. The study emphasized the importance of providing accurate information to avoid misinformation <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Cherchi, 2017)</ref>. In the research conducted by Yang et al. using the fsQCA methodology, it was found that social conformity plays a significant role in increasing demand for EVs and that effective policy measures, such as tax exemptions and purchase subsidies, in combination with a favorable policy environment for EV supply, can lead to the diffusion of EVs. The study also emphasized the importance of charging infrastructure in promoting EVdispersal . It highlighted that countries wishing to promote EVs need to spread charging infrastructure along with tax exemptions and purchase subsidies. The study also noted that there is no single effective policy tool or set of circumstances for EV supply and that a compelling policy mix considering the circumstances of the countries concerned, is necessary to promote EV diffusion. The study highlighted the high penetration rate of EVs in Norway and suggested that this is due to a combination of factors, including a tax credit system, direct aid subsidy system, high economic status, and relatively good charging infrastructure <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Yong &amp; Park, 2017)</ref>.</p><p>The research by Krishna aimed to understand consumer perception and barriers to adopting electric vehicles through electronic word-of-mouth (eWOM) and thematic analysis. Collected data revealed several concerns, such as safety, affordability, infrastructure, and intangible factors like authenticity and heritage. The study found that these concerns were interdependent, and solutions proposed by previous research were discussed. Some concerns, like safety, were found to be not entirely true, while others, like affordability, required more attention. The study concluded that incorporating desirability in electric vehicles is vital for widespread adoption and that the interdependency of barriers highlights the complexity of providing solutions <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Krishna, 2021)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Noela et al.</ref> argued that driving range anxiety, a common concern among consumers regarding the limited driving range of EVs, is not solely a technical or psychological issue but also a rhetorical construction. They suggest that policy solutions addressing driving range anxiety should also consider rhetorical responses and that understanding the role of rhetorical construction in innovation diffusion can have broader implications for effectively implementing new technologies. Additionally, the authors suggest that further research should apply the concept of reactionary rhetoric to other theories on user behavior in technology diffusion and transitions <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Noela et al., 2019)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Encarnação et al. (2018)</ref> suggest that transitioning to EVs requires collective action and government intervention. This includes subsidies, "green" taxes, and public-civil sector synergies to increase demand and offset costs. The civil sector can also play a key role in promoting EV adoption by organizing and influencing public policy. Overall, a coordinated effort from all sectors of society is necessary for widespread EV adoption <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Encarnação et al., 2018)</ref>.</p><p>A study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Debnath et al. (2021)</ref> used a mixed-method approach of Social Network Analysis (SNA) and Latent Dirichlet Allocation (LDA) to extract critical policy design information from 36,000 Facebook posts related to electric vehicles in the US. They used the PESTLE (Political, Economic, Social, Technological, Legal, and Environmental) framework to classify the information and found high modularity in the posts related to political, economic, and legal categories. The results also revealed the influence of the 2020 presidential election on clean energy and low-carbon programs impacting EVs and their funding allocation. The study concluded that a data-driven approach using computational social sciences could be used to classify policy information and retrieve knowledge on EV-related public communications <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Debnath et al., 2021)</ref>. In the United States, a study conducted by <ref type="bibr">Bushnell et al. and Diamond found a</ref> strong link between fuel costs and EVs adoption. Through a spatially-disaggregated panel dataset of monthly EV registration data and detailed records of gasoline and electricity costs in California from 2014 to 2017, the research shows that an equivalent shift in gasoline prices has around four to six times the effect on EV demand as a similar proportion change in electricity prices. These results bring up implications for optimum EV subsidies and how gas prices influence car purchasing decisions, consistent with the evidence in literature concerning vehicle selection and consumer behavior in electricity markets. Policymakers striving to drive demand for EVs will likely be limited in their efforts to do so if input costs produce rewards that significantly differ based on location and, in significant instances, dissuade the behavior they are attempting to support <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Bushnell et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Diamond, 2009</ref>). Kodjak's study pointed out that there are significant gaps between consumer expectations and EVs performance, such as limited driving range, high purchasing price, long charging time, and insufficient charging stations, which will limit the market size and result in automobile manufacturers hesitating to enter the EVs market <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Kodjak, 2012</ref>).</p><p>Eppstein's study suggested the high purchase cost, limited range, long recharge time, limited recharge availability, and consumers' unfamiliarity with EVs as potential barriers for consumers to adopt EVs <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Eppstein et al., 2011)</ref>.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> provides a comprehensive overview of the factors influencing the adoption of EVs. It highlights key findings from various studies, shedding light on incentives and barriers that impact the acceptance and uptake of EVs. The factors that were examined encompass various aspects, including financial incentives, policy measures, technical considerations, social factors, and infrastructure-related challenges. By summarizing these factors and their corresponding results, the table offers valuable insights into the complex dynamics surrounding EV adoption.  Conversely, the lower rib branches and sub-branches depict the potential barriers, including economic and market, technical, policy, and social factors, that can hinder the widespread adoption of EVs. By utilizing this advanced fishbone diagram, policymakers and stakeholders are equipped with a valuable tool to make informed decisions and develop effective strategies. The diagram enables a detailed analysis of the interplay between various factors, allowing for a better understanding of their impact on EV adoption. This comprehensive model has been applied to the field of EVs and can be with other cause-and-effect scenarios. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Economic and market incentives</head><p>Economic and market incentives are crucial in developing and adopting EVs. Lower maintenance costs, tax incentives, subsidies, availability of different EV models, income and economic status, fuel prices, country of manufacture, and EV availability at nearby dealers are some of the incentives that can encourage consumers to choose EVs over traditional vehicles. These incentives can also help manufacturers and policymakers promote the growth and advancement of EV technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Zheng et al., 2018)</ref>.</p><p>EVs maintenance cost. Due to the fewer moving parts and consequently less wear and tear, EVs need significantly less maintenance than traditional vehicles, reducing the associated costs. Without regular oil changes, brake replacements, and engine maintenance, EV owners benefit from lower maintenance costs. This costsaving feature serves as a draw for potential buyers, thus emphasizing the importance of considering the lower maintenance costs when comparing EVs versus ICE vehicles.</p><p>Fiscal support such as tax incentives, exemptions, and deductions. Tax incentives, exemptions, and credits are important economic tools that greatly influence the adoption of eEVs. Studies indicate that these measures, such as tax exemptions and purchase subsidies, play a crucial role in promoting EV uptake <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Krupa et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Yong &amp; Park, 2017)</ref>. In the United States, federal tax credits of up to $7,500 are available for plug-in hybrid electric vehicle (PHEV) purchases, while many states offer additional financial incentives like sales tax exemptions and extra tax credits. These economic incentives make EVs more appealing and financially viable for consumers.</p><p>Availability of different EV models. The availability of different EV models is considered an incentive for EV development. It provides consumers with more options and increases their satisfaction with EV use. Studies show that the availability of EV models positively affects EV acceptance and is one of the attributes influencing consumer satisfaction with EVs.</p><p>Income. Income played a significant role in shaping the preferences and attitudes of each class towards Evs. Gong et al. examined different income groups and their attitudes toward electric vehicles (EVs) in Australia. Class 1 represented lower-middle-income households, often traditional families without children; a significant portion (63.9%) did not own a car. Class 2 consisted of high-income households with bachelor's degrees, who favored second-hand EVs and emphasized fuel efficiency and EV safety. Class 3 comprised high-income households with college certificates, emphasizing improved EV charging infrastructure and expressing concerns about EV efficiency and driving safety. Class 4 included young middle-income families familiar with EVs, preferred second-hand vehicles, and prioritized battery efficiency. Lastly, Class 5 represented classic families in Australia, showing a preference for small EVs and large sedans while emphasizing fuel efficiency and driving safety. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Gong et al., 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Economic status (GDP per capita). High GDP is essential in incentivizing the development of EVs in countries. Countries with high economic status and tax exemptions/purchase subsidies, such as Norway, USA, Iceland, Sweden, Netherlands, UK, Germany, and Belgium, are likelier to adopt EVs. Effective policy measures, such as tax exemption and purchase subsidies, can lead to the diffusion of EVs when combined with a favorable policy environment for the supply of EVs. Therefore, countries wishing to promote EVs need to spread charging infrastructure along with tax exemption and purchase subsidies <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Yong &amp; Park, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Zhou et al.)</ref>. Fuel prices. The cost of fuel can significantly influence consumer preferences and decisions in favor of EVs, directly impacting demand. Individuals may feel free to switch to EVs if traditional vehicle fuel prices remain low. However, rising fuel expenses could motivate more people to transition to EVs, as they are more costeffective over time.</p><p>Country of manufacturer. In the United States, there is a growing trend of domestic assembly for electric vehicles, with 64% of plug-in electric vehicles (PEVs) and 79% of battery electric vehicles (BEVs) assembled locally in 2021. This shift towards local assembly, along with increased use of domestically sourced materials, has positive economic implications, including job creation and support for the local automotive industry, serving as economic and market incentives for EV development <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Gohlke et al., 2022)</ref>.</p><p>EVs availability in nearby dealers. Consumers are more likely to be satisfied with EV availability if various models of EVs are offered by their favorite carmakers at nearby local EV dealers. Carmakers must introduce new EV models and make them available in the market to give consumers the option to choose their desired EV. Policymakers can support carmakers by providing incentives and imposing market regulations to make EVs more widely available. Therefore, the availability of EV models, brands, and nearby local EV dealers is a crucial consideration in influencing consumer satisfaction and driving EV development and adoption.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Economic and market barriers</head><p>EVs purchasing cost. The comparatively higher purchase cost is the primary financial obstacle to increased EV ownership. Many buyers, especially those without access to financing, need help to cover the upfront price, despite EVs generally having lower operational expenses than their gas-powered counterparts.</p><p>Battery replacement costs. The experts' opinions reveal that EVs' relatively high purchase price and battery replacement cost are ranked as the highest economic barriers against EV diffusion <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Adhikari et al., 2020)</ref>. EV batteries typically have a warranty of 8-10 years; after that period, the battery replacement cost falls on the user. Limited battery life and frequent replacements increase the cost burden on EV users, making ICE vehicles more economically advantageous.</p><p>Market penetration. EVs' market penetration signifies the amount of EV adoption amongst customers in a particular market. This market penetration is both a financial and market impediment to EV progress. When initially introduced EVs, their penetration is typically weak because of little customer cognizance, high early expenses, and range apprehension. Consequently, EVs may only be viable for some shoppers, restraining their reception. However, as EV market penetration rises, the financial and market impediments to their advancement might wane. As more shoppers buy EVs, the economies of scale in manufacturing and charging infrastructure may bring about cheaper customer costs. Moreover, as more EVs hit the road, the accessibility of charging infrastructure may increase, easing range anxiety and making EVs more desirable to more customers.</p><p>Electricity price for charging. The increased cost of electricity used to charge EVs is a significant economic and market impediment to their progress. Consumers are especially attuned to the expense of fuel, meaning higher electricity prices can diminish the desire for EVs. As the daily cost of operating an EV depends primarily on electricity, lower electricity costs can motivate potential EV owners to purchase one.</p><p>Sales conversion inability. Sales conversion challenges hinder the adoption of EVs by making it difficult for companies to convert potential consumers into actual buyers. Limited vehicle supply and choices, longer waiting periods compared to traditional vehicles, and dealerships' reluctance to sell and provide accurate information about EVs contribute to these obstacles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Technical incentives</head><p>Increasing EVs driving range. The limited driving range of EVs is a primary concern for consumers and a significant barrier to widespread adoption. Consumers associate EVs with negative functional perceptions of lower battery range, long recharging time, and lower driving performance at low temperatures. Increasing the driving range of EVs is, therefore, a critical technical incentive for development. It would help mitigate consumers' range anxiety and improve their perception of EVs, increasing their market volume and making automobile manufacturers more willing to enter the EV market.</p><p>Increasing reliability. Improving the reliability of electric vehicles is a technical incentive for their development. This implies that by enhancing the reliability of EVs will, ultimately increase their adoption rate. Moreover, addressing concerns regarding EVs' technological performance, stability, and system reliability can help eliminate barriers to their deployment. Encouraging reliability and performance improvement can result in increased consumer confidence in EVs, driving their adoption and accelerating the transition to a more sustainable transportation system <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Rogers et al., 2014)</ref>.</p><p>Increasing battery life. Typically, the battery life of an EV lasts between eight and ten years, and consumers are responsible for the cost of battery replacement.</p><p>The limited battery life necessitates frequent replacements, a significant financial burden for EV users. Experts have also expressed doubts about the technical performance of EVs due to limited battery life and a lack of evidence regarding reliability and performance. Therefore, increasing battery life is a critical technical incentive for EV development to overcome these barriers and encourage EV adoption.</p><p>Increasing battery density. Increasing battery density can store more energy in a smaller volume or mass, resulting in extended driving ranges. However, pursuing higher battery density is challenging as safety concerns come into play. To address this issue, researchers are actively exploring new materials and technologies that can improve battery density while prioritizing safety.</p><p>Repurposing and recycling of batteries. Researchers have revealed that understanding battery reusability and recyclability influences consumer choice regarding PHEVs and EVs. This awareness is a significant driving force that stimulates the uptake of electric vehicles. Knowing that batteries can be efficiently reused and recycled increases consumer satisfaction and removes their worries about sustainability and environmental impact. Such insight allows buyers to make informed choices that adhere to their ecological principles, consequently broadening PHEVs and EVs as greener transportation alternatives.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Technical barriers</head><p>Charging time. Consumers are less likely to adopt EVs due to the inconvenience of long charging times, limiting their usability and mobility. To address this challenge, governments are issuing policies to support the development of EV infrastructure, including charging infrastructure construction and technical support policies. Providing information on EV charging time and battery life can also help consumers make informed decisions about adopting EVs. Overall, reducing charging time is critical to promoting the adoption of EVs.</p><p>Vehicle body size and type. Consumer preference for EVs is affected by factors such as the size and type of vehicle they desire; thus, vehicle body size and type can act as an impediment to the progress of EVs. Without options that fit particular types of vehicles, demand for EVs decreases, delaying the shift towards an EV-dominant market. Automakers must invest in research and development to design EVs that appeal to a broader range of body sizes and types to combat this technical barrier.</p><p>Energy consumption. Energy consumption represents a general technical barrier to accepting and adopting electric vehicles (EVs). As EVs operate on electricity, their energy efficiency is a critical factor. Efforts have been made to improve the energy efficiency of EVs over time, particularly for battery electric vehicles (BEVs). However, challenges remain, such as maintaining efficiency in plug-in hybrid electric vehicles (PHEVs) and addressing potential increases in energy consumption due to market shifts towards larger vehicle models like SUVs. Enhancing energy efficiency is crucial for minimizing overall energy consumption and promoting the broader adoption of EVs as a sustainable transportation option.</p><p>The limited battery range during winter. The limited battery range during winter is a significant technical barrier to developing and adopting EVs in the United States (US). Cold temperatures affect EVs' battery performance, resulting in a reduced range and increased range anxiety for users in many parts of the country. To mitigate this issue, the US must install publicly accessible charging infrastructure and provide recharging options at home or workplaces. Additionally, regional factors should be considered when developing EV technology and infrastructure to ensure they are suitable for different regions and populations in the US. Addressing this technical barrier could make EVs a more viable and attractive option for consumers in the US, contributing to the transition towards more sustainable transportation.</p><p>Difficulties in getting the PHEV engine serviced or repaired. The challenge of servicing or repairing the PHEV engine is a notable technical hurdle that poses significant implications for electric vehicle development and widespread adoption. Extensive surveys have revealed that many participants have expressed concerns about this issue. These concerns underscore the importance of strengthening investments in training programs and infrastructure to support PHEV maintenance and repair. The voiced concerns regarding PHEV engine servicing and repair highlight the need for a robust support system that can effectively address the technical challenges associated with electric vehicle maintenance. By investing in comprehensive training programs, technicians and mechanics can acquire the specialized skills and knowledge to proficiently service and repair PHEV engines. Furthermore, adequate infrastructure must be established to provide convenient access to maintenance facilities and spare parts, ensuring a seamless servicing experience for PHEV owners.</p><p>The potential inconvenience of recharging the battery. A survey <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Krupa et al., 2014)</ref> among EV users revealed that having recharge facilities at home for convenient overnight charging was crucial. Participants expressed the importance of recharging their vehicles quickly and comfortably in their residences. Additionally, the availability of recharging infrastructure at workplaces or close to frequented businesses was seen as a valuable factor. The lack of publicly accessible recharging stations was identified as a major drawback by EV owners in certain regions. This highlights the significance of a well-established and widespread network of a recharging infrastructure to support the widespread adoption of EVs.</p><p>The lack of evidence on reliability and performance. The lack of evidence on the reliability and performance of EVs compared to conventional vehicles (CVs) presents a unique challenge. With EV technology being relatively new, potential users have concerns regarding the technological performance of EVs, which in turn affects their perceptions. This lack of performance and system stability is a barrier to the widespread deployment of EVs. A survey conducted by Adhikari et al. revealed that within the technical barriers category, the need for more evidence regarding the reliability and performance of EVs ranked third (23.66%), following limited range and battery life. This finding emphasizes the importance of addressing this concern to enhance user confidence and accelerate EV adoption <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Adhikari et al., 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Lack of repair and maintenance workshops. Current EV owners express their disappointment with the limited number of support centers or automotive service stations available for EV compared to those catering to conventional vehicles (CVs). The need for dedicated repair and maintenance facilities for EVs poses a challenge for EV owners needing professional services. This disparity in service availability between EVs and CVs not only creates inconvenience for existing EV owners but also deters potential buyers concerned about their vehicles' future maintenance. . Safety. Safety concerns regarding batteries in electric vehicles (EVs) are prevalent, particularly the fear of battery explosions during accidents or extreme weather conditions, leading to fires that require specialized firefighting approaches. Lithium-Ion batteries, commonly used in EVs, tend to explode and generate heat if punctured or damaged, resulting in a chain reaction known as "thermal runaway." Another safety issue is the lack of noise produced by electric vehicles, making users feel unsafe as they rely on engine noise to gauge speed. However, studies have shown that appropriate noise levels exist in electric cars to ensure attention, especially at low speeds, and comparisons with conventional vehicles reveal similar sound levels at high speeds.3.5</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Policy incentives</head><p>Availability of fast and public charging station. Developing a reliable and efficient charging infrastructure is vital for the widespread adoption of EVs in the United States <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Madina et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Schroeder &amp; Traber, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Sovacool, 2009)</ref>. Users face challenges in planning their trips due to the different charging infrastructure across locations and the unreliability of the existing charging points, leading to range anxiety. Home charging solutions pose issues for households without a garage or allocated parking space, and residents of apartments face similar problems. These significant challenges include the need for more prevalent and fast charging points in rural/suburban areas and the limited number of charging points overall. Long waiting times due to the overpopulation of chargers and the issue of the vehicle-to-refueling index add to the adoption challenges.</p><p>Accessing EV to high occupancy vehicle (HOV)/bus lanes. EVs access to high occupancy vehicles (HOV)/bus lanes is a convenience policy measure implemented in the United States to promote the adoption of EVs. This policy measure allows EVs to use the dedicated lanes meant for public transportation and high occupancy vehicles, thus reducing travel time and improving convenience for EV users. Studies have provided mixed evidence in support of the positive effect of this policy measure on EV purchase intention. However, in Norway, the use-based policy measure of bus-lane access and exemption from road tolls, parking fees, and ferry fees have been found to influence EV adoption. Use-based policy measures such as these reduce the operating costs of EV use and contribute to consumers' overall satisfaction with Evs.</p><p>Unrestricted by the rules of even-and odd-numbered license plates. The policy of allowing EVs to be unrestricted by the rules of even-and odd-numbered license plates is a convenience policy measure implemented in the United States to promote EV penetration. This policy measure is part of relevant government agencies' efforts to provide EV buyers with "privileges" to facilitate their adoption, such as allowing EVs to access high occupancy vehicle (HOV) lanes and dedicated parking spaces. Unrestricted by the rules of even-and odd-numbered license plate policy measures are desirable to consumers because it allows them to avoid vehicle purchase and traffic restrictions based on license plates implemented in some cities to alleviate congestion and air pollution <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Sun et al., 2017)</ref>.</p><p>Road tolling exemption. Road tolling exemption is a use-based policy measure that is implemented in the United States to encourage the adoption of electric vehicles and reduce operating costs. This policy measure is part of the financial incentive policies that aim to lower EVs' purchasing and operating costs alongside direct subsidy and tax exemption policies. Although the efficacy of policy measures on EV adoption is still inconclusive, the exemption from road tolls, parking fees, ferry fees, and access to bus lanes have contributed to consumers' overall satisfaction with EV use.</p><p>Free parking policy or rebate on fee. The policy of offering free parking or rebates on parking fees is a convenience-based policy measure implemented in some countries to encourage the adoption of EVs. This policy measure aims to reduce the cost of EV use and improve convenience for EV users. Studies have found mixed evidence on the effectiveness of this policy measure on EV adoption, with some suggesting a positive impact, while others have found no significant effect. However, in Norway, the use-based policy measure of exemptions has been found to influence EV adoption. While the efficacy of financial incentives is sometimes criticized, free parking or rebates on parking fees can be an effective policy incentive to encourage EV adoption in specific contexts.</p><p>Daytime charging policy. Daytime charging implies that the parking spot next to a charging station is exclusively allocated for electric vehicles during a specified time period of the day.. When charging stations are underutilized compared to average parking occupancy, this can lead to increased parking pressure in neighborhoods with relatively abundant charging infrastructure. To deal with this problem, municipalities can implement a daytime charging policy. Findings indicate that this policy effectively decreases parking pressure due to underutilized EV charging stations. Occupation of charging points is lower where daytime charging policies are implemented. Literature shows that creating uncertainty about the availability of charging stations near home, though, e.g., daytime charging, reduces the purchase intention for EVs <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Wolbertus et al., 2018)</ref>.</p><p>Energy bill discount. Energy bill discounts are government financial supports that can incentivize the purchase of EVs in the United States. These discounts provide a subsidy for annual electricity bills at specific rates, which can help to offset the high cost of electrical energy in the country. As shown in a study conducted in New South Wales, Australia, energy bill discounts until 2025 were the most preferred subsidy by respondents, increasing the probability of purchasing an EV by 0.712% for Class 3 households <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Gong et al., 2020)</ref>. This subsidy was even more attractive than rebates on upfront costs and parking fees, which are popular incentives for EV adoption.</p><p>Ferry fee exemption/reduction. Ferry fee exemption/reduction is a use-based policy measure in the US to reduce the operating costs of EVs and encourage their adoption. Along with other policies like subsidies and tax exemptions, use-based policies such as exemption from road tolls, parking fees, and ferry fees have increased consumers' satisfaction with EV use.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stamp duty discount.</head><p>A stamp duty discount until 2025, is a policy incentive for EV development in the US that provides a one-off offset on stamp duty payable when purchasing an EV. However, it had a minimal impact on consumer preferences compared to other government incentives, such as rebates on upfront costs and parking fees until 2025, which were found to be more effective.</p><p>Battery warranty. In the United States, a robust and extended warranty for plug-in hybrid electric vehicle (PHEV) batteries is pivotal in instilling confidence and peace of mind among potential buyers. According to a survey by <ref type="bibr">Krupa et al.,</ref><ref type="bibr">80</ref>.2% of respondents indicated that a reliable battery warranty would significantly increase their comfort level, provided that the PHEV met their desired features and remained within their budget. This warranty emerged as one of the top seven crucial factors related to PHEV battery recharging and lifespan, alongside considerations such as home recharging capability, access to public recharging stations, battery exchange, and leasing programs, concerns about battery replacement costs, and battery life <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Krupa et al., 2014)</ref>.</p><p>Clean and low-carbon energy programs. Clean and low-carbon energy programs significantly shape the policy incentives for developing EVs in the United States. In particular, the political dimension of EV postings highlights the current need for robust EV policies and funds to support national and state efforts towards electrifying transportation, as well as the institutional discourse around the modernization of vehicle fleets and technology policy efforts concerning the battery and charging infrastructure. Furthermore, the environmental and social justice discourse of EVs is cumulatively shaping the legal dimensions. The social dimension of EV emphasizes this technology's equity and justice aspects, highlighting the welfare effects of EVs and clean energy that connect better health, clean air, and economic saving elements.</p><p>Battery leasing policy. Battery leasing policies have emerged as a promising incentive driving the development and adoption of EVs in the United States. A survey conducted by Krupa et al. revealed that 62.4% of participants recognized the significance of battery leasing, acknowledging its potential to significantly enhance the convenience and attractiveness of owning or leasing a plug-in hybrid electric vehicle (PHEV) <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Krupa et al., 2014)</ref>. By providing battery leasing options, potential buyers can alleviate the upfront costs associated with battery replacements, addressing a primary concern that often dissuades consumers from opting for EVs. Moreover, battery leasing policies contribute to tackling the challenges of battery disposal and recycling, promoting sustainability throughout the vehicle's lifecycle.</p><p>Battery exchange programs. Battery exchange programs could incentivize the adoption of electric vehicles in the United States. Over half of survey participants (62.8%) considered them essential for increasing comfort or for being a deciding factor in purchasing or leasing a PHEV <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Krupa et al., 2014)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6">Policy barriers</head><p>Fossil fuels tax incentives. These incentives, which provide tax advantages and subsidies for fossil fuel-based vehicles, can create an uneven playing field and make EVs less economically competitive. By favoring traditional ICE vehicles, fossil fuels tax incentives can discourage consumers from transitioning to cleaner and more sustainable alternatives like EVs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ignoring enviromental concerns.</head><p>Ignoring environmental concerns is a significant policy barrier to developing EVs in the US. While environmental concern is an essential determinant for individual changes toward environmentally friendly behavior, the market penetration of EVs is not just relying on supportive policy measures. Consumers' environmental concerns and intentions to adopt EVs is also essential. Despite the environmental advantages and properties of EVs, consumers with low environmental concerns may need to pay more attention to the benefits of EVs for the environment and may choose to adopt them.</p><p>Ecological costs of battery disposal. While concerns surrounding battery replacement costs, repair accessibility, and battery lifespan were expressed by a notable percentage of potential EV buyers, 33.3% of participants in a study expressed high levels of concern, specifically regarding the ecological costs of battery disposal <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Krupa et al., 2014)</ref>. This divergence in attitudes may stem from participants perceiving recycling as a convenient and hassle-free method of battery disposal or placing greater emphasis on the energy savings achieved by maximizing battery usage before disposal rather than the hazardous waste issue. To address this policy barrier effectively, policies should focus on incentivizing the development of sustainable and efficient battery recycling processes</p><p>The ecological and political costs for manufacturing the battery. Surprisingly, the results of a study showed that only 28.5% of potential EV buyers expressed concerns about these costs <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Krupa et al., 2014)</ref>. However, more than half of the participants acknowledged that the ability to repurpose and recycle PHEV batteries after their PHEV propulsion capacity diminishes would positively impact their willingness to consider a PHEV. This apparent discrepancy suggests that participants may prioritize EVs' financial and energy-saving benefits over potential ecological and/or political costs related to battery manufacturing.</p><p>Lack of long-term planning and goals on the government's part. Long-term planning and goal action by the government could stimulate more rapid EV diffusion by including appropriate legislation, government procurement strategies, environmental awareness, subsidized purchasing, and enough charging networks in long-term plans and goals for accelerated EV uptake. A comprehensive policy framework for EVs is necessary, and the government can implement different policies to encourage EV uptake, including raising awareness, tax exemption, and long-term goal-based planning.</p><p>Restrictive policies regarding charging infrastructure. Research studies often assess the impact of policies on EV adoption rates and charging infrastructure utilization. However, these studies typically focus on either long-term effects on EV adoption or short-term effects on current EV owners' use of public charging stations. It is crucial to recognize that restrictive policies concerning charging infrastructure can harm both the charging behavior of existing EV owners and the intention of current ICE owners to transition to EVs. For example, more stringent policies may disrupt the duration of charging sessions, impacting efficient utilization of charging stations. To avoid unintended consequences, policymakers must consider the combined short and long-term implications of managing charging infrastructure demand.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.7">Social incentives</head><p>Environmental concern. Consumers' environmental concern has increased due to environmental degradation, worsening health problems, and government propaganda. Consumers' environmental concern positively influences their intention to adopt EVs. To measure environmental concerns and examine the relationship between environmental concerns and EV adoption, we defined two factors: 1) search interest in auto emissions, and 2) global warming. These factors serve as indexes that reflect the severity and importance of environmental concerns within society. By incorporating these factors into our analysis, we gain insights into the public's perception of environmental issues and how it relates to their intention to adopt EVs. The data on search interest provides a quantifiable measure of environmental concerns and helps us understand the influence of these concerns on consumer behavior.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Social conformity.</head><p>The studies discussed in the previous response found that social conformity can compensate for adverse impacts such as higher purchase prices or lower driving ranges, suggesting that social incentives can be a powerful tool for promoting EV adoption. Marketing campaigns that highlight the social and environmental benefits of EVs and emphasize the growing popularity among consumers can effectively create a sense of social norm and encourage individuals to adopt EVs. By leveraging the power of social conformity, policymakers and stakeholders can accelerate the transition to a more sustainable transportation system.</p><p>Social norm that celebrates EV owners. Creating a social pattern that celebrates EV owners as eco-conscious champions can catalyze EV development in the United States. Extensive research reveals that the attitudes of EV users towards the economic and environmental advantages, such as reducing pollution, minimizing traffic noise, and long-term cost savings, have a substantial impact on their commitment to EV usage, surpassing the influence of subjective norms and perceived barriers. Moreover, individuals' attitudes can be influenced by the opinions and behaviors of their peers. Therefore, establishing a societal trend linking EV ownership with a strong dedication to sustainability can inspire more people to embrace EVs. This can be achieved through targeted marketing campaigns that highlight the environmental benefits of EVs, ultimately fostering widespread adoption of EVs and paving the way toward a greener future nationwide.</p><p>Social pattern that an EV owner is at the forefront of new technology. Positioning oneself at the forefront of new technology by owning an EV has emerged as a compelling social incentive for EV development in the United States. A survey revealed that 17% of participants viewed owning a plug-in hybrid electric vehicle (PHEV) as a statement of being at the forefront of new technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Krupa et al., 2014)</ref>. In comparison, 25% believed it reflected their solid environmental values. Early studies on hybrid electric vehicle (HEV) consumers also indicated that purchasing decisions were influenced by the desire to project an image of environmental consciousness <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Krupa et al., 2014)</ref>.</p><p>Welfare effects of EV (better health and clean air). The spotlight has been on EVs due to their ability to lower air pollution and reduce the impacts of climate change. As they emit fewer pollutants than their gas-powered counterparts, EVs aid in improving air quality and promoting public health. In this context, we define CO2 emissions reduction as a measure of the welfare effects of EVs, focusing on better health and clean air. EVs have garnered significant attention due to their ability to contribute to lower air pollution and mitigate the impacts of climate change. By emitting fewer pollutants compared to their gas-powered counterparts, EVs play a crucial role in improving air quality and promoting public health.</p><p>Advertising campaigns and social groups. Advertising campaigns highlighting the environmental benefits of green products can increase consumers' awareness and willingness to pay for EVs while bridging the gap between their intents and actions. Simultaneously, active social groups such as non-governmental organizations (NGOs) can influence public policy and create synergies between the public and civil sectors. These synergies can help avoid the costly boycotts of EVs and instead push for regulatory standards, operational programs, and support for member activities in collaboration groups. Therefore, promoting advertising campaigns and supporting the formation of social groups can effectively increase public awareness and support for EVs, ultimately encouraging their development in the United States.</p><p>Education and employment. Individuals who lack awareness tend to prefer maintaining the current state of affairs rather than adopting new technologies..The limited knowledge about ecological transition issues among those with lower education levels may explain their reluctance to participate in environmental efforts <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Almulhim &amp; Abubakar, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Bourdin &amp; Chassy, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Sidhu et al., 2018)</ref>. In a study conducted by <ref type="bibr">Gong et al., it</ref> was discovered that the level of Evs acceptance increases with education, employment, and income <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Gong et al., 2020)</ref>. This finding suggests that people with higher education and stable employment are more likely to consider purchasing an EV. Moreover, the study revealed that preferences for government incentives vary among different population segments based on their socio-demographic characteristics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.8">Social barriers</head><p>The lack of knowledge about EVs. Consumers' understanding regarding quality (42.42%) is the most influential social barrier, followed by the lack of knowledge about EVs (31.14%) and lack of environmental awareness about using EVs (27.52%) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Adhikari et al., 2020)</ref>. Potential EV buyers' awareness of the benefits of EVs, financial incentives, infrastructure availability, and fuel-related savings are likely essential factors affecting their uptake. However, the lack of information provision and consumer understanding of EVs' advantages, quality, and actual performance hinder their adoption. It is crucial to disseminate information about EVs to heighten consumer understanding and awareness to alleviate this social barrier and encourage greater adoption of EVs in the United States.</p><p>Lack of environmental awareness regarding EVs. Despite the critical benefit of reducing emissions through EVs, many consumers still need to learn about the environmental advantages. They are unaware of the detrimental effects of greenhouse gas emissions caused by conventional vehicles. In fact, according to an analysis by Adhikari et al. , the absence of environmental awareness regarding EVs was recognized as the third most effective social barrier, following consumer understanding of quality and knowledge gaps about EVs <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Adhikari et al., 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Consumers' limited understanding of the product quality of Evs. Only informed consumers are likely to be willing to buy EVs. There may be a perception gap among potential EV users related to performance and reliability, range capacity, and other technical issues. As EV technology is relatively new in the market, consumers must be informed about the quality of EVs, as this particular social factor is a prerequisite for their acceptance. Proper information provision is crucial to aid the shift towards products such as EVs, and potential users' awareness of the benefits of an EV, financial incentives, infrastructure availability, and fuel-related savings are likely to be essential factors affecting the uptake of EVs. Lack of trust. Concerns about EV reliability, limited lifespan, battery degradation, charging infrastructure dependability, and battery recycling options contribute to a lack of trust in EVs. Manufacturers can address these concerns by increasing EV range to alleviate strain on charging infrastructure and providing accurate information about autonomous driving features. By addressing these trust-related issues, manufacturers can build consumer confidence in EVs.</p><p>Lack of Desirability. People perceive EVs as lacking the qualities of classic cars and car cultures, such as sound, character, repairability, cultural alignment, driving enjoyment, attractive design, and performance. Additionally, there is a perception that the EV culture is seen as "hipster" and lacking authenticity. These factors contribute to an emotional attachment to traditional ICE technology and view the adoption of electric vehicles as a threat to car culture and personal beliefs.</p><p>Range anxiety. Consumers' concerns about the limited driving range of EVs and the availability of charging infrastructure are influenced by technical and psychological factors. However, how these concerns are communicated and framed also plays a significant role in shaping consumer perceptions. Effective communication strategies highlighting EVs' benefits and addressing potential challenges can help alleviate these concerns and promote greater acceptance of EV technology.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Quantitative Analysis of Influencing Factors</head><p>During this study phase, we focused on collecting quantitative data for a specific set of factors related to EV adoption. Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> and<ref type="table">4</ref> present the comprehensive data we gathered for incentives and barriers, offering a deeper understanding of their impact on EV adoption. Furthermore, Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>, the Pearson correlation coefficients matrix, provides a quantitative analysis of the relationships between featured variables, allowing us to identify key influencing factors and their interdependencies.</p><p>The dataset and analysis presented in this study serve as a valuable foundation for future research. By expanding the quantitative dataset to include all identified features and employing statistical techniques, researchers can delve deeper into each factor's relative importance and its impact on electric vehicle adoption. Within the scope of this work, "PEV" is used to denote Plug-in Electric Vehicles, also commonly known as electric vehicles (EVs). PEVs encompass Battery Electric Vehicles (BEVs) and Plug-in Hybrid Electric Vehicles (PHEVs). These vehicles can be charged by connecting them to an external electric power source, and they play a crucial role in facilitating the shift towards more sustainable transportation alternatives. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref> illustrates the yearly sales of PEVs in the US market, serving as a representative indicator of EV adoption.</p><p>The graph showcases the progression of emerging EVs from 2011 onwards. In Table <ref type="table">4</ref>. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref> enhances our understanding by presenting scatterplots that illustrate the relationship between feature variables and the target variable of PEV sales. These scatterplots allow us to analyze the potential influencing factors and their impact on the sales performance of PEVs. By examining the scatterplot patterns and trends, we can identify any correlations or associations between the feature variables and the target variable, providing insights into the factors contributing to higher or lower PEV sales.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data</head><p>To further explore the relationships between the feature variables, Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref> showcases the Pearson correlation coefficients matrix. This matrix quantitatively measures the strength and direction of the linear relationship between each pair of feature variables. By analyzing the correlation coefficients, we can identify potential influencing factors that exhibit strong positive or negative correlations with one another. This information helps us understand the interdependencies among the factors and identify key drivers that have the potential to impact PEV sales significantly.    The results of the Pearson correlation coefficient analysis between PEV sales and selected factors influencing EV adoption in the categories of incentives and barriers are as follows:</p><p>Incentives:</p><p>• Fiscal support: Both fiscal support in the form of tax credits to corporations and tax credits to individuals to show strong positive correlations with PEV sales. This suggests that financial incentives provided through tax credits play a significant role in driving EV adoption. • Availability of different EV models: The availability of various EV models also shows a strong positive correlation with PEV sales. This indicates that consumers are more likely to adopt EVs when they have more options. • Income per capita and GDP per capita: Income and GDP per capita positively correlate with PEV sales. This suggests that higher levels of individual and national income are associated with increased EV adoption.</p><p>• Fuel prices: Gasoline retail prices in the U.S. negatively correlate with PEV sales. This indicates that consumers are more likely to consider EVs as an alternative as gasoline prices increase. • BEVs energy consumption: The energy consumption of battery electric vehicles measured in kWh per 100 miles shows a robust negative correlation with PEV sales. This suggests that consumers prioritize energy efficiency when considering EV adoption. • Fossil fuels tax incentives: The availability of fossil fuels tax incentives shows a strong negative correlation with PEV sales. This indicates that the presence of incentives for fossil fuel vehicles can hinder the adoption of EVs.</p><p>Overall, these correlation results provide valuable insights into the factors that influence EV adoption. The positive correlations in the incentives category highlight the importance of financial support, availability of EV models, performance attributes, charging infrastructure, supportive policies, environmental concerns, and socioeconomic factors in driving PEV sales. The negative correlations in the barriers category shed light on the potential barriers related to purchasing costs, battery replacement costs, market penetration, electricity prices, vehicle characteristics, and incentives for fossil fuel vehicles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Conclusion</head><p>In conclusion, this study provides a comprehensive analysis of the incentives and barriers influencing the adoption of EVs in the US. By simultaneously considering incentives and barriers, this study offers a holistic understanding of the factors impacting EV development. The advanced fishbone diagram used in the study enables a detailed explanation system, capturing the complexity and interrelatedness of the influencing factors.</p><p>The findings highlight the importance of various factors across economic, market, technical, policy, and social dimensions. Economic and market incentives, such as financial support and diverse EV models, play a significant role in encouraging EV uptake. Technical incentives, including extended driving range and reliable charging infrastructure, are crucial for promoting adoption. Policy incentives, such as toll exemptions and access to charging stations, facilitate EV deployment. Social incentives, driven by environmental concerns and social conformity, also impact EV adoption.</p><p>Furthermore, the study's quantitative analysis reveals the positive correlations between PEV sales and factors such as fiscal support, availability of EV models, performance attributes, charging infrastructure, supportive policies, and environmental concern. Conversely, factors such as purchasing costs, battery replacement costs, market penetration, electricity prices, vehicle characteristics, and incentives for fossil fuel vehicles show correlations that may hinder PEV sales.</p><p>These findings provide valuable insights for policymakers, EV manufacturers, and stakeholders seeking to promote widespread EV adoption. By combining different incentives and strategies, policymakers can create an enabling environment for EV uptake, addressing economic, technical, policy, and social aspects. The advanced fishbone diagram used in this study is a versatile tool that can be applied to various industries beyond EV adoption.</p><p>Additionally, the study highlights the significance of environmental concerns and their positive correlations with PEV sales. Consumers who are environmentally conscious are more likely to consider EVs as a cleaner and greener transportation option. The welfare effects of EVs, such as better health and reduced CO2 emissions, contribute to the appeal of EVs. This reinforces the importance of addressing environmental concerns and promoting the advantages of EVs to drive adoption.</p><p>In conclusion, this study contributes to the existing literature on adopting electric vehicles by comprehensively reviewing the incentives and barriers affecting their deployment in the US. The study offers a novel approach by simultaneously considering incentives and barriers, allowing for a more holistic view of the factors impacting EV development. The findings of this study can assist policymakers and stakeholders in making informed decisions and implementing effective strategies to promote the widespread adoption of EVs, leading to a more sustainable and efficient transportation system. Continued research and collaboration are necessary to further explore and address these factors, ensuring a successful transition to a low-carbon future.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Future research</head><p>By incorporating expert-centered methods and conducting statistical and historical data analysis, future research can develop a comprehensive framework for prioritizing the critical factors that significantly influence electric vehicle (EV) growth. This framework can involve assigning measures and historical data to all factors to determine their relative importance and impact on EV adoption. By employing robust methodologies and leveraging insights from domain experts, researchers can establish a systematic approach to identify the key drivers and barriers of EV adoption. In the context of future research, we suggest the utilization of various multi-criteria decision-making approaches, including the Simple Additive Weighting (SAW) method, the Technique for Order Preference by Similarity to an Ideal Solution (TOPSIS), and cognitive valuation techniques. These methodologies have been employed by researchers in the field of environmental management to evaluate and address topics related to development and adaptation <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Bourdin &amp; Chassy, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Dolge et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Morkunas &amp; Volkov, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Ulibarri et al., 2023)</ref>. By identifying the most significant factors, policymakers can focus their actions and resources on addressing the most crucial obstacles and incentives to EV adoption. Furthermore, future research could examine the effectiveness of different policy measures and initiatives to foster EV uptake. Evaluating the impact of existing policies and identifying gaps in policy implementation can help policymakers develop more effective strategies to support the development of a sustainable and efficient transportation system. Finally, additional research could investigate the potential of emerging technologies and innovations, such as battery recycling and second-life applications, to overcome barriers to EV adoption and promote a more sustainable transportation system.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>3</head><label></label><figDesc>Incentives and barriers to EVs developmentIn Section 3 of our study, we thoroughly categorized influential factors related to the adoption of electric vehicles. These factors were grouped into four main categories: economic and market, technical, policy, and social. Within each category, we delved deeper into critical incentives and barriers, gaining valuable insights into their specific contributions to the overall landscape of EV adoption. The advanced fishbone diagram developed in this study (Fig 1)provides a comprehensive modeling approach to promote the adoption of electric vehicles (EVs). It simultaneously considers all incentives and barriers, offering a holistic view of the factors influencing EV adoption. The fishbone diagram's upper rib branches and sub-branches highlight the significant positive factors and incentives that can encourage EV adoption.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Advanced fishbone diagram illustrating influential factors and barriers to the adoption of electric vehicles (EVs) and their interplay. The upper rib branches highlight positive factors and incentives, while the lower rib branches depict potential barriers.</figDesc><graphic coords="12,124.58,186.96,569.87,218.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure3, the histograms visually represent the distribution of selected influencing factors. By examining the shape and spread of these histograms, we can gain insights into the frequency and range of each factor, allowing us to assess their potential impact on plug-in electric vehicle sales. The histograms serve as a valuable tool for identifying patterns and understanding the significance of these factors in shaping consumer behavior and adoption of PEVs.Figure4enhances our understanding by presenting scatterplots that illustrate the relationship between feature variables and the target variable of PEV sales. These scatterplots allow us to analyze the potential influencing factors and their impact on the sales performance of PEVs. By examining the scatterplot patterns and trends, we can identify any correlations or associations between the feature variables and the target variable, providing insights into the factors contributing to higher or lower PEV sales.To further explore the relationships between the feature variables, Figure5showcases the Pearson correlation coefficients matrix. This matrix quantitatively measures the strength and direction of the linear relationship between each pair of feature variables. By analyzing the correlation coefficients, we can identify potential influencing factors that exhibit strong positive or negative correlations with one another. This information helps us understand the interdependencies among the factors and identify key drivers that have the potential to impact PEV sales significantly.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Annual Sales of Plug-in Electric Vehicles in the US Market from 2011 onwards,showcasing the growth and adoption of emerging EV<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Gohlke et al., 2022)</ref>.</figDesc><graphic coords="30,154.12,414.70,284.19,205.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Histograms depicting the distribution of Selected Influencing Factors for Electric Vehicle Adoption.</figDesc><graphic coords="31,133.25,147.40,362.98,440.30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Scatterplots illustrating the relationship between feature variables and the target variable of plug-in electric vehicle sales.</figDesc><graphic coords="32,130.40,147.40,379.50,495.30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Pearson correlation coefficients matrix displaying the relationships among the feature variables in the context of EV adaption.</figDesc><graphic coords="33,133.25,147.40,368.75,327.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Analyzing the Impact of Incentives and Barriers on Electric Vehicle Adoption: Insights from Literature Review and Case Studies</figDesc><table><row><cell>Reference</cell><cell>Factors</cell><cell>Results</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Financial incentive policy measures</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(Wang et al., 2017)</cell><cell>Government subsidies, road toll exemptions, purchase tax exemptions, and value-added tax exemptions Information provision policy measures Information on EV practicality and reliability, driving ranges, EV charging time and battery life, EV fuel consumption, and environmental concern Convenience policy measures Access to HOV lanes, dedicated parking</cell><cell>The results show that financial incentive policy measures, information provision policy measures, and convenience policy measures have significant and positive impacts on EV adoption intention.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>spaces, license plate exemptions, and</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>streamlined vehicle inspections</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Range-Recharge satisfaction</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Battery range, battery range during</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>winter, and recharging duration</cell><cell>This research finds that</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Cost satisfaction Purchase cost, maintenance cost, Recharging cost</cell><cell>EV users' mindsets towards financial and environmental values</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Policy measures satisfaction</cell><cell>(e.g., EV declines air</cell></row><row><cell>(Hasan, 2021a,</cell><cell>Toll, ferry, parking fee, and access to bus</cell><cell>pollution and traffic</cell></row><row><cell>2021b)</cell><cell>lane</cell><cell>noise and saves money</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Environmental-attributes satisfaction Tailpipe emission, traffic noise, type of energy usage, Availability satisfaction Availability of dealers nearby, availability</cell><cell>in the long term) substantially impact their behavioral intention to purchase an EV.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>of different EV models, country of</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>manufacturer, manufacturer's reputation</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Vehicle Property</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(Gong et al., 2020)</cell><cell>Vehicle body type, price, set up cost, operating cost, recharge time, range in a single recharge Support Scheme Availability of fast charging station , access to the bus lane, rebate on upfront cost, rebate on parking fee, energy bill discount, Stamp duty discount Market penetration</cell><cell>The study suggests that upfront cost rebates, operational incentives, and higher education, employment, and income levels contribute to increased EV acceptance.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Current portion of EVs sold</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><p><p>Desirability</p>Culture, bad looks and futuristic concept, repair, bad image, emotional attachment, soul/character, sound, lack of fun and performance Sales conversion inability Dealers and supply and choice of vehicles</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Noela et al., 2019)</ref> </p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Selected Influencing Factors for Electric Vehicle Adoption Numbers represent search interest relative to the highest point on the chart for the given region and time. A value of 100 is the peak popularity for the term. A value of 50 means that the term is half as popular. A score of 0 means there was not enough data for this term.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Category</cell><cell>Symbol</cell><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Unit</cell><cell>Source</cell></row><row><cell>and Market Incentives Economic</cell><cell>CRDTAX_CORP CRDTAX_INDV INCOME GDP GAS_PRICE</cell><cell>Fiscal support such as tax in-centives, exemptions, and de-ductions-credit tax to corpo-rations Fiscal support such as tax in-centives, exemptions, and de-ductions-credit tax to individ-uals Availability of different EV models-Income-Income per capita Economic status-GDP per capita Fuel prices-gasoline retail prices in the U.S.</cell><cell>Billion U.S. $ Billion U.S. $ current U.S. $ current U.S. $ U.S. $ per gallon</cell><cell>(Sherlock, 2019a) (Sherlock, 2019a) (Consumer Guide to Electric Vehicles, 2021) (W. Bank, 2023) (Bank, 2021) (Administration, 2023)</cell></row><row><cell>and Market Barriers</cell><cell>DOMESCONT RETAIL_PRICE BATT_PRICE PENETRATION</cell><cell>Country of manufacturer-do-mestic content for PEVs sold in the United States EVs purchasing cost-BEV Vol-ume weighted average retail price Battery replacement costs-Battery Prices Power EV Market penetration-PEV Sales Share of New Vehicle Sales</cell><cell>Percent EURO U.S. $ per kwh Percent</cell><cell>(Gohlke et al., 2022) (Dowling, 2022) (Henze, 2021) (Gohlke et al., 2022)</cell></row><row><cell>Economic</cell><cell>ELECTRICITY_PRICE</cell><cell>Electricity price for charging-Electricity per Kilowatt-Hour in U.S. City Average</cell><cell>U.S. $</cell><cell>(F. R. Bank, 2023a)</cell></row><row><cell>Incentives Technical</cell><cell>DRIV_RANGE ACCELERATION_S PWER_KW BATCAPACITY_KWH</cell><cell>Increasing EVs driving range-Average PEVs range PEVs performance-Average 0-60 Acceleration PEVs performance-motor power Battery capacity</cell><cell>Miles second KW kWh</cell><cell>(Gohlke et al., 2022) (Gohlke et al., 2022) (Gohlke et al., 2022) (Gohlke et al., 2022)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Data for Selected Influencing Factors (Incentives) in EV Adoption</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Year</cell><cell>2011</cell><cell>2012</cell><cell>2013</cell><cell>2014</cell><cell>2015</cell><cell>2016</cell><cell>2017</cell><cell>2018</cell><cell>2019</cell><cell>2020</cell><cell>2021</cell></row><row><cell>Barriers</cell><cell>RETAIL_PRICE</cell><cell>15,473</cell><cell>28,133</cell><cell>32,494</cell><cell>25,742</cell><cell>47,404</cell><cell>50,921</cell><cell>42,622</cell><cell>41,074</cell><cell>37,558</cell><cell>35,166</cell><cell>28,836</cell></row><row><cell>Market</cell><cell>BATT_PRICE</cell><cell>946</cell><cell>744</cell><cell>684</cell><cell>607</cell><cell>393</cell><cell>303</cell><cell>226</cell><cell>185</cell><cell>161</cell><cell>140</cell><cell>132</cell></row><row><cell>and Economic</cell><cell>PENETRATION ELECTRICITY_PRICE</cell><cell>0.29 0.13</cell><cell>0.68 0.13</cell><cell>1.23 0.13</cell><cell>1.49 0.14</cell><cell>1.43 0.14</cell><cell>1.80 0.14</cell><cell>2.58 0.14</cell><cell>5.43 0.14</cell><cell>5.63 0.14</cell><cell>5.24 0.14</cell><cell>6.97 0.14</cell></row><row><cell>Barriers</cell><cell>PEV_WEIGHT</cell><cell>3762.00</cell><cell>3833.00</cell><cell>3953.00</cell><cell>3908.20</cell><cell>4084.31</cell><cell>4387.82</cell><cell>4357.85</cell><cell>4384.07</cell><cell>4376.58</cell><cell>4526.46</cell><cell>4600.00</cell></row><row><cell>Technical</cell><cell>EV_SUV_VAN</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>0.61</cell><cell>1.22</cell><cell>1.22</cell><cell>2.43</cell><cell>18.85</cell><cell>17.93</cell><cell>13.68</cell><cell>16.41</cell><cell>42.55</cell><cell>58.05</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ENERGY_CONS</cell><cell>35.07</cell><cell>34.45</cell><cell>33.72</cell><cell>33.05</cell><cell>32.49</cell><cell>33.39</cell><cell>32.27</cell><cell>30.03</cell><cell>29.63</cell><cell>29.63</cell><cell>29.41</cell></row><row><cell>Policy Barriers</cell><cell>FOSSILFU_TAX_INC</cell><cell>4.08</cell><cell>5.10</cell><cell>5.31</cell><cell>5.82</cell><cell>5.82</cell><cell>5.31</cell><cell>4.69</cell><cell>3.16</cell><cell>1.73</cell><cell>1.94</cell><cell>2.04</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Domestic content for PEVs: The domestic content of PEVs sold in the United States shows a strong positive correlation with PEV sales. This implies that consumers have a preference for domestically produced EVs. • Performance factors: Increasing EV driving range, PEVs' performance attributes (average 0-60 acceleration, motor power), and battery capacity positively correlate with PEV sales. This suggests consumers value EVs with longer driving ranges, better performance, and larger battery capacities. • Charging infrastructure: The availability of fast and public charging stations, measured by the number of EVSE ports and EV charging station locations, shows positive correlations with PEV sales. This implies that convenient and accessible charging infrastructure is essential to EV adoption. • EV law and incentive additions: EV-specific laws and additional incentives strongly correlate with PEV sales. This indicates that supportive policies and regulations are crucial in promoting EV adoption. • Environmental concern: Informed interest in auto emissions and global warming positively correlates with PEV sales. This suggests that environmentally conscious consumers are more likely to consider EVs as a cleaner and greener transportation option. • Welfare effects, education, and employment: The welfare effects of EVs, as measured by CO2 emissions reduction and better health and clean air, as well as factors related to education and employment (total college enrollment and employment rate), show positive correlations with PEV sales. This indicates that environmental and socioeconomic factors influence EV adoption. Battery replacement costs: Battery prices per kWh strongly correlate negatively with PEV sales. This suggests that high battery replacement costs can hinder the adoption of EVs. • Market penetration: The PEV sales share of new vehicle sales shows a strong positive correlation with PEV sales. This indicates that as PEV market penetration increases, more consumers are likely to adopt EVs. • Electricity price: The electricity price per kilowatt-hour in the U.S. shows a moderate positive correlation with PEV sales. This suggests that higher electricity prices can influence consumer decisions regarding EV adoption. • PEVs equivalent test weight: The weight of PEVs measured in pounds shows a positive correlation with PEV sales. This indicates that consumers may prefer larger and heavier PEVs. • Vehicle type: The share of EV SUVs and vans in total EV sales shows a strong positive correlation with PEV sales. This implies that consumers are inclined to use SUVs and vans in the EV market.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Barriers: • EVs purchasing cost: The BEV volume-weighted average retail price weakly</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>correlates with PEV sales. This implies that higher purchasing costs can hinder</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>wider PEV adoption.</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification and Analysis of Barriers against Electric Vehicle Use</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Adhikari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ghimire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Aryal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Khadka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/su12124850</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3390/su12124850" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sustainability</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4850" to="4850" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">U.S. All Grades All Formulations Retail Gasoline Prices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">S E I</forename><surname>Administration</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.eia.gov/dnav/pet/hist/LeafHandler.ashx?n=PET&amp;s=EMM_EPM0_PTE_NUS_DPG&amp;f=A" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Dollars per Gallon</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding public environmental awareness and attitudes toward circular economy transition in Saudi Arabia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Almulhim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Abubakar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sustainability</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10157</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhancement of electric vehicles&apos; market competitiveness using fuzzy quality function deployment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H K</forename><surname>Babar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/J.TECHFORE.2021.120738</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/J.TECHFORE.2021.120738" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technological Forecasting and Social Change</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">167</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120738" to="120738" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/APU000072610#0" />
		<title level="m">Price: Electricity per Kilowatt-Hour in U.S. City Average (APU000072610</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023a</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Employment Rate: Aged 15-64: All Persons for the United States (LREM64</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/LREM64TTUSM156S" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">TTUSM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">156</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023b</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">GDP per capita (current US$) -United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Bank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/NY.GDP.PCAP.CD?locations=US" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Adjusted net national income is GNI minus consumption of fixed capital and natural resources depletion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Bank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/NY.ADJ.NNTY.PC.CD?name_desc=true&amp;locations=US" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bibra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Connelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dhir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Drtil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Henriot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-B</forename><surname>Le Marois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mcbain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Paoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Teter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Global EV outlook 2022: Securing supplies for an electric future</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bibra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Connelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gorner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lowans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Paoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tattini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Teter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Global EV Outlook 2021: Accelerating ambitions despite the pandemic</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Net zero by 2050: A roadmap for the global energy sector</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bouckaert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Pales</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mcglade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Remme</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wanner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Varro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>D'ambrosio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Spencer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Are Citizens Ready to Make an Environmental Effort? A Study of the Social Acceptability of Biogas in France</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bourdin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chassy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environmental Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Energy prices and electric vehicle adoption</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bushnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Muehlegger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rapson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A stated choice experiment to measure the effect of informational and normative conformity in the preference for electric vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cherchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">https:/doi.org/10.1016/j.tra.2017.04.009</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tra.2017.04.009" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transportation Research Part A: Policy and Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Consumer Guide to Electric Vehicles</title>
		<ptr target="http://mydocs.epri.com/docs/public/EPRI-ConsumerEVBroch2021-20210629-For%20Press.pdf" />
		<editor>E. P. R. Institute</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021. 000000003002021789</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Political, economic, social, technological, legal and environmental dimensions of electric vehicle adoption in the United States: A social-media interaction analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Debnath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bardhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Reiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">152</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">111707</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of government incentives for hybrid-electric vehicles: Evidence from US states</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Diamond</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="972" to="983" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dolge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Balode</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Laktuka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Kirsanovs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Barisa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kubule</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A Comparative Analysis of Bioeconomy Development in European Union Countries</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="233" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EVs: A Pricing Challenge</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Dowling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://premium.goauto.com.au/jato-shows-huge-ev-pricing-challenge/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">GOAUTONEWS</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Paths to the adoption of electric vehicles: An evolutionary game theoretical approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Encarnação</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Blass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pacheco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Portugali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://afdc.energy.gov/data/10360" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Energy, U. S. D. o. (2023b). Law and Incentive Additions by Fuel/Technology Type</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Energy, U. S. D.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="33" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Electric Vehicle Charging Infrastructure Trends</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An agent-based model to study market penetration of plug-in hybrid electric vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Eppstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Grover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rizzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/J.ENPOL.2011.04.007</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/J.ENPOL.2011.04.007" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3789" to="3802" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Fast Facts: U.S. Transportation Sector Greenhouse Gas Emissions.</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>Epa, Us of Transportation, Office Quality, Air Division, Standard, Issue. U. o. T. Epa, Office Quality, Air Division, Standards</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">a study of the relationship between energy coconsumption and urbanization in iran using the ARDL (Auto Regressive Distributed Lag) Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ghanbari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gallavani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Javadnejad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Economics Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="119" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gohlke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Courtney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Assessment of Light-Duty Plug-in Electric Vehicles in the United States</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2022. 2010-2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of government incentives on the market penetration of electric vehicles in Australia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ardeshiri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hossein</forename><surname>Rashidi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/J.TRD.2020.102353</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/J.TRD.2020.102353" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transportation Research Part D: Transport and Environment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="102353" to="102353" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">01%202021-12-30&amp;geo=US&amp;q=%2Fg%2F11ksgqqmy&amp;hl=en-US Green Vehicle Guide</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Google</forename><surname>Trends</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.epa.gov/greenvehicles/electric-vehicle-myths#Myth1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">United States Environmental Protection Agency-EPI</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2023. 2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Google</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessment of electric vehicle repurchase intention: A survey-based study on the Norwegian EV market</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hasan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/J.TRIP.2021.100439</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/J.TRIP.2021.100439" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transportation Research Interdisciplinary Perspectives</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100439" to="100439" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessment of electric vehicle repurchase intention: A survey-based study on the Norwegian EV market</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hasan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transportation Research Interdisciplinary Perspectives</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100439</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021b</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Battery pack prices fall to an average of $132/kWh, but rising commodity prices start to bite</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Henze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://about.bnef.com/blog/battery-pack-prices-fall-to-an-average-of-132-kwh-but-rising-commodity-prices-start-to-bite/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BloombergNEF URL</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021-07">2021. 7, 2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Iea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.iea.org/data-and-statistics/data-tools/global-ev-policy-explorer" />
		<title level="m">Global EV Policy Explorer</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Consumer acceptance of electric vehicles in the US. USA: The International Council for Clean Transportation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kodjak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2012. 2014-2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding and identifying barriers to electric vehicle adoption through thematic analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Krishna</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transportation Research Interdisciplinary Perspectives</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100364</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of a consumer survey on plug-in hybrid electric vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Krupa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rizzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Eppstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Brad Lanute</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gaalema</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lakkaraju</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Warrender</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/J.TRA.2014.02.019</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/J.TRA.2014.02.019" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transportation Research Part A: Policy and Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Methodology for assessing electric vehicle charging infrastructure business models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Madina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Zamora</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Zabala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="284" to="293" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Morkunas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Volkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Progress of the Development of a Climate-smart Agriculture in Europe: Is there Cohesion in the European Union? Environmental Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fear and loathing of electric vehicles: The reactionary rhetoric of range anxiety</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Noela</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>De Rubensa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sovacoola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kestera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Research &amp; Social Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="107" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of innovations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Singhal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Quinlan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">An integrated approach to communication theory and research</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="432" to="448" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The economics of fast charging infrastructure for electric vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Traber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="136" to="144" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The plug-in electric vehicle tax credit</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Sherlock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019a</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Value of Energy Tax Incentives for Different Types of Energy Resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Sherlock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Congressional Research Service</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">44852</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019b</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A social cost benefit analysis of gridscale electrical energy storage projects: A case study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sidhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Pollitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Anaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">212</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="881" to="894" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rejecting renewables: The socio-technical impediments to renewable electricity in the United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sovacool</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.enpol.2009.05.073</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.enpol.2009.05.073" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4500" to="4513" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A completive survey study on the feasibility and adaptation of EVs in Beijing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kashyap</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">https:/doi.org/10.1016/j.apenergy.2016.11.027</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apenergy.2016.11.027" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">China. Applied energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">187</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="128" to="139" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exact approaches for routing capacitated electric vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tahami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rabadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Haouari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/J.TRE.2020.102126</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/J.TRE.2020.102126" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transportation Research Part E: Logistics and Transportation Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">144</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="102126" to="102126" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drivers and dynamics of collaborative governance in environmental management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ulibarri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Imperial</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Siddiki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Henderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environmental Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="495" to="504" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of policy measures on consumer intention to adopt electric vehicles: Evidence from China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transportation Research Part A: Policy and Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Policy effects on charging behaviour of electric vehicle owners and on purchase intentions of prospective owners: Natural and stated choice experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wolbertus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kroesen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Van Den Hoed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Chorus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transportation Research Part D: Transport and Environment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="283" to="297" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A qualitative comparative analysis on factors affecting the deployment of electric vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.egypro.2017.09.066</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.egypro.2017.09.066" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Procedia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="497" to="503" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sustainability of crop-based biodiesel for transportation in China: Barrier analysis and life cycle ecological footprint calculations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Bai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.techfore.2020.120526</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.techfore.2020.120526" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technological Forecasting and Social Change</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">164</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120526" to="120526" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Manufacturing Decisions and Government Subsidies for Electric Vehicles in China: A Maximal Social Welfare Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Llopis-Albert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/SU10030672</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3390/SU10030672" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sustainability</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="672" to="672" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/ijerph16173018</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph16173018" />
		<title level="m">How Does Financial Development Affect Reductions in Carbon Emissions in High-Energy Industries?-A Perspective on Technological Progress</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
