<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Causal relationship among elderly residents&apos; quality of life, recognition of aging, and lifestyle in Japan</title>
				<funder ref="#_NbNP2d6">
					<orgName type="full">Liaison Council for the Promotion of Bright Longevity Society</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2022-07-28">July 28th, 2022</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Tanji</forename><surname>Hoshi</surname></persName>
							<email>star@onyx.dti.ne.jp</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Tokyo Metropolitan University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Causal relationship among elderly residents&apos; quality of life, recognition of aging, and lifestyle in Japan</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2022-07-28">July 28th, 2022</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.21203/rs.3.rs-1837228/v1</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T22:25+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Elderly residents</term>
					<term>QOL</term>
					<term>Lifestyle</term>
					<term>Recognition of aging</term>
					<term>Causal relationship</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>OBJECTIVE:</head><p>The purpose of this study is to make clear the causal relationship among three latent variables including QOL, lifestyle, social activity, and the recognition of aging.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS:</head><p>The survey area was nationwide in Japan; we surveyed 9,508 elderly residents in 2013. The number of respondents to the basic survey was 4,343, with a recovery rate of 45.7%. A follow-up survey was conducted 6 years later, and responses were obtained from 3,345 people, with a recovery rate of 86.7%. In this study, 2,859 people aged 65 to 85 years were analyzed. A questionnaire about [QOL]([]indicate a latent variable) measured subjective health and life satisfaction. The causal relationship among the latent variables was analyzed by covariance structure analysis of the cross-lagged effect model and the synchronous effect model shown by Finkel. RESULTS: [Pain, illness, and lifestyle] was the most stable at 6 years. Based on the 6-year effect among the different latent variables, [QOL] was favorably in uenced by [pain, illness, and lifestyle] rather than [recognition aging and disease preventability] six years prior. At the same time, desirable [QOL] and [pain, illness, and lifestyle] were shown to have a causal effect on [recognition aging and disease preventability] after 6 years. These associations showed a similar tendency by gender and in the younger and older age groups.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Japan has the longest life expectancy in the world and at the same time is facing a rapidly aging society against the backdrop of a declining birthrate. In general, the prevalence of some diseases increases with aging. Therefore, the difference between healthy life expectancy and average life expectancy is approximately 10 years <ref type="bibr">1)</ref> .</p><p>In such an aging society, it is becoming more important to not only to live longer but also live a uently, that is, to maintain quality of life <ref type="bibr">2)</ref> .</p><p>In recent years, long-term care prevention with an emphasis on frailty has been promoted as a new health policy for the elderly population <ref type="bibr">3)</ref> .</p><p>It has been reported that to prevent frailty and eventually maintain survival and quality of life, a desirable daily lifestyle <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> , including diet, and social participation <ref type="bibr">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> , play a large role.</p><p>Furthermore, the signi cance of maintaining a positive life to achieve healthy longevity has also been reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> .</p><p>According to Nakagawa's report <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10)</ref> on a 19-year follow-up research survey, those with positive acceptance of aging can live four years longer than those with negative thinking, even when various factors are controlled . <ref type="bibr">Shirai 11)</ref> analyzed 319 elderly people aged 75 years and over and took negative thinking as a factor to distinguish between the long-term care risk group and the healthy group; for those with negative thinking, their social relations were weak, and their life satisfaction and self-esteem were low.</p><p>A questionnaire survey of 93 elderly people showed that acceptance of aging was associated with subjective well-being and economic status, according to Egami et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12)</ref> . The authors <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13)</ref> previously followed up the elderly in rural areas of the northern part of Okinawa and clari ed that the level of feeling happy was a highly valid indicator that could predict survival after three years.</p><p>It has been reported that living positively in this way is associated with maintaining survival and preventing the need for long-term care. However, the causal relationship between lifestyle-related diseases, including diet and pain, and social activities and QOL through living positively is not su ciently clear.</p><p>In other words, there is no report that the causal relationship has been clari ed as to indicate whether living positively results in higher QOL and leads to survival maintenance or, rather, whether living positively leads to survival maintenance in conjunction with positive living.</p><p>It has been reported that in preventing frailty and maintaining and improving QOL, the effect is enhanced by a combination of physical activity, nutrition, cognitive function, and social participation <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14)</ref> .</p><p>By clarifying the causal relationship and causal structure between these various factors, a more effective intervention effect can be achieved. Compared to independent elderly people who engage in physical activity, cultural activity, and community activities at least once a week, those who do not engage in these activities have a higher risk of needing nursing care and being recommended comprehensive health support <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15)</ref> .</p><p>On the other hand, the WHO has proposed support guidelines (Integrated care for older people: ICOPE) that provide personalized support at the local level for individuals that comprehensively assess the health of elderly people <ref type="bibr">16)</ref> . The WHO also focused on the needs of elderly people in the areas where they are accustomed to living to prevent the deterioration of their ability.</p><p>The health support model that has been used in health education thus far is based on the premise that health is linked to health-oriented behavior, in which it is desirable to recognize the health effects of health behavior as a merit. A health belief model was shown to result in improved health <ref type="bibr">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19)</ref> . Advanced research on how comprehensive interventions using such a health belief model can affect health and quality of life should be performed. In these cases, scienti c evidence on what kind of causal relationship can be observed between each factor is also needed. Therefore, we conducted a nationwide longitudinal survey of elderly individuals in the region twice in 6 years. The purpose of the research was to clarify the comprehensive causal structure, including the presence or absence of diseases and pain, as well as the recognition of aging and the possibility of preventing diseases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method 1 Research subject</head><p>The subjects of the survey were 9,508 elderly people who participated in the Longevity Center for Social Development project in 25 prefectures nationwide in Japan. The survey was conducted by conducting an initial survey in 2013 (referred to as [T1]) by mail using the self-administered questionnaire method.</p><p>A follow-up survey was conducted in 2019, six years later (referred to as [T2]), for 3,856 of the 4,343 respondents who consented to the follow-up survey with informed consent.</p><p>As a result, the recovery rate was 86.7%, and 3,345 people responded. In this study, 2,859 people aged 65 to 85 years were included in the analysis(Table <ref type="table">1</ref>). The overall outline of the basic survey and some of the research results were reported in previous research <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Analysis items</head><p>With reference to the questionnaire for elderly individuals in the late stages of life resented by the Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22)</ref> , we created a questionnaire related to 1) physical health, 2) mental health, 3) weight change, 4) exercise, 5) smoking, and 6) social participation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1) Physical health</head><p>The sickness score was 1 if there was an illness, including heart disease, liver disease, diabetes, or depression.</p><p>In addition, the pain score was also calculated by scoring one point for each case of pain in the back, hips, knees, and feet. The scoring ranged from 0 to 4 points.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2) Mental health</head><p>Regarding mental health, we investigated subjective health and life satisfaction.</p><p>Subjective health was quanti ed via a four-score t scale using questions pertaining to the respondent's perceived overall health: "In general, would you say your health is very poor, poor, fair or excellent?".</p><p>The questions about life satisfaction were as follows. How are you satis ed with your current life? There were three options: yes, no, and neither. In the analysis, an ordinal scale was used.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3) Lifestyle</head><p>The calculated BMI was divided into four categories: less than 18, less than 25, less than 30, or more than 30. If there was no change between categories in 6 years, 1 point was given for no change in body weight.</p><p>One point was added for exercising more than 3 times a week. In the case of nonsmokers, one point was also added.</p><p>For sleep, which is another lifestyle, we added one points for respondents who selected 6 to 8 hours.</p><p>Lifestyle-related scores ranged from 0 to 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4) Social participation</head><p>As an index of social participation, we measured relationships with people, community activities, hobbies, and frequency of having fun in life. For social activity scores, if the respondent selected at least once a week, he or she received get 1 point each, for a score ranging from 0 to 4 points.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5) Nutritional status</head><p>The frequency of food intake per week was classi ed into the following ve categories: 5 points for eating every day, 4 points for eating from 5 to 6 days, 3 points for eating from 3 to 4 days, 2 points for eating from 1 to 2 days, and 1 point for not eating.</p><p>The consumption of four types of foods that have shown a signi cant association with survival, including soybeans, eggs, milk products, and fruits, over 6 years was assessed, and the food diversity total score ranged from 4 to 20.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>6) Recognition of aging and disease preventability</head><p>First, regarding the recognition of aging, we selected 2 items from the 5 items of the revised Philadelphia Geriatric Center (PGC) Morale Scale. The question asked respondents what they thought about their aging. There were three options for the question: good, neither good nor bad, and bad.</p><p>Another question asked respondents how they felt about your role as they got older. There were three options: it became important, it did not change much, and it became less important.</p><p>The question about disease preventability asked what respondents thought about the idea that illness could be prevented by taking care of oneself. There were three options: it is right, it is not right, and either.</p><p>One point was given when the explanation for getting older was good, and in the question on disease preventability, one point was given when "Yes" was selected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Analytical method</head><p>Finkel's model was used to clarify the causal relationship and stabilizing effect 6 years after the basic survey.</p><p>Finkel's model includes the following two methods: the cross-lagged effect model and the synchronous effect model <ref type="bibr">26)</ref> .</p><p>The analysis method used covariance structure analysis by both gender and two age groups <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref><ref type="bibr">[28]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> .</p><p>The goodness-of-t index of the model was the chi-square test degree of freedom and P value, including the normed t index (NFI), comparative t index (CFI), and root mean square error of approximation (RMSEA).</p><p>The criteria for adopting the most suitable model were based on the condition that the goodness-of-t index was the best and the path cases between latent variables and observed variables were dominant in the Wald test.</p><p>Since the units of each observed variable were different, standardized estimates were used for all of the following estimates.</p><p>The t test was used to compare the continuous quantities between the two groups, and the Mann-Whitney U test was used to test the ordinal category. The chi-square test and the Kendal τ test were used to compare the categories. The analysis software used was SPSS 28.0 and AMOS 28.0 (IBM), with a statistical signi cance level of 5%.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Research ethics</head><p>This survey was conducted for 6 years beginning in 2013 as joint research between the International Longevity Center and Tokyo Metropolitan University. Both parties planned the joint research, thoroughly enforced con dentiality, and centrally managed personal information at the Longevity Center for Social Development. For the protection of personal information, the questionnaire was anonymized using an ID number so that no individual could be identi ed. Analysts mutually assured that ID data would be used in conjunction.</p><p>This investigation was approved by the consent of the Institutional Review Board on Human Research at Sagami Women's University, acceptance number 1,793, October 27, 2017.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">- 1 Basic distribution of survey items</head><p>The survey items were analyzed by gender and age (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>). Regarding subjective health, the percentage of people who were very healthy was 12.3 to 17.1% in both surveys, including the initial survey (T1) and the survey 6 years later (T2), and the percentage of people who were reasonably healthy was 69.6 to 76.0%.</p><p>It was shown that the percentage of people who were satis ed with their lives was very high, ranging from 72.6 to 83.1%. In the basic studies (T1), the younger age group of elderly women was signi cantly more satis ed than the older age group of elderly women.</p><p>The percentage of people who were good at getting older ranged from 21.4 to 43.1%, and the basic survey showed that the number of elderly men in the younger age group was signi cantly higher than that in the older age group(Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).</p><p>Body pain scores ranged from 0.67 to 0.87. In both the initial survey (T1) and the 6-year survey (T2) for men in only the initial survey for women, respondents in the younger age group tended to score signi cantly higher.</p><p>The social activity score ranged from 0.87 to 2.15 and was signi cantly lower for both men and women in the older age group.</p><p>Lifestyle-related bene t points ranged from 2.65 to 3.08 scores and showed no signi cant difference between men and women.</p><p>Thus, the number of pains and illnesses increased signi cantly in the older age group for both men and women, while social networks decreased signi cantly(Table <ref type="table">3</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Exploratory factor analysis</head><p>An exploratory factor analysis using the maximum likelihood method by varimax rotation was performed to search for latent variables. As a result, the rst factor was subjective health, life satisfaction, pain score, and illness score. Lifestyle-related scores and the food diversity total score were extracted as the second factor. The third factor was the social activity score. The fourth factor was awareness of aging, role changes, and the possibility of disease prevention (Table <ref type="table">4</ref>).</p><p>Therefore, the latent variable whose observation variables were subjective health and life satisfaction was named [QOL]([ ] indicate a latent variable). In addition, the recognition of age-related changes in roles and the possibility of disease prevention were named [recognition of aging and disease preventability]. The cumulative contribution rate of the whole was 38.2%, and a large contribution rate could not be obtained.</p><p>Cronbach's reliability coe cient for subjective health and life satisfaction as the rst factor was 0.43. The fourth factor was recognition of age-related changes, recognition of role changes, and disease preventability and had a Cronbach's reliability coe cient of 0.42.</p><p>The 2nd factor and 3rd factor were combined and named [pain, disease, and lifestyle].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Observed variables of each latent variable</head><p>The estimated values of subjective health and life satisfaction, which were observed variables related to the latent variable [QOL], were 0.47 to 0.75 for both T1 and T2(Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref>).</p><p>Estimates of the observed variables associated with pain, illness, and lifestyle ranged from 0.09 to 0.32 for both T1 and T2(Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref>).</p><p>Over time, [perception of aging and disease preventability] and the estimated values of the three observed variables showed a strong association both [T1] and [T2] survey, from 0.35 to 0.47. The estimated values of each observed variable showed almost the same tendency by gender and by the younger and older age groups. Only the social activity score of [T1] showed no signi cant difference between the observed and latent variables(Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Stability and causal effect between each latent variable</head><p>The 6-year stability effect of the same latent variable was analyzed using the cross-lagged effect model. As a result, the estimated values of [T1] and [T2] of [pain, illness, and lifestyle] were 0.80 to 0.99, showing the highest stabilizing effect(Table <ref type="table">5</ref>).</p><p>Next, the estimates for [T1] and [T2] [recognition of aging and disease preventability] ranged from 0.56 to 0.71. Similarly, the estimated values of [QOL] were 0.54 to 0.80, both of which showed a certain stabilizing effect(Table <ref type="table">5</ref>).</p><p>A 6-year causal relationship between different latent variables was analyzed using the cross-lagged effect model. As a result, the estimated value showing the causal effect on [recognition of aging and disease preventability] 6 years later by [pain, illness, and lifestyle] was 0.26 to 0.77.</p><p>Similarly, [QOL] after 6 years was 0.66 to 0.99, both of which showed signi cant relationships(Table <ref type="table">5</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Estimates of causal effects on [recognition of aging and disease preventability] 6 years later by [QOL]</head><p>ranged from 0.26 to 0.77.</p><p>Estimates of causal effects on [pain, illness, and lifestyle] 6 years later by [QOL] ranged from 0.26 to 0.86, both of which showed signi cant effects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Estimates of causal effects on [QOL] 6 years after by [recognition of aging and disease preventability]</head><p>ranged from 0.09 to 0.20(Table <ref type="table">5</ref>).</p><p>There was no signi cant difference in [pain, illness, and lifestyle] 6 years later by [recognition of aging and disease preventability], which ranged from 0.01 to 0.27(Table <ref type="table">5</ref>).</p><p>Therefore, [recognition of aging and disease preventability] showed a causal effect from [QOL] along with [pain, illness, and lifestyle] 6 years prior. On the other hand, the relationship between [pain, illness, and lifestyle] and [QOL] had a strong causal effect on QOL after 6 years, but they had a strong signi cant in uence on each other(Table <ref type="table">5</ref>).</p><p>The causal effects between different latent variables at the same time score were analyzed by the synchronous effect model. As a result, the estimated values of [pain, illness, and lifestyle] and [QOL] were 0.37 to 0.43, showing a mutually signi cant causal effect.</p><p>On the other hand, the relationship between [pain, illness, and lifestyle] and [recognition aging and disease preventability] was estimated to be 0.06 to 0.08, and there was no signi cant difference. In addition, a signi cant association was found from [QOL] with an estimated value of 0.61 in [recognition of aging and disease preventability].</p><p>However, the estimated value for [QOL] was as small as 0.07 from the [recognition of aging and disease preventability], and no signi cant association was shown (Table <ref type="table">6</ref>, Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>).</p><p>We analyzed the causal effect of 6 years between different latent variables using a synchronous effect model that could determine the causal effect, including the indirect effect.</p><p>At the initial survey and 6 years later, [pain, illness, and lifestyle] gave estimates ranging from 0.08 to 0.17, indicating their impact on [recognition and disease preventability] 6 years later. Similarly, the indirect effect on [QOL] from [pain, illness, and lifestyles] ranged from 0.01 to 0.42(Table <ref type="table">6</ref>, Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>).</p><p>After the initial survey at [T1] and the [T2] survey of [QOL], indirect estimates of effect on [recognition of aging and disease preventability] ranged from 0.05 to 0.63.</p><p>After the initial survey of [QOL], the indirect effect on [pain and illness and lifestyle] was 0.15 to 0.82. On the other hand, the estimated indirect effect on [QOL] after the [T1] and [T2] surveys of [recognition of aging and disease preventability] ranged from 0.02 to 0.24. Similarly, the estimate of the effect on [pain, illness, and lifestyle] was small, at 0.01 to 0.14.</p><p>By gender, large estimates were obtained, especially for older age group of elderly women (Table <ref type="table">7</ref>). Based on the coe cient of determination of each latent variable, it was shown that the older age group tended to have a slightly greater explanatory power for both men and women (Table <ref type="table">7</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion 1 Causality between the same latent variable and different latent variables</head><p>For latent variables such as [pain, illness, and lifestyle], the estimated judgment effect, which indicates stability after 6 years, was as high as 0.73 to 0.97. On the other hand, the estimated values of the stabilizing effect of both [QOL] and [recognition of aging and disease preventability] were approximately 0.55 to 0.66. [Pain, illness, and lifestyle] were shown to be most stable after 6 years. Reproducibility is needed.</p><p>[Pain, illness, and lifestyle] were unaffected by [recognition of aging and disease preventability] six years prior. Rather, [recognition of aging and disease preventability] was shown to be in uenced by [pain, illness, and lifestyle] six years prior. In addition, [QOL] was shown to be more in uenced by [pain and illness and lifestyle] than by [recognition of aging and disease prevention] 6 years prior.</p><p>On the other hand, [recognition of aging and disease preventability] was shown to have a causal structure in uenced by [QOL] and [pain, illness, and lifestyle] 6 years prior.</p><p>In health education, the health belief model has been used as a model to support health <ref type="bibr">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> . This model is based on the premise that the person recognizes the merits of behavior as information provision that is a prerequisite for promoting behavior change to a favorable health habit.</p><p>However, the results of this study indicate that cognition in uences behavior and may not be a sign that subsequent health is ultimately maintained. Rather, causal structures were shown in which desirable QOL, less pain and illness and a favorable lifestyle raise the acceptance of recognition of aging and the possibility of disease prevention after 6 years. Therefore, it is suggested that it may be possible to propose that the desired physical health status regulates the recognition of aging and disease preventability. Reproducibility is needed.</p><p>Fujita <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30)</ref>, who conducts research on suicide, has presented a virtuous cycle model from physical deterioration to psychological factors.</p><p>It is considered that the virtuous circle hypothesis model presented by Fujita30) was made clear by the follow-up survey results of this study.</p><p>In a study of elderly people across the country, Kodama et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21)</ref> showed their readiness to prevent a decline in IADLs, which are a means of daily life behavior, after 3 years. It was reported that the degree of obesity was standard in the younger elderly age group, and it is important for the older elderly age group to exercise at least three times a week for fun and purpose in life and to avoid eating meat frequently.</p><p>Considering this, together with the results of this survey, it was clari ed that favorable lifestyle habits, including diet, may affect the subsequent maintenance of QOL through prevention of frailty.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Research issue</head><p>This research has several research issues, as shown below. First, it is a condition for inferring a causal relationship. To infer a causal relationship, it is necessary to satisfy the conditions of universality and consistency related to 1) temporal relationships, 2) strength of the relationship, 2) strength of relevance, 3) no intervention, 4) universality of relevance, and 5) related consistency <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31)</ref> .</p><p>In this study, preference was ensured, and it was considered that the association and the consistency of the association were satis ed to some extent. However, to strengthen universality, additional tests are needed. In addition, intervention studies involving control groups are expected to verify the essential causal relationship.</p><p>Oomi et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32)</ref> surveyed 539 junior high school students three times at three-year intervals and reported that free internet use for lessons had a long-term effect after one year instead of three years by analysis using the cross-lagged effect model shown by the Finkel model 26 . As a long-term effect, the author reported that the effect was seen in creating Web pages and using e-mail. In this way, making the causal effect more universal through three follow-up studies is an issue for future research.</p><p>Next is the issue of selection bias. The subjective feelings of health of the survey analysts were shown to be very high in both T1 and T2. The results of a similar survey of elderly people living at home in the suburbs of the city revealed that there was a selection bias in which healthier people were included in the analysis. However, since a certain sample was obtained, it was considered that the error by chance was small <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34)</ref> .</p><p>The challenge is to verify less biased reproducibility with sampled national surveys. There is also the issue of the scale used in the survey. The PGC Morale Scale <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25)</ref> is a systematic scale that includes psychological upset, isolation, satisfaction, and attitude toward aging.</p><p>However, the simple scale used in this survey was only the recognition and attitude toward aging, and the research results were limited as a matter scale that measured only a part of the systematic scale.</p><p>Previous studies on the scales that can be obtained that are related to the importance of aging have mainly been reported to have predictive validity for survival maintenance and life satisfaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> .</p><p>After reporting a signi cant relationship between the Morale Scale and survival maintenance, Nakagawa et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10)</ref> suggested the need to investigate the mechanism between the Morale Scale and survival maintenance. Therefore, it is a research subject to clarify the survival maintenance mechanism as well as the reproducibility, including not only the relational factors but also the causal factor, through an intervention study for the comprehensive analysis utilizing all of the systematic scales.</p><p>Using the Morale Scale, Lavey et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35)</ref> clari ed that self-assessment of positive living could maintain subsequent survival even if the other factors were controlled. At the same time, the authors determined that the respondents looked younger than their actual age as a relative subjective assessment from the perspective of others.</p><p>It was suggested that it is highly meaningful to add the subjective evaluation of youthfulness from the perspective of a third party as a related item.</p><p>Toyosato et al. <ref type="bibr">36)</ref> surveyed 42 elderly people in Okinawa Prefecture and reported the relationship between positive emotions and objective evaluation indicators. This study revealed that older people with lower positive emotions and emotional satisfaction and poorer application for social support such as relationships and friendships and the environment had a higher indicator of the free-MHPG(3-methoxy-4hydroxy-phenylethyleneglycol) as a stress indicator.</p><p>For other research subjects, improvement of the causal structure is required along with causal relationships, including socioeconomic factors such as academic background and annual income, which can be considered the basis of health.</p><p>The background is that socioeconomic factors affect the green environment, living environment, and mental health according to structural analysis by Finkel's model 26) related to the extension of healthy life expectancy <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21)</ref> . Oshige et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37)</ref> reported that there was a causal relationship in which the formation of a favorable residential area environment led to the maintenance and promotion of the health of residents.</p><p>Intervention studies on subjective health for the elderly in the community have been reported by Sappiro et al <ref type="bibr">38)</ref> . It was reported that the health effect of admission to the facility and death was more effective than that of the control group, as the effect of the health education intervention centered on the subjective feeling of health for 18 months. Therefore, effective support for healthy longevity for elderly people in the future should be based on support for socioeconomic factors to lead to a good sense of subjective health. At the same time, it is expected that intervention studies can be used to create a complex support program that combines multiple activities, such as physical activities, dietary patterns, psychological factors, social participation, and living environment, and to clarify the effects of QOL and health and longevity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>Pain, illness, and lifestyle were the most stable over 6 years. Quality of life, which was also determined to be stable, was signi cantly in uenced by pain, illness, and lifestyle and recognition of aging and disease preventability six years prior. It was also shown that desirable quality of life and pain, illness and lifestyle could signi cantly affect the recognition of aging and disease preventability after 6 years. Improving external validity is an issue for future research.   </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Declarations</head><label></label><figDesc>Consent of the InstitutionalThis investigation was approved by the consent of the Institutional Review Board on Human Research at Sagami Women's University, acceptance number 1,793, October 27, 2017.This study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. All participants responded to the questionnaire based on informed consent.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figures</head><label></label><figDesc>Figures</figDesc><graphic coords="16,28.00,74.29,460.16,581.77" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 1 Structure</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>This research was carried out with the great cooperation of the Longevity Center for Social Development and the <rs type="funder">Liaison Council for the Promotion of Bright Longevity Society</rs>. We would like to express our sincere gratitude to <rs type="person">Mr. Kiyoyuki Yakushiji</rs>, <rs type="person">Yamato Kazuki</rs> of the Longevity Center and all the people nationwide who cooperated in the questionnaire survey. This research was supported by the great cooperation of the Longevity Center for Social Development and the <rs type="funder">Liaison Council for the Promotion of Bright Longevity Society</rs> <rs type="grantName">Grant-in-Aid for Scienti c Research</rs>.</p><p>Not applicable for another section.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_NbNP2d6">
					<orgName type="grant-name">Grant-in-Aid for Scienti c Research</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Publication consent</head><p>We agree to publish this original paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Possibility of data and materials</head><p>Analytical data and materials are available from the author using the mail.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Con ict of interest statement</head><p>The Author declares that there is no con ict of interest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Division of roles for writing a treatise</head><p>Hoshi summarized the entire sentence. Collaborator Fujita, Kurimori, and Kodama were involved in data collection and analysis. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trends in national hygiene</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Labor Statistics Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018. 2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="84" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The aim of Health Japan 21</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sakurai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hoshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">hokennokagaku</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="552" to="557" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The second edition of the Health Business Guidelines based on the characteristics of the elderly</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.mhlw.go.jp/content/12401000/000604327.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Medical Division for the Elderly, Insurance Bureau, Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>access May.20th in 2022</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nutritional determinants of frailty in older adults: A systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lorenzo-López L</forename><surname>Maseda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>De Labra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Geriatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">108</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dietary patterns and frailty: a systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rashidi-Pourfard N Amirabdollahian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Haghighatdoost</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nutr Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="498" to="513" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The way of Living</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Morimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hoshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<publisher>HBJ Pub</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="98" />
			<pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceived health and mortality: a nine-year follow-up of the human population laboratory cohort</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kaplan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Camacho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="292" to="304" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social networks, host resistance, and mortality: a nine-year follow-up study of Alameda County residents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Berkman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Syme</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="204" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social network ties and mortality among the elderly in the Alameda County Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Seeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kaplan Ga Knudsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="714" to="723" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Positive age stereotypes predict longevity among older adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Nakagawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yasumoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Japanese journal of gerontology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="270" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing the differences in positive thinking between the healthy elderly and the elderly with long-term care risk. Japanese</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shirai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of public health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Examination of Factors Promoting / Restraining the acceptance of aging among the Elderly</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Egami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hashimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hokkaido Pshychological Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Association between feelings of happiness among communitydwelling, independent, elderly individuals in an Okinawan farm village and survival three years later</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kodama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kurimori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hoshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of public health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="209" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nutritional, Physical, Cognitive, and Combination Interventions and Frailty Reversal Among Older Adults: A Randomized Controlled Trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Nyunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1225" to="1236" />
			<date type="published" when="1221">2015. 1221</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The associations of frailty with regular participation in physical, cultural, and community social activities among independent elders in Japan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Yoshizawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Takahashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of public health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="306" to="316" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Japan as the front-runner of super-aged societies: perspectives from medicine and medical care in Japan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Arai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ouchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Toba</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geriatr Gerontol Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="673" to="687" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Integrated care for older people: guidelines on community-level interventions to manage declines in intrinsic capacity</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>World Health Organization</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">46</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Geneva</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new approach to explaining sick-role behavior in low-income populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Drachman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kirscht</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="216" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Attitudes and Behavior of Patients to Improve the Self-Management of Ischemic Heart Disease A Literature Review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Taira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Murofushi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Oogama</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bulletin of Dokkyo Medical University School of Nursing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship between subjective well-being and degree of independence after 3 years in the frequency of exercise in the elderly</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kodama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kurimori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Yamato</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Health and Welfare Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decline in independence after three years and its association with dietary patterns and IADL-related factors in community-dwelling older people: an analysis by age stage and sex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kodama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hoshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kurimori</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Geriatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">385</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Explanation and points to note in the questionnaire for the late-stage elderly. Medical Division for the Elderly, Insurance Bureau, Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.mhlw.go.jp/content/12401000/000557576.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>access Feb.20th in 2022</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measurement of competence: reliability and validity of the TMIG Index of Competence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Koyano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Shibata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nakazato</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch Gerontol Geriatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="116" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Philadelphia Geriatric Center Morale Scale: a revision</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lawton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Gerontol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="89" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Meaning of Life Measurement: Revised PGC Moral Scale Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Koyano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Japanese journal of gerontology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Causal analysis with panel data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Finkel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<publisher>Sage Publications</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="56" />
			<pubPlace>California</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Covariance structure analysis that can be seen graphically</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wakui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wakui</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jitsugyounotomoshya</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Covariance structure analysis and analysis example 2nd edition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Onodera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<publisher>Kyoto Nakanishiya Publishing</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="20" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to covariance structure analysis and its actuality Tokyo Kodansha</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Asano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kojima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="20" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Suicide and it&apos;s prevention in the elderly</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fujita</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Japanese journal of gerontology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Statistics dictionary</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Takeuchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Edit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<publisher>Tokyo Keizai Inc</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="619" to="620" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causal Relationships between the Internet Use and the Skill to Practically Use Information : A Three-Wave Panel Study of Junior High School Students</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Oomi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Adachi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Japan Society for Educational Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relationship between the reality of green-related enjoyment and purpose of life and subjective health in the elderly in the suburbs of the city</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hoshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kurimori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ino</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Health and Welfare Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why do we need some large, simple randomized trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yusuf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Collins R Peto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="409" to="422" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Longitudinal bene t of positive self-perceptions of aging on functional health</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Levy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Slade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kasl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Gerontol B Psychol Sci Soc Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="409" to="417" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship between free-MHPG, a Stress-related Substance in Saliva, and Mental Health in the Elderly</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Toyosato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Koyoshida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Okamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Japanese journal of psychosomatic medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Housing and Community for Promotion of Health and Well-Being</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ooshige</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shiraishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ikaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A Modeling of Health Related Factors Structure in the City of Kitakyushu Considering Temporal Relationship. Summaries of Technical Papers of Annual Meeting</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Architectural Institute of Japan</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1023" to="1024" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Part 65</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of a community-based early intervention program on the subjective wellbeing, institutionalization, and mortality of low-income elders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gerontologist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="334" to="341" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Tables Tables 1 to 7 are available in the Supplementary Files section</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
