<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Vrije Universiteit Brussel A Model for Range Estimation and Energy-Efficient Routing of Electric Vehicles in Real-World Conditions</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Agency for Innovation by Science and Technology in Flanders (IWT)</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>Cauwer</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Cedric</forename><forename type="middle">;</forename><surname>Coosemans</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Van</forename><surname>Mierlo</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Cedric</forename><surname>De Cauwer</surname></persName>
							<email>cedric.de.cauwer@vub.be</email>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0003-3495-2256</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wouter</forename><surname>Verbeke</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Joeri</forename><forename type="middle">Van</forename><surname>Mierlo</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Thierry</forename><surname>Coosemans</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Cedric</forename><surname>De</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Cauwer</forename><surname>De Cauwer</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Van Mierlo</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Mobil- ity, Logistics and Automotive Technology Research Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Electrical Engineering and Energy Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vrije Universiteit Brussel</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1050</postCode>
									<settlement>Brussels</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Mobility, Logistics and Automotive Technology Research Centre, Business Technology and Operations Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vrije Universiteit Brussel</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1050</postCode>
									<settlement>Brussels</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Vrije Universiteit Brussel A Model for Range Estimation and Energy-Efficient Routing of Electric Vehicles in Real-World Conditions</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TITS.2019.2918019</idno>
					<note type="submission">received February 2, 2018; revised September 26, 2018 and December 6, 2018; accepted April 14, 2019.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T01:03+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>IEEE Transactions on Intelligent Transportation Systems Electric vehicles</term>
					<term>energy-efficient routing</term>
					<term>energy consumption</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>with details of the nature of the infringement. We will investigate the claim and if justified, we will take the appropriate steps.</p><p>This article has been accepted for inclusion in a future issue of this journal. Content is final as presented, with the exception of pagination.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>T HE Electric vehicle (EV) has great potential to reduce the impact of the transport sector on global warming by decreasing greenhouse gas emissions, particularly in combination with low emission electricity production, and to improve local air quality by not emitting tail-pipe emissions <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. However, despite advances in battery technology and decreasing battery prices, which result in higher installed battery capacity in commercial vehicles, the EV's driving range is still low compared to its conventional technology competitor <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> and energy consumption reported to be up to 60% higher in reallife than measured on New European Drive Cycle (NEDC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. This limited battery capacity, combined with a highly variable energy consumption and limited availability of charge infrastructure, lead to range-anxiety <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. To address the issue of range-anxiety, this paper proposes an integrated model for range estimation and energy-efficient routing. Energy Efficient routing, or E-routing, in general stands for generating energyefficient alternative routes to travel from an origin to a destination in a road network. The calculation of the path with the lowest energy consumption is generally done by allocating an energy cost to the road segments and applying cost-optimization algorithms, generally known as shortest path algorithms (SPA). Compared to energy-efficient routing for ICE vehicles <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, energy-efficient routing for EVs apply different energy prediction models, and further differentiate themselves by the range restrictions, charging requirements and the presence of negative costs. Literature on models for energyefficient routing generally only focuses on either the prediction of the energy consumption on road segments or making the routing algorithm computationally superior, in which case the energy prediction model and translation into driving range are often generic, serving only to illustrate the capabilities of the routing algorithm. This paper continues the work presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, where a data-driven energy consumption prediction for electric vehicles in real-world conditions was presented, by adding an analysis of internal losses of the battery and integrating the energy consumption as a cost function in the routing. The integrated model presented in this research is a functional, validated model for range estimation and energyefficient routing in real-world conditions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. STATE-OF-THE-ART OF ENERGY-EFFICIENT ROUTING FOR ELECTRIC VEHICLES</head><p>Literature ranges from methods to generate E-routes for an individual driver <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, possibly with range restrictions and the option to charge <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, to research that calculates routes to obtain network energy optima <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. Other specific traditional cost-optimization problems such as the vehicle routing problem or travelling salesman problem, where a monetary cost-optimization of delivery problems is sought (i.e. delivery of goods, products and services to multiple costumers considering time constraints, range constraints, and operational cost), are adapted to the case of electric vehicles <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> and electric vehicle fleets including charge scheduling and battery degradation <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. Recently, mobility-on-demand serviced by electric vehicles has triggered routing algorithms that minimize overall trip time for all customers considering charging needs <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Shortest-Path-Algorithm</head><p>Generating cost optimal routes for single drivers are generally done by applying shortest path algorithms to a graph representation of the road network. The graph representation of the road network consists of edges (also called links) connected at vertices (also called nodes), where the edges represent road segments and the vertices represent the intersections. The edges in the graph are given a cost, and shortest path algorithms calculate cost optimal solutions between vertices in the graph. In navigation applications, the cost function is traditionally the travelled distance or travel time between vertices. In the case of E-routing, the cost between vertices is the energy consumption. SPAs are well established since the late 1950s, with the Bellman-Ford algorithm (1958) <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, <ref type="bibr">Floyd-Warshall (1962)</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, and the most famous, generally applied in navigation applications, Dijkstras algorithm (1959) <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. Both Bellman-Ford and Dijkstras expansion procedures guarantee optimal solutions, but will expand unintelligently to the full network (or a large part of the network for Dijkstra) before reaching the destination vertex with an optimal solution. Heuristic algorithms can be used to decrease the calculation time by intelligently expanding to vertices in the network in such a way that vertices, unlikely to provide the shortest path, are excluded from the expansion. The drawback of heuristics SPA is the fact that they are not guaranteed to produce optimal solutions. A literature overview of heuristic approaches to shortest path algorithms for transportation was presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</p><p>Energy-efficient routing for EVs introduces the specific challenge of the presence of range restrictions and negative edge costs, for which the Dijkstras algorithm is not suited. The Bellman-Ford algorithm can deal with negative links, yet increases computational time. It has been proposed in several publications as the shortest path algorithm for EVs <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. Other specific shortest path algorithms for electric vehicles have been proposed and evaluated: metaheuristic approach in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, particle swarm optimization in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, Dijkstras algorithm with shifting technique (Johnsons) <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. Some authors extend the SPA to include state-of-charge requirements <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>.</p><p>Algorithms that provide the shortest path from any origin vertex to any destination vertex, are generally called all-pair shortest path algorithms (APSPA). APSPA can be advantageous when shortest paths must be found in real-time in large networks. By pre-calculating all-pair shortest paths, shortest paths can later be queried fast from memory. In general, shortest paths can be programmed through dynamic programming, and the established algorithms are variants to the dynamic programming structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Energy-Efficient Routing</head><p>A number of solutions for energy-efficient routing of electric vehicles are proposed in literature. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, the platform for a route planner is presented which implements a standard routeplanner in combination with an EV vehicle model, which was presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>. However, this platform assumes the speed profile is known and inserted into the vehicle model. No evaluation of that proposed model was presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> or found in other publications of the same authors. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, an energy consumption estimation model was constructed using multiple linear regression based on historical data of average speed, accelerations, road gradient and future data of the driving speed assumed to be known. The methodology applies Dijkstras algorithm to determine the most energyefficient route on a simplified network. This methodology has an interesting structure and applies sufficient averaging to be usable for large scale, network prediction. However, only a limited number of parameters are accounted for in the linear regression model and the link with the vehicle dynamics is largely lost. Moreover, no validation and no accuracy of the proposed methodology are presented. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, a generic energy consumption estimation model is developed, which calculates the power requirements from the driving resistance and auxiliary consumption. The driving resistance is calculated using speed dependent functions that estimate the share of the link spent in different driving phases (i.e. cruising, acceleration, deceleration and idle) based on the historic link speed, and uses average fixed values for the acceleration and deceleration. The method was evaluated by comparing the model results with results obtained from a model developed with the Passenger and Heavy Duty Emission Model (PHEM) on real GPS measured driving patterns. However, this paper lacks an in-depth evaluation with real energy consumption data and assumes link speeds are known or extractable and is therefore not immediately usable in its current form. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> (and from the same author <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>), the statistical representation of traffic-, driver-, and situation-related features in speed profiles on specific road segments are correlated with the deviation from the normalized energy consumption of the respective vehicles, in order to estimate the energy consumption over a given route. A regression model estimates the energy consumption from the established most influential principle components, which themselves are predicted by historic mean values of these traffic-, driver-, and situation related features. A validated vehicle model is used to calculate the energy consumption based on real-world GPS measured driving data. Although energy-efficient routing was not discussed in this publication, the separation of trips in road segments for the energy prediction, allows for energy efficient routing. A model for energy consumption forecasting based on vehicle-, road-, traffic-, weather-, and driver profile-related parameters using a neural network was presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> and extended to be applied in e-routing application by the same authors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. To decrease computational times associated with shortest path algorithms that can handle negative link costs such as Floyd-Warshall, the authors propose the shifting technique described by Johnson in <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>. An energy-efficient routing model for EVs based on real-time data of a local traffic center has been presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>. The authors proposed an altered Bellman-Ford algorithm that can deal with time-variant, negative links and dimensionless nodes are expanded to areas of intersections to be able to implement the dynamic traffic data. However, the presented energy estimation model is basic and few values on model accuracy are reported. Only in a limited number of publications, the energy-efficient routing has been extended to range estimation by including the battery capacity. A holistic approach towards routing for electric vehicles is presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. The authors focus on the challenges for the calculation of a route in the EV context, including the SoC and recharging requirements, and propose approaches to deal with these. However, very little information on the energy estimation model and its input drive cycles is provided, nor does it contain an implementation and evaluation of the proposed approach. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, a data mining approach for range prediction of electric vehicle is proposed. It uses a regression model based on past driver behavior (separated in vehicle-related, driver-related and environment-related parameters) to estimate the available range. The methodology is implemented in an Electric Vehicle Assistant as a mobile application which displays the driver centric available range on a map with a 25% uncertainty band. Although the architecture and its implementation are well explained in <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> and in consecutive publications of the same authors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, none of these publications presents any measured result, model fit or model accuracy. This methodology contains two other drawbacks: the range is the result of the SoC requirements per unit distance, losing information on the energy consumption itself, and is not calculated on each individual segment. As a consequence, energy-efficient routes cannot be generated. Another driver centric estimation of the vehicle range is presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>. A destination attainability map is calculated based on a weighed probability of choosing a route to a set of destinations. The energy consumption is calculated from speed profiles by a simplified vehicle model. The speed profiles are calculated based on a car-following algorithm which incorporates road attributes as rules. This model is evaluated by comparing the calculated maps with the model based results from the actual driven routes. A variant of that model is presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>, where the energy calculation is now considered a normal distributed parameter and the results are validated with the Nissan Leaf.</p><p>The literature shows there are a number of solutions already presented for energy-efficient routing of electric vehicles. The approaches vary from statistical and data-driven, to deterministic. Some of these solutions have interesting methodologies that show promising results. However, most of the presented literature has a very basic energy estimation algorithm, which lacks to include one or more influencing factors (such as altitude difference, auxiliaries, or wind) and are not based on actual measured consumption of proposed routes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. THE PROPOSED METHOD FOR RANGE ESTIMATION AND ENERGY-EFFICIENT ROUTING</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Energy Consumption Prediction Model</head><p>The energy consumption prediction model is a data-driven model that combines vehicle monitoring data with road information, weather information (temperature, precipitation) and temporal data (time of the day, day of the week) to predict the energy consumptions of an electric vehicle over actual road segments. The model has a first stage for speed profile prediction using a neural network and a second stage for energy consumption estimation, given the predicted speed profile from the first stage and other influential parameters, using a multiple linear regression model. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> presents a schematic diagram of the energy model, its inputs and outputs. The AF (aerodynamic factor) and CMF (constant motion factor) are two characteristics that were defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and are measures for the aerodynamic and inertial losses respectively. The neural network for speed profile prediction is trained from road, traffic and weather related parameters. The road segment characteristics consist of its length, the altitude difference, the road type, presence of traffic lights and information on the crossings. The crossings were categorized in straight, light right turn, heavy right turn, light left turn, and heavy left turn. The linear regression model estimates the energy consumption from the AF and CMF (predicted by the neural network), the altitude difference, the covered distance and temperature scaled time dependent variable ( Aux t ,Aux T ) that represent the contribution of the auxiliaries to the energy consumption. Equation 1 expresses the energy consumption in function of its dependent variables for the energy estimation by the multiple linear regression. Distance between measurement point i -</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">E = B 1 s + B 2 n i=2 v 2 i s i + B 3 C M F + s + B 4 C M F -s + B 5 H pos + B 6 H neg + B 7 Aux T + B 8 Aux t +<label>(1) where</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">1 and i s = n i=2 s i Distance driven t Time difference (duration) T Ambient temperature in • C v i Vehicle speed at measurement point i C M F - Negative kinetic energy changes C M F +</formula><p>Positive kinetic energy changes Error term This is the cost function for the proposed model and must thus be calculated for each segment in the road network. For an elaborate description of the energy consumption model, the reader is referred to <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, which focuses on the development and evaluation of this energy prediction model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Battery Model</head><p>The range of the vehicle will essentially be a function of energy that can be drawn from the battery, and the energy consumption per unit distance. The useful energy that can be drawn from the battery depends on the remaining battery Most of the existing literature studies the behavior of batteries at cell level for different types of chemistries. The internal resistance fluctuates with battery temperature and increases in time due to ageing effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>. The ageing of the battery is generally expressed as the state-of-health (SoH). Battery models for SoC estimation, SoH estimation and thermal behavior of Li-ion batteries exist with various levels of complexity. SoC and SoH estimation methods can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>, and complex models for internal resistance calculation for the purpose of online SoC and SoH estimation on cell level are available in literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>. This type of dedicated modeling for complex behavior of the battery cells is out of scope for this application. However, for this application, modeling the internal resistance of the battery on pack level, together with the assumption that the SoC and SoH are known, is sufficient to translate the energy consumption into driving range.</p><p>If the battery temperature is measured, having a model that estimates the internal resistance based on the battery temperature will allow translating energy consumption into driving range. If we characterize the internal resistance by using the most simple representation of a battery, i.e. a voltage source and a resistance, the open circuit voltage (OCV) equals the terminal voltage (TV) plus the voltage drop over the internal resistance, or OCV = R i .I bat + T V . By modeling the battery in this way, only the steady state behavior of the battery is included and transients are neglected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Routing Algorithm</head><p>Calculating energy-efficient routes for EVs with SPA has 2 specific characteristics:</p><p>• The edge cost is the energy consumption • Negative edge costs are possible The possibility of negative edge costs impose using Bellman-Ford for single query shortest paths, if necessary with calculation time improving heuristics, and using the currently known computational optimal Johnsons algorithm (for sparse graphs) for all-pair shortest paths. In the design of systems for querying shortest paths, the combination of network size, processing power, storage capacity, and user requirement will determine the approach. The calculation of the cost (energy consumption), can either be done during expansion (while determining the shortest path), or can be pre-calculated for the complete network if the energy cost is static and independent from the path. Pre-calculation of the energy consumption in the complete network reduces the waiting time for the user but requires pre-calculation of the look-up tables for every combination of the state variables.</p><p>Applying SPAs to a network using the energy consumption prediction model presented in Section III-A as a cost function requires some additional changes. The particularity of including turn information for the energy prediction, is the fact that the energy consumption on a segment will depend on the turn type from the preceding segment into the current segment. Moreover, some other segment characteristics of a preceding segment influence the consumption of the current one. For example, the difference in speed limit between two sequential segments will cause the driver to accelerate or decelerate accordingly. Therefore, the road type, indicated travel speed of the preceding segment and turn type into the current segment were taken into the neural network input variables. As a consequence, this cost calculation method cannot be used if the road network is represented by the classical directed graph where road segments are represented by edges and intersection by vertices. To be able to use the proposed method for energy consumption prediction, the graph representation of the road network has to be adapted in a similar way to what is done to include turn costs in literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>. Two methods can be applied: network expansion and network transformation. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> illustrates both methods on two simple network examples. The expansion method consists of replacing each vertex, representing a single intersection, with a combination of vertices and edges, according to the possible turn combinations. In example A, vertex V 3 can be travelled coming from vertex V 1 or V 2 , and the cost associated with e 3 = (V 3 , V 4 ) will vary according to the V 3 s incoming edges. To represent this choice in the graph, three extra edges and three extra vertices are added. Note that this representation guarantees that the SPA algorithm will still find the optimal solution. In example B, V 3 can be travelled coming from either e 1 or e 2 and be left on either e 3 or e 4 . To represent these combinations, vertex V 3 is replaced with 8 extra vertices and 8 edges. It is clear that with increasing complexity of the network, the adapted network expands rapidly. The second method is less straightforward, yet very elegant, and consists in transforming the graph in such way that the edges in the original graph become the vertices in the transformed graph, and the combinations of travel possibilities become edges in the transformed graph. For example A, edges e 1 , e 2 , and e 3 become nodes in the transformed graph, and the combinations of travelling V 3 from e 1 → e 3 or e 2 → e 3 , which become the edges in the transformed graph. A similar reasoning can be done for example B. In the general </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">= (V, E) become vertices of G = (E, E ), E = ((u, v), (v, w)) ∈ E x E.</formula><p>As for the expansion method, the transformation method will increase the number of vertices and edges, but less than with the expansion method. If v is a node in G = (V, E), with n incoming edges and m outgoing edges, the node expands to 3nm -(n + m) edges and (2nm) nodes in the expansion method, while it increases the number of vertices to n + m and the number of edges to nm in the transformation method. Considering the Bellman-Ford shortest path has complexity O(V E), the calculation times of the transformed graph (edge-based graph) will be smaller compared to the expanded graph. Because of the lower calculation times of the edge-based graph transformation solution, this method was implemented.</p><p>In order to make the transformed edge-based graph equivalent to its original node-based graph, the edge-based graph must be further extended with entry and exit nodes. The entry and exit nodes allow shortest paths between vertices of the node-based graph to be queried in the same way as in its edgebased form. As shortest paths are queried between vertices of a graph, queries in the edge-based graph as presented until now, would calculate the cost between two edges in the original graph. However, in order to query shortest paths in both G and G which are equivalent (in between nodes of G), G must be further extended such that each vertex v of G , corresponding to edge e = (u, v) of G, can be accessed by its origin node u in G and exited by its destination node v in G. This can be done by extending the graph G with entry vertices V en = u E en = (V en , e), with u ∈ V of G(V, E) and e ∈ E of G (E, E ), and <ref type="figure">,</ref><ref type="figure">E</ref>) and e ∈ E of G (E, E ). Note that if G had n nodes, this operation will increase the number Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">V ex = v E ex = (e, V ex ), with v ∈ V of G(V</formula><p>Conversion of a simple node-based network to its edge-based equivalent with the addition of entry and exit nodes.</p><p>of edges and number of edges of G with at most 2n. Lets consider the cost allocation of all edges, entry edges and exit edges in our specific case. In general we can say that if we consider an edge e i with preceding edge e i-1 , the edge cost of e i will be a function of the characteristics of the preceding edge (characteristics of the edge and turn type from i → i -1). Therefore, we define the cost associated with an edge of the edge-based graph c(e i-1 , e i ) as the energy consumption at reaching the end of segment i , considering we travelled from edge i -1. To define the cost associated with the entry and exit edge, consider the simple example presented in Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> and apply this to the general case. If we start in node i of the node-based graph, we will enter the edge-based graph through the entry node en which has an associated of c = f (en, e i ), according to this definition. Since en does not represent an actual road segment, its characteristics and the turn type associated with travelling from en to e i , do not exist and cannot be allocated. The cost allocated to entry edges are therefore calculated based on an average consumption value. For the exit edge, the case is simpler. By calculating all cost according to the procedure above, the cost when residing in a vertex of G , which represents a road segment (=edge in the node-based graph), is the energy consumption after the segment is travelled. Exiting from the last vertex through the exit edge to the exit vertex (=destination node in the nodebased graph), should therefore have a cost that equals zero. Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> illustrates the transformation from a node-based graph to an edge based graph, with entry-and exit node extension, and the cost allocation according to the reasoning above.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Integrated Model for Range Estimation and Energy-Efficient Routing</head><p>The objective of this research is a model for energy consumption prediction and range estimation, capable of energy efficient-routing. If we use the energy prediction model  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>This integrated model is implemented in an offline way to investigate the impact of energy-efficient optimal solutions on the route choice. The model is implemented for the a selection of the network Brussels Capital Region (BCR) network for a Nissan Leaf 2013 model. The model is implemented on a selection of the road network to limit the calculation time of the energy prediction on all segments in the selected road network. Since the energy consumption has to be re-calculated on the complete network with changing state variable, limiting the implemented network improves the workability for this study. The network pre-processing (e.g. calculating crossing category, calculating altitude differences) on segments is done in ArcGiS®. Apart from the network pre-processing, the complete integrated model was implemented in Matlab®. The network is imported in the form of a shapefile, which Matlab allows to visualize. The network described in the shapefile is then translated into its mathematical representation of a directed graph after performing the following actions:</p><p>• duplicating the edges corresponding to two-way streets (while inverting the road attributes of heading and altitude difference)</p><p>• inverting edges corresponding to one-way streets with opposing traffic flow and edge directions • deleting edges which correspond to road segments with unknown road type or closed for passenger transportation (e.g. roads in parks). • create the node-based graph associated with the selected road network must then be transformed into an edgebased graph, as explained in Section III. The energy-optimal solutions will be calculated on the edgebased graph using Bellman-Ford algorithm, while distanceoptimal solutions are calculated using Dijkstra algorithm on the original node-based graph (which is the benchmark of current practice in classical routing). The network size, the size of its node-based graph representation, and the size of its edge-based representation is given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">I</ref>. The table also presents values for the calculation times to build the nodebased graph, the edge-based graph and the average calculation time for the time-optimal and distance-optimal solutions of 5 randomly chosen origin and destinations with a 2.9GHz Intel®Xeon®CPU E3-1545M v5 processor. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">I</ref> shows the size of the edge-based graph is significantly higher with approximately 5 times the number of vertices and edges of the node-based graph. The calculation time for the energyoptimal routes with Bellman-Ford on the edge-based graph is an order of magnitude slower than running Dijkstra on the node-based graph for distance-optimal routes. Calculating the energy cost for the selected network for one combination of state variables was time-consuming and must therefore be executed and stored prior to querying origin destination pairs in order to be useable in real user applications.</p><p>To construct the temperature dependent battery internal resistance model, battery temperature data of different vehicles was used since battery temperature data was lacking for the vehicles that provided the data to build the energy consumption model. Although this might impact the accuracy of the range  A similar linear regression is used to determine the internal resistance in all temperature regions and SoC bins, which are presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>. The internal resistance shows a clear temperature dependence and a slight linear increase with decreasing SoC. Although Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref> shows a clear temperature dependence of the battery's internal resistance, the associated losses will also depend on the load profile (current). The battery losses, P Loss battery , dissipated in the internal resistance R internal by drawing a current I batter y equal P Loss battery = R internal I 2 batter y . Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7</ref> presents the average resistive losses relative to the total power consumption in function of the battery temperature during braking and driving for the same vehicle of the dataset. It shows that the resistive losses during braking are about 1%,  while the resistive losses during driving are between 3-6%, depending on the battery temperature. The limited current during regeneration leads to these lower battery losses for braking compared to driving.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. E-Routing Analysis</head><p>To evaluate the performance and application potential of the proposed model for energy efficient routing, the model will be applied to a chosen scenario and to a random selection of origin-destination pairs. The first allows to have feel with the dynamics (different energy consumption influencing factors) that shift a time-optimal or distance-optimal route to an energy-optimal route, while the latter allows to have a more general evaluation of the effect of energy-efficient routing on • Travelling across town: the driver approaches one side of the city on a highway and has its destination on the other side of the city. The scenario presents a dilemma to the driver: drive through the city or go around the city using the ring way. This scenario is chosen because it is expected to occur in real-life and have non-marginal differences in travelled distance, travel time, and energy consumption. The distance-optimal, time-optimal and energy-optimal solution will be calculated with the integrated model and analyzed for different cases of the main scenario. All different set-ups of the scenario will be based on the model which was developed. All cases are based on the main scenario where a driver approaches the east side of town on a highway, and is bound for home on the outskirts of the west side of the city. The origin segment will be the last segment of the highway approaching the city before crossing the ring way R0. The first 2 cases of the scenario have the same origin and destination, but have different values of the state variables. The first case (case A) has moderate ambient temperatures without using auxiliaries and the second case has low ambient temperatures with the vehicles auxiliaries on. All other state variables are kept constant. The description of both cases and their state variables is given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">II</ref>. To understand the general trends in the route choice, it is important to understand how distance, speed and time contribute to the energy consumption (weights in equation 1). In <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, a figure depicting the average consumption in function of trip speed illustrates the more or less constant contribution of the rolling resistance in function of speed, the decreasing contribution of accelerations with increasing speed, the increasing contribution of aerodynamic losses with increasing speed and an increasing contribution of auxiliary consumption with decreasing speed. The distanceoptimal, energy-optimal, and time-optimal route for the first case as calculated by the model are presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8a</ref>. Both the distance-optimal and energy-optimal route cross the inner city, while the time optimal route takes the ring way. This is not unexpected as the increase in distance is outweighed by the difference in travel speed along a highway route. However, the increase in aerodynamic losses during highway driving and increased distance makes the energy cost of this route much higher. Like the distance-optimal, the energy-optimal route also crosses the inner city, yet still differs for a large part of the route.</p><p>The same scenario in low ambient temperature conditions with the vehicles auxiliaries on can shift the time-distanceenergy balance because of the increased impact of the travel time on the total consumption by the auxiliaries. The distanceoptimal, energy-optimal, and time-optimal route for the second case (case B) as calculated by the model are presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8b</ref>. The energy-optimal route shifts and almost coincides with the time-optimal route. In the third (C) and fourth variant (D) of the general scenario, the origin is shifted to another highway coming into the south-east side of Brussels. Case C and D are identical to A and B respectively, except for their starting point, which shifts the distance ratio of cutting across the city and going around it. One case will have moderate ambient temperature without the use of auxiliaries, the other case low ambient temperatures with the vehicles auxiliaries on, similar to Case A and B respectively. The description of both cases and their state variables is given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">III</ref>. The distance-optimal, energy-optimal, and timeoptimal route for the third case (case C), as calculated by the model, are presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9a</ref>. Similar to case A, the time-optimal route takes the ring way, while the, partly coinciding, distance-optimal and energy-optimal routes cross the city. In case D, with low temperatures and the vehicles auxiliaries on, only minor shifts in the energy-optimal route occur, increasing the percentage coinciding with the distanceoptimal route, as is shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9b</ref>. This means the impact of the increased distance and aerodynamic losses on total energy consumption by taking the ringway outweigh the reduction in auxiliary consumption associated with the gain in travel time for this case. In general we can state that the energy optimal route is a trade-off between travel time (speed) and distance and will lean towards the distanceoptimal route in the case of a low auxiliary consumption and will lean towards the time-optimal route in the case of a high  auxiliary consumption. The differences between the distanceoptimal route and energy-optimal route passing through the city are small, yet generally we observe that the energyoptimal route selects roads of higher importance, with less intersections, and limits the number of turns.</p><p>The results of the distance-, energy-, and time-optimal routes for all four cases are presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">IV</ref>. The results are absolute values of the travelled distance, travel time, and energy consumption and show the relative difference compared to the time-optimal. The time-optimal route is selected as the reference case because it is considered the preferred choice of a driver in general. The relative numbers presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">IV</ref>, indicate the gain or loss in travel time, travel distance and energy consumption in case the driver opts to divert from the time-optimal route. These numbers show the potential benefits of the different routes and could be used to inform the driver when such dilemmas present themselves. In case A, there is a moderate gain efficiency (-9%), yet a large increase in travel time (45%) for the distance-optimal route, and slightly more so for the energy-optimal route (-16% and 68% respectively). Therefore, the energy-efficient route in this case will not likely benefit the driver, unless the vehicle is critical on SoC. In case B, the obvious choice is to divert from the distance-optimal route to either the energy-efficient or time-efficient route. Since the gain in energy efficiency is insignificant (-1%) compared to a 9% loss in time between the energy-optimal and time-optimal route, the latter seems the most beneficial in this case. Note that the increase in energy consumption between the energy-optimal routes of case A and case B is 45%, illustrating the large choice-based gain or loss in different conditions. Case C is identical to case A except for its starting point, which makes cutting across the city much shorter than going around it. Therefore, the energy-efficient route becomes much more attractive to drivers, because of its large energy-efficiency gain (-37%) and moderate time-loss (34%). Furthermore, the distance-optimal route might be even more attractive because its energy-efficiency gain (-31%) is almost as large as the energy-optimal route, but its time loss is only half (17%). Case D has similar time losses as Case C, yet loses competitiveness with the time-optimal route because of its decreased energy-efficiency gain. These scenarios and their different cases illustrate energy-optimal routes shift according to the ratio of travel time and travel distance, and according to values of the state-variables. Of course, road altitude differences, intersections, road types, which are also accounted for in the energy consumption prediction model, will also further shift the energy-optimal route and differentiate it from the time-optimal route or distance-optimal route it is leaning towards. Depending on the relative gain or loss of travel time and energy consumption, drivers can make informed decisions on the appropriate route. For a more general evaluation of the e-routes, the model was applied to a random selection of 100 origin-destination pairs in the case with moderate ambient temperature and the case with low ambient temperature conditions (and use of heating), similarly to what was done before with the difference between case A and B, and case C and D. The average relative differences in travel distance, travel time, and consumed energy between the time-optimal route and energy-optimal route for both conditions are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">V</ref>. To illustrate the spread in the relative differences, a boxplot is given in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">10</ref>. The results are consistent to what was observed in the analysis of the scenario. In both temperature conditions, the numbers show an average reduction of the energy consumption at a considerate time loss for the energy-optimal routes compared to the time-optimal routes. In the case with low ambient temperatures (and use of auxiliaries), the energy savings and time losses of the e-routes are smaller compared to the case with moderate temperatures. This is consistent with the case B of the examined scenario, where it was observed that in the case of an important consumption of the auxiliaries, the travel time has an important contribution to the energy consumption, which shifts the e-route closer to the time-optimal case. The 16.6% average energy consumption reduction for the case with moderate ambient temperatures demonstrate that, on average, important energy savings can be obtained by consistently applying e-routing, while the boxplot illustrate there is large spread in the potential energy consumption reductions which will probably lead to a case by case evaluation by the driver for a route choice depending on his priorities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Real-Life Tests</head><p>To test and evaluate the operation of the integrated model in real-life, case A of the general scenario and its inverse (inverting origin and destination) was driven with an electric vehicle. The electric vehicle at hand is a 2011 Nissan Leaf which has been used by a MOBI research group staff member for the last year. The vehicle was purchased in 2013 and had at the time of test a mileage over 83.000 km. The energy estimation model is developed based on the last 6 months of data from the vehicle, according to the methodology presented in III-A. The regression coefficient for negative altitude differences (B 4 in equation 1) was larger than the regression coefficient for positive altitude differences (B 3 in equation 1). Because this is not only physically impossible, but can also lead to the perverse effect that altitude differences are preferred instead of being avoided for energy-efficient routes, and lead to negative cycles in the graph representing the road network, this regression model is not workable in the integrated model. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">11</ref> illustrates this situation on a very simple network represented by a graph with three vertices with associated altitude, and three edges. Travelling from node</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">V 1 → V 2 → V 3 → V 1 ,</formula><p>with associated altitudes 1, 3, 5 and 1 respectively, will cause the cycle to have a negative cost (e.g. 2 + 2 -6 = -2) if the regression coefficient for negative altitude differences is larger than the regression coefficient for positive altitude changes (e.g at ratio 1.5), and will cause any shortest path to evolve to minus infinity. To deal with this issue, the model was changed to have only one term for the altitude difference contribution. The formula then becomes (cf. Section III-A):</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">E = B 1 s + B 2 n i=2 v 2 i s i + B 3 n i=2 |v 2 i -v 2 i-1 | + B 4 H + B 5 |20 -T | t Aux + B6t + (2)</formula><p>Note that this will effectively shift the contribution of the intermediate altitude differences to the terms and only  account for the net altitude differences explicitly. This also means that intermediate altitude differences will no longer affect route choice. However, the impact on the prediction accuracy and route choice is expected to be limited because of the small contribution of intermediate altitude differences in the BCR region to the total consumption. The regression coefficients as used by the model are presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">VI</ref>. The distance-optimal, energy-optimal, and time-optimal route for the real-life test case as calculated by the integrated model are presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">12</ref>. The results of the model predictions and measurement of the routes are presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">VII</ref>. The predicted and measured values of the energy consumption match well and the ranking of the routes in terms of their travel distance, energy consumption and travel time, is preserved, thus satisfying the prime goals of the integrated model for energy-efficient routing. If we consider the time-optimal route as the benchmark route, the relative differences of the distance-optimal and energy-optimal routes are presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">VIII</ref>. The table shows that the measured travel times are way off the model predictions, due to the use of the available link travel times which do not take into account a time cost for passing intersections. Table VIII also shows the trip distances in the model slightly differ from the measured trip distances, which is due to the difference between the lengths of the links (segments) in the road database and the GPS measured distances during the trip, which were affected by GPS inaccuracy and long standstill times during inner city trips. However, this will not affect the result as all calculations are done based on the road database segments' length. Similar to the analysis made in Section V-A above, despite significant Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">12</ref>. The real-life test cases distance-optimal route (black), energy-optimal route (green), and time-optimal route (yellow).</p><p>energy-efficiency gains (around 30%), the large increase in travel time for the energy-efficient routes compared to the time-optimal route makes these energy-efficient routes in these cases unattractive from the drivers point of view, unless the vehicle is critical on SoC. In terms of accuracy, the model prediction shows small errors for the Home-E40 case (1-7%) and reasonable errors for the E40-Home case (12%-17%). These measurements serve to proof this is a functional model for energy consumption prediction of electric vehicles and energy-efficient routing, with good accuracy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. DISCUSSION</head><p>The scenario considered in the evaluation of the proposed solution is chosen such that is expected to generate nontrivial differences between a distance-optimal, time-optimal and energy-optimal route from an origin to a destination in order to illustrate to the reader the potential of energy-efficient routing and the usability of the proposed model. However, more thorough investigation of the potential of energyefficient routing can be performed (e.g. random selection of origin-destination pairs, or cases with different traffic conditions) using the proposed solution, but this lies outside of the scope of this paper, which focuses development of the model itself. The validation of the model has been done on times where traffic conditions were considered congestion free, as no real-time information on the traffic conditions was available and the lack of real-time traffic conditions was already highlighted as a cause for reduced accuracy of the energy consumption prediction in the thorough evaluation that of part of this model in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. CONCLUSIONS</head><p>This paper proposes an integrated model for range estimation and energy-efficient routing. It is based on the energy consumption prediction model, presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, and extended with a temperature dependent, internal resistance model of the EV battery, in order to translate energy consumption into driving range. The energy consumption is predicted on all segments of a road network, and shortest path algorithms are applied to generate energy-efficient routes. The road network is represented by a digraph with edges and vertices, where the edges represent road segment and vertices represent intersections. Because the proposed model calculates the energy consumption of a segment based on its characteristics and the characteristic of the preceding road segment, classical shortest path algorithms cannot be applied to the graph in its standard form. The graph is transformed into an edgebased graph where vertices now represent segments and edges represent combinations of segments. Transforming the network in this way increases the number of nodes and edges in the graph, which will increase calculation time of the SPA by an order of magnitude for the selected network. To be able to deal with negative edge costs (which corresponds to energy recovery), Bellman-Fords SPA is applied. The integrated model is investigated in a selection of the road network by means of evaluating a scenario with multiple cases, and using a random selection of 100 origin-destination pairs. The results showed energy-efficient routes with efficiency gains up to 37% for specific cases of the chosen scenario and 8-16% on average for a random selection of origin-destination pairs. Further analysis showed that the energy-optimal route is different from the time-and distance-optimal route, but leans towards a distance optimal in the case of low auxiliary consumption and leans towards a time-optimal in the case of high auxiliary consumption. When the energy-optimal is close to the distance-optimal, it tends to avoid intersections and turns, and tends to select roads of higher importance compared to the distance-optimal. Analysis also showed that the gain in energy-efficiency often comes at the cost of high increase of travel time (up to 68% for the scenario and 11-23% on average for the random selection). These results indicate consistently applying e-routing can lead to important energy savings, yet is likely to be subject to a case by case evaluation by the driver for his preferred route based on his priorities (such as the vehicle being critical on SoC or time pressure). Presenting the driver with different options will allow him to make an informed decision regarding his preferred route. The integrated model for energy-efficient routing was also tested in real-life for one case of the chosen scenario. The measured results showed a good match with the predicted values for the energy consumption (a 9% mean relative error) and preserved the ranking of the routes in terms of the travelled distance, travel time and energy consumption of all routes. The proposed integrated model is thus a functional model for energy consumption in real-life, that differentiates many energy consumption influencing factors, and is capable of producing energy-efficient routes.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Schematic representation of the energy consumption prediction from segment road characteristics and state variables which represents the cost function. capacity during operation, or state-of-charge (SoC), and the internal losses in the battery during operation. The internal losses in the battery are caused by battery cell balancing and current losses dissipated in the internal resistance of the battery.Most of the existing literature studies the behavior of batteries at cell level for different types of chemistries. The internal resistance fluctuates with battery temperature and increases in time due to ageing effects<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>. The ageing of the battery is generally expressed as the state-of-health (SoH). Battery models for SoC estimation, SoH estimation and thermal behavior of Li-ion batteries exist with various levels of complexity. SoC and SoH estimation methods can be found in<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> and<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>, and complex models for internal resistance calculation for the purpose of online SoC and SoH estimation on cell level are available in literature<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>. This type of dedicated modeling for complex behavior of the battery cells is out of scope for this application. However, for this application, modeling the internal resistance of the battery on pack level, together with the assumption that the SoC and SoH are known, is sufficient to translate the energy consumption into driving range.If the battery temperature is measured, having a model that estimates the internal resistance based on the battery temperature will allow translating energy consumption into driving range. If we characterize the internal resistance by using the most simple representation of a battery, i.e. a voltage source and a resistance, the open circuit voltage (OCV) equals the terminal voltage (TV) plus the voltage drop over the internal resistance, or OCV = R i .I bat + T V . By modeling the battery in this way, only the steady state behavior of the battery is included and transients are neglected.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,49.43,58.25,250.15,165.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Illustration of the expansion method and transformation method for the representation of a variable cost according to the turn type with two simple network examples.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,49.43,58.97,250.10,258.26" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Overview of the complete integrated model for energy-efficient routing and range estimation.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,53.99,58.73,504.09,233.54" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>presented in III-A to calculate and predict the energy consumption on all road segments in network, and apply the SPA on the transformed edge-based representation of the road network, energy optimal routes are generated. If we input the energy consumption over the calculated path into the temperature dependent battery capacity model, such as presented in Section III-B, together with information on the SoC and SoH, the model can predict the remaining driving range at the destination in the form of the remaining SoC. The lay-out of this integrated model for energy consumption prediction, energy-efficient routing and range estimation is presented in Figure4.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Regression plot for the battery internal resistance in the 4-9 • C and 50-55% SoC bins.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,48.95,205.37,250.10,150.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Internal resistance for all temperature regions and SoC bins for one vehicle in the dataset.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,347.51,391.61,180.02,135.14" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Average resistive battery losses in function of the battery temperature during braking and driving for 1 vehicle of the dataset.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Case A (a) &amp; Case B (b) Bs distance-optimal route (black), energyoptimal route (green), and time-optimal route (yellow).</figDesc><graphic coords="9,440.63,174.89,121.94,137.54" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Case C (a) &amp; Case D (b) Ds distance-optimal route (black), energyoptimal route (green), and time-optimal route (yellow).</figDesc><graphic coords="10,177.59,429.65,121.94,136.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Boxplot for the relative difference in energy consumption for the random selection of 100 origin-destination pairs in both low and moderate ambient temperature conditions.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,311.99,175.97,250.10,149.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. Example of the creation of negative cycles because of the larger energy recovery during downhill than energy consumption during uphill, illustrated with a simple 3-segment network.</figDesc><graphic coords="12,48.95,218.45,250.10,111.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE I OVERVIEW</head><label>I</label><figDesc>OF THE NETWORK SIZE, THE SIZE OF ITS REPRESENTATION BY NODE-BASED GRAPH, AND THE SIZE OF ITS EQUIVALENT EDGE-BASED GRAPH. THE AVERAGE CALCULATION TIME OF RUNNING DIJKSTRA ON THE NODE-BASED GRAPH AND BELLMAN-FORD ON THE EDGE-BASED GRAPH ON 5 ORIGIN-DESTINATION PAIRS</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>TABLE II DESCRIPTION</head><label>II</label><figDesc>OF THE STATE VARIABLES OF CASE A AND CASE B OF THE GENERAL SCENARIOtravel time and consumed energy. The following scenario is considered:</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>TABLE III DESCRIPTION</head><label>III</label><figDesc>OF THE STATE VARIABLES OF CASE C AND CASE D OF THE GENERAL SCENARIO TABLE IV OVERVIEW OF THE RESULTS OF THE DISTANCE-, ENERGY-, AND TIME-OPTIMAL ROUTES FOR ALL FOUR CASES OF THE MAIN SCENARIO</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>TABLE V OVERVIEW</head><label>V</label><figDesc>OF THE AVERAGE RELATIVE DIFFERENCES IN DISTANCE, TRAVEL TIME, AND CONSUMED ENERGY BETWEEN THE ENERGY-OPTIMAL ROUTES COMPARED TO THE TIME-OPTIMAL ROUTES FOR A RANDOM SELECTION OF 100 ORIGIN-DESTINATION PAIRS</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>TABLE VI RESULT</head><label>VI</label><figDesc>OF THE MULTIPLE LINEAR REGRESSION FOR THE 2011 NISSAN LEAF TEST VEHICLE</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>TABLE VII RESULTS</head><label>VII</label><figDesc>OF THE PREDICTED AND MEASURED ENERGY CONSUMPTION VALUES FOR THE DISTANCE, ENERGY, AND TIME-OPTIMAL ROUTES FOR THE CHOSEN SCENARIO TABLE VIII THE RELATIVE DIFFERENCE IN TRAVEL DISTANCE, TRAVEL TIME AND CONSUMED ENERGY FOR THE DISTANCE-OPTIMAL AND ENERGY-OPTIMAL ROUTE COMPARED TO THE TIME-OPTIMAL ROUTE</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>DE CAUWER et al.: MODEL FOR RANGE ESTIMATION AND ENERGY-EFFICIENT ROUTING OF EVs</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</head><p>The authors would like to acknowledge: the <rs type="funder">Agency for Innovation by Science and Technology in Flanders (IWT)</rs> as the funder for the PhD grant of the first author; <rs type="person">Punch Powertrain</rs> for their contribution in providing data; and <rs type="person">Flanders Make</rs> for the support to our team.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Wouter Verbeke is currently an Assistant Professor in business informatics and data analytics with Vrije Universiteit Brussel. His research is situated in the field of data mining, predictive analytics, and complex network analysis, and is driven by real-life business problems that require a data-driven solution, including applications in marketing, finance, as well as transport and mobility. He teaches several courses in information systems and advanced modeling for decision making to business students, and has tutored several courses on credit risk modeling and customer analytics to business professionals.</p><p>Joeri Van Mierlo was a Visiting Professor with the Chalmers University of Technology, Sweden, in 2012. He is a Key Player in the electromobility scene. He is currently a Professor with Vrije Universiteit Brussels, one of the top universities in this field. He leads the MOBI Mobility, Logistics and Automotive Technology Research Centre, a multidisciplinary and growing team of 70 staff members. He is an expert in the field of electric and hybrid vehicles (batteries, power converters, and energy management simulations) as well as to the environmental and economical comparison of vehicles with different drive trains and fuels (LCA, TCO).</p><p>Thierry Coosemans received the Ph.D. degree in engineering sciences from Ghent University in 2006. After several years in the industry, he became a member of the MOBI Research Team, VUB, where he is currently the Electric and Hybrid Vehicle Team Leader. He is currently involved in the scientific support for the Green Energy Park Zellik, Flanders Make and had an active role in the Living Labs Electric Vehicles Flanders. On a European level, he was and is involved in the H2020 and FP7 projects SafeDrive, OPERA4FEV, SuperLIB, Smart EV-VC, Batteries20202, GO4SEM, FIVEVB, ELIPTIC, MOBILITY4EU, COLHD, FUTURE-RADAR, and GO4SEM, which he coordinated. His main research interests include electric and hybrid propulsion systems and the performances of electric-vehicle fleets under real-life conditions, including in a V2G perspective. He is an active member of EARPA and EGVIA.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Messagie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F.-S</forename><surname>Boureima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Coosemans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Macharis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Van Mierlo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A range-based vehicle life cycle assessment incorporating variability in the environmental assessment of different vehicle technologies and fuels</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1467" to="1482" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">European Alternative Fuels Observatory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Eafo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.eafo.eu/fuels-vehicles/bev" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018-01">Jan. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Realistic estimates of EV range based on extensive laboratory and field tests in Nordic climate conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Laurikko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Granström</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Haakana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/lpdocs/epic03/wrapper.htm?arnumber=6914919" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. World Electr. Vehicle Symp. Exhib. (EVS)</title>
		<meeting>World Electr. Vehicle Symp. Exhib. (EVS)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-11">Nov. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Plugto-wheel energy balance-Results of a two years experience behind the wheel of electric vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Vroey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">El</forename><surname>Baghdadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Van Mierlo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. World Electr. Vehicle Symp. Exhib</title>
		<meeting>World Electr. Vehicle Symp. Exhib</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electric vehicle use and energy consumption based on real-world electric vehicle fleet trip and charge data and its impact on existing EV research models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Cauwer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maarten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Heyvaert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Coosemans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Van Mierlo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Electr. Vehicle J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="436" to="446" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Electric vehicles the phenomenon of range anxiety</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nilsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>ELVIRE Project Rep</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Lindholmen Science Park, Gothenburg, Sweden</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Eco-routing navigation system based on multisource historical and real-time traffic information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Boriboonsomsin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Barth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/6236175/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Intell. Transp. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1694" to="1704" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-12">Dec. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energy consumption prediction for electric vehicles based on real-world data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Cauwer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Van Mierlo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Coosemans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/8/8/8573/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8573" to="8593" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A data-driven method for energy consumption prediction and energyefficient routing of electric vehicles in real-world conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Cauwer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Verbeke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Coosemans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Faid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Van Mierlo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/10/5/608" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">608</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017-05">May 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energy-efficient routing based on vehicular consumption predictions of a mesoscopic learning model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Masikos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Demestichas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Adamopoulou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Theologou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S1568494614006243" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Soft Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="114" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-03">Mar. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards route planning algorithms for electric vehicles with realistic constraints</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Baum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dibbelt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gemsa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00450-014-0287-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Sci.-Res. Develop</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="109" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electric vehicle shortest path problem with replenishment constraint</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Baouche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Trigui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Billot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">E El</forename><surname>Faouzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7297600/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Int. Conf. Connected Vehicles Expo (ICCVE)</title>
		<meeting>Int. Conf. Connected Vehicles Expo (ICCVE)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-11">Nov. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="514" to="515" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electric-vehicle navigation system based on power consumption</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-Y</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L.-D</forename><surname>Chou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-J</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7277117/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5930" to="5943" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-08">Aug. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electric vehicle green routing with possible en-route recharging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Baouche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Billot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Trigui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Faouzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Eddin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/6958136/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 17th Int. Conf. Intell. Transp. Syst. (ITSC)</title>
		<meeting>17th Int. Conf. Intell. Transp. Syst. (ITSC)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-10">Oct. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2787" to="2792" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electric vehicle routing problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Wolfson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S2352146516000089" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transp. Res. Procedia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="508" to="521" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-06">Jun. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal routing and scheduling of charge for electric vehicles: A case study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Guerra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Muñoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Quijano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Problems Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2017</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8509783</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017-11">Nov. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal routing with in-route charging of mobility-on-demand electric vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ammous</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Belakaria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sorour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Abdel-Rahim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Veh</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Veh</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-09">Sep. 2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On a routing problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bellman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quart. Appl. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="90" />
			<date type="published" when="1958">1958</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithm 97: Shortest path</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Floyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?doid=367766.368168" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commun. ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">345</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1962-06">Jun. 1962</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A note on two problems in connexion with graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Dijkstra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Numer. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="269" to="271" />
			<date type="published" when="1959-12">Dec. 1959</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heuristic shortest path algorithms for transportation applications: State of the art</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rilett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S030505480500122X" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Oper. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3324" to="3343" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-11">Nov. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Bellman-Ford approach to energy efficient routing of electric vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Abousleiman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Rawashdeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7165772/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Transp. Electrific. Conf. Expo (ITEC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Transp. Electrific. Conf. Expo (ITEC)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-06">Jun. 2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="4" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electric vehicle modelling and energy-efficient routing using particle swarm optimisation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Abousleiman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Rawashdeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1049/ietits.2014.0177</idno>
		<ptr target="http://digital-library.theiet.org/content/journals/10.1049/ietits.2014.0177" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IET Intell. Transport Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Machine-learning methodology for energy efficient routing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Masikos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Demestichas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Adamopoulou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Theologou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1049/iet-its.2013</idno>
		<idno>0006 IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON INTELLIGENT TRANSPORTATION SYSTEMS</idno>
		<ptr target="http://digital-library.theiet.org/content/journals/10.1049/iet-its.2013" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IET Intell. Transp. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="265" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-05">May 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The shortest path problem revisited: Optimal routing for electric vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Artmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Haselmayr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sachenbacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-642-16111-7_35</idno>
		<ptr target="http://link.springer.com/10.1007/978-3-642-16111-7_35" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="316" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dijkstra&apos;s algorithm revisited: The dynamic programming connexion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sniedovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Control Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="599" to="620" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An improved route planner-simulator with battery performance considerations for Electric Vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Herrando</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Nofuentes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rosado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">Á</forename><surname>Fernández</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/lpdocs/epic03/wrapper.htm?arnumber=6915048" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. World Electr. Vehicle Symp. Exhib. (EVS)</title>
		<meeting>World Electr. Vehicle Symp. Exhib. (EVS)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-11">Nov. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating the effect of a driver&apos;s behaviour on the range of a battery electric vehicle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Alvarez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>López</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>De</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Torre</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0954407014561483</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Inst. Mech. Eng. D, J. Automobile Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">229</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1379" to="1391" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Routing systems to extend the driving range of electric vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Neaimeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hübner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Blythe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IET Intell. Transp. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="327" to="336" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-09">Sep. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating energy consumption for routing algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kraschl-Hirschmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fellendorf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/6232127/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Intell. Veh. Symp</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Intell. Veh. Symp</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-06">Jun. 2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="258" to="263" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Driver-and situation-specific impact factors for the energy prediction of EVs based on crowd-sourced speed profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Grubwinkler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hirschvogel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lienkamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.scopus.com/inward/record" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Intell. Vehicles Symp</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Intell. Vehicles Symp</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-07">Jul. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1069" to="1076" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>eid=2-s2.0-84905396634&amp;partnerID=tZOtx3y1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A system for cloudbased deviation prediction of propulsion energy consumption for EVs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Grubwinkler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kugler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lienkamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Veh. Electron. Saf. (ICVES)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Veh. Electron. Saf. (ICVES)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-07">Jul. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="104" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mesoscopic forecasting of vehicular consumption using neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Masikos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Demestichas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Adamopoulou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Theologou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00500-014-1238-4</idno>
		<ptr target="http://link.springer.com/10.1007/s00500-014-1238-4" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soft Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="156" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-01">Jan. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient algorithms for shortest paths in sparse networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?doid=321992.321993" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energy-efficient routing strategies based on real-time data of a local traffic management center</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Liebscher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Krumnow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Krimmling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hanisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bäker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7223239/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Int. Conf. Models Technol</title>
		<meeting>Int. Conf. Models Technol</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-06">Jun. 2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="80" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data mining approach for range prediction of electric vehicle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ferreira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">D F</forename><surname>Monteiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Afonso</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Conf. Future Automot. Technol.-Focus Electromobility</title>
		<meeting>Conf. Future Automot. Technol.-Focus Electromobility</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-03">Mar. 2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic range prediction for an electric vehicle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ferreira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Monteiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Afonso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/lpdocs/epic03/wrapper.htm?arnumber=6914832" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. World Electr. Vehicle Symp. Exhib. (EVS)</title>
		<meeting>World Electr. Vehicle Symp. Exhib. (EVS)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-11">Nov. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electric vehicle assistant based in driver profile</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ferreira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">D F</forename><surname>Monteiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Afonso</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Electr. Hybrid Vehicles</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="335" to="349" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The route not taken: driver-centric estimation of electric vehicle range</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ondruska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Posner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.aaai.org/ocs/index.php/ICAPS/ICAPS14/paper/viewPaper/7899" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 24th Int. Conf. Automated Planning Scheduling (ICAPS)</title>
		<meeting>24th Int. Conf. Automated Planning Scheduling (ICAPS)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="413" to="420" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabilistic attainability maps: Efficiently predicting driver-specific electric vehicle range</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ondruska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Posner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/6856572/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Intell. Vehicles Symp</title>
		<meeting>Intell. Vehicles Symp</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-06">Jun. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1169" to="1174" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lithium iron phosphate based battery-Assessment of the aging parameters and development of cycle life model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Omar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.apenergy.2013.09.003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1575" to="1585" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-01">Jan. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combined state of charge and state of health estimation over lithium-ion battery cell cycle lifespan for electric vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jpowsour.2014.09.146</idno>
		<ptr target="http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0378775314015572" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Power Sour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">273</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="793" to="803" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-01">Jan. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Critical review of state of health estimation methods of Li-ion batteries for real applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Berecibar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Gandiaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Villarreal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Omar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Van Mierlo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Van Den Bossche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.rser.2015.11.042</idno>
		<ptr target="http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S1364032115013076" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Renew. Sustain. Energy Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="572" to="587" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-04">Apr. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Online estimation of internal resistance and open-circuit voltage of lithium-ion batteries in electric vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-H</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W.-Y</forename><surname>Sean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-C</forename><surname>Ke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jpowsour.2011.01.005</idno>
		<ptr target="http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0378775311000772" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Power Sour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">196</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3921" to="3932" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient routing in road networks with turn costs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Geisberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Vetter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Experimental Algorithms</title>
		<title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6630</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="111" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling costs of turns in route planning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Winter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1023/A:1020853410145</idno>
		<ptr target="http://link.springer.com/10.1023/A:1020853410145" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">GeoInformatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="345" to="361" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
