<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Discovery of associative patterns between workplace sound level and physiological wellbeing using wearable devices and empirical Bayes modeling</title>
				<funder ref="#_EBFpYAu">
					<orgName type="full">United States General Services Administration</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Karthik</forename><surname>Srinivasan</surname></persName>
							<email>karthiks@ku.edu</email>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-1608-6190</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Kansas</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lawrence</settlement>
									<region>KS</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Faiz</forename><surname>Currim</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Management Information Systems</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Eller College of Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Arizona</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tucson</settlement>
									<region>AZ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Casey</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lindberg</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">HKS Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Denver</settlement>
									<region>CO</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute on Place, Wellbeing, and Performance</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Arizona</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tucson</settlement>
									<region>AZ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Javad</forename><surname>Razjouyan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Innovations in Quality, Effectiveness and Safety (IQuESt)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Baylor College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Baylor College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Big Data Scientist Training Enhancement Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">VA Office of Research and Development</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Washington</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Brian</forename><surname>Gilligan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">District of Columbia</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Office of Federal High Performance Green Buildings</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hyoki</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="institution">U.S. General Services Administration</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Washington</settlement>
									<region>DC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kelli</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Canada</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">District of Columbia</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Office of Federal High Performance Green Buildings</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nicole</forename><surname>Goebel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="institution">Best Buy</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Matthias</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mehl</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff10">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aclima, Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>San Francisco</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Melissa</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lunden</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="institution">Best Buy</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Judith</forename><surname>Heerwagen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">District of Columbia</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Office of Federal High Performance Green Buildings</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bijan</forename><surname>Najafi</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-0320-8101</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff12">
								<orgName type="department">Michael E. DeBakey Department of Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Center to Stream HealthCare in Place (C2SHIP)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Baylor College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Esther</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sternberg</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute on Place, Wellbeing, and Performance</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Arizona</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tucson</settlement>
									<region>AZ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff13">
								<orgName type="department">Andrew Weil Center for Integrative Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Arizona</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tucson</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><surname>Kampschroer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">District of Columbia</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Office of Federal High Performance Green Buildings</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sudha</forename><surname>Ram</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Management Information Systems</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Eller College of Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Arizona</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tucson</settlement>
									<region>AZ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff11">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Arizona</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tucson</settlement>
									<region>AZ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff14">
								<orgName type="institution">Seoul National University Bundang Hospital</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Discovery of associative patterns between workplace sound level and physiological wellbeing using wearable devices and empirical Bayes modeling</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41746-022-00727-1</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 22 February 2022; Accepted: 29 November 2022;</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T23:05+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We conducted a field study using multiple wearable devices on 231 federal office workers to assess the impact of the indoor environment on individual wellbeing. Past research has established that the workplace environment is closely tied to an individual's wellbeing. Since sound is the most-reported environmental factor causing stress and discomfort, we focus on quantifying its association with physiological wellbeing. Physiological wellbeing is represented as a latent variable in an empirical Bayes model with heart rate variability measures-SDNN and normalized-HF as the observed outcomes and with exogenous factors including sound level as inputs. We find that an individual's physiological wellbeing is optimal when sound level in the workplace is at 50 dBA. At lower (&lt;50dBA) and higher (&gt;50dBA) amplitude ranges, a 10 dBA increase in sound level is related to a 5.4% increase and 1.9% decrease in physiological wellbeing respectively. Age, body-mass-index, high blood pressure, anxiety, and computer use intensive work are person-level factors contributing to heterogeneity in the sound-wellbeing association.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Wellbeing is the ability of the human body to cope with day-to-day stress. On average, four out of ten employees in organizations in the U.S. find their job and workplace stressful and that it adversely affects their health <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> . Past studies have shown that the workplace environment is closely tied to an office worker's wellbeing markers including mental state, productivity, stress, and longevity 2 . Among environmental stressors, sound level is considered a significant contributor to a variety of adverse health outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> . The World Health Organization (WHO) has identified elevated sound level or noise as the second leading environmental cause of health problems after air quality, causing serious health effects including stress, coronary heart disease, stroke, and disturbances in communication, rest and sleep <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> . While past research has focused on industrial settings and environmental noise (e.g., aircraft and traffic), research on the effect of more moderate levels of workplace sound on our wellbeing has been lacking due to technological and study design challenges <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> . We conduct a large-scale natural experiment in a real office environment using multiple wearables and develop explainable methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> to meticulously model the sound-wellbeing association. By gaining insights into the association between workplace sound level and physiological wellbeing, organizations can make informed policy changes that impact the longevity, morale, and productivity of its workers.</p><p>Our present study enquiring into the sound-wellbeing association is part of the U.S. General Services Administration (GSA)'s Wellbuilt-for-Wellbeing (WB2) program, an interdisciplinary research collaboration <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> to assess the impact of workplace environment on the wellbeing of white-collar office-workers. Study participants wore two sensors for three days while carrying out their day-to-day activities, a heart and physical activity monitor, and a personal environment quality sensor-based device. Preliminary data analysis using mixed-effects regression models show a significant curvilinear association between sound level and two heart rate variability (HRV) measures -SDNN and normalized-HF. We develop an empirical Bayes model to characterize physiological wellbeing as a function of SDNN and normalized-HF and to quantify its functional relationship with sound level and other predictors. Thereafter, we analyze the heterogeneity in the effect of sound level across study participants using a regularization-based method. We use predictive power assessment to benchmark our methods against alternative methods applicable for tackling the modeling challenges of analyzing multiple outcomes simultaneously and capturing heterogeneity in effects. We show that our proposed methods have better predictive performance than existing methods and are vital to the discovery of associative patterns between workplace sound level and physiological wellbeing. Our study can inform policies affecting the wellbeing of office workers worldwide and contributes to literature in explainable methods for analyzing wearables data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participant information</head><p>A total of 248 office workers expressed interest in participating in our study, representing approximately 12% of the workforce located in areas of the office buildings where recruitment took place. Pregnant women and those wearing pacemakers or insulin pumps were excluded. Participants taking medication known to affect cardiac activity were noted but not excluded. Due to scheduling problems, sickness and exclusionary criteria, 17 office workers did not participate, resulting in a total enrollment of 231 participants. Due to unexpected changes in work schedules, 8 of the 231 participants were only observed for two, rather than the full three days. The participant's average age was 44.15 (SD = 12.22), 49.78% female, with an average body mass index (BMI) of 27.60 (SD = 6.10).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dataset description</head><p>Data was collected from participants using an intake survey, a neck-worn environment sensing device, a chest-worn heart and physical activity monitor, and experience sampling mobile surveys recorded every two hours while participants were in the office premises. After pre-processing, our dataset contained 31,557 observations aggregated at five-minute intervals and processed approximately 200,000 min of wearable data streams from the 231 participants. More information about the data and variables can be found in the WB2 program website <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> and a previous study <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pilot analysis</head><p>We trained two independent multilevel regression models on our data with SDNN and normalized-HF as respective outcomes. Sound level was included as a fixed effect as well as a random effect in the models. We found that the fixed effect of workplace sound level was significant, both first order as well as second order, in the two models, i.e., β Sound;SDNN ¼ 0:1038 (p &lt; 0.0001, 95% CI = 0.0448-0.1627, Cohen's d = 0.23), β Sound 2 ;SDNN ¼ À0:0075 (p &lt; 0.0001, 95% CI = -0.0096--0.0054, Cohen's d = 0.45), β Sound;normalizedÀHF ¼ À0:0979 (p &lt; 0.0001, 95% CI = -0.1216 to -0.0742, Cohen's d = 0.53), and β Sound 2 ;normalizedÀHF ¼ 0:0013 (p = 0.015, 95% CI = 0.0003-0.0023, Cohen's d = 0.17). Furthermore, the quality of fit measured by Akaike Information Criteria (AIC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> for the curvilinear models were better than the corresponding models with only linear effects of sound level. This shows that sound level has a significant curvilinear effect on both physiological wellbeing measures. Secondly, we also found that including sound level as a random effect improves the quality of fit of the models, implying that the association between sound level and physiological wellbeing varies across individuals.</p><p>The curvilinear association can be further visualized through a smooth function of sound level as a non-parametric input in a Generalized additive mixed model (GAMM) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> with outcome as a univariate transformation <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> of SDNN and normalized-HF. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> shows the smooth function from GAMM for the sound-wellbeing association having an extremum around 50 dBA. The point estimate of 50 dBA as the optimal sound level was verified using an optimization procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Population-level sound-wellbeing association</head><p>We used an empirical hierarchical Bayes model to simultaneously model the association of sound level with HRV measures -SDNN and normalized-HF, which are common indicators of physiological wellbeing <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> . In the model, fixed effects were introduced for inputs: sound level, physical activity level, time of day, day of week, age group, BMI group and gender. Random effects were introduced for sound level and physical activity. We standardized the input (sound level) and outcomes (SDNN and normalized-HF) to remove sensitivity and challenges in posterior estimation convergence due to scale differences in units. The error variances were assigned a diffused half-Cauchy prior, and all other hyperparameters were assigned a diffused Normal prior <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> . The Hamiltonian Monte Carlo algorithm was used for sampling four parallel chains <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> . The R-hat statistic cutoff &lt;1.1 and zero divergence check were used as validation tests for posterior estimates of parameters and assessing quality of fit <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> .</p><p>The mean posterior distribution estimates and the 90% credible intervals (between 5th and 95th percentile of the posterior distribution) of the fixed effects coefficients of the empirical Bayes model is given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">1</ref>. The posterior estimates of the fixed effects indicates a significant association between sound level, time of day, day of week, physical activity level, age, BMI, and physiological wellbeing at workplace.</p><p>The fixed effect of sound level in the empirical Bayes model represents the sound-wellbeing association on entire study population after accounting for individual heterogeneity as random effects coefficients. The coefficient for sound level indicates a change in physiological wellbeing by a standard deviation (SD) related to a unit standard deviation (SD) change in sound level as both input and outcomes are standardized. Knowing that the SD of sound level in the dataset is 8.79 dBA and the coefficients in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">1</ref> are standardized, we can compute the unstandardized coefficient estimates to make the following inferences. For sound amplitudes lower than 50 dBA, a 10 dBA increase in sound level is related to a 5.4% (0.95% CI = 2.2-7.4%, Cohen's d = 0.11) increase in physiological wellbeing. For sound amplitudes higher than 50 dBA, a 10 dBA increase in sound level is related to decrease in physiological wellbeing by 1.9% (0.95% CI = 0.5-3.8%, Cohen's d = 0.09).</p><p>We compared the predictive performance of the empirical Bayes model with the following three alternative methods that can be used for simultaneously modeling two outcomes: (i) a classical univariate transformation method 11 , (ii) a univariate transformation method trained using a Bayesian approach, and (iii) a classical multilevel structural equation modeling method <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> . Models using the classical approach are trained using the R packages lavaan <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref> and nlme 20 in a 16 GB RAM, 2.7 GHz processor PC, whereas the empirical Bayes model was written and executed using Stan program through the RStan interface <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> , in a highperformance computer cluster with 28 nodes (192 GB RAM per node, Intel Haswell v3 28 core processors). The predictions from the models for SDNN and normalized-HF are compared with the (actual) measured values of the two measures to compute Root Mean Squared Error (RMSE) and Mean Absolute Percentage Error (MAPE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref>). Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref> shows that the model trained using the empirical Bayes model has the lowest RMSE and MAPE, indicating that our method is superior to other methods for simultaneous modeling of SDNN and normalized-HF.</p><p>Further, we compared the predictive performance of our Bayesian model with five popular machine learning models -Neural Network (NN), Classification And Regression Trees (CART) and Multivariate Adaptive Regression Splines (MARS), Random Forest (RF), and Gradient Boosting Machine (GBM) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> . We trained these models on training data with and without sound level as an input variable to assess if sound level is a good predictor of SDNN and normalized-HF. The results (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">3</ref>) show that our model outperforms NN, CART, MARS, and its performance is comparable to ensemble learning methods RF and GBM. Except for NN and CART, performance of all other models improves when sound level is included as in input. This shows that sound level is predictive of both the physiological wellbeing measures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Heterogeneity in sound-wellbeing association</head><p>The heterogeneity in sound-wellbeing association across individuals is accounted for by the random effects coefficients of sound level inputs in the empirical Bayes model. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> shows a caterpillar plot visualization of posterior estimates of random effects of sound level and their 60% credible interval (probability that sample from posteriori distribution falls in given range) in the empirical Bayes model. The vertical lines show the corresponding fixed effects coefficients of sound level. The spread of mean values of posterior estimates of the random effects indicates substantial heterogeneity in the sound-wellbeing association across study participants.</p><p>We developed a regularization-based feature-selection method to identify person-level variables contributing to heterogeneity. The person-level variables input into the model were neuroticism, noise sensitivity, age, BMI, presence of high blood pressure (BP), anxiety, sleep problems, computer-use intensive (CUI) worktype, managerial work, meeting intensive work, technical work, and  We considered two subsets of the data, one with sound levels &lt;50 dBA (low sound levels) and the other with sound levels ≥50 dBA (high sound levels), to fit two independent sets of models. By fitting two independent sets of models, we were able to make independent inferences about individual heterogeneity effects for each scenario. The coefficients for the regularized feature selection models are in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref>.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref> shows that Age, BMI, High BP, Anxiety, and CUI work-type are factors contributing to interpersonal variability in the soundwellbeing association. The blank cells show that coefficients of corresponding variables have been shrunk to zero by the corresponding feature selection method (i.e., lasso, adaptive lasso, elasticnet). For all the person-level variables not listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref>, all three feature selection methods shrunk the corresponding coefficients to zero.</p><p>To evaluate the performance of our method, we compared the predictive performance of the empirical Bayes model with three sets of input variables: (i) inputs including no person-level variables as moderators, (ii) inputs including all person-level variables as moderators, and (iii) inputs including person-level variables identified by varying-coefficients modeling method as moderators. Moderators were included as two-way interactions with fixed effect of sound level. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">5</ref> shows the prediction errors of all three models with respect to SDNN and normalized-HF. The model with specific person-level variables identified using our regularizationbased method has the smallest (best) RMSE and MAPE values.</p><p>High BP and Computer-use intensive (CUI) worktype were the person level factors that contributed most to the heterogeneity in sound-wellbeing association. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3(a),</ref><ref type="figure">(b</ref>) are plots showing the change in outcome due to the interaction effects of High BP and CUI worktype variables with the sound level fixed effect in the model. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>(a) shows that office-workers with high blood pressure are more negatively affected than participants with normal blood pressure. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>(b) shows that office-workers involved in CUI work have higher positive effects of sound levels on physiological wellbeing at amplitudes less than 50 dBA, but they have higher negative effects of sound levels on physiological wellbeing at amplitudes over 50 dBA compared to other office-workers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p>Workplaces can be designed to evoke positive emotions, stimulate creativity and collaboration, and intensify engagement <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> . On the other hand, unsuitable workplace environments have a potential to cause employee stress and health problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref> . Psychological  wellbeing consists of positive relationships with others, personal mastery, autonomy, a feeling of purpose and meaning in life, and personal growth and development <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref> . On the other hand, physiological wellbeing is associated with a dynamic, everadapting balance in the human physiological system conditioned by momentary demands <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref> . Sources of sounds in offices include other people's conversations, telephone-calls, and mechanical equipment. Favorable worker perception of a workplace is tightly coupled with ambient sound level exposure <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> . Consequently, sound level is an important workplace environmental factor that could impact employee health and wellbeing <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> . Sound amplitude has been shown to not only affect mood and productivity, but also physiological state of wellbeing <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> . For example, sound levels close to 70 dBA was observed to be optimal for creative cognition <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30</ref> , while levels above 85 dBA appeared detrimental to health <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31</ref> . In terms of sound-wellbeing association, some studies revealed a negative relationship between high sound levels (i.e., noise) and physiological wellbeing measures <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32</ref> , while other studies reported inconclusive results <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33</ref> . It was also shown that the sources and types of noise do not have a significant effect on physiological wellbeing <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35</ref> . Also, the effect of sound level on physiological outcomes, if present, were observed to be consistent for low as well as high sound frequencies <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36</ref> . The nature of the sound-wellbeing relationship has also been observed to be nonmonotonic <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37</ref> and instantaneous <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38</ref> . A table summarizing studies on sound-wellbeing association has been provided in Supplementary Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">1</ref>. Existing studies analyzing the sound-wellbeing association suffer from three major limitations. First, the majority of the studies in the past employed experiments with a limited set of treatments, small sample sizes, and limited number of control variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36</ref> . Consequently, the results from those studies cannot be easily generalized to the real office workplaces. Second, studies report results from multiple models corresponding to different measures of physiological wellbeing <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref> making it difficult to generalize insights and take actions. Third, the sound-wellbeing association has not been precisely quantified using a model <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37</ref> . Our present study seeks to address these limitations by conducting a large-scale natural experiment in an office environment using wearables and developing a set of statistical methods to model the sound-wellbeing association.</p><p>HRV is the variability between heart beats and is considered as a proxy measure for the physiological wellbeing of a person, i.e., the higher the variability, the higher the wellbeing <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39</ref> . It is a relatively less intrusive and more reliable measure than recording alternative physiological wellbeing signals such as salivary cortisol and skin conductance <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40</ref> . While many measures of HRV exist, each serves as a slightly different lens to view the body's physiological stress response <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41</ref> . The mean of standard deviation for all successive R-R intervals (SDNN) is a global index of HRV and reflects longer term circulation differences or the overall activity in the autonomic nervous system (ANS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42</ref> . The normalized high frequency component (normalized-HF) of HRV is the ratio between the absolute value of the High Frequency and the difference between Total Power and Very Low Frequency bands in the frequency domain power spectrum of heart rate that emphasizes changes in parasympathetic nervous system (PNS) regulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42</ref> . SDNN and normalized-HF are indicators of temporal stress and vagal/parasympathetic modulation respectively, and high values of SDNN and normalized-HF have consistently been found to indicate better health and wellbeing <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> . Since there is no single unified measure of physiological wellbeing identified in prior literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> , we take an empirical approach by defining physiological wellbeing as a latent (i.e., hidden) variable (θ) in a Bayesian model, that captures the variations of SDNN and normalized-HF simultaneously. Other measures of HRV such as RMSSD, SDRR, HF, LF, normalized-LF, LF/HF, Poincare plots <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39</ref> were examined but not considered as outcomes since their variance was either low in our data or their inclusion did not significantly improve the quality of fit of our model.</p><p>Existing digital health studies analyzing multiple outcomes fit an independent model for each outcome and report coefficients for each of the models separately <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37</ref> . Interpretation and communication of results from multiple models for decisionmaking can be challenging. A statistical model with a single set of coefficients for multiple outcomes, known as simultaneous modeling, is suitable for this purpose <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44</ref> . Simultaneous modeling differs from multivariate modeling, where coefficients are estimated for each outcome along with cross-correlation parameters <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46</ref> . For example, for three outcomes and three inputs, a simultaneous multiple regression model will contain three coefficients (excluding the intercept), whereas a multivariate regression modeling procedure will estimate nine coefficients (excluding the intercepts for outcomes) and corresponding covariance between the coefficients. One approach for simultaneous modeling involves carrying out a univariate transformation of multiple outcomes after accounting for heterogeneity in error variances <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47</ref> . In this univariate transformation method, even though different outcomes have different error variances in the model, the effects of input variables are assumed to be uniform across outcomes. Latent variable modeling is another approach for simultaneous modeling of multiple outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> . However, classical latent variable modeling approaches such as structural equation modeling requires individual items of the latent construct(s) to be theoretically related and to have construct validity <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49</ref> . Moreover, the estimation procedure becomes complex with longitudinal data such as that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51</ref> . Our proposes an empirical hierarchical Bayesian modeling method to overcome these challenges related to simultaneous modeling of multiple outcomes. While it is useful to understand the population-level effects of input(s) on outcome(s), insights regarding how and why effects differ across individuals can be valuable. The random effects in a multilevel model indicate the presence of individual heterogeneity in input effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50</ref> . A simple approach to identify factors contributing to individual heterogeneity is to introduce each factor in an interaction term with the input variable and test its significance. This is known as slopes-as-outcomes modeling <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50</ref> . However, this approach is sensitive to noise in longitudinal data and becomes cumbersome as the number of potential factors increases <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50</ref> such as in our case. Therefore, we propose the heterogeneity modeling method to identify person-level factors moderating the sound-wellbeing relationship.</p><p>Predictive modeling and explanatory modeling go hand in hand as the former predicts the future using existing data, focusing on questions of "What will be", while the latter illuminates hidden patterns and tells us about "What is" with respect to a phenomenon <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51</ref> . Both are important for creating value using data generated from digital sources such as wearables. As wearable technology-based applications increase in the future, the amount of available data to analyze will exponentially increase and warrant more advancements in explanatory modeling for meaningful pattern interpretations. While machine learning methods such as ensemble learners and neural networks can predict outcomes, their ability to explain the functional relationship(s) between input(s) and outcome(s) is limited <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> . Therefore, in this study, we develop new explainable methods for digital data generated from wearables and apply them to explore the soundwellbeing association. Our study allows researchers and practitioners to not only reconcile some of the differences in past work on the effect of sound on wellbeing, but to also separate out factors that should be controlled for in future work (e.g., blood pressure and nature of work). As wearable technology becomes widely available, personalized measurement is feasible and allows understanding the impact of our surroundings at an individual level. This can improve workplace design, personalized and targeted medicine, and also provide individuals with knowledge to make personal choices to maximize wellbeing. These in turn, improve our ability to function at our best in the workplace.</p><p>Our study has the following assumptions and limitations. We focused on modeling the effects of workplace sound levels on the physiological wellbeing of office workers, but we have not collected information about the sound types (e.g., conversation, mechanical background noise, etc.) and frequencies (e.g., low frequency, speech tones, high frequency, etc.) due to individual privacy concerns and sensor technology limitations. However, since prior research has shown that office sound type and frequency do not moderate the effects of sound level on physiological wellbeing outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35</ref> , we believe our findings will still hold when controlling for the type and frequency of ambient sounds. Secondly, we have aggregated the sound level and other level-1 variables at 5-min intervals to match the grain of short-term physiological wellbeing HRV measures -SDNN and normalized-HF following clinical guidelines <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53</ref> . Therefore, the lasting effects of spikes in sound level due to sudden events (e.g., shouting, objects falling or breaking, etc.) or sound level variance within a short timeframe have not been investigated, which can be examined in future research. Nevertheless, the effects of events repeated multiple times as well as background noises consistent across the five-minute interval are accounted for in our models. Next, we hypothesized that SDNN is capable of tracking temporal stress and normalized-HF is capable of tracking vagal/parasympathetic modulation of stress response and their combination is a proxy of physiological wellbeing as both these measures have been shown to be related to physical health and wellness <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> .</p><p>Possible HRVs' combination both on temporal and spectral domains are an ongoing effort within the research communities. Other combinations of physiological wellbeing indicators can be examined using our method for other scenarios as future research (e.g., LF and HF as physiological wellbeing indicators in a factory setting). Finally, data from each of the 231 participants was collected for a maximum of 3 days, thus our study does not make any inference related to long term effects of sound on physiological wellbeing. Future studies can examine data for a larger study population for a longer period to report long-term effects of workplace sound level on wellbeing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study design</head><p>The Wellbuilt-for-Wellbeing (WB2) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> consisted of a sixteen-month multi-phase field study funded by the U.S. General Services Administration to understand the impact of workplace environment on the wellbeing of white-collar office-workers. In the study, self-described healthy adult workers involved in a variety of officebased roles for the U.S. government were recruited across four federal office buildings across the country. Buildings were selected for their representation of common office workstation types across the U.S. General Services Administration's portfolio of office space which houses over one million employees. Staff in sections of each office building, from organizations with leadership approval, were offered the opportunity to participate. After giving written informed consent, participants completed an intake survey consisting of demographic questions. Participants wore two sensors for three days while carrying out their day-to-day activities, a heart and physical activity monitor, and a personal environment quality sensor-based device. The study also included experience sampling mobile surveys to collect individuals' perceived psychological responses at periodic intervals of one to two hours. Our study was approved by the University of Arizona Institutional Review Board.</p><p>The HRV measures-SDNN and normalized-HF were calculated using guidelines of the European Society of Cardiology and the North American Society of Pacing and Electrophysiology <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52</ref> . Physical activity levels were assessed in g (i.e., 1 unit of gravitational force) from the EcgMove3's triaxial accelerometer sensor <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54</ref> . Sound levels were aggregated at 5-min intervals to be integrated with physiological wellbeing measures SDNN and normalized-HF, assuming no lagged effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38</ref> . Only observations with both outcome values present were considered in the analysis. Observations with outcome values above the 99.5th percentile were discarded. Age and BMI were discretized to five and four levels, respectively, for ease of interpretation. Data of participants with less than one hour of recorded data were excluded from analysis. Missing values in input variables were imputed using mean values. Apart from sound level as the input variable and SDNN and normalized-HF as the outcomes, person-level variables (e.g., age group, BMI group, gender, etc.), temporal indicators (time of day, day of the week), and physical activity levels were included as covariates in the statistical models. Observations from day 1 and day 2 of participation of all participants were considered as the training dataset, and day 3 observations were used as the holdout sample (i.e., test dataset) for evaluating the predictive performance of models. The input variables and personlevel variables were collected based on prior literature on environment-wellbeing modeling <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56</ref> and domain knowledge. Post stepwise feature selection, only significant inputs were considered in the final model and reported. Summary statistics of the input variables is given in Supplementary Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Empirical Bayes model</head><p>As mentioned earlier, there is no single theoretical construct that unifies multiple measures of physical wellbeing though there are numerous independent indicators of physiological wellbeing <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57</ref> SDNN and normalized-HF as HRV measures are differently related to the sympathetic and parasympathetic activities of the autonomous nervous system (ANS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42</ref> . Instead of analyzing their associations with sound-level separately using two models, an empirical Bayes model makes it possible to combine the two outcomes into a single latent construct of physiological wellbeing which can then be modeled as a function of sound level and other exogenous variables. Following Merkle and Wang (2018) <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">58</ref> , we define a Bayesian model with a latent variable combining multiple outcomes Y ¼ fy 1 ; y 2 ; ; y h ; ; y H g as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">y h jθ i ; γ h ; λ h ; σ h $ N μ h ; σ 2 h À Á<label>(1)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">μ h ¼ γ h þ X m k¼1 λ hk θ k ; where θ k $ N m ð0; ΦÞ In Eq. (1), N μ h ; σ 2 h À Á</formula><p>is a normal distribution with a noninformative prior for variance σ 2 h , γ h is the intercept for outcome h, and θ ik is the k th latent factor value. Φ and λ hk are other hyperparameters to be estimated. In our study, we set m ¼ 1 as we have physiological wellbeing as the single latent variable that combines two outcomes SDNN (y 1 ) and normalized-HF (y 2 ). We express the above equation at an observation-level for longitudinal wearables data by adding subscripts i and j corresponding to the i th observation for the j th individual as shown below:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">y ijh jθ ij ; γ h ; λ h ; σ h $ N μ h ; σ 2 h À Á<label>(2)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">μ h ¼ γ h þ λ h θ ij ; where θ ij $ Nð0; ΦÞ</formula><p>The latent variable θ ij is expressed as an outcome of a mixedeffects model as shown below:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">θ ij ¼ β 0 þ γ 0j þ X K k¼1 β k x kij þ X M m¼1 γ mj z mij þ ξ ij<label>(3)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">γ 0j $ N 0; σ 2 γ 0 ; γ mj $ N 0; σ 2 γ m ; ξ ij $ Nð0; σ 2 θ Þ</formula><p>Upon centering the outcomes and dropping the outcome intercept parameter γ h , we can combine the within-individual level error variances (i.e., σ 2 ih and σ 2 θ ). The resultant model is represented as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">y hij À y hij ¼ β 0 þ γ 0j þ X K k¼1 β k x kij þ X M m¼1 γ mj z mij ! Á λ h þ ϵ ðhÞ ij<label>(4)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">γ 0j $ N 0; σ 2 γ 0 ; γ mj $ N 0; σ 2 γ m ; ϵ ðhÞ ij $ Nð0; σ 2 h Þ</formula><p>The empirical Bayes model shown in Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">4</ref>) can be used for modeling the sound-wellbeing association. The factor loadings, λ h , automatically assign different weights to each outcome (i.e., λ 1 and λ 2 ). Alternatively, a latent variable model can be developed using the classical (i.e., frequentist) approach as well, known as a hierarchical Structural Equation Model (SEM). Software such as Mplus, LISREL, EQS, lavaan, OpenMx can fit a two-level SEM with random intercepts <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">59</ref> . In the two-level SEM model, each outcome y ijh is split into a within and a between component as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">y ij ¼ y ij À y j À Á þ y j ¼ y W þ y B<label>(5)</label></formula><p>In Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">5</ref>), both the within and between covariance components are treated as orthogonal and additive latent variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60</ref> . The maximum likelihood estimate for parameters is derived by minimizing the overall loglikelihood which is the sum of likelihood of data from J groups. The latent variable model using the classical approach offers less flexibility than its Bayesian counterpart, for it solicits more data-related assumptions and its basic formulation does not account for random effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60</ref> . Detailed explanations on multilevel modeling using classical statistical modeling and Hierarchical Bayesian modeling is included in the following sub-section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Multilevel model inference using classical and Bayesian approaches</head><p>Multilevel or hierarchical levels of grouped data are a commonly occurring phenomenon <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> . For example, in organizational studies, information about firms as well as workers are available such that there exists a hierarchical structured data of individual workers nested within multiple firms. Multilevel models (also called as hierarchical linear models, random coefficients models, mixedeffects models) are statistical models with parameters that capture variability across multiple levels of data.</p><p>In the classical or frequentist approach, multilevel models can be considered as an extension of an ordinary least squares (OLS) regression model used to analyze variance in the outcome variables when the predictor variables are at varying hierarchical levels. A two-level hierarchical linear model can be mathematically expressed as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">Level 1 : Y ij ¼ β 0j þ X K k¼1 β kj V kij þ r ij<label>(6)</label></formula><p>Level 2 :</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">β kj ¼ γ k0 þ X M m¼1 γ km W mj þ u kj<label>(7)</label></formula><p>In Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">6</ref>), Y ij is the outcome, β kj are the level-1 coefficients, V kij are level-1 input variables, r ij are level-1 residuals, γ km are level-2 coefficients, W mj are level-2 input variables and u kj are level-2 variables for i th observation of j th individual for k 2 Z K and m 2 Z M . The assumptions for the model are as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">E r ij À Á ¼ 0; var r ij À Á ¼ σ 2 ; Eðu kj Þ ¼ 0; cov u kj ; r ij À Á ¼ 08i; j; k; u 11 u kj ! ¼ T<label>(8)</label></formula><p>In Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">8</ref>), T is the level-2 variance covariance component that model the inter-relationship between level-2 errors. Combining Eqs. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">1</ref>) and (2), we can represent hierarchical linear models as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">y ij ¼ β 0 þ γ 0j þ X K k¼1 β k x kij þ X M m¼1 γ mj z mij þ ϵ ij<label>(9)</label></formula><p>In Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_12">9</ref>), β ¼ β 0 ; β 1 ; ; β K f g are fixed effects coefficients, γ ¼ γ 0j ; γ 1j ;</p><p>; γ Mj È É are random-effects coefficients for J groups j 2 Z J , and ϵ ij is the sum of fixed-effects error and random-effects error components. In matrix notation, the above equation is represented as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">Y ¼ α þ Xβ þ Zγ þ ϵ<label>(10)</label></formula><p>In Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">10</ref>), X is a matrix of fixed effects and Z is a matrix of random effects. Conditional to the above assumptions, the parameters in the model can be estimation by maximizing the likelihood function y as shown below:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">y $ Nðα þ Xβ; σ 2 I þ Z 0 TZÞ<label>(11)</label></formula><p>The significance of the fixed effects and random effects are tested using Wald test, Likelihood Ratio Test, F-test, parametric bootstrap or MCMC methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> . Model fit can be compared using AIC, deviance and R-squared approximations <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> .</p><p>Bayesians, on the other in-hand describe their beliefs about the unknows in a hierarchical linear model before observing data with prior distributions and the following likelihood function:</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">y $ Nðα þ Xβ Zb; σ 2 IÞ<label>(12)</label></formula><p>A single level regression disregards between-group heterogeneity is called model with complete pooling and can yield parameter estimates that are wrong if there is between-group heterogeneity. On the other hand, regression models for each group of the level-2 data independently are called modeling with no pooling and result in imprecise parameter estimates, for they ignore common variance across groups. Hierarchical linear models are considered as a subset of Hierarchical Bayesian models that are models with partial pooling <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> . Parameters are allowed to vary by group at lower levels of the hierarchy while estimating common parameters at higher levels. Note that the level-2 and higher effects are not part of the error variance as in the classical/frequentist approach but modeled as parameters themselves (also called varying coefficients). The varying parameters have hyper-parameters that are estimated based on level-2 and higher order grouping in the data. The estimated posterior distribution of parameters for a hierarchical linear model with normally distributed error and identity link function has the following form:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">p α; β; γ; σ Y ; σ γ Y; X; Z; U j À Á /<label>(13)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_17">Y J j¼1 Y nj i¼1 N Yjβ 0 þ γ 0j þ βX þ γ j Z; σ 2 Y À Á Y J j¼1 N γ 0j ; γ j α 0 þ αU; σ 2 γ</formula><p>MCMC estimation approaches such as Metropolis Hastings, Gibbs Sampling, and Hamiltonian Monte Carlo families of methods are used to estimate the posterior probability given the prior distribution of all parameters and likelihood of given data <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> . Comparison of implementations and general purpose software packages for classical and Bayesian multilevel modeling is done in West and Galecki <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">63</ref> , Mai and Zhang <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">64</ref> , respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Heterogeneity modeling</head><p>As discussed earlier, insights regarding how and why effects differ across individuals can be valuable. We develop a two-step method to find person-level variables explaining the heterogeneity in sound-wellbeing association across individuals. In the first step, we fit an empirical Bayes model with all input variables with random effects coefficients having normal priors with non-zero means. Person-level variables (e.g., age, BMI, gender, etc.) are not included in the model since their value is constant for each individual (i.e., the random effects coefficients for person-level variables have a distribution with zero variance). The empirical Bayes model for step 1 is shown below:</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">y hij ¼ γ 0j þ X M m¼1 γ mj z mij ! Á λ h þ ϵ ðhÞ ij (14) γ 0j $ N μ γ 0 ; σ 2 γ 0 ; γ mj $ N μ γ m ; σ 2 γ m ; m 2 Z M ; ϵ ðhÞ ij $ Nð0; σ 2 h Þ</formula><p>The mean values μ γ 0 and μ γ m in Eq. ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>) are analogous to the model intercept and the corresponding fixed effects coefficients of the m th variable in the empirical Bayesian model shown in Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">4</ref>). In the second step, we formulate the random effects coefficients of sound level as an outcome of a linear model with person-level variables as the input variables as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">γ rj ¼ β 0 þ X P p¼1 β p x pj þ ϵ j ; ϵ j $ Nð0; σ 2 r Þ<label>(15)</label></formula><p>In Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_19">15</ref>), Γ r ¼ γ r1 ; γ r2 ; ; γ rJ f gare the random effects coefficients for the input in the empirical Bayes model from step 1, fx 1Á ; x 2Á ; ; x PÁ g are P person-level variables, and ϵ j is a normally distributed residual error varying across J individuals.</p><p>The problem of identifying person-level factors contributing to individual heterogeneity effects is presented as a variable selection problem in our linear model. Traditional stepwise feature selection methods for regression models are ridden with challenges such as sensitivity to changes in data and low external validity <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> . These challenges are particularly relevant in our problem, where there are multiple person-level variables that could be factors contributing to heterogeneity in the sound effects on wellbeing across individuals. Therefore, we choose three regularization-based methods, lasso, elasticnet, and adaptive lasso <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> to determine significant inputs in the linear model shown in Eq. (15). The lasso uses an l-1 penalty to shrink coefficients of insignificant inputs to zero <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> . The elasticnet and adaptive lasso methods are improvements over the lasso feature selection method and account for correlated features and possess oracle properties. The hyperparameters for the penalty functions of these models are determined using a grid-search procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> . The initial adaptive weights are set as inverse of the absolute values of coefficients of a vanilla regression as proposed by Zou <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">61</ref> . The person-level variables that have non-zero coefficients in all three regularized models are chosen as the final set of factors contributing to individual heterogeneity effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52</ref> .</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref> Explanatory modeling framework consisting of an empirical Bayes model and heterogeneity modeling method for identifying population-level and interpersonal sound-wellbeing association.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> shows an illustration of our overall explanatory modeling consisting of two novel methods for capturing population-level and interpersonal associations between sound levels and physiological wellbeing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experiments</head><p>To validate the presence of optimal sound level for physiological wellbeing at 50 dBA and the influence of blood pressure and work involving intensive computer use in moderating the soundwellbeing relationship, we conducted post-hoc comparison of wellbeing across different stratified populations for three sound level conditions: sound level less than 45 dBA, sound level between 45 dBA and 55 dBA, and sound level greater than 55 dBA. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">6</ref> shows the post-hoc comparisons of mean wellbeing score adjusted for random effects for the three sound level ranges for different sub-populations in our data. In support of our finding that 50 dBA is an optimal sound level at workplace, we find that sound level range 45-55 dBA has the highest mean adjusted wellbeing score across the complete population, when compared to low and high sound level ranges. However, for individuals with high blood pressure, the lowest sound level range (i.e., sound level &lt; = 45 dBA) is optimal, which is different from individuals with normal blood pressure. Finally, individuals with computer use intensive work have a lower mean adjusted wellbeing score for low as well as high sound level ranges (i.e., sound level &lt;=45 dBA and sound level &gt;55 dBA), when compared to individuals with regular computer use at work. In other words, this group benefits more (than the average individual) from both (a) an increase in sound level at the lower range and (b) a decrease in sound level in the higher range. These post-analysis group comparison findings validate the findings based on our proposed methods. Mean value of wellbeing is adjusted for random effects using estimated marginal means procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">62</ref> .</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1 Component smooth function of sound level in GAMM for physiological wellbeing as a bivariate function of SDNN and normalized-HF. The solid line indicates how physiological wellbeing varies as a function of sound level, while the dashed lines are confidence intervals.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,321.39,59.30,228.02,159.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2 Caterpillar plots of posterior estimates of varying coefficients of sound level and their 60% credible interval in the empirical Bayes model. The vertical dashed line is the fixed effect coefficient while the horizontal blue lines indicate the random effects of sound level on physiological wellbeing across participants. a Caterpillar plot for sound level &lt;50 dBA, and b the plot for sound level &gt;=50 dBA.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,140.37,59.30,324.00,105.51" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3 Interaction plots of the top two person-level variables moderating the sound-wellbeing association. a Green solid line: Normal blood pressure. Red dashed line: High blood pressure. b Green solid line: Computer use intensive work. Red dashed line: Not computer use intensive work.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,130.90,59.30,324.00,148.82" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="8,140.37,535.86,324.00,174.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Comparing predictive performance of different simultaneous</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">modeling methods.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model</cell><cell></cell><cell>SDNN</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Normalized-HF</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>RMSE</cell><cell>MAPE</cell><cell>RMSE</cell><cell>MAPE</cell></row><row><cell>Classical</cell><cell>Univariate</cell><cell>20.12</cell><cell>34.13</cell><cell>10.98</cell><cell>54.36</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Latent</cell><cell>23.71</cell><cell>44.78</cell><cell>11.22</cell><cell>57.10</cell></row><row><cell>Bayesian</cell><cell>Univariate</cell><cell>21.50</cell><cell>37.39</cell><cell>10.04</cell><cell>52.64</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Latent</cell><cell>17.06</cell><cell>26.56</cell><cell>8.90</cell><cell>44.36</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Comparing predictive performance of machine learning models with and without sound as an input.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Model</cell><cell></cell><cell>SDNN</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Normalized-HF</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>RMSE</cell><cell>MAPE</cell><cell>RMSE</cell><cell>MAPE</cell></row><row><cell>Without Sound</cell><cell>NN</cell><cell>23.77</cell><cell>45.00</cell><cell>12.56</cell><cell>84.20</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>CART</cell><cell>20.58</cell><cell>36.11</cell><cell>11.60</cell><cell>75.43</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>MARS</cell><cell>19.85</cell><cell>35.04</cell><cell>11.04</cell><cell>73.57</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>RF</cell><cell>17.08</cell><cell>28.78</cell><cell>9.77</cell><cell>57.35</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>GBM</cell><cell>17.98</cell><cell>26.55</cell><cell>10.30</cell><cell>51.98</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Our model</cell><cell>17.50</cell><cell>27.80</cell><cell>9.42</cell><cell>50.27</cell></row><row><cell>With Sound</cell><cell>NN</cell><cell>23.77</cell><cell>45.00</cell><cell>12.56</cell><cell>84.20</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>CART</cell><cell>20.58</cell><cell>36.11</cell><cell>11.60</cell><cell>75.43</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>MARS</cell><cell>19.21</cell><cell>33.97</cell><cell>10.83</cell><cell>72.64</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>RF</cell><cell>16.96</cell><cell>28.48</cell><cell>9.58</cell><cell>56.79</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>GBM</cell><cell>17.05</cell><cell>26.07</cell><cell>9.24</cell><cell>51.35</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Our model</cell><cell>17.06</cell><cell>26.56</cell><cell>8.90</cell><cell>44.36</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fixed effects of empirical Bayes model.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Coefficients</cell></row></table><note><p>average sound exposure. All person-level variables except age, BMI and average sound exposure were based on a survey completed by the participants at the beginning of the study.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Coefficients of person-level input variables contributing to heterogeneity.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Predictors</cell><cell></cell><cell>Below 50 dBA</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Above 50 dBA</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Lasso</cell><cell>Elastic-net</cell><cell>Adaptive lasso</cell><cell>Lasso</cell><cell>Elastic-net</cell><cell>Adaptive lasso</cell></row><row><cell>Age (years)</cell><cell>Below 30</cell><cell>baseline</cell><cell>baseline</cell><cell>baseline</cell><cell>baseline</cell><cell>baseline</cell><cell>baseline</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>30-40</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.0011</cell><cell>-0.0076</cell><cell>-0.0002</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>40-50</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>50-60</cell><cell>-0.0026</cell><cell>-0.0141</cell><cell>-0.0003</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Above 60</cell><cell>-0.0047</cell><cell>-0.0224</cell><cell>-0.0007</cell><cell>0.0084</cell><cell>0.0160</cell><cell>0.0010</cell></row><row><cell>BMI (kg/m²)</cell><cell>Below 25</cell><cell>baseline</cell><cell>baseline</cell><cell>baseline</cell><cell>baseline</cell><cell>baseline</cell><cell>baseline</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>25-30</cell><cell>-0.0009</cell><cell>-0.0044</cell><cell>-0.0001</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.0004</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>30-35</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.0001</cell><cell>-0.0096</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Above 35</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.0076</cell><cell>0.0123</cell><cell>0.0011</cell></row><row><cell>HighBP</cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell>-0.0133</cell><cell>-0.0764</cell><cell>-0.0021</cell><cell>-0.0207</cell><cell>-0.0203</cell><cell>-0.0042</cell></row><row><cell>Anxiety</cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell>-0.0015</cell><cell>-0.0013</cell><cell>-0.0002</cell><cell>0.0060</cell><cell>0.0148</cell><cell>0.0007</cell></row><row><cell>Computer use intensive work</cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell>0.0187</cell><cell>0.0881</cell><cell>0.0036</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Performance comparison of models with different set of person-level factors as moderators.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Moderators of sound level in empirical</cell><cell>SDNN</cell><cell>Normalized-</cell></row><row><cell>Bayes model</cell><cell></cell><cell>HF</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">RMSE MAPE RMSE MAPE</cell></row><row><cell>No moderators</cell><cell cols="2">17.06 26.56 8.90 44.36</cell></row><row><cell>All person-level variables</cell><cell cols="2">19.66 31.38 11.13 47.73</cell></row><row><cell>Person-level variables identified in</cell><cell cols="2">16.65 24.97 8.41 43.23</cell></row><row><cell>our study</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Post-hoc group comparisons across sound level ranges.Repeated measures MANOVA shows significant differences across sound level ranges for each sub-population except high BP. † †</figDesc><table><row><cell>Sub-population</cell><cell cols="2">Mean adjusted wellbeing score  † †</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Sound</cell><cell>45 dBA &lt; Sound</cell><cell>Sound</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>&lt;=45 dBA</cell><cell>&lt;=55 dBA</cell><cell>&gt;55 dBA</cell></row><row><cell>Complete dataset</cell><cell>0.0054</cell><cell>0.0174</cell><cell>-0.0203</cell></row><row><cell>High BP  †</cell><cell>-0.1395</cell><cell>-0.1600</cell><cell>-0.1884</cell></row><row><cell>Normal BP</cell><cell>0.0120</cell><cell>0.0302</cell><cell>-0.0081</cell></row><row><cell>Intensive</cell><cell>-0.0407</cell><cell>-0.0186</cell><cell>-0.0985</cell></row><row><cell>computer use</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Regular</cell><cell>0.0229</cell><cell>0.0333</cell><cell>0.0144</cell></row><row><cell>computer use</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>†</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>npj Digital Medicine (2023) 5Published in partnership with Seoul National University Bundang Hospital 1234567890():,;</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>Published in partnership with Seoul National University Bundang Hospital npj Digital Medicine (2023) 5</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_2"><p>npj Digital Medicine (2023) 5Published in partnership with Seoul National University Bundang Hospital</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>This study was funded by a <rs type="funder">United States General Services Administration</rs> contract # <rs type="grantNumber">GS-00-H-14-AA-C-0094</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_EBFpYAu">
					<idno type="grant-number">GS-00-H-14-AA-C-0094</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DATA AVAILABILITY</head><p>The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CODE AVAILABILITY</head><p>The code used for analysis in this study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reporting summary</head><p>Further information on research design is available in the Nature Research Reporting Summary linked to this article.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</head><p>K.S. developed the empirical Bayes model and heterogeneity modeling method and performed data analyses. F.C. and S.R. advised on the development of the empirical Bayes model and heterogeneity modeling method, and presentation of analysis results. J.R., H.L., and B.J. consolidated heart and physical activity data. N.G., and M.M.L. consolidated environment sensor data. S.R., C.M.L., B.G., M.R.M., J.H., E.M.S., and K.K. conceived of and designed the study. K.S., F.C., and S.R., drafted the manuscript. All authors contributed to interpretations of the results. All authors have read and approved the manuscript. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>COMPETING INTERESTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ADDITIONAL INFORMATION Supplementary information</head><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-022-00727-1">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-022-00727-1</ref>.</p><p>Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to Karthik Srinivasan.</p><p>Reprints and permission information is available at <ref type="url" target="http://www.nature.com/reprints">http://www.nature.com/ reprints</ref> Publisher's note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Harvard School of Public Health. The workplace and health</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The human factors of sustainable building design: Post occupancy evaluation of the Philip Merrill Environmental Center</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heerwagen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zagreus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Indoor Environmental Quality</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Environmental noise induces the release of stress hormones and inflammatory signaling molecules leading to oxidative stress and vascular dysfunction-Signatures of the internal exposome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Daiber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/biof.1506</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/biof.1506" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BioFactors</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Who</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Noise</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.euro.who.int/en/health-topics/environment-and-health/noise" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Best practices for analyzing large-scale health data from wearables and smartphone apps</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hicks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Digital Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ideal algorithms in healthcare: Explainable, dynamic, precise, autonomous, fair, and reproducible</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Loftus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLOS Digital Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gsa</forename><surname>Wellbuilt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wellbeing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.gsa.gov/governmentwide-initiatives/federal-highperformance-green-buildings/resource-library/health/wellbuilt-for-wellbeing" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of office workstation type on physical activity and stress</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lindberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Occup. Environ. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="689" to="695" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model selection and Akaike&apos;s Information Criterion (AIC): The general theory and its analytical extensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bozdogan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3450370</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stable and efficient multiple smoothing parameter estimation for generalized additive models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Stat. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="673" to="686" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing multiple outcomes in clinical research using multivariate multilevel models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Baldwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Imel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Braithwaite</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Atkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Consulting Clin. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="920" to="930" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Algorithms for minimization without derivatives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Brent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Dover publications</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Physical activity and heart rate variability in older adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Soares-Miranda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2100" to="2110" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heart rate variability as a marker of healthy ageing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P H</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Beilharz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Vollmer-Conna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cvejic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">275</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="103" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heart rate variability with photoplethysmography in 8 million individuals: a cross-sectional study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Natarajan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pantelopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Emir-Farinas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Natarajan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Lancet Digital Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="650" to="e657" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian Data Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Bayesian Data Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stan: A probabilistic programming language</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Carpenter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stat. Softw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principles and practice of structural equation modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Guilford</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">156</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">lavaan: An R Package for Structural Equation Modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Rosseel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stat. Softw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pinheiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Debroy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sarkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nlme: Linear and Nonlinear Mixed Effects Models. R package version 3 Preprint at</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hastie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tibshirani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Friedman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Elements of Statistical Learning: Data Mining, Inference, and Prediction</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Managing by design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gruber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>De Leon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acad. Manag. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Organizational change and employee stress</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Dahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Manag. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="240" to="256" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Happiness is everything, or is it? Explorations on the meaning of psychological well-being</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ryff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Personal. Soc. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1069" to="1081" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Boron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Boulpaep</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Medical Physiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The work environment pilot: An experiment to determine the optimal office design for a technology company</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pitchforth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Nelson-White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Van Den Helder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Oosting</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">232943</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring soundscaping options for the cognitive environment in an open-plan office</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Flynn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jackman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Building Acoustics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of noise on self-rated job satisfaction and health in open-plan offices: a structural equation modelling approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Jeon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ergonomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="222" to="234" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open-plan office noise: Cognitive performance and restoration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jahncke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hygge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Halin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dimberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Environ. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="373" to="382" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is noise always bad? exploring the effects of ambient noise on creative cognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mehta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cheema</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Consum. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="784" to="799" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Occupational Noise Exposure. Occupational Safety and Health Administration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Osha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.osha.gov/noise" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cardiovascular and stress responses to short-term noise exposures-A panel study in healthy males</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cherniack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Laden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cavallari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">150</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="391" to="397" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of noise on arousal in a speech communication setting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Cvijanović</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kechichian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Janse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kohlrausch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Speech Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of floor impact noise on psychophysiological responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Build. Environ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="181" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effects of different noise types on heart rate variability in men</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Yonsei Med. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="243" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Study of the physiological and mental health effects caused by exposure to lowfrequency noise in a simulated control room</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Abbasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Motamedzade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Aliabadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Golmohammadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tapak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Building Acoustics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Individual daytime noise exposure during routine activities and heart rate variability in adults: a repeated measures study. Environ. Health Perspect</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Kraus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="607" to="612" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Regularization Approach for Identifying Cumulative Lagged Effects in Smart Health Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Srinivasan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 7th International Conference on Digital Health</title>
		<meeting>the 7th International Conference on Digital Health</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="103" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Passive detection of COVID-19 with wearable sensors and explainable machine learning algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gadaleta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Digital Med. 2021</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prolonged non-metabolic heart rate variability reduction as a physiological marker of psychological stress in daily life</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Verkuil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Brosschot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Tollenaar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Thayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Behav. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="704" to="714" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heart rate variability today</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Xhyheri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Manfrini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mazzolini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Pizzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bugiardini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog. Cardiovascular Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="331" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An overview of heart rate variability metrics and norms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Shaffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ginsberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A repeated measures approach for simultaneous modeling of multiple neurobehavioral outcomes in newborns exposed to cocaine in utero</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Das</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Poole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">159</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="891" to="899" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Applied Multivariate Statistics for the Social Sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pituch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simultaneous inference for multilevel linear mixed models-with an application to a large-scale school meal study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pilmann Laursen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Trab Damsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. R. Stat. Soc.: Ser. C. (Appl. Stat.)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="311" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Healthcare predictive analytics for risk profiling in chronic care: A Bayesian multitask learning approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-K</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>MIS Q. 41</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="473" to="495" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Extending the linear model with R: generalized linear, mixed effects and nonparametric regression models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Faraway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Muthén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sem</forename><surname>Beyond</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">General latent variable modeling</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="117" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Assumptions in structural equation modeling. Handbook of structural equation modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Guilford</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Raudenbush</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bryk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Hierarchical Linear Models: Applications and Data Analysis Methods</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Sage</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">To explain or to predict?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Shmueli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="310" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heart rate variability: Standards of measurement, physiological interpretation, and clinical use</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Malik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1043" to="1065" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heart rate variability metrics for fine-grained stress level assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Pereira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Almeida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P S</forename><surname>Cunha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aguiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Methods Prog. Biomedicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wearable sensors and the assessment of frailty among vulnerable older adults: an observational cohort study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Razjouyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sensors</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1336</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of the physical work environment on physiological measures of stress</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Thayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Cardiovascular Prev. Rehab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="439" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Environmental perceptions and health before and after relocation to a green building</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Macnaughton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Build. Environ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="138" to="144" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Wearable sensor derived decompensation index for continuous remote monitoring of COVID-19 diagnosed patients. npj Dig</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Richards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">155</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian latent variable models for the analysis of experimental psychology data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Merkle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychonomic Bull. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="256" to="270" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Generalized latent variable modeling: Multilevel, longitudinal, and structural equation models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Skrondal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rabe-Hesketh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Heck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">An Introduction to Multilevel Modeling Techniques: MLM and SEM Approaches using Mplus</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The adaptive lasso and its oracle properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Stat. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1418" to="1429" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Population marginal means in the linear model: An alternative to least squares means</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Searle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Speed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Milliken</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="216" to="221" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Overview of Current Software Procedures for Fitting Linear Mixed Models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Galecki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="274" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Software Packages for Bayesian Multilevel Modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Mai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Struct Equ Modeling</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="650" to="658" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
