<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The common drivers of children and young people&apos;s health and wellbeing across 13 local government areas: a systems view</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Siobhan</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>O'halloran</surname></persName>
							<email>s.ohalloran@deakin.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Global Centre for Preventive Health and Nutrition</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Health and Social Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Faculty of Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Institute for Health Transformation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Deakin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3220</postCode>
									<settlement>Geelong</settlement>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Joshua</forename><surname>Hayward</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Global Centre for Preventive Health and Nutrition</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Health and Social Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Faculty of Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Institute for Health Transformation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Deakin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3220</postCode>
									<settlement>Geelong</settlement>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Melissa</forename><forename type="middle">Valdivia</forename><surname>Cabrera</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Intelligent Systems Research and Innovation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Deakin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>75 Pigdons Rd Waurn Ponds</addrLine>
									<postCode>3216</postCode>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tiana</forename><surname>Felmingham</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Global Centre for Preventive Health and Nutrition</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Health and Social Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Faculty of Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Institute for Health Transformation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Deakin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3220</postCode>
									<settlement>Geelong</settlement>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Penny</forename><surname>Fraser</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Global Centre for Preventive Health and Nutrition</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Health and Social Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Faculty of Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Institute for Health Transformation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Deakin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3220</postCode>
									<settlement>Geelong</settlement>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Cindy</forename><surname>Needham</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Global Centre for Preventive Health and Nutrition</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Health and Social Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Faculty of Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Institute for Health Transformation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Deakin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3220</postCode>
									<settlement>Geelong</settlement>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jaimie</forename><surname>Poorter</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Global Centre for Preventive Health and Nutrition</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Health and Social Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Faculty of Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Institute for Health Transformation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Deakin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3220</postCode>
									<settlement>Geelong</settlement>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Doug</forename><surname>Creighton</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Intelligent Systems Research and Innovation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Deakin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>75 Pigdons Rd Waurn Ponds</addrLine>
									<postCode>3216</postCode>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Johnstone</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Intelligent Systems Research and Innovation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Deakin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>75 Pigdons Rd Waurn Ponds</addrLine>
									<postCode>3216</postCode>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Melanie</forename><surname>Nichols</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Global Centre for Preventive Health and Nutrition</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Health and Social Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Faculty of Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Institute for Health Transformation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Deakin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3220</postCode>
									<settlement>Geelong</settlement>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Steven</forename><surname>Allender</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Global Centre for Preventive Health and Nutrition</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Health and Social Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Faculty of Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Institute for Health Transformation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Deakin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3220</postCode>
									<settlement>Geelong</settlement>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The common drivers of children and young people&apos;s health and wellbeing across 13 local government areas: a systems view</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12889-024-18354-8</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 30 November 2023 / Accepted: 13 March 2024</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T19:35+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Social network analysis</term>
					<term>Local government</term>
					<term>Systems thinking</term>
					<term>Community</term>
					<term>Health</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Background System dynamics approaches, including group model building (GMB) and causal loop diagrams (CLDs), can be used to document complex public health problems from a community perspective. This paper aims to apply Social Network Analysis (SNA) methods to combine multiple CLDs created by local communities into a summary CLD, to identify common drivers of the health and wellbeing of children and young people.</p><p>Methods Thirteen community CLDs regarding children and young people health and wellbeing were merged into one diagram involving three steps: (1) combining variable names; (2) CLD merging, where multiple CLDs were combined into one CLD with a set of unique variables and connections; (3) paring, where the Decision-Making Trial and Evaluation Laboratory (DEMATEL) method was used to generate a cut-point to reduce the number of variables and connections and to rank the overall importance of each variable in the merged CLD.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>Combining variable names resulted in 290 variables across the 13 CLDS. A total of 1,042 causal links were identified in the merged CLD. The DEMATEL analysis of the merged CLD identified 23 common variables with a net importance between 1.0 and 4.5 R + C values and 57 causal links. The variables with the highest net importance were 'mental health' and 'social connection &amp; support' classified as high net receivers of influence within the system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>Combining large CLDs into a simple diagram represents a generalisable model of the drivers of complex health problems.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p>Lifestyle related chronic diseases such as obesity, diabetes, cancer and cardiovascular disease are influenced by multiple modifiable risk factors. The complex range and interactions of these risks and their determinants make it difficult to understand and address layers of cause and effect <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Methods and practises from system dynamics are becoming more commonly used to understand and address the complexity of health issues <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref>. Applicable methods include group model building (GMB), where stakeholders are engaged to capture complexity in graphic representations like causal loop diagrams (CLDs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. CLDs are comprised of variables that are dynamic causes or effects of the complex problem, and arrows that represent hypothesised causal relationships between the variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. The orientation of each relationship is either positive, where variables change in the same direction, or negative, where variables change in the opposite direction (known as positive or negative polarity) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Both methods are increasingly being applied in population health research as they provide tangible, participatory methods to explore systems thinking concepts such as non-linearity, unintended consequences and time delays in systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. The growing focus on using these techniques in co-design of community-based prevention approaches is based on the hypothesis that enhanced understanding of these systems by community stakeholders is required to ensure good design and successful implementation <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</p><p>Promising examples of using co-design as an approach to address complexity in public health issues are beginning to emerge in the literature. One recent study demonstrated GMB processes with collaborative, cross-sectoral participant groups, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> while others have described whole-of-community systems-based prevention initiatives within Australia <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> and internationally <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr">13]</ref>. As examples of these projects continue to grow, attention has turned to understanding and comparing how multiple communities attempt to recognise the commonalities of chronic disease risk (e.g., poor nutrition, lack of physical activity). Determining these commonalities may be valuable for identifying key population-level drivers and potential solutions. CLDs have been used with large numbers of locally based government and community members and are a unique representation of the stakeholder perspectives in a community. More recently multiple CLDs have been generated across a number of communities within the same project, targeting the same outcome <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. An example is the VicHealth Local Government Partnership working in multiple municipalities, building CLDs independently from each other as part of public health planning; and the findings, from each CLD providing additional insight for other municipalities that were not revealed during their independent GMB workshops <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Another example is the 'Confronting obesity: Co-creating policy with youth' (CO-CREATE), which used a complex systems framework to explore the drivers of adolescent obesity and potential policy actions across five European countries <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[14]</ref>. Testing methods to combine and compare CLDs developed by multiple stakeholders is an important next step in the field to understand the factors that influence complex health problems at the population level.</p><p>Social Network Analysis (SNA), which involves investigating social structure and how it influences health through the use of networks and graph theory, has previously been used as a computational tool to analyse and combine CLDs <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[15]</ref>. One recent example was the use of SNA to converge 13 CLDs, from within one community, into a summary diagram designed to represent the common perspectives of the entire participant group <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[16]</ref>. The combined diagram was rated favourably by participants for its representation of their perspective, connection to other perspectives and insights and usefulness as a communication tool <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[16]</ref>. In this paper we extend these SNA methods to explore the utility for larger CLDs developed with multiple stakeholders and assess whether they can identify commonalities between different communities considering children and young people's health and wellbeing from a systems perspective.</p><p>The aims of this paper were:</p><p>1. To apply SNA methods to combine the multiple CLDs created by local communities into one merged CLD containing the full set of unique variables and connections from each of the community diagrams. 2. To identify and describe the similar variables representing key drivers of the health and wellbeing of children and young people from the merged CLD.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study context</head><p>The data used in this analysis were collected in GMB workshops facilitated by local government-based prevention workforce (referred to hereon as "councils") as part of the VicHealth Local Government Partnership (VLGP), implemented across the state of Victoria, Australia. The VLGP has been described in detail in a prior publication <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Briefly, the partnership provides support to councils to deliver evidence-based actions to improve children and young people's health and wellbeing. Eight evidenceinformed health promotion modules were designed to provide a series of practical 'how-to guides' for policy, program development/delivery and practice change <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">17]</ref>. One of the VLGP modules, Connecting the Dots (CtD), consisted of structured training and ongoing support for councils to deliver GMB sessions as a mechanism to incorporate systems thinking and community co-design principles into local government prevention practise <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">17]</ref>. The resultant CLDs, created with community input from across each Local Government Authority, were used to inform relevant council health and wellbeing planning and action delivery until 2025.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GMB workshops and CLD creation</head><p>The GMB workshops and CLD development has been described elsewhere <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">17]</ref>.</p><p>Thirteen councils completed the CtD module, and subsequently facilitated GMB workshops. The GMB process undertaken by councils was designed to be delivered across three interactive sessions, each 2-3 h in duration, although on occasions there were minor modifications to the process due to COVID19 restrictions and time constraints <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[18]</ref>. The GMB workshops engaged a range of participants including councils' stakeholders and partnering organisations, and local community members (including children and young people) to develop a CLD that visually represented the interrelationships between the locally relevant drivers of the health and wellbeing of children and/or young people from the community's perspective <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. The systems mapping software program called Systems Thinking in Community Knowledge Exchange (STICKE) was used to build the CLDs during the workshops <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</p><p>The workshops were structured around three GMB scripts: "Graphs over time, " (assists in framing a problem, to identify variables and gather input that influences the topic for the workshop process. It is used at the beginning of a workshop <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[18]</ref>); "Connection Circles, " (used after graphs over time, to identify connections between variables and additional variables not identified in graphs over time <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[18]</ref>); "Action Ideas" (used to identify and prioritize actions after a CLD has been developed <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[18]</ref>) which were adapted from the Scriptapedia database <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[19]</ref>. Each script was chosen to guide the facilitation of the workshop process and build the CLDs. These scripts have been applied in previous prevention trials <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>. In the final workshop, council teams facilitated an action codesign process, using the CLD as a reference in order to identify intervention targets and corresponding community-led actions for consideration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis</head><p>Developing commonality between the 13 CLDs comprised three steps; (1) Variable name combination (2) CLD merging, and (3) Paring (i.e., reducing the size of CLDs).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Variable name combination</head><p>All variable names across the 13 CLDs were reviewed and collapsed into unique combined variable names to ensure consistency in language across the data set <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[20]</ref>. Combination of variable names by commonality from the 13 CLDs was independently performed by two reviewers (SO'H and JH). Where variables clearly referred to the same construct but were named differently, a combined variable name that adequately reflected the construct was selected as a replacement. For example, the variables 'consumption of healthy food' , 'eating healthy food' , and 'healthy eating' were combined to 'healthy food consumption' . In other instances, variables referring to different, but related constructs could be collapsed into a combined variable name. For example, the variable names, 'substance abuse' , 'alcohol and drug use' 'tobacco' , were collapsed together into a new variable called 'alcohol and other substance use' . Following independent review and combination of the variable names, differences in the variables identified for combination, and final names selected, were reviewed and discussed between the two researchers, and a final decision was reached by consensus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CLD merging</head><p>Following variable combination, the 13 constituent CLDs were combined into a single CLD that contained the full set of unique variables and connections from the constituent diagrams. This was achieved by converting each diagram into an adjacency matrix, wherein relationships between each pair of diagram variables could be represented as a 0 (no connection), 1 (connection, positive relationship), or -1 (connection, negative relationship).</p><p>The matrices were then merged, with each unique variable name appearing only once, and connections appearing in more than one constituent diagram represented by increasing the integer used to signify a connection (i.e., where a positive connection existed in two constituent diagrams, the relevant cell in the merged matrix contained a "2", etc.). Conflicting links were identified before the merge and the original maps were adjusted to resolve the conflicts by the map builders. Once all constituent CLD's had been combined into the merged matrix, the matrix was converted back into a CLD by using STICKE.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Paring</head><p>Finally, two cut points were used to reduce the merged CLD from the full set of variables names and connections present across all constituent CLD's, to a summary diagram describing the key commonality between the 13 CLD's.</p><p>Decision making trial and evaluation laboratory (DEMATEL) methods were used to generate a cut point that could be used to reduce the number of variables in the merged CLD <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[16]</ref>. DEMATEL is an analytical technique from SNA, used to rank components within networks by their influence, as determined by their position within the overall network structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[16]</ref>. The approach provides ranking metrics on the overall "importance" of each variable within a network, which can be conceptualised as the sum of its score as a net influencer and/or net receiver of influence <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[21]</ref>. Inspection of a scatterplot of the overall importance of diagram variables against their net "influencer" or "receiver of influence" score can identify clustering within the data, which was used in this case to generate and apply a cut-point to reduce the number of variables and connections in the merged CLD. This resulted in a sub-set of variables from the merged CLD, representing the most significant drivers of the health and wellbeing of children and young people, according to the aggregated perspective of participants from across the 13 constituent communities.</p><p>Notably, use of the DEMATEL approach necessitated the "loss" of connection polarity as the analysis requires all values relating to connections to be positive (i.e., when one variable increases, it causes an increase in another). However, the final diagram was reviewed, and polarity reintroduced with reference to the original data.</p><p>Lastly -after the final set of variables had been identified, a cut-point was applied to reduce the total number of connections in the diagram. While DEMATEL provides diagram structure it does not provide insight into where a cut point should be applied and so the research team set a cut point. To further reduce connections between variables, connections that appeared in only one of the original constituent diagrams (i.e., had a value of 1 or -1) were removed. This approach was intended to remove connections that had been identified by one community but were not confirmed as being relevant to other communities by appearing in at least one other diagram.</p><p>Of note, we did not observe a significant change to our final model when the cut-point was modified by 5,10 and 15% during a sensitivity analysis. For example, our initial cut-off point was of net importance 1.0. Increasing it by 5% excluded the variable "sleep" (net importance 1.02) and decreasing it by 5% did not include more variables. An increase of 10% excluded the variables "sleep" and "alcohol and other substance use" (net importance 1.09) without the inclusion of more variables. A 15% increase and decease excluded "sleep" and "alcohol and other substance use" and included "cultural awareness &amp; safety" (net importance 0.89) and "availability of healthy food" (net importance 0.86) respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>Step 1 resulted in 290 unique variables across the 13 CLD's. The collapsing of the 13 diagrams into one merged diagram (step 2) resulted in a total of 1,042 causal links. In step 3, DEMATEL analysis identified 23 variables with a net importance between 1.0 and 4.5 R + C (267 variables were excluded resulting in the final 23).The cut-point was selected based on the clear boundary between the two nodes on the scatter plot. DEMATEL provides an importance ranking and a balance is required to keep the most important variables, without resulting in an excessive number where the map becomes too visually complex.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> shows the variables on a scatter plot, classified on the horizontal axis according to the total net importance (an output of the DEMATEL analysis, unrelated to the frequency of the variable appearing in the original maps) and on the vertical axis classified as positive if the variables were an overall network influencer (C) or as negative if the variable was a receiver of overall network influence (R).</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> shows the 23 most important variables according to the DEMATEL R + C value across the 13 CLD's. The variables with the highest net importance were 'mental health' and 'social connection &amp; support' classified as high net receivers of influence within the system. The highest net influencers of the network were 'access to transport' and 'financial security' .</p><p>The variables were also analysed according to their frequency of occurrence across the 13 constituent diagrams. 'Social connection &amp; support' and 'sport and recreation' had the highest frequency, appearing in 12 out of the 13 CLDs, while 'social isolation' appeared fewest times in 3. Using the DEMATEL cut point, the merged diagram retained 155 causal connections. Application of the 2-CLD cut point to connections resulted in a final set of 57 causal connections. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> shows the final CLD with the most important variables and their connections representing the most important drivers of the health and wellbeing of children and young people.</p><p>Data including a list of the excluded variables can be obtained by contacting the corresponding author.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>This study presents a method for collating causal loop diagrams across communities where comparable group model building processes have been employed to understand the common drivers of children and young people's health and wellbeing in 13 communities. The method for combining these 'system maps' was able to condense a very large number of variables and connections to a reduced number of related terms and mathematically derive a summary model of the most critical variables common across all communities. The ability to objectively collate and describe data from GMBs across 13 communities represents an important step to creating generic models of the key commonalities of complex health issues such as causes of chronic disease, that includes stakeholder's perspectives.</p><p>As the use of system methods in co-creation continues to grow, new analytic techniques such as those presented here will be needed to gather full insight across multiple communities. There are few previous examples, a notable exception being the work of Brennan and colleagues which used similar steps to reduce the size of the variable list across CLDs about healthy eating, active living and child obesity from 49 different communities <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[22]</ref>. The resulting CLD was larger than that presented here, including 227 unique variables coded into five thematic areas. Their findings about key determinants (healthy eating policies and environments, active living policies and environments, health and health behaviors, partnership and community capacity, and social determinants) parallel several of our findings that key drivers include social connection and support, supporting environments and access to services.</p><p>A characteristic of systems methods when used to address complex public health issues is the focus on understanding multiple relations of cause and effect and going beyond single health determinants to understand the interrelationships between drivers of health outcomes. This is at odds with many public health programs and policies which focus on single (or a small number of ) health issues or determinants or siloed programs that from outcome-specific priority-setting and funding mechanisms.</p><p>The combination of CLDs, to generate a CLD that represents the core issues that are common across communities provides powerful data to inform decision makers, (such as at state and regional levels of governance), about key determinants and assist in identifying high impact policy responses. An example of the importance of capturing this complexity is a school food study in New Zealand <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[23]</ref> which interviewed school lunch providers to identify potential intervention points to improve the programme and build a representative CLD. In this study twelve semi-structure interviews were analysed to create CLDs which were collated into one CLD which shows that providing healthy school lunches is driven by interactions between government nutrition policy, supply chain issues, ingredient supplies, school support and student demand <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[23]</ref>. This insight into what prima facie would appear a simple problem (how do we provide healthy school food) shows the importance of understanding this complexity to optimise potential interventions. While this example has a relatively narrow focus on food in schools in one district, the recent Lancet Commission on Obesity demonstrated how this complexity impacts planetary health on a global scale <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[24]</ref>.</p><p>Notably the outcomes of any given GMB process are influenced significantly by the size and composition of the participant group, who act as the source of data that the GMB process aims to synthesise into a qualitative CLD <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[25]</ref>. issue that is unique to a community may also be the most important driver for that community.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Implications for practice</head><p>Currently, the quality of community-based prevention is a function of the capacity and capabilities of the prevention workforce, the breadth and strength of their partnerships and stakeholder networks, and their access to evidence-based prevention practices. There is a high rate of turnover, in an environment where capacity is difficult to build and sustain, and partnerships and networks are continually disrupted by organisational churn. In this context, there is a need for tools and practise that maximise the insights available to communities systems-based approaches, especially where these approaches are embedded in larger initiatives that may be able to provide the framework for contextualisation and comparison. Merged maps could be used as a tool for communicating with policy makers to apply findings to a more general understanding of a complex problem providing new directions for the practice of prevention and population health more broadly. In another way, a merged map could be used as a 'backbone' or a starting point for future community GMBs to give them a head start in identifying harmful system drivers.</p><p>There are several tensions here, for example the move to system science reflects the acceptances that the complexity of the drivers of chronic disease are multiple and dynamic and engaging with this complexity is critical to a successful response. Conversely, capturing every variable and every relationship between these variables creates a 'detail complexity' that becomes overwhelming in the scale and breadth of the information presented. A tension arises from the recognition that co-creation of chronic disease prevention is powerful because it engages communities to understand and address their unique characteristics that impact the success of generic health promotion interventions. The work presented here provides direction to a generalisable model of the causes of disease, which removes the heterogeneity between communities from the design of intervention. One potential solution is a distributed model of system thinking, whereby a health promotion workforce is trained in system thinking, able to use these techniques at a local level with local data, and share lessons back to a central repository towards a generalised model not just of cause and effect, as presented here, but also for tried and tested solutions operating across all facets of the systems as mapped.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Future research</head><p>In Australia, as elsewhere in the world, government health prevention strategies are often in action or under development over a 3-4-year cycle. If the average time to translate research into practice is 17 years, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[26]</ref> then research is currently of limited use to practice. Better methods are needed to translate and test lessons about prevention of chronic disease in a timely manner into standard practice, whether this is at a local, state, or national scale. The ability to co-create logic models is an important step towards a generic model of community wellbeing. Such models provide the potential for universal standards of practice so that multiple communities can understand the drivers of ill health in their context and access the best evidence and practice globally to optimise their response.</p><p>Sensitivity analysis around thresholds and the evaluation of the utility and/or acceptability of merged maps could be a potential focus for further research. Future work could also explore the possibility to iterate from merged maps over time to determine new community data to better understand whether this could improve them. Another research effort would be to begin with individual CLDs that had weighted edges i.e., the communities could nominate a value for the importance (or strength) of the connection. This would help to overcome the issue that all connections are treated equally, and only weighted by the number of communities that identified it. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Strengths</head><p>A of this merging approach is a simpler model that represents something that is more manageable, and generalisable than the complex original diagram, one which could be used as a valuable tool for advocacy and communication with community stakeholders.</p><p>The methods described here have the potential to be scaled up to represent even larger representations of key variables within CLDs examining complex problems.</p><p>As individual GMB processes can only be representative of the participants who contributed to the development of a given CLD, so too these results can only be representative of the constituent CLDs which were analysed to produce the final diagram. This diagram is not presented as a generic model of children and young people's health and wellbeing cause in Victoria or generalisable beyond the 13 local governments included in this study. Rather, the diagram presented in this study demonstrates the utility of a process designed to centralise and share insights between communities using GMB and comparable participatory systems mapping processes in a shared problem space. Notably communities need to be relatively similar for this approach to synthesis to be meaningful.</p><p>During the variable name combination and CLD merging process subjective decisions were made which could not be entirely mitigated despite the inclusion of an independent review.</p><p>There is no established convention for determining a cut-point, 'saturation' , or the minimum number of CLDs that are needed in order to be able to generate a useful merged version that adequately represents the core issues in a system. A possible way to address this would be to set a higher R + C value threshold for inclusion when merging a larger number of maps.</p><p>There is likely a relationship between the number of CLDs and the 'right' threshold to use, for example with a low number of CLDs important detail may be lost compared to merging with a greater number of CLDs (i.e., 100). If a greater number of CLDs are included a higher threshold could be reasonably set. Even so, some detail is lost in the merging process regardless of the number of CLDs included as some maps are more valuable than others. There is also a risk that an important variable only identified in one community is missed if the threshold of importance is &gt; 1 in the identified community. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>The use system science techniques to optimise efforts for health prevention is increasingly being used to inform government policy <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> and community-based prevention practice.</p><p>The opportunity to translate local contextually relevant data, combine common drivers and interrelationships across multiple communities. It is vital that researchers continue to tailor efforts to support these approaches in ways that advance the field globally.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1 DEMATEL analysis indicating 23 variable cut point ranging from a net importance between 1.0 and 4.5 R + C value</figDesc><graphic coords="5,56.69,84.00,481.92,301.44" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2 Final merged CLD after applying DEMATEL and causal connection cut points. Positive causal relationships are denoted by a solid arrow and negative causal relationships by a dashed arrow. Variables marked in black were duplicated in several places on the CLD to minimize arrow crossover and improve readability</figDesc><graphic coords="7,56.69,84.00,481.92,282.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Variable rankings by DEMATEL score, and constituent CLD frequency</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">DEMATEL</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell cols="2">R + C R-C</cell><cell>Frequency*</cell></row><row><cell>1 Mental health</cell><cell>4.44</cell><cell cols="2">-2.47 10</cell></row><row><cell>2 Social connection &amp; support</cell><cell>3.5</cell><cell cols="2">-1.09 12</cell></row><row><cell>3 Access to services and resources</cell><cell>2.6</cell><cell>0.19</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>4 Sport and recreation</cell><cell>2.54</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell></row><row><cell>5 Financial security</cell><cell>1.99</cell><cell>0.97</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>6 Education and training</cell><cell>1.99</cell><cell>0.09</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>7 School attendance</cell><cell>1.98</cell><cell>-0.1</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">8 Work &amp; employment opportunities 1.75</cell><cell cols="2">-0.25 9</cell></row><row><cell>9 Access to transport</cell><cell>1.65</cell><cell>1.18</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>10 Physical activity</cell><cell>1.6</cell><cell cols="2">-0.26 6</cell></row><row><cell>11 Healthy role modelling</cell><cell>1.57</cell><cell>0.54</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>12 Supportive family environment</cell><cell>1.53</cell><cell>0.22</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>13 Healthy food consumption</cell><cell>1.48</cell><cell cols="2">-0.75 7</cell></row><row><cell>14 Physical health and fitness</cell><cell>1.44</cell><cell cols="2">-1.04 4</cell></row><row><cell>15 Family violence</cell><cell>1.42</cell><cell>0.25</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>16 Social media</cell><cell>1.41</cell><cell>0.8</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>17 Bullying</cell><cell>1.35</cell><cell>0.06</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>18 Access to housing</cell><cell>1.28</cell><cell>0.18</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>19 Social isolation</cell><cell>1.2</cell><cell cols="2">-0.47 3</cell></row><row><cell>20 Activities and events</cell><cell>1.18</cell><cell cols="2">-0.06 9</cell></row><row><cell>21 Safe and inclusive environments</cell><cell>1.15</cell><cell cols="2">-0.06 5</cell></row><row><cell>22 Alcohol and other substance use</cell><cell>1.09</cell><cell cols="2">-0.39 5</cell></row><row><cell>23 Sleep</cell><cell>1.02</cell><cell cols="2">-0.18 6</cell></row></table><note><p>*Frequency is the occurrence in the original maps</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			
			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>Not applicable.</p></div>
			</div>


			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data availability</head><p>The datasets used and/or analysed during the current study are not publicly available. Reasonable data access request can be to the corresponding author via email s.ohalloran@deakin.edu.au.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Abbreviations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Declarations Ethics approval and consent to participate</head><p>Written informed consent was obtained from all subjects. Ethical approval was granted by Deakin University for the completion of this research project. The approval reference for this study is HEAG-H 121_2022.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Consent for publication</head><p>Not applicable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Competing interests</head><p>The authors declare that they no competing interests.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Publisher's Note</head><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Implications of the foresight obesity system map for solutions to childhood obesity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Finegood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Merth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rutter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obes (Silver Spring)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">Suppl 1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systems science: a good investment for the public&apos;s health</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mabry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kaplan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Educ Behav</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Systems practice. How to act in a climate-change world</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hovmand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Group Model Building and Community-based System Dynamics process</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY; New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Community Based System dynamics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantifying a systems Map: Network Analysis of a childhood obesity Causal Loop Diagram</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mcglashan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Johnstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Creighton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>De La Haye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Allender</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>0165459. 10.1371</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A community based systems Diagram of obesity causes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Allender</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Owen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kuhlberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Nagorcka-Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Whelan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">129683</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Success of community based systems dynamics in prevention interventions: a systematic review of the literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Felmingham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Backholder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hoban</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Nagorcka-Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Allender</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<publisher>Front Public Health</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1103834</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">System Dynamics Approaches and Collective Action for Community Health: an integrative review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cilenti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Issel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wells</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Link</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Community Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3/4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="527" to="545" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whole of Systems Trial of Prevention Strategies for Childhood Obesity: WHO STOPS childhood obesity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Allender</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Millar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hovmand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moodie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Carter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Environ Res Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building capacity for the use of systems science to support local government public health planning: a case study of the VicHealth Local Government Partnership</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>O'halloran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hayward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Strugnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Felmingham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Poorter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kilpatrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">68190</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<pubPlace>Victoria, Australia</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reflexive evidence and Systems interventions to Prevention obesity and non-communicable disease (RESPOND): protocol and baseline outcomes for a stepped-wedge cluster-randomised prevention trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Whelan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hayward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nichols</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Orellana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">57187</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developing the logic framework underpinning a whole-systems approach to childhood overweight and obesity prevention: Amsterdam Healthy Weight Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sawyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Den Hertog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Verhoeff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Busch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Stronks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obes Sci Pract</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="591" to="605" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying the views of adolescents in five European countries on the drivers of obesity using group model building</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Savona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Macauley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aguiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/eurpub/ckaa251</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/eurpub/ckaa251" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="391" to="396" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Corbie-Smith G. Integrating systems science and community-based participatory research to achieve health equity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Frerichs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dave</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="222" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tools and analytic techniques to synthesise community knowledge in CBPR using computer-mediated participatory system modelling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hayward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Morton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Johnstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Creighton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Allender</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NPJ Digit Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">22</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Local Government Partnerships. 24</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Vichealth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.vichealth.vic.gov.au/programs-and-projects/local-government" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022-01">January 2022. March 23, 2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systems thinking in local government: intervention design and adaption in a community based study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Felmingham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>'halloran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Poorter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rhook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Needham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hayward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fraser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kilpatrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Leahy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Allender</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Res Policy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Under review</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Scriptapedia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Scriptapedia" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023-05">09/05/2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using thematic anlaysis in psychology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Clarke</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Qual Res Pyschol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DEMATEL technique: a systematic review of the state-of-the-art literature on methodologies and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Si</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>You</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math Probl Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2018</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="33" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systems thinking in 49 communities related to healthy eating, active living, and childhood obesity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Brennan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sabounchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kemner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hovmand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Public Health Manag Pract</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">Suppl 3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chote</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rees</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Swinburn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mckelvie-Sebileau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Glassey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tipene-Leach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Systems Mapping of the New Zealand free and Healthy School Lunch Programme: perspectives from lunch providers</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The global syndemic of obesity, Undernutrition and Climate Chamge: the Lancet Commission report</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Swinburn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Kraak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Allender</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">393</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="791" to="846" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Group model building effectiveness: a review of assessment studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rouwette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vennix</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mullekom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst Dynamics Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The answer is years, what is the question: understanding time lags in translational research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wooding</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Zs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Grant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J R Soc Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="510" to="520" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
