<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of the Work Environment, Organizational Commitment and Organizational Citizenship Behavior on Employee Performance and Motivation as Intervening (Studies in the Matahari Department Store Tbk. Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya, Indonesia)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2019-12-31">December 31 st 2019</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hj</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Enny Widyaningrum</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Lecturer of Faculty of Economics and Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Lecturer of Faculty of Economics and Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Bhayangkara Surabaya</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of PGRI</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Adi Buana Surabaya</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mochammad</forename><forename type="middle">Munir</forename><surname>Rachman</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Lecturer of Faculty of Economics and Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Lecturer of Faculty of Economics and Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Bhayangkara Surabaya</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of PGRI</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Adi Buana Surabaya</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of the Work Environment, Organizational Commitment and Organizational Citizenship Behavior on Employee Performance and Motivation as Intervening (Studies in the Matahari Department Store Tbk. Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya, Indonesia)</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2019-12-31">December 31 st 2019</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.7176/EJBM/11-35-08</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T00:35+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Work Environment</term>
					<term>organizational commitment</term>
					<term>OCB</term>
					<term>motivation</term>
					<term>performance</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The purpose of this study is to analyze the influence of the Influence of the Work Environment, Organizational Commitment And Organizational Citizenship Behavior On employee Performance through Motivation as an intervening Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. The population of this research was conducted by using the sampling technique of the research is taken from the population by using the method the sample is saturated, meaning that all existing populations as a complement to the sample, so the sample used the same magnitude with the population of 125 employees. Path analysis and hypothesis test using t test. The results of this study show that work environment has positive and significant effect on employee performance; work environment influential positive and significantly to the motivation; organizational commitment and significant positive effect on employee motivation; organizational commitment and significant positive effect terhaadap employee performance; OCB positive and significant effect on employee performance. OCB have a positive and significant impact on employee motivation; motivation has positive and significant effect on employee performance; work environment influential positive and significant on employee performance through motivation; commitment otganisasi positive and significant effect on employee performance through motivation, and OCB positive and significant effect on employee performance through motivation.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Employment growth in the external environment of the organization nowadays is more diverse especially in labor quality, due to labor or employee is as the tip of the spear that supports work activities in the organization. Therefore, the quality of employees in an organization have an important role to carry out duties and responsibilities. Because, to meet the needs of the quality employees required an employee who has the ability, skill and high creative as well as the problems faced in the environment of PT. Matahari Department Store Tbk in Tunjungan Plaza Surabaya. Because the results of the assessment of the performance of employees is still below the assessment standard used organization where the employee is working so that the expectations in the produce a high performance leadership of the organization need to make changes and increase performance through a variety of proactive in order to be closer and interact with employees who are considered to have a rating of its performance under the standards specified organization. Performance or achievement is the result of the work of a in carrying out activities of a job well done in quality and quantity in a certain period of time <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Mangkunegara, 2017)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dessler (2015)</ref>, that performance management is a continuous process for the future, to identify, measure, and develop the performance of individuals and teams, and straighten the results of the performance of employees in accordance with the goals of the organization.</p><p>In addition, there are several factors that became decisive for the achievement of the results of the performance of the employee among the working environment, organizational commitment, motivation and organizational citizenship behavior. Meanwhile, according to Nitisemito in <ref type="bibr">Suwardi and Daryanto (2018)</ref>, that the working environment is as something existing in the environment of the labor affects the labor or the person in carrying out work activities that become a burden on them, such as in the Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza Surabaya which has yet to show the conditions of the work offered. Because of the condition of the working environment still has not shown such a comfort to work activities, so that employees feel distracted and not at ease with environmental conditions that narrow or the arrangement or placement of various items presented is less interesting for the visitor or customer Matahari Department Store.</p><p>Porter and Minner in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Kusumaputri (2015)</ref> explained that organizational commitment as the attachment (attachment) with the organization characterized by the will to survive, the identification of the values and goals of the organization, as well as the willingness to strive more in his behavior. Organizational commitment on the Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya, such as in affective commitment that employees still have the feeling in the organization. In an ongoing commitment or the commitment of normative, the employees have no desire to stay at the Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya because they feel they have no obligation to be executed in this company. While organizational commitment is one of the factors that can produce maximum performance. Organizational Citizenship Behavior (OCB) is individual contributions that exceed the demands of the role in the workplace. OCB is a behavior of employees in organizations that do voluntary out of the description of the work that has been established to enhance the progress of the performance of the organization. Therefore, Organizational Citizenship Behavior (OCB) is a form of some people's behavior in doing activities such as behavior to help others, volunteer for tasks extra, obedient to the rules and procedures in the workplace. So this person's behaviour is as "value added employee" and one of only forms of prosocial behavior, that social behavior positive, constructive and meaningful help. While the view of Aldag and Resckhe cited by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Titisari (2014)</ref>, that organizational citizenship behavior (OCB) is individual behavior that is free, not related directly or explicitly with a reward system, so as to improve the effective functioning of the organization. Organizational citizenship behavior (OCB) at the Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya is good enough so that needs to be maintained on each employee so that company goals can be achieved. While <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Afandi (2016)</ref> that motivation is the desire that arises from within one's self or the individual as inspired, impassioned, and motivated to do activity with sincerity, happily and earnestly so that the results of the activity he is doing to get good results and quality. Motivation in the Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya, the company has to provide motivation in the form of allowances, rewards and so on to the employees. So should the performance of employees can be increased so that corporate objectives can be achieved. Therefore, the purpose of this study is to to analyze the work environment and organizational commitment influence on motivation and employee performance Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Literature Review Work Environment</head><p>Nitisemito in <ref type="bibr">Suwardi and Daryanto (2018)</ref>, that the working environment is something that is around the workers and that affects him in the line of duty-duty charged. Meanwhile, according to Sedarmayanti cited by <ref type="bibr">Suwardi and Daryanto (2018)</ref>, that the working environment is overall equipment tooling and materials encountered, the surrounding environment such as people work, methods of work, as well as a work setting either as an individual or in groups. Furthermore, Suwardi and Daryanto (2018) the type of work environment is divided into 2 namely the physical working environment, including for example temperature, humidity, air circulation, lighting, noise, mechanical vibration, odor, color and others, and non physical work environment includes relationships with superiors and fellow co-workers or relations with subordinates. Then <ref type="bibr">Sedarmayanti (2009)</ref> describes some of the indicators measuring the work environment includes lighting/light, color, ventilation or air handling, decoration, noise, music and security.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Organizational Commitment</head><p>According to Spencer in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Sedarmayanti (2017)</ref> organizational commitment is the individual's ability and willingness to align behavior with needs, priorities, and goals of the organization, as well as the act for the purpose or needs of the organization. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Sutrisno (2016)</ref> explains that commitment can be defined as the degree of relationship of the individual to look at himself with the work in the organization. Meanwhile, according to Newstrom in <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Wibowo (2014)</ref> stated that organizational commitment i.e. the levels where the work identify with the organization and have the desire to continue actively participating in it.</p><p>Furthermore, Alen and Mayer in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Sedarmayanti (2017)</ref> argues that there are three component indicators of organizational commitment, namely: affective Commitment (Affective comitment), sustainable Commitment (basis of continuance commintment), and the Commitment normative (Normative commitment).</p><p>Organizational Citizenship Behavior (OCB) Organizational citizenship behavior is the individual contributions that exceed the demands of the role in the workplace. OCB is a behavior of employees in organizations that do voluntary out of the description of the work that has been established to enhance the progress of the performance of the organization. Organizational citizenship behavior involves some of the behaviors people like to help people, volunteer for extra assignments, comply with the rules and procedures in the workplace. The behavior of the people it describes as "added value for employees" and as one form of prosocial behavior, i.e. behave in a positive, constructive and meaningful help. According to Aldag and Resckhe in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Titisari (2014)</ref>, that the organizational citizenship behavior as individual behavior that is free, not related directly or explicitly with the reward system and can improve the effective functioning of the organization. While Dyne et al in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Titisari (2014)</ref> which proposes the construction of organizational citizenship behavior (OCB), namely: Behaviors that benefit the organization and / or tend to benefit the organization, voluntarily and exceed what become the demands of the role. While the research Djati in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Titisari (2014)</ref> revealed that organizational citizenship behavior (OCB) is employee behavior that does not appear good terhadaprekan work or against the company, where such behavior exceeds the behavior standards established by the company and provide benefits for the company. Thus by Organ et al in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Titisari (2014)</ref> who argued with the five indicators of organizational citizenship behavior (OCB) includes altruism, conscientiousness, sportmanship, courtesy and civic virtue.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Motivation</head><p>Motivation is derived from the latin word "Movere" which means to push know move. Motivation in management is only present for human resources in general and subordinates in particular. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Afandi (2016)</ref> gives the explanation that the motivation is a desire that arises from within one's self or the individual as inspired, impassioned, and motivated to do activity with sincerity, happily and earnestly so that the results of the activity he is doing to get good results and quality. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Nawawi (2008)</ref>, that the word motivation the word is essentially a motif that means a push, rhyme or reason someone does something. Thus motivation means a condition that encourages or makes because someone is doing an activity which takes place consciously. While <ref type="bibr">Sedarmayanti (2011)</ref>, motivation can be defined as a driving force that causes people to do something or that done because you are afraid of something, for example, want to increase the salary then his actions will support the achievement of these desires. That became the driving force in such a case is a variety of factors, including factors want to stand out more among work colleagues or the environment and need for achievement. Furthermore, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Sutrisno (2016)</ref> proposed a theory of motivation was developed by Maslow on human needs are classified into five hierarchy of needs, among others: the physiological needs (physiological), safety and security needs (safety), the need for social relationships (affiliation), the need for recognition (esteem) and self-actualization needs (self actualization).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Employee Performance</head><p>Performance is an action or activity displayed by the person in carrying out the specific activities to be his duty. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Mangkunegara (2017)</ref>, human resources performance is a work achievement or the results of the work both in quality and quantity achieved human resources unity period of time in carrying out his duties in accordance with responsibility given to him. A company requires employees as a workforce in order to improve product quality. Remember the employees become an important asset for the company, a lot of things that need to be considered related to the improvement of its performance. According to Siswanto in Sandy (2015), performance is the feat achieved by a person in carrying out the tasks and work given to him. According to Rivai in Sandy (2015), that performance is the result or degree of success of the person as a whole during a certain period in performing the task compared with the range of possibilities, such as work standards, targets or objectives or criteria that have been determined in advance and agreed upon together. While Mathis and Jackson in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Fadillah et al. (2017)</ref> suggests five indicators of employee performance, namely: quality, quantity, timeliness, effectiveness and presence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Model Conceptual Framework and Research Hypothesis</head><p>The basic conceptual framework of this research is formed from the framework of the process of thinking, based on the background of the problem, and a literature review first which are used as guidelines to analyze problems that occur on the employee Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. The desire of a maximum of the company to realize the performance of the employee when supported from factors such as work environment, organizational commitment, motivation, organizational citizenship behavioral (OCB) and employee performance, and as proposed in this study can be described as follows:</p><p>Source: the Researchers ( <ref type="formula">2019</ref> : Organizational commitment has positive and significant effect on employee performance through employee motivation Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. H10 : OCB has positive and significant effect on employee performance through employee motivation Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Research Method</head><p>Research Design According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Rachman (2018)</ref>, that the research design is a form of frame work in carrying out the research.</p><p>Because of the design of this study detailing the procedures important to obtain information needed in preparing and/or solve the research problem. Furthermore <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Rachman (2018)</ref> confirms that this type of research design is the research eksplanatori (explanatory) the research aims to analyze the relationships between one variable with another variable or how a variable affects other variables. Therefore, this study intends to explain the causal relationship between variables through hypothesis testing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Population, Sample and Sampling Technique</head><p>Population in this research is employees of the Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya.</p><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Rachman (2018)</ref>, that the sample in the study is a part of the population. Furthermore, the sampling technique is taken into account by using the technique of minimal multiplication by 5 indicators observations <ref type="bibr">(Hair et al. in Rachman, 2018)</ref>. While this study has 25 indicators observation then the sample of this research are as many as 125 respondents.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Testing Research Instruments</head><p>The testing of the research instrument this is the beginning of data testing to determine the validity of the questionnaire have been distributed on the respondents denngan use validity test and reliability test with degrees of freedom respectively greater than 0,30 and 0,60.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis Of Research Data</head><p>In analyzing the data this research used path analysis model (Path Analysis), which was formed through Structural equation models or also called the structural model, namely when each dependent variable/endogenous (Y and Z) in a unique situation determined by a set of independent variable/exogenous (X).</p><p>The next image which displayed the structure of the causal relationship between variables is called the diagram the Path (Path Analysis) using the model equation structural.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hypothesis Test</head><p>Test this hypothesis using a statistical Test-t because it is used to test the partial regression coefficient of the independent variable. This test is done to test the hypothesis 1 to hypothesis 10, the hypothesis is formulated as follows <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Ghozali, 2011)</ref>: Ho: ρyx1/ρzx1= ……ρyx2/ρzx3 = 0, and Hi: ρyx1/ρzx1= ……. ρyx3/ρzx3 ≠ 0 Next; If the t-count &gt; t-table (α, n-k-l), then Ho is rejected; and</p><p>If the t-count &lt; t-table (α, n-k-l), then Ho is accepted. The results of the significance between the independent variables against the dependent variable determined in the bottom 5% or α = 0.05. The value of t can be searched with the following formula: <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Gujarati &amp; Porter, 2009)</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Results and Discussion</head><p>The Results Of The Analysis Test Instruments The results of the data analysis is done by using the validity test is pounded in the  <ref type="table">2</ref>. Above, shows that the five variables are the working environment, the organizational commitments, OCB, the motivation and performance of employees showing the results of the analysis on Cronbach's Alpha having a coefficient value of each greater than 0.60. So the five variables are declared reliable, therefore the questionnaire that is propagated to the respondent can be done and continued for research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Testing Analysis</head><p>Influence of inter-variable model of sub-structural pathway analysis in full lane describing the influence between working environment, organizational commitment and OCB towards employee motivation and performance, shown in the image below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 2. Line Analysis Model</head><p>Hypothesis Testing Analysis Based on the analysis of the sub-structural pathways can be described hypotheses proposed as research, as follows:</p><p>1. The first hypothesis, that the working environment negatively affects the motivation of employees, as demonstrated through the value T =-3.719 with a probability value (sig.) 0.000 &lt; 0.05 It can be concluded that the working environment variables are Negative and significant to the motivation of employees whose environmental conditions are inversely proportional to expected estimates even if the results are received. 2. The second hypothesis, that organizational commitment has a positive effect on the motivation of employees shows the value of t = 11,417 with a probability value (sig.) Of 0.000 &lt; 0.05 it can be concluded that the variables of organizational commitment and significant positive effect on employee motivation in the direction of the estimate of the expected, and the result is acceptable. 3. Hypothesis three, that OCB has a positive effect on the motivation of employees shows the value of t = 7,255 with a probability value (sig.) Of 0.000 &lt; 0.05 it can be concluded that the variables of OCB have a positive and significant impact on employee motivation in the direction of the estimate of the expected, and the result is acceptable. 4. The fourth hypothesis, that the work environment negatively affect the employee's performance shows the value of t = -2,688 with a probability value (sig.) Are 0.008 &lt; 0.05 it can be concluded that work environment variables have a negative effect and significant on employee performance which is inversely proportional to the estimated expected although the result is acceptable. 5. The fifth hypothesis, that organizational commitment negatively affect the employee's performance shows the value of t = -.303 with the value of the probability (sig.) 0,762 &gt; 0.05 it can be concluded that organizational commitment variables and no significant negative effect on the performance of employees whose condition is inversely proportional to the estimated expected and shows results that are not significant, and the result is rejected. 6. The hypothesis sixth, that the OCB affect positively on employee performance shows the value of t = 8,404 with a probability value (sig.) Of 0.000 &lt; 0.05 it can be concluded that the variables OCB positive and significant effect on employee performance which is in line with the estimate of the expected, and the result is acceptable. 7. Hypothesis seven, that motivation affect positively on employee performance shows the value of t = 8,404 with a probability value (sig.) Of 0.000 &lt; 0.05 it can be concluded that the variable of motivation has positive and significant effect on employee performance which is in line with the estimate of the expected, and the result is acceptable. 8. The hypothesis of the eighth, that no direct influence of work environment on employee performance through motivation. X1 Y Z = -0,197 The results of the analysis of the working environment of -0,197 then concluded that the work environment negatively affect the employee performance through motivation. The result is acceptable. 9. The hypothesis of the ninth, that the indirect influence of organizational commitment to employee www.iiste.org <ref type="bibr">ISSN 2222</ref><ref type="bibr">-1905</ref><ref type="bibr">(Paper) ISSN 2222</ref><ref type="bibr">-2839</ref><ref type="bibr">(Online) Vol.11, No.35, 2019</ref> 66 performance through motivation. X2 Y Z = 0,471 The results of the analysis of organizational commitment by 0,471 then concluded that organizational commitment has a positive effect on employee performance through motivation. The result is acceptable. 10. The hypothesis of the tenth, that no direct influence of OCB on employee performance through motivation.</p><p>X2 Y Z = 0,378 The results of the analysis of the OCB by 0,378 then concluded that OCB has a positive effect on employee performance through motivation. The result is acceptable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>The results of the analysis of research conducted individually showed a variable working environment and a significant negative effect on employee performance. It means that the working environment is still able to improve the performance of the employee significantly even if the result is negative. Because the expectations of employees if the leadership of the organization pay attention to the improvement of the performance of employees then it can be done through motivation and persuasion on the employee so that the employee does not decline to the work environment encountered in the work. It is necessary that the influence of negative work environment can change the behavior or appearance of the employee in completing the task-the task to which it aspires.</p><p>Such is the case with organizational commitment in the absence of serious attention from the leadership of the organization then the activity of that employee performed less konduksif, employees are often tired, employees are often saturated and easily bored, in addition to it the attention of the leadership to the subordinates should be more close with subordinates when there are new problems encountered on the job done, but it could also be a homage on the subordinates because they feel to receive supervision and support in completing the work. Based on the study of the theory that organizational commitment has a major role in influencing the performance of employees. If organizational commitment are less supportive on the employees then the tendency of organizational commitment becomes less good and very troubling employee itself, so that it can degrade the performance of the employees in the activity if done high motivation on the employees. While OCB has a positive influence on employee performance because the results are accepted has a coefficient of yag better in improving employee performance. The results of this analysis show the performance of the employees who are high in change or improve employee performance withto better. Therefore, the OCB have more value if the response it gets better. The results of this study are not yet supported from the research Ticoalu (2013), Al-Mahasneh (2015), <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Tunggal et al. (2018)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Astuti and Oktaria (2018)</ref>, than Deddy (2014), <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Maftri et al. (2017</ref><ref type="bibr">), Lutfi et al. (2017</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">), Trigunajasa (2017)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Arianto (2017</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">), Ferry (2017)</ref> which states the work environment and the negative effect and significant on motivation and performance and organizational commitment and the negative effect and significant on employee performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p>The results of the analysis discussion of the research that has been discussed on the model of the sub-structural previous, as follows: 1. Work environment influential positive and significant impact on employee motivation Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. The result is acceptable. 2. The work environment and the negative effect and significant on employee performance Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. The result is acceptable. 3. Organizational commitment and significant positive effect on employee motivation Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. The result is acceptable. 4. Organizational commitment and a significant negative effect on the performance of employees Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. The result is acceptable. 5. OCB have a positive and significant impact on employee motivation Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. The result is acceptable. 6. OCB has positive and significant effect on employee performance Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. The result is acceptable. 7. Motivation has positive and significant effect on employee performance Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. The result is acceptable. 8. Work environment influential positive and significant on employee performance through employee motivation Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. The result is acceptable. 9. Organizational commitment has positive and significant effect on employee performance through employee motivation Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. The result is acceptable. 10. OCB has positive and significant effect on employee performance through employee motivation Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya, the Result is acceptable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Rekomenndasi</head><p>Associated with the strong (seen from the value of the beta coefficient) the effect of motivation on employee Performance as intervening, then it can be given suggestions to increase motivation, by giving an opportunity to the employees to do the work yourself, give the opportunity to do something different from time to time, gives the opportunity to become an important person in the community, giving the opportunity to employees to do something that does not conflict with the conscience of the respondents, the organization ensures certainty of work, and the organization guaranteeing the opportunity to move forward on this work. In addition, the work environment, organizational commitment and OCB is also significant effect on employee performance through motivation. So hope to the future of the employees are able to cope individually in the face of challenging work then it is possible to increase the performance and motivation of employees become more fun. Therefore leaders need to more seriously pay attention to the conditions of employees in order not to experience a decline in performing its activities, also the leadership should be concerned with his subordinates so that the desired subordinate to the Sun Department Store can achieve its objectives and survive in competing with stores that are similar.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>) Figure 1. The Conceptual Framework Of The ResearchFrom the model the conceptual framework of this study can be filed hypothesis in accordance with the formulation of the problem as follows: H1: Work environment influential positive and significant impact on employee motivation Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. H2: Work environment influential positive and significant on employee performance Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. H3: Organizational commitment and significant positive effect on employee motivation Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. H4: Organizational commitment has positive and significant effect on employee performance Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. H5: OCB have a positive and significant impact on employee motivation Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. H6: OCB has positive and significant effect on employee performance Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. H7: Motivation has positive and significant effect on employee performance Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. H8: Work environment influential positive and significant on employee performance through employee motivation Matahari Department Store Tbk Tunjungan Plaza in Surabaya. H9</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>error of estimation / estimated deviation</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>table as follows: Table 1. Test The Validity Of The Variable Primary Data Processed Researchers Based on the results of the validity test in table1. the above states that the overall indicators of the variables of the research used show the results of validity, because all coefficients of correlation item-total correlation number is greater than the critical value of 0.30. Means all indicator variables are tested as research instruments can be accepted.Next, reliability can be done by using testing, and the result can be seen in the table as follows:</figDesc><table><row><cell>From table</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">Corrected Item-Total Correlation</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Item</cell><cell>X1</cell><cell>X2</cell><cell>X3</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Z</cell><cell>Description</cell></row><row><cell>Work Environment</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.600</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2</cell><cell>.471</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>3</cell><cell>.607</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>4</cell><cell>.383</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>5</cell><cell>.553</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>6</cell><cell>.564</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>7</cell><cell>.378</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell>Organizational Commitment</cell><cell>8</cell><cell></cell><cell>.625</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>9</cell><cell></cell><cell>.580</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>10</cell><cell></cell><cell>.662</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell>OCB</cell><cell>11</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.507</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>12</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.742</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>13</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.511</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>14</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.351</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>15</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.705</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell>Motivation</cell><cell>16</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">.331</cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>17</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">.374</cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>18</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">.573</cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>19</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">.427</cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>20</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">.546</cell><cell></cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell>Employee Performance</cell><cell>21</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.404</cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>22</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.408</cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>23</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.462</cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>24</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.576</cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>25</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.361</cell><cell>Valid</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Source: Table 2 Reliability Test Variable</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Variabel</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Cronbach's Alpha</cell><cell></cell><cell>Description</cell></row><row><cell>Work Environment (X1)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0,756</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Reliabel</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Organizational Commitment (X2)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0,783</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Reliabel</cell></row><row><cell>OCB (X3)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0,778</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Reliabel</cell></row><row><cell>Motivation (Y)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0,693</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Reliabel</cell></row><row><cell>Employee Performance (Z)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0,686</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Reliabel</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Source: Primary Data Processed Researchers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Concept &amp; Indicator Human Resources Management for Management Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Afandi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Deepublish</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Yogyakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of Organizational Citizenship Behavior on Job Performance at Greater Amman Municipality. IISTE</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mohammad</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Al-Mahasneh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ISSN 2222-2839</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Business and Management</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">2222-1905</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">36</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Paper. Online</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pengaruh Kepuasan Kompensasi Dan Lingkungan Kerja Terhadap Motivasi Serta Dampaknya Pada Kepuasan Kerja Karyawan Perusahaan Daerah Air Minum (PDAM) Kabupaten Bantul Daerah Istimewa Yogyakarta</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Deddy</forename><surname>Arta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Novie Citra Dan Harsono</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Bisnis, Teori dan Implementasi</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014. 2014</date>
			<pubPlace>Yogyakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Universitas Muhammadiyah</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pengaruh Kepuasan Kerja Terhadap Kinerja Karyawan Melalui Organizational Citizenship Behavior Sebagai Variabel Intervening (Studi Pada Staff PT Kepuh Kencana Arum Mojokerto</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Arianto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Deny</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Ilmu Manajemen</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Universitas Negeri Surabaya</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyze Organizational Citizenship Behavior (OCB), Discipline, And Work Motivation Towards Employee Performance. IISTE</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yuni</forename><surname>Astuti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Irma</forename><surname>Oktaria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ISSN 2222-2839</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Business and Management</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">2222-1905</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Paper. Online</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia. (Human Resource Management/Gary Dessler</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gary</forename><surname>Dessler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2015. 2013</date>
			<publisher>Salemba Empat</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New Jersey; Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>th ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pengaruh Kompetensi, Disiplin Kerja Dan Lingkungan Kerja Terhadap Kinerja Karyawan Pada Kantor Bank Kalsel Cabang Pembantu di Banjarmasin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rozi</forename><surname>Fadillah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sulastini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Dan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hidayati</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Bisnis dan Pembangunan</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">2541-178X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pengaruh Lingkungan Kerja Terhadap Kinerja Karyawan Melalui Variabel Mediator Motivasi Kerja (Studi Pada Karyawan PT Telkom Indonesia, Tbk Witel Jatim Selatan, Jalan A. Yani, Malang)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bambang</forename><surname>Ferry Moulana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Swasto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dan</forename><surname>Sunuharyo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nayati</forename><surname>Gamidah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Utami</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Administrasi Bisnis (JAB)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Universitas Brawijaya Malang</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Maret</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Aplikasi Analisis Multivariate Dengan Program SPSS</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ghozali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Badan Penerbit Universitas Diponegoro</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Damodar</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Gujarati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dawn</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Porter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Basic Econometrics. 5th Edition</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, McGraw-Hill/Irwin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Komitmen pada Perubahan-Perubahan Organisasi dalam Perspektif Islam dan Psikolog</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Erika</forename><surname>Kusumaputri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Setyani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>Deepublish</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Yogyakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pengaruh Disiplin Dan Komitmen Terhadap Motivasi Kerja Karyawan Di Pabrik Kelapa Sawit PTPN I Tanjung Seumantoh, Aceh Tamiang</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Luthfi</forename><surname>Parinduri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yusmartato</forename><surname>Yusmartato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tri</forename><surname>Hernawati</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Buletin Utama Teknik</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Universitas Islam Sumatera Utara</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pengaruh Lingkungan Kerja, Disiplin Kerja, Dan Kepuasan Kerja Terhadap Kinerja Karyawan BMT Taruna Sejahtera Ungaran</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maftri</forename><surname>Yuliana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Leonardo</forename><surname>Budi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Edward</forename><surname>Gagah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Ekonomi dan Bisnis</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<pubPlace>Semarang</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Universitas Pandanaran</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mangkunegara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Anwar Prabu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Rosda</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Bandung</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hadari</forename><surname>Nawawi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Gadjah Mada University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Yogyakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mochammad</forename><surname>Rachman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Munir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Metodologi Penelitian, Cetakan Kedua</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Surabaya</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Penerbit Unipress Universitas PGRI Adi Buana</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pengaruh Kemampuan Kerja dan Komitmen Organisasional Terhadap Kinerja Karyawan (Studi Pada Karyawan Perusahaan Daerah Air Minum Kota Malang)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rositha</forename><surname>Dini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Permatasari</forename><forename type="middle">Bambang</forename><surname>Swasto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mohammad</forename><surname>Iqbal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Administrasi Bisnis (JAB)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016-04">2016. April 2016</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Universitas Brawijaya Malang</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Karakteristik Pekerjaan dan Kinerja Dosen Luar Biasa UIN Sunan Gunung Djati Bandung: Komitmen Organisasi Sebagai Variabel Moderating</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Muhammad</forename><surname>Sandi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Martha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sumber Daya Manusia dan Produktivitas Kerja. Bandung: CV. Mandar Maju. Sedarmayanti. 2011. Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia</title>
		<title level="s">Reformasi Birokrasi Manajemen Pegawai Negeri Sipil</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Bandung</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Rafika Aditama</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2015. 2009</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Tesis di Universitas Widyatama Bandung. Sedarmayanti</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sedarmayanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Refika Aditama</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Bandung</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manajemen Sumber Daya Manusia. Jakarta: Kencana Pernada Media Group. Suwardi dan Daryanto</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Edy</forename><surname>Sutrisno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2018</date>
			<publisher>Gava Media</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Yogyakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Pedoman Praktis K3LH: Keselamatan dan Kesehatan Kerja dan Lingkungan Hidup</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Organizational Citizenship Behavior (OCB) Dan Komitmen Organisasi Pengaruhnya Terhadap Kinerja Karyawan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Linda</forename><surname>Ticoalu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kartini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal EMBA</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">2303-1174</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="782" to="790" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Peranan Organizational Citizenship Behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Purnamie</forename><surname>Titisari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Mitra Wacana Media</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Bandung</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pengaruh Tipe Kepribadian, Komitmen Organisasi, Motivasi Terhadap Organization Citizenship Behavior (OCB) Dan Kinerja Petugas Di Taman Wisata Alam Kawah Ijen</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Trigunajasa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">Andi</forename><surname>Sunandar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Purnamie</forename><surname>Sularso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Titisari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Bisnis dan Manajemen</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="297" to="310" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-09">2017. September 2017</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Universitas Jember</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect Of Work Motivation On Performance With Organizational Citizenship Behavior As Intervening Variable</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fiqih</forename><surname>Tunggal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hidayah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Business and Management Invention (IJBMI)</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">(Online): 2319 -8028</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2319" to="2801" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Print</note>
	<note>ISSN</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wibowo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Manajemen Kinerja. Edisi Keempat</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Rajawali Pers</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
