<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Understanding the key drivers in using mobile payment among Generation Z</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lisana</forename><surname>Lisana</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laura</forename><surname>Blackburne</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Koorosh</forename><surname>Gharehbaghi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ken</forename><surname>Farnes</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Olivia</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Melisa</forename><surname>Russo</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Informatics Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Surabaya</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Surabaya</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Journal of Science and Technology Policy Management | Emerald Insight</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Understanding the key drivers in using mobile payment among Generation Z</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1108/JSTPM-08-2021-0118</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 13 August Revised 30 January 28 May Accepted 15 July Journal of Science and Technology Policy Management</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T19:01+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>M-payment</term>
					<term>Generation Z</term>
					<term>Moderating factor</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Purpose -This quantitative study aims to examine the determinants that impact the behavioral intention to use mobile payment (m-payment) among Generation Z (Gen Z) customers in Indonesia.</p><p>Design/methodology/approach -The theoretical model comprises seven latent variables: effort expectancy, performance expectancy, social influence, facilitating conditions, promotional activities, perceived security and behavioral intention. In addition, the two moderating factors of education and gender are used to investigate the significant effect of the determinants on intention to adopt m-payment. This study obtained the final data size of 430 respondents. The data analysis is conducted using structural equation modeling.</p><p>Findings -The results substantiate the significance of promotional activities, perceived security, performance expectancy, effort expectancy and social influence, on the behavioral intention to accept m-payment systems. Gender is revealed to significantly moderate two constructs: social influence and promotional activities, on the m-payment usage intention. Meanwhile, education moderates the effect of perceived security on behavioral intention.</p><p>Originality/value -This research is expected to fill the gap because only a few studies discuss the determinants affecting m-payment usage in Indonesia, especially among Gen Z-ers. Furthermore, the new findings associated with the role of two moderating factors become important practical implications because most of the prior studies often ignore the moderating factors.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>The rapid growth of mobile technology and the high penetration rate of mobile internet users have made the mobile phone an essential device to support many daily life activities. Because of its diverse functionality, more users use their smartphones to do payment transactions, referring to mobile payment (m-payment). <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Handarkho et al. (2021)</ref> declared that m-payment is a digital payment service to perform financial transactions using mobile devices and wireless communication technologies. As an online digital payment, m-payment can create the process of payment become more convenient yet faster for customers without carrying any physical cards or money.</p><p>Globally, the adoption of m-payments has continued to rise in the past five years. Mordor Intelligence (2021) reported that the global value of m-payments had reached US $1,449.56billion in the year 2020 and forecasted will amount to US$5,399.6bn in 2026, reflecting a compound annual growth rate (CAGR) of 24.5% between 2021 and 2026. As the market size, there were 1.3 billion global m-payment users in the year 2020, increasing 225% from 2015 <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Business of Apps, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Despite the rapid global growth of m-payment, a study revealed that the willingness of Indonesian customers to adopt m-payment is considered low and still at the infancy stage <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Lisana, 2021)</ref>. Central Bank of Indonesia reported that m-payment transactions were valued at US$13.95bn in 2020, increasing 38.6% from 2019 and expected to obtain US$18.5bn in 2021 <ref type="bibr">(The Asian Banker, 2020)</ref>. Another survey showed that the percentage of m-payment penetration in <ref type="bibr">Indonesia was 15.9% in 2019</ref><ref type="bibr">(Boston Consulting Group, 2020)</ref>. However, Indonesia is still considered a big market in developing access to m-payment systems because of large geographical and population conditions. The adoption of m-payment is expected to continue to rise because of huge support from both government agencies, the Indonesia Central Bank (BI) and the Financial Service Authority (OJK) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Isnurhadi, 2021)</ref>. The Indonesia Central Bank reported the number of licensed bank and non-bank e-money providers was 14 and 37, respectively <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Fintechnews Indonesia, 2020)</ref>. This study focuses on m-payment systems provided by non-bank services.</p><p>Indonesia is the fourth largest country globally, having a population of 271.35 million in the year 2020. Central Bureau of Statistics Indonesia reported that Generation Z (Gen Z) dominated the people of Indonesia in 2020, with 27.94% <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Triyasni, 2021)</ref>. Gen Z describes youth born between 1997 and 2012 <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Dimock, 2019)</ref>. Research conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Turner (2015)</ref> explored the uniqueness of Gen Z-ers in technology and smartphone usage. As the dominating generation in Indonesia, it is necessary to examine the behavior among Gen Zers in using m-payment.</p><p>Most of the extant studies in m-payment acceptance have been conducted using one of the popular technology acceptance models, unified theory of acceptance and use of technology (UTAUT) <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Lisana, 2021)</ref>. Originally, UTAUT comprises four main constructs, namely performance expectancy, effort expectancy, social influence and facilitating conditions, that affect the user's intention to accept new technology. Because of the impossibility of the four constructs to fully address the uniqueness of m-payment platforms, the UTAUT model has been extended by adding several different constructs such as personal innovativeness <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Wang and Dai, 2020)</ref>, trust <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Zhao and Bacao, 2021)</ref> and individual mobility <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Liébana-Cabanillas, 2021)</ref>. Moreover, UTAUT has introduced the importance of four moderating factors: age, gender, experience and voluntariness of use, on the relationships between the constructs and behavior intention.</p><p>Even though UTAUT has been adopted by many authors to explore the user's intention toward m-payment usage in several countries <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Zhao and Bacao, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Wei et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Al-Saedi et al., 2020)</ref>, only limited studies are conducted in Indonesia. Indeed, a systematic review conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Pramana (2021)</ref> showed that only two articles related to the adoption of m-payment in Indonesia had been published in journals from online major scientific databases between 2016 and 2020. Moreover, to the best of my knowledge, no studies examine the factors that influence the Gen Z-er's intention, as a dominant population in Indonesia, to accept m-payment. Additionally, in the m-payment adoption context, only a few authors adopted the moderating factors in their research model, specifically for education <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Lisana, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Pramana, 2021)</ref>. This study aims to fill the void by investigating the factors that affect the behavior intention among Indonesian Gen Z-ers. The proposed research model uses extended UTAUT theory by adding another two constructs that are closely related to the characteristics of Gen Z: perceived security and promotional activities. Meanwhile, to obtain a deeper understanding, this study analyzes the role of two moderating factors: gender and education, on the direct effects of Gen Z-er's intention toward m-payment usage and its antecedents. All stakeholders, including m-payment service providers and bank policy-makers, may benefit from the findings of this study by providing a profound understanding of how JSTPM Gen Z customers in Indonesia developed their intention to use m-payment platforms. Thus, this research proposes two research questions as follows:</p><p>RQ1. Which factors have a positive impact on Gen Z customers' intention to accept mpayment?</p><p>RQ2. Do Gen Z customers' gender and education have a significant moderating effect on the intention to accept m-payment?</p><p>The article is organized into eight sections. Section 2 presents the theoretical review based on the existing studies in m-payment acceptance, followed by developing the research model and hypotheses in Section 3. Sections 4 and 5 describe the research methodology and preliminary analyses, respectively. SEM analysis of the research model and hypotheses testing are then presented in Section 6, followed by discussion in Section 7. Finally, the conclusion is presented in Section 8.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Literature review</head><p>In the last decade, many authors have explored the adoption of m-payment as a new innovative payment method. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Dahlberg et al. (2015)</ref> discovered that 34 m-payment adoption articles had been published from 2007 to 2014. Another systematic review study found that between 2014 and 2018, there were a total of 54 publications on m-payment adoption research <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Karsen et al., 2019)</ref>. Of those 54 publications, 38 articles (or 70%) were published in scientific journals and the remaining 16 (or 30%) were published in conference proceedings.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> summarizes the prior m-payment adoption studies conducted in different countries. Both Technology Acceptance Model (TAM) and UTAUT were found to be the most adopted theories to investigate how users develop their intention to use m-payment platform. Because those two basic models were not sufficient to explain the user's behavior to accept m-payment, many authors have added other various variables as listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</p><p>UTAUT, as one of the most popular technology adoption models, has been adopted by many studies in m-payment usage. UTAUT originally includes four primary constructs: effort expectancy, performance expectancy, facilitating conditions and social influence to be significant in influencing intention to use technology. Many studies have examined the significance of those constructs on the user's intention toward m-payment <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Do et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Zhao and Bacao, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Moorthy et al., 2020)</ref>. Other relevant determinants were added to get a better explanation of user's behavior in using m-payment, such as perceived security <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Jin et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Moorthy et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Cobanoglu et al., 2015)</ref> and promotional activities <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Wei et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Wang and Dai, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Not only four constructs, but the UTAUT model also provides four moderating factors: gender, age, experience and voluntariness of use. However, limited studies in m-payment adoption are concerned about moderating factors in their research model. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Pramana (2021)</ref> verified that only 13 out of 72 articles (18 %) published from 2016 to 2020 investigated the role of moderating factors among determinants in their research model. His study also found that gender is one of the moderating factors often used in m-payment adoption studies. Furthermore, some authors explored education as another important moderating factor <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Jin et al.,2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Sobti, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Park et al., 2019)</ref>.</p><p>As defined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Dimock (2019)</ref>, Gen Z-ers are between the ages of 9 and 24 by the year 2021. His study highlighted that Gen Z has grown up in an environment with "always-on" technology. Therefore, mobile technology plays an essential role for Gen Z youth. They behave that smartphone is everything to them as they can perform many activities using their smart portable handled device <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Turner, 2015)</ref>.</p><p>The extant studies in m-payment acceptance have been done in various countries. However, not many authors focused on Southeast Asian countries, more specifically Indonesia. Additionally, some scholars disregarded the role of moderating factors in their research models. This empirical study focuses on investigating the development of Indonesian Gen Z-er's intention to use m-payment based on extended UTAUT, including two moderating factors.  Performance expectancy refers to the individual's perception that m-payment systems will enhance his/her job performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Zhao and Bacao, 2021)</ref>. The higher customers believe that m-payment offers some incentives, the higher they will adopt it <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Al-Saedi et al., 2020)</ref>. Most prior studies confirmed that performance expectancy was an essential determinant of the adoption of m-payment <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Zhao and Bacao, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Moorthy et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Al-Saedi et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Do et al., 2020)</ref>. However, <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Wei et al. (2021)</ref> reported that the effect of performance expectancy was insignificant. Therefore, this hypothesis is proposed:</p><p>H1. Performance expectancy has a positive effect on the Gen Z customers' intention to accept m-payment.</p><p>Effort expectancy is defined as the degree of belief that the use of m-payment systems is easy <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Wei et al., 2021)</ref>. The easier m-payment is used, the higher user's willingness to adopt. Effort expectancy was one of the most influential determinants affecting m-payment acceptance <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Sobti, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Al-Saedi et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Gupta and Arora, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">de Sena Abrahão et al., 2016)</ref>. Contrary, some authors confirmed an insignificant effect of effort expectancy on customers' intentions <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Zhao and Bacao, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Wei et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Lee et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Moorthy et al., 2020)</ref>. However, literature review studies revealed that effort expectancy was the most frequently used factor in m-payment studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Karsen et al., 2019)</ref>. This leads to this hypothesis:</p><p>H2. Effort expectancy has a positive effect on the Gen Z customers' intention to accept m-payment.</p><p>Wang and Dai (2020) described social influence as the extent to which other people's opinions can sway the decision to use a particular system. It reflects the influence of close friends, relatives and family on behavioral intention to use m-payment. In several mpayment adoption research, social influence was considered a significant antecedent of users' intention <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Lisana, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Wei et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Zhao and Bacao, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Wang and Dai, 2020)</ref>. However, some studies reported the insignificance of this effect <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Moorthy et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Gupta and Arora, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Teo et al., 2015)</ref>. A study showed that Gen Z-ers used social networks actively and built their relationship based on social media channels <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Cho et al., 2018)</ref>. This gives rise to the following hypothesis:</p><p>H3. Social influence has a positive effect on the Gen Z customers' intention to accept mpayment. <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Teo et al. (2015)</ref> defined facilitating conditions as the degree to which an individual believes that he or she was equipped with configuring and operating wireless internet mobile phones to perform m-payment. The support of the organizational and technical infrastructure of mpayment platforms can increase the customers' intention to adopt m-payment. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Moorthy et al. (2020)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Molina-Castillo et al. (2020)</ref> argued that the effect of facilitating conditions on customers' intention to use m-payment was significant, while other authors, <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Wei et al. (2021)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Lee et al. (2019)</ref>, showed the contradictory result. Thus, the following hypothesis is proposed:</p><p>H4. Facilitating conditions has a positive effect on the Gen Z customers' intention to accept m-payment.</p><p>Perceived security is defined as the degree to which an individual believes that using m-payment systems is secure <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Zhao and Bacao, 2021)</ref>. Customers will perform the financial transactions using m-payment if they feel secure against confidential data loss. Most m-payment studies confirmed perceived security as a significant determinant that influences the usage of m-payment <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Zhao and Bacao, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Oliveira et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Moorthy et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Liébana-Cabanillas et al., 2018)</ref>. Surprisingly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Jin et al. (2020)</ref> found that perceived security did not positively influence customers' behavior intention to use m-payment in Malaysia. However, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Francis and Hoefel (2018)</ref> argued that Gen Z-ers put security as their priority. Therefore, this hypothesis is proposed:</p><p>H5. Perceived security has a positive effect on the Gen Z customers' intention to accept m-payment.</p><p>Promotional activities refer to activities related to promoting a product or service, such as offering both rewards: monetary and nonmonetary <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Wei et al., 2021)</ref>. It reflects the more promotion offered to the customers, the higher their interest in using m-payments. <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Wang and Dai (2020)</ref> showed the strong effect of the promotions provided to the customers on the positive attitude and intention to accept m-payment in China. Furthermore, a prior study also argued that the number of promotion activities effectively attracted and attained more young generations to adopt m-payment in Taiwan <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Wei et al., 2021)</ref>. Unfortunately, the role of promotional activities in m-payment adoption is still under-investigated. This gives rise to the following hypothesis:</p><p>H6. Promotional activities has a positive effect on Gen Z customers' intention to accept m-payment.</p><p>Several m-payment studies confirmed that gender significantly influences the direct effects of the following variables: effort expectancy <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Hamza and Shah, 2014)</ref>, performance expectancy <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(Yunpeng and Jamal, 2018)</ref>, social influence <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Hamza and Shah, 2014)</ref>, perceived security <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Musa et al., 2015)</ref> on the behavioral intention to m-payment usage. However, the exploration of moderating effect of education in m-payment studies is still limited. <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Park et al. (2019)</ref> appear to be the only study that argued the moderating factor of education significantly influences the relationship between perceived security and behavioral intention. As a result, this study proposed 12 hypotheses associated with the influences of the two moderating factors (education and gender) on the six aforementioned hypotheses H1-H6: H7-H12. Gender moderates the positive effect of performance expectancy, effort expectancy, social influence, facilitating conditions, perceived security and promotional activities on behavioral intention.</p><p>H13-H18. Education moderates the positive effect of performance expectancy, effort expectancy, social influence, facilitating conditions, perceived security and promotional activities on behavioral intention.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Theoretical model</head><p>The proposed theoretical model is developed after extensively reviewing the extant studies in m-payment usage. The model offers a different perspective by extending the UTAUT model with promotional activities and perceived security variables to provide an understanding of the factors that influenced Indonesian Gen Z-ers to use m-payment JSTPM systems. UTAUT theory was selected as a basic model because it contains not only performance expectancy and effort expectancy constructs, which are similar to perceived usefulness and perceived ease of use constructs in TAM <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Venkatesh et al., 2003)</ref>, but also social influence and facilitating conditions constructs. According to Hofstede-insights (2022), Indonesia is a collectivist society, thus it is necessary to include social influence construct in the theoretical model. Furthermore, as the dominating population in Indonesia <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Triyasni, 2021)</ref>, Gen Z-ers highlights several characteristics. They care much about security matters and rely heavily on technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Francis and Hoefel, 2018)</ref>. Additionally, they can be categorized as shrewd consumers <ref type="bibr">(Annie Foundation, 2021)</ref>. Therefore, this study employs another three constructs: facilitating conditions, perceived security and promotional activities, in the proposed theoretical model to represent the characteristics of Gen Z-ers. To enrich the findings, the model also includes two moderating factors: gender and education, as seen in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Methodology</head><p>This study is exploratory research and uses a field study method because the impact of variables on the dependent variable is uncontrollable, which is possible in experimental designs <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Boudreau et al., 2001)</ref>. This method is also excellent in identifying relatively strong effects on dependent variables that could enhance the statistical results <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Cook and Campbell, 1979)</ref>. As a quantitative cross-sectional study, the questionnaire is used to gather information related to the customers' experiences when they are using m-payment systems. The questionnaire is designed into three parts. The first part is an introduction explaining the understanding of m-payment. The second section contains the questions related to the characteristic of the participants (age, gender and education). The last section consists of measuring instruments developed based on prior studies in m-payment adoption. Both </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Key drivers in using mobile payment</head><p>English and Indonesian questionnaires are then reviewed by expert users knowledgeable in English and Indonesian languages.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> lists all measuring instruments from seven variables in the theoretical model adapted from the existing studies. Each indicator is measured using a five-point Likert scale. The value of gender is either male or female and education is either high school or below or higher education or above.</p><p>This study used a purposive sampling method to gather the data. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Gupta and Arora (2019)</ref>, the purposive sampling method chooses the most productive targeted respondents to answer the research questions. This method was considered to be used following the research guidance from <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Neuman (2014)</ref>. The questionnaires were administered via a google form. Concerning the aforementioned research objectives, the target </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>JSTPM</head><p>respondents of interest for this study are Indonesian Gen Z-ers living in five urban cities and actively using m-payment systems. Furthermore, following the guideline from <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Israel (2003)</ref>, the minimum sample size used in this study is 400 respondents because the target population is more than 100,000.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Descriptive analyses</head><p>Initially, this study collected 481 responses from Indonesian Gen Z-ers. The respondents' participation is arranged through personal contacts with the author to ensure that only Gen Z-ers could participate in this study. Moreover, the first part of the questionnaire also states the range of respondents' age who can participate. The data from google forms were then transferred to the SPSS version 23 worksheet and checked whether they contained at least one outlier value for each indicator. As a result, 51 responses were removed, bringing the final sample size to 430 to be further analyzed. This number has exceeded the minimum sample size of 400 based on criteria from <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Israel (2003)</ref>.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> shows the characteristics of the participants based on the received questionnaires. The number of male respondents (57.4%) is greater than females (42.6%). The respondents' age is between 15 and 24 years old in accordance with the Gen Z-er's criteria. Meanwhile, more respondents have higher education or above (62.6%) compared to those with high school or below (37.4%).</p><p>This study used SPSS version 23 to analyze 430 valid data. A confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) was used to measure the validity of all variables. Based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Straub et al. (2004)</ref>, the CFA results of the construct validity for seven latent variables were satisfactory because all indicators had a factor loading value greater than 0.4 with an eigenvalue of at least 1. However, there was a problem because all indicators for two latent variables, facilitating conditions (FC1-4) and promotional activities (PA1-3), have loaded onto the same component. This implied that all indicators of both latent variables did not satisfy the discriminant validity. Consequently, one of those two variables should be excluded from the model. The Promotional Activities variable is closely related to Gen Z'ers <ref type="bibr">(Annie Foundation, 2021)</ref>. Therefore, this study eliminated facilitating conditions variable from the The second iteration of the CFA demonstrated that all indicators from six latent variables were found to satisfy the condition of discriminant and convergent validity. Another testing, average variance extracted (AVE), was executed to confirm the convergent validity. The AVE values of all latent variables exceeded the minimum acceptable values of 0.5, assuring the convergent validity based on the recommendation from <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Fornell and Larcker (1981)</ref>.</p><p>Cronbach Alpha coefficients were used to test the equivalence reliability of all indicators from six latent variables. All construct's coefficients confirmed internal consistency with a value higher than the threshold value of 0.7 <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(George and Mallery, 2003)</ref>. Another assessment to test the internal consistency reliability is composite reliability (CR). The CR values of all latent variables were above 0.7, confirming internal consistency reliability <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Fornell and Larcker, 1981)</ref>. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref>. presents the results of validity and reliability testing showing that the measurement model has been satisfactory.</p><p>The descriptive statistics for all indicators of model variables can be seen in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">5</ref>. The following formula is used to calculate the single scale measure (SCM) of each variable <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Pramana, 2018)</ref>:   <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">5</ref> shows that the indicators from each latent variable have both values of kurtosis and skewness are below the maximum value of 7 and 3, respectively, as suggested by <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kline (2016)</ref>. This condition is necessary as one of the main prerequisites for conducting SEM analyses. Table <ref type="table">6</ref> presents the correlation for the relationships among the single-scale measures for the model variables. With exception to the association between perceived security and promotional activities (the shaded cell), all six variables are significantly correlated with each other.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">SCM ¼ X n i¼1 SD ½i Ã FL½i</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Analyses of modified theoretical model and hypotheses testing</head><p>Because facilitating conditions construct was deleted from the theoretical model, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, three hypotheses were excluded from the modified theoretical model. One hypothesis is related to the direct effect on behavioral intention (H4) and the other two are related to the moderating factors (H10 and H16).</p><p>The analyses of the modified theoretical model were conducted using structural equation modeling (SEM) done using AMOS Version 21 software. The results were measured by standardized path coefficients (in parentheses) that can be used to determine the relationships among variables, as depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref>. The five proposed hypotheses are significant positive predictors of behavioral intention (confirming H1-H6).</p><p>Following the recommendation from <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kline (2016)</ref>, the results of fit statistics of the modified theoretical model are satisfactory, as presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">7</ref>. A reasonable model fit  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>JSTPM</head><p>As seen in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, the modified theoretical model employs two moderating factors: gender and education, hypothesized to moderate the relationship between each of the five determinants of behavioral intention significantly. Table <ref type="table">8</ref> shows the detailed hypotheses results related to two moderating factors. The difference between the unstandardized effects for each pair of groups is also included.</p><p>The results indicate that gender significantly moderates two direct effects: social influence on behavioral intention and promotional activities on behavioral intention. Meanwhile, education moderates significantly the direct effect of perceived security on behavioral intention only. It claims that only three out of ten proposed hypotheses related to two moderating factors are statistically significant (confirming H9, H12 and H17).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1">Direct and moderating effects</head><p>The study found that all determinants directly affect behavioral intention, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref>. Performance expectancy was revealed to be the most significant effect on customers' intention to use m-payment. Previous research also yielded a similar result <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Sobti, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Gupta and Arora, 2019)</ref>. The result implies that Indonesian Gen Z customers have a strong enthusiasm to adopt m-payment as long as it provides them some benefits. Performing financial transactions easily and faster attracts Gen Z customers to use the m-payment platform. This finding also strengthened the research from <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Mu and Lee (2021)</ref> that confirmed the significance of performance expectancy on Korean university students'  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>JSTPM</head><p>switching intention from traditional payment to m-payment. Additionally, a study conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Cho et al. (2018)</ref> argued because Gen Z-ers use the internet frequently and comfort with technology usage, performance has become the top priority among Gen Z-ers in adopting m-payment systems.</p><p>The second determinant affecting Indonesian Gen Z customers' use of m-payment was effort expectancy. This finding was supported by some existing studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Al-Saedi et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Sobti, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Gupta and Arora, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">de Sena Abrahão et al., 2016)</ref>. The result indicates that the degree of effort-free experienced by Gen Z customers when they use m-payment will lead to a greater inclination to adopt the platform. Therefore, providing m-payment systems with an effortless, user-friendly and intuitive user interface will increase Gen Z customers' chance to switch from traditional payment to m-payment when performing their financial transactions. Further, the result is reasonable because Gen Z students have already used many applications and have been familiar with technologies since their youth <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Lisana and Suciadi, 2021)</ref>.</p><p>Social influence was the third influential antecedent on the Gen Z customer's intention to use m-payment. The finding was in line with the studies conducted by Lisana ( <ref type="formula">2021</ref> (2020) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Do et al. (2020)</ref>. The finding implies that Gen Z customers rely more on the suggestions and recommendations from their important people in formulating their intentions to adopt m-payment. Moreover, according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Cho et al. (2018)</ref>, Gen Z is a generation engaged with social networking and has high regard for the opinions of their close friends, relatives and family members.</p><p>The fourth determinant, promotional activities, significantly affected Gen Z customers toward m-payment. This finding strengthened the studies from <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Wei et al. (2021)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Wang and Dai (2020)</ref>. They argued both promotions and incentives offered by m-payment were essential factors affecting the development of users' intention to adopt m-payment, specifically for the young generation. Meanwhile, the result confirms the degree to which Gen Z-ers' impulse to react to any promotions, including financial rewards, significantly influences behavior intentions to use m-payment.</p><p>Perceived security was the last factor that significantly influenced Gen Z customers' intention toward m-payment. Most authors supported the result and agreed that security becomes the major barrier for customers to switch from traditional payment to m-payment <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Zhao and Bacao, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Moorthy et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Liébana-Cabanillas et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Cobanoglu et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Oliveira et al., 2016)</ref>. The finding indicates that the ability of m-payment systems to protect their financial and information privacy is a crucial and important factor that affects the development of Indonesian Gen Z-ers' intention toward the platform. Furthermore, according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Francis and Hoefel (2018)</ref>, security matter is the most important consideration for Gen Z.</p><p>Moreover, the findings also convinced the significant moderating effect of gender on two paths. First, gender significantly moderates the direct effect of social influence on behavioral intention in m-payment usage. The result reflects that female Gen Z customers are more influenced by opinions from their close friends, relatives and family members than male Gen Z customers in deciding to use m-payment. This finding is consistent with a study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Hamza and Shah (2014)</ref>.</p><p>Second, gender significantly moderates the effect of promotional activities on behavioral intention to adopt m-payment. Surprisingly, male Gen Z customers are more interested in all activities related to promotion when they perform m-payment than female Gen Z customers. To the best of my knowledge, this can be considered a new finding because no prior studies Key drivers in using mobile payment discussed the significant moderating effect of gender on the direct effect of promotional activities on customers' intention to use m-payment.</p><p>Other findings showed education moderates significantly the direct effect of perceived security on the behavioral intention to use m-payment. The result implies that low-educated Gen Z customers perceive higher security when they use m-payment than highly educated Gen Z customers. This finding strengthens the research conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Park et al. (2019)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2">Theoretical implication</head><p>This research contributes to the extant studies in m-payment adoption, especially for Gen Z, which is still limited in Indonesia. The results regarding the influence of all determinants on Gen Z-er's intention toward m-payment usage are considered new findings. Moreover, only a few authors examined the significance of promotional activities on users' intention to accept m-payment <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Wei et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Wang and Dai, 2020)</ref>. There are also new findings related to the moderating factors of gender and education, as presented in Table <ref type="table">8</ref>.</p><p>Instead of new findings, this study also presents inconsistent results with the existing literature. While <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Wei et al. (2021)</ref> failed to demonstrate the influence of performance expectancy and effort expectancy on young generations' intention to accept m-payment platforms in Taiwan, this study shows both determinants become the strongest factors. Moreover, some authors did not support the findings that social influence has a positive effect on users' intention toward m-payment acceptance <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Moorthy et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Gupta and Arora, 2019)</ref>. Finally, the finding that perceived security significantly affects Gen Z-er's intention to use m-payment is not in line with the research conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Jin et al. (2020)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3">Practical implication</head><p>This study provides a comprehensive understanding of the factors influencing Gen Z-ers to use m-payment systems. The findings can be used by m-payment service providers to create strategic regulations to attract more users to accept m-payment platforms. The results show that all determinants directly affect behavioral intention toward m-payment usage. Because performance expectancy becomes the strongest factor, m-payment service providers are encouraged to keep improving and promoting the useful features of m-payment as the best marketing strategy to boost the number of Gen Z customers using m-payment systems.</p><p>The following practical contributions are related to the other influential determinants and moderating effects results. First, with regard to effort expectancy, m-payment service providers need to continuously enhance the m-payment application's user interface by following the standard guidelines to lead prospective Gen Z customers to accept m-payment. Second, related to social influence and moderating effect of gender, m-payment service providers are suggested to create some approaches that take advantage of the social network to advertise m-payment systems by more focusing on female Gen Z customers. Third, associated with promotional activities and the moderating effect of gender, m-payment service providers are recommended to develop attractive promotions more specifically to male Gen Z customers by offering discounts and incentives. Finally, regarding perceived security and the moderating effect of education, m-payment service providers should actively advertise the safety of m-payment systems and provide 24/7 responsive help support, especially for low-educated Gen Z customers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Conclusion, limitations and future studies</head><p>This research aims to investigate the determinants that influence Gen Z customers in Indonesia to use m-payment. The proposed theoretical model was initially developed based on the extended UTAUT model consisting of six determinants: performance expectancy, JSTPM effort expectancy, facilitation conditions, social influence, perceived security and promotional activities. However, after conducting the first iteration of CFA, facilitating conditions must be eliminated from the model, so five determinants remain. The SEM analysis results show that all determinants positively affect Gen Z customers' intention to accept m-payment, with performance expectancy becoming the strongest factor. The findings strengthen the research from <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Francis and Hoefel (2018)</ref> and Annie Foundation (2021), which confirmed that Gen Z-ers always put security as their top priority and can be categorized as smart customers. With regard to the moderating factors, the results declare that gender significantly moderates the relationship between two determinants: social influence and promotional activities on behavioral intention. In addition, the finding proves the significance of education on the direct effect between perceived security and behavioral intention. The highlighted results are expected to give practical contributions to all stakeholders as guidelines for developing a successful m-payment application, especially for countries having more Gen Z-ers.</p><p>However, this study is associated with some limitations. First, the study is restricted to the Indonesian Gen Z m-payment customers. Future research may be done in other countries to improve the generalizability of the results. Second, the result failed to show the significance of facilitating conditions on the customer's intention to use m-payment, as reported in many prior studies. Thus, future studies need to retest the effect of this construct. Third, this study primarily focuses on the adoption of m-payment platforms provided by non-bank. Future research may explore the m-payment acceptance using bank service providers. Fourth, future research may add other variables to the theoretical model to enhance the explanatory power. Lastly, to complement the research findings, future research should investigate the Gen Z-ers' switching intention toward m-payment usage using a qualitative approach.  HTML  PDF (633 KB)</p><p>The effect of cultural orientations (performance and sociality) on country innovation: a trajectories analysis perspective</p><p>Agustin Ramirrez-Urraya, Diana Escandon-Barbosa, Jairo Salas</p><p>This study aims to analyze the e�ects of cultural orientations (performance and sociality) on the trajectories of innovation inputs and their results in di�erent…</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">DOWNLOADS  26  HTML  PDF (350 KB)</formula><p>Weather index insurance viability in mitigation of climate change impact risk: a systematic review and future agenda</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pankaj Singh</head><p>The purpose of the present paper is to review studies on weather index-insurance as a tool to manage the climate change impact risk on farmers and to explore the study… The purpose of this paper is to evaluate the green building certi�cation systems. In doing so, a validation process, using con�rmatory factor analysis (CFA), was undertaken.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DOWNLOADS</head><p> 314</p><p> HTML  PDF (827 KB)</p><p>Monetization of customer futures through machine learning and artificial intelligence based persuasive technologies</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Som Sekhar Bhattacharyya</head><p>The purpose of this study was to ascertain how real options investment perspective could be applied towards monetization of customer futures through the deployment of… The impact of the digital economy paradigm on the productivity and monetary system of Oman Faris ALshubiri, Amina Ahmed ALmaashani, Sharqoof Musallam Thuaar </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>BI = Behavioral intention, EE = Effort expectancy, FC = Facilitating condition, IU = Intention to use, PU = Perceived usefulness, PEU = Perceived ease of use, PI = Personal innovativeness, PT = Perceived trust, Personal security, PR = Perceived risk, PE = Performance expectancy, PC = Perceived cost, SN = Subjective norms, SI = Social influence JSTPM 3. Theoretical model and hypotheses development 3.1 Hypotheses development</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 1. Theoretical model</figDesc><graphic coords="7,48.30,374.40,344.35,228.19" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Deviation; FL = Factor Loading; and n = number of variable indicator.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 2. Modified theoretical model</figDesc><graphic coords="10,100.18,423.16,344.35,179.49" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Result of hypotheses testing</figDesc><graphic coords="13,48.30,84.81,344.35,178.53" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>), Wei et al. (2021), Zhao and Bacao (2021), Wang and Dai (2020), Al-Saedi et al. (2020), Jin et al.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head> 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>An era of digitalization: mobile banking adoption in India Shweta Sharma, Manpreet Kaur Khurana This study aims to identify the critical factors that can explain the intention of customers to adopt mobile banking services (MBSs) in an emerging country like India… DOWNLOADS  55  HTML  PDF (583 KB) Social media marketing activities on brand equity and purchase intention among Chinese smartphone consumers during COVID-19 Jiang Shuyi, Abdullah Al Mamun, Farzana Naznen The world has been forced to implement movement restriction strategy because of the COVID-19 pandemic, and industries have to embrace online technologies and social media… DOWNLOADS  57  HTML  PDF (405 KB) Customer acceptance of online delivery platform during the COVID-19 pandemic: the case of Brunei Darussalam Mohammad Nabil Almunawar, Muhammad Anshari As a result of the COVID-19 pandemic, numerous businesses have migrated to an online delivery platform (ODP) to survive and reconnect with their customers. This study aims… DOWNLOADS  118  HTML  PDF (394 KB) Modelling the intention and adoption of cashless payment methods among the young adults in Malaysia Uma Thevi Munikrishnan, Abdullah Al Mamun, Nicole Kok Sue Xin, Ham Siu Chian, Farzana Naznen Cashless payment is gradually replacing physical currency in almost every �nancial transaction across the world. Even though cashless payment methods have been available… DOWNLOADS  118  HTML  PDF (356 KB) Toward a model for assessing smart hospital readiness within the Industry 4.0 paradigm Mohammad Hossein Ronaghi The fourth industrial revolution and digital transformation have caused paradigm changes in the procedures of goods production  Journal of Science and Technology Policy Management | Emerald Insight https://www.emerald.com/insight/publication/issn/2053-4620</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The bane of P2P lending: credit scoring governance on the ASEAN fintech triumvirate Dini Rosdini, Ersa Tri Wahyuni, Prima Yusi Sari This study aims to explore credit scoring regulations, governance, variables and methods used by peer-to-peer (P2P) lending platforms in key players of the Association of… Journal of Science and Technology Policy Management | Emerald Insight https://www.emerald.com/insight/publication/issn/2053-4620#earlycite 3 of 19 11/14/2022, 11:50 AM Students' perspectives on using e-learning applications and technology during the COVID-19 pandemic in Indonesian higher education Sevenpri Candra, Florensia Sarlin Jeselin The e-learning-based approach is critical in keeping the wheels of education turning in the face of the COVID-19 epidemic. In this scenario, analyzing the implementation… DOWNLOADS  23  HTML  PDF (383 KB) Determinant factors of lean start-up-based incubation metrics on post-incubation start-up viability: case-based study Iwan Iwut Tritoasmoro, Udisubakti Ciptomulyono, Wawan Dhewanto, Tatang Akhmad Tau�k This paper aims to investigate the e�ect of business incubation metrics based on an adaptation of the lean start-up (LS) framework on start-up survival after incubation… DOWNLOADS  58  HTML  PDF (270 KB) Key performance factors for integration of Industry 4.0 and sustainable supply chains: a perspective of Indian manufacturing industry PRC Gopal, Punitha Kadari, Jitesh J. Thakkar, Bimal Kumar Mawandiya The purpose of this paper is to identify the key performance factors that can lead toward sustainability in the Industry 4.0 supply chains of manufacturing industries. DOWNLOADS  98  HTML  PDF (487 KB) Influence of digital government innovation on transformational government in resource-constrained contexts Njabulo Ndlovu, Nixon Muganda Ochara, Robert Martin The purpose of this study was to examine the in�uence of digital government innovation on transformational government. Journal of Science and Technology Policy Management | Emerald Insight https://www.emerald.com/insight/publication/issn/2053-4620#earlycite 4 of 19 11/14/2022, 11:50 AM A strategic framework to analyse the East Asian miracle within triple helix model -lessons for Kuwait Husam Arman, Sulayman Al-Qudsi This paper aims to propose a framework that combines the triple helix model with competitive strategies concepts to capture and guide any innovation-led national… DOWNLOADS  8  HTML  PDF (260 KB)Understanding the key drivers in using mobile payment among Generation ZLisana LisanaThis quantitative study aims to examine the determinants that impact the behavioral intention to use mobile payment (m-payment) among Generation Z (Gen Z) customers in Indonesia.DOWNLOADS  153 HTML  PDF (671 KB)A review of telehealth during the COVID-19 emergency situation in the public health sector: challenges and opportunitiesNtibaneng Hunadi Maleka, Walter MatliThe purpose of this study is to provide current state of knowledge on how the COVID-19 emergency situation necessitated the behaviour in�uencing use and acceptance of… DOWNLOADS  453 ALTMETRICS  HTML  PDF (324 KB) Student and faculty perceptions on an entrepreneurship course: an exploratory study from Oman Samia Naqvi, Maria Teresa De Guzman Matriano, Jamel Terzi Alimi Entrepreneurship-oriented courses are increasingly being o�ered in higher education institutions (HEIs) around the world. However, in the case of Oman, where this study… DOWNLOADS  44  HTML  PDF (882 KB) Empirical study on consumers' reluctance to mobile payments in a developing economy Manimay Ghosh This paper aims to investigate the e�ect of factors that inhibit adoption of mobile payments service in India.  HTML  Journal of Science and Technology Policy Management | Emerald Insight https://www.emerald.com/insight/publication/issn/2053-4620framework of the information behaviour of SMEs on emerging information communication technology (EICT) adoption Sunday C. Eze, Vera C. Chinedu-Eze, Hart Okorie Awa, Temitope A. Asiyanbola This paper aims to consolidate the state of research on information behaviour. Regardless of the scholarly surge on information behaviour using numerous models and… DOWNLOADS  48  HTML  PDF (496 KB) E-banking services and the satisfaction of customers in the Jordanian banks Asem Tahtamouni This study aims to discuss the main points in the dimensions of the quality of the electronic services to be considered in the future to adapt to future transactions and… DOWNLOADS  199  HTML  PDF (328 KB) Creating digital ecosystem for small and medium enterprises: the role of dynamic capability, agile leadership and change readiness Ardian Adhiatma, Olivia Fachrunnisa, Nurhidayati , Tina Rahayu The digitization e�orts for small and medium enterprises (SMEs) as a result of advances in information technology are challenging, with one of them being the creation of… DOWNLOADS  219  HTML  PDF (244 KB) Enhancing e-government with a digital twin for innovation management Muhammad Anshari, Mahani Hamdan The implementation of digital twin in e-government services will become the future of public service delivery. It has a great promise for signi�cantly optimizing… DOWNLOADS  95  HTML  PDF (741 KB)  Journal of Science and Technology Policy Management | Emerald Insight https://www.emerald.com/insight/publication/issn/2053-4620#earlycite 6 of 19 11/14/2022, 11:50 AM Renewable energy in Bangladesh: economic growth and policy perspectives Swati Anindita Sarker, Shouyang Wang, K.M. Mehedi Adnan, Prithila Pooja, Kaynath Akhi, Khadija Akter The purpose of this study is to see the energy relation to economic growth and �nd a way to solve the energy crisis for Bangladesh. Bangladesh is facing a high rate… DOWNLOADS  40  HTML  PDF (1.1 MB) What determines 3D printing adoption in the GCC region? Soud Mohammad Almahamid, Nehal Almurbati, Adel Ismail Al-Alawi, Mohammed Al Fataih The study aims to develop an integrated model for three-dimensional (3D) printing adoption in the Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC) context to form a baseline for more… DOWNLOADS  54  HTML  PDF (826 KB) Achieving an agile organisation in an Indonesian telecommunications company: investigation on leadership impact and mediation variables Ade Irma Susanty, Eko Budiharjo, Wahyu Winarto Agility is an important characteristic that every organisation requires in today's competitive digital era. Telecommunications companies in Indonesia face various types of… DOWNLOADS  121  HTML  PDF (461 KB) Factors influencing the implementation of cloud accounting: evidence from small and medium enterprises in Oman Omar Ikbal Taw�k, Omar Durrah, Khaled Hussainey, Hamada Elsaid Elmaasrawy This study aims to investigate the factors in�uencing the adoption of cloud accounting (CA) in Oman's small and medium enterprises (SMEs). The research model is developed… DOWNLOADS  194  HTML  PDF (514 KB) Barriers and facilitators to adoption of e-learning in higher education institutions of Pakistan during COVID-19: perspectives from an emerging economy Muhammad Arsam Qazi, Muhammad Aiyaz Sharif, Ather Akhlaq  90 A decision support approach for financial policy measures selection Parisa Alizadeh, Maghsoud Amiri Business research and development (R&amp;D) is of critical importance for innovation and economic growth. The purpose of this study is to present an application of the… DOWNLOADS  18  HTML  PDF (660 KB) Industry 4.0-based enterprise information system for P2P lending K.S. Sastry Musti, Neeta Baporikar This study aims to deliberate and illustrate the overall peer-to-peer (P2P) business process, user requirements and design considerations under Industry 4.0 based on… DOWNLOADS  48  HTML  PDF (631 KB) Digitalization of the supply chain: transformation factors Ammar Aamer, Chelinka Ra�esta Sahara, Mohammed Ali Al-Awlaqi There is an increasing interest in the supply chain's digitalization, yet the topic is still in the preliminary stages of academic research. The academic literature has no… DOWNLOADS  446  HTML  PDF (537 KB) Cashless preferences during the COVID-19 pandemic: investigating user intentions to continue UPI-based payment systems in India Mohd Danish Kirmani, Md. Asadul Haque, Muhammad Ahsan Sadiq, Faiz Hasan This study aims to examine the factors in�uencing user satisfaction with uni�ed payment interface (UPI)-based payment systems during the COVID-19 pandemic in India. The… DOWNLOADS  160 HTML  PDF (467 KB)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>method study on the barriers of industry 4.0 adoption in the Indonesian SMEs manufacturing supply chains Yudi Fernando, Ika Sari Wahyuni-T.D., Anderes Gui, Ridho Bramulya Ikhsan, Fineke Mergeresa, Yuvaraj Ganesan This paper aims to investigate the adoption barriers of Industry 4.0 in the Indonesian manufacturing supply chains. in the Post COVID-19 New-Normal and Role of Smart Technologies in Transforming Business: a Review Pragati Agarwal, Sanjeev Swami, Sunita Kumari Malhotra The purpose of this paper is to give an overview of arti�cial intelligence (AI) and other AI-enabled technologies and to describe how COVID-19 a�ects various industries… DOWNLOADS  936  HTML  PDF (797 KB) The changing activities of business incubation clients: an Irish case study Simon Stephens, Roisin M. Lyons This paper presents a conceptual framework based on a literature review and the �ndings from an empirical study using data collected from entrepreneurs (business…  HTML  Journal of Science and Technology Policy Management | Emerald Insight https://www.emerald.com/insight/publication/issn/2053-4620Exploring the experts' perceptions of barriers to using internet of things for chronic disease management in Iran Mehdi Dadkhah, Mohammad Mehraeen, Fariborz Rahimnia, Khalil Kimiafar Internet of things (IoT) promises advantages in di�erent sectors, especially the health-care sector. Due to its capabilities for chronic disease management, IoT has… DOWNLOADS  57  HTML  PDF (435 KB) Survey analysis for the adoption of 3D printing technology: consumers' perspective Maria Mavri, Evgenia Fronimaki, Athanasia Kadre� Although the adoption of 3D printing technology in many sectors such as medicine, aerospace, jewelry and the food industry is remarkable, the adoption of 3D printing… DOWNLOADS  216  HTML  PDF (2.1 MB) Strategies for risk management in adopting Industry 4.0 concept in manufacturing industries Bhaveshkumar Nandanram Pasi, Subhash K. Mahajan, Santosh B. Rane This paper aims to concentrate on classifying and analyzing the risks associated with the Industry 4.0 (I4.0) concept in manufacturing industries and developing strategies… DOWNLOADS  103  HTML  PDF (990 KB) Deficiencies in China's innovation systems for coal-bed methane development: comparison with the USA Philip Andrews-Speed, Xiangyang Xu, Dingfei Jie, Siyuan Chen, Mohammad Usman Zia This paper aims to identify the factors that are constraining technological innovation to support the development of coalbed methane in China. DOWNLOADS  360  HTML  PDF (391 KB)  110 A bibliometric evaluation and critical review of the smart city concept -making a case for social equity Chigozie Collins Okafor, Clinton Aigbavboa, Wellington Didibhuku Thwala This study aims to promote the idea that social equity is a signi�cant objective that needs to be achieved to attain a smart city and further reveal the current research… DOWNLOADS  198  HTML  PDF (1.5 MB) Assessing patient readiness for a patient portal implementation in the UAE Jamil Razmak This paper proposes a Web-based patient portal based on the electronic medical record. Such a portal can allow patients to manage their own health care, reduce health-care… DOWNLOADS  79  HTML  PDF (856 KB) Grassroots innovations and sustainable energy use in urban contexts: case studies from India Hemant Kumar, Gautam Sharma Grassroots innovations, developed by local people using locally available resources, have shown the potential to provide low-cost technological solutions to the problems… DOWNLOADS  49  HTML  PDF (198 KB) Innovation models and interdisciplinarity in science, technology and innovation policy in Costa Rica Luis Diego Soto Kiewit, Bianca Vienni Baptista This paper aims to analyse innovation models and interdisciplinarity in science, technology and innovation (STI) policy in Costa Rica between 2015 and 2021. The core focus… DOWNLOADS  137  HTML  PDF (261 KB) Integration of UTAUT model in Thailand cashless payment system adoption: the mediating role of perceived risk and trust Kanokkarn Snae Namahoot, Viphasiri Jantasri  Journal of Science and Technology Policy Management | Emerald Insight https://www.emerald.com/insight/publication/issn/2053-4620#earlycite 13 of 19 11/14/2022, 11:50 AM The purpose of this paper is to propose a model that examines the relationships among the �ve dimensions of the uni�ed theory of acceptance and use of technology (UTAUT… DOWNLOADS  756  HTML  PDF (758 KB) Designing a multi-division model of national innovation capability promotion based on social network analysis Mohammad Ali Torabandeh, Behrouz Dorri, Masood Rabieh, Ali Reza Motameni This study aims to design a national innovation capability appraisal model. This would indicate Iran's competitiveness situation among regional countries and suggest… DOWNLOADS  110 HTML  PDF (1.8 MB)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Digitalisation has become closely related to various economic sectors in terms of economic impact and discovery of new technologies. In this regard, this study aims to… DOWNLOADS  99  HTML  PDF (909 KB) Can government financial support enhance job creations: insights from Oman Abdullah Mohammed Al Shukaili, Kawther Al Kindi, Norizan Mohd Kassim, Zunaith Ahmed, Khdija Al Hosni Promoting and supporting entrepreneurship is a critical pillar of Oman's vision 2040. The need to understand to what extent the e�ectiveness of public funds given to… DOWNLOADS  94  HTML  PDF (286 KB) ICT-enabled organisational flexibility to support sustainable growth in Europe amidst a pandemic Renata Slabe-Erker, Kaja Primc Information and communications technology (ICT) is helping to create a sustainable information society and foster development. This study aims to investigate the… DOWNLOADS  874  HTML  PDF (401 KB)  Innovating with government digital platforms in low-income countries: the dynamic capabilities of Woredas in Ethiopia Debas Senshaw, Hossana Twinomurinzi This paper aims to identify the dynamic capabilities of government organisations in Woredas of Ethiopia that digitally innovate on the existing government digital… DOWNLOADS  235  HTML  PDF (1.8 MB) State, institutional entrepreneurship and the creation of the biopharmaceutical industry in a developing country Ali Babaee, Ali N. Mashayekhi, Rouholah HamidiMotlagh This study aims to explore the emergence and development of new industries, especially in the context of developing countries, by considering industry emergence and… DOWNLOADS  42  HTML  PDF (440 KB) User trends of electronic payment systems adoption in developing countries: an empirical analysis Mohmed Y. Mohmed Al-Sabaawi, Ali Abdulfattah Alshaher, M.A. Alsalem Electronic payment (e-payment) systems literature analysis reveals that they are growing in developing countries; however, they are limited in the Arab countries and, more… DOWNLOADS  713  HTML  PDF (1.1 MB) Study of awareness, adoption and experience of telemedicine technology services; perspectives during coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic crisis and associated economic lockdown in India Som Sekhar Bhattacharyya, Prasad Vidyasagar Mandke The purpose of this paper is to study the phenomenon of abrupt shift by both doctors and patients to telemedicine during the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic and associated… DOWNLOADS  246  HTML  PDF (712 KB) Drivers and outcomes of green information technology adoption in service organizations: an evidence from emerging economy context Samar Mouakket, Mohamed Aboelmaged This paper aims to examine the technology-organization-environment (TOE) predictors of green information technology adoption in an emerging economy, namely, the United…  HTML  Journal of Science and Technology Policy Management | Emerald Insight https://www.emerald.com/insight/publication/issn/2053-4620Evaluation of sustainable supply chain risk: evidence from the Iranian food industry Yasamin Tavakoli Haji Abadi, Soroush Avakh Darestani The food industry is directly related to the health of humans and society and also that little attention has been paid to the assessment of sustainable supply chain risk… DOWNLOADS  256  HTML  PDF (885 KB) Effect of private and public investment in R&amp;D on innovation in Mexico's biotechnology firms Rubén Oliver-Espinoza, Federico Stezano In light of the controversy between the theoretical importance of �nancing biotechnology �rms' research and development (R&amp;D), and the �rms' contradictory and… DOWNLOADS  47  HTML  PDF (234 KB) Impact of AI regulation and governance on online personal data sharing: from sociolegal, technology and policy perspective Sheshadri Chatterjee, Sreenivasulu N.S. The purpose of this study is to investigate the impacts of regulations and governance of arti�cial intelligence (AI) on personal data sharing (PDS) in the context of… DOWNLOADS  212  HTML  PDF (1.5 MB) Malaysian SMEs m-commerce adoption: TAM 3, UTAUT 2 and TOE approach Maruf Gbadebo Salimon, Olanrewaju Kareem, Sany Sanuri Mohd Mokhtar, Olayemi Abdullateef Aliyu, Jibril Adewale Bamgbade, Adekunle Qudus Adeleke The purpose of this study is to examine the factors that in�uence Malaysian Small and Medium Enterprises (SMEs) to adopt mobile commerce (m-commerce) by integrating the… DOWNLOADS  830 ALTMETRICS  HTML  PDF (1.1 MB)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="23,72.00,72.00,467.76,302.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="23,72.00,375.00,467.76,301.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Overview</figDesc><table><row><cell>of prior m-</cell></row><row><cell>payment studies</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Variables measurement</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">Variable (symbol) Indicator Measuring instrument</cell><cell>Reference</cell></row><row><cell>Performance</cell><cell>PE1</cell><cell>Mobile payment is useful to perform my financial</cell><cell>Gupta and Arora</cell></row><row><cell>Expectancy (PE)</cell><cell></cell><cell>transactions</cell><cell>(2019)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PE2</cell><cell>Mobile payment helps me to conduct transactions</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>faster</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PE3</cell><cell>Mobile payment makes me perform transactions easily</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PE4</cell><cell>Mobile payment increases my productivity</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Effort</cell><cell>EE1</cell><cell>I can easily learn how to use mobile payment</cell><cell>Zhao and Bacao</cell></row><row><cell>Expectancy (EE)</cell><cell>EE2</cell><cell>I can easily become skillful in using mobile payment</cell><cell>(2021)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>EE3</cell><cell>My interaction with mobile payment is clear and</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>understandable</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>EE4</cell><cell>It is easy to follow all the steps of mobile payment</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Social Influence</cell><cell>SI1</cell><cell>People whose opinions that I value prefer that I use the</cell><cell>Al-Saedi et al.</cell></row><row><cell>(SI)</cell><cell></cell><cell>mobile payment</cell><cell>(2020)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>SI2</cell><cell>People who are close to me encourage me to use the</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>mobile payment</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>SI3</cell><cell>People who influence my behavior think that I should</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>use the mobile payment</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Facilitating</cell><cell>FC1</cell><cell>My existing resources support me to use mobile</cell><cell>Gupta and Arora</cell></row><row><cell>Conditions (FC)</cell><cell></cell><cell>payment</cell><cell>(2019)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>FC2</cell><cell>I have the knowledge to use mobile payment</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>FC3</cell><cell>Mobile payment provides me with online assistance</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>FC4</cell><cell>Mobile payment is compatible with the existing device</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>that I use</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Perceived</cell><cell>PS1</cell><cell>Mobile payment is trustworthy</cell><cell>Lisana (2021)</cell></row><row><cell>Security (PS)</cell><cell>PS2</cell><cell>Mobile payment can protect my financial information</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PS3</cell><cell>Mobile payment can protect my personal information</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PS4</cell><cell>The security system adopted by the mobile payment is</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>reliable</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Promotional</cell><cell>PA1</cell><cell>I am interested in the cashback reward points given by</cell><cell>Wei et al. (2021)</cell></row><row><cell>Activities (PA)</cell><cell></cell><cell>mobile payment and the merchants</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PA2</cell><cell>I am interested in promotional offers given by mobile</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>payment</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PA3</cell><cell>Promotional offers provided by mobile payment are</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>reliable</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Behavioral</cell><cell>BI1</cell><cell>I will use mobile payment frequently in my financial</cell><cell>Wang and Dai</cell></row><row><cell>Intention (BI)</cell><cell></cell><cell>transaction</cell><cell>(2020)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>BI2</cell><cell>Given the opportunity, I continue to use mobile</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>payment in the future</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>BI3</cell><cell>I am willing to continuously use mobile payment</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Characteristics of</cell></row><row><cell>participants</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>ResultsThe result of R 2 is satisfactory, showing the explanatory power of the research model. The remaining fit results such as root mean square residual (RMR), adjusted</figDesc><table><row><cell>of CFA and</cell></row><row><cell>Cronbach's alpha</cell></row></table><note><p>Notes: Extraction method: Principal Component Analysis. Rotation Method: Equamax with Kaiser Normalization. Rotation converged in six iterations. Kaiser-Meyer-Olkin Measure of Sampling Adequacy = 0.880. Bartlett's Test of Sphericity: Approx. Chi-Square = 5,637.020, df = 210, Sig. = 0.000. Only eigenvalues of 1 or more are shown. AVE = Average variance extracted goodness of fit index (AGFI), normed fit index (NFI), incremental fit index (IFI), comparative fit index (CFI) and root mean square error of approximation (RMSEA) are good within their acceptable threshold limit.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Descriptive statisticsNotes: ** = statistical significance at a level of 0.01; ns = not statistically significant at a level of 0.05 or less</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Variable/Indicator</cell><cell cols="2">Mean</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell cols="2">Skewness</cell><cell>Kurtosis</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Performance expectancy</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.64</cell><cell>0.431</cell><cell></cell><cell>À1.006</cell><cell>0.051</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PE1</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.64</cell><cell>0.553</cell><cell></cell><cell>À1.222</cell><cell>0.517</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PE2</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.75</cell><cell>0.434</cell><cell></cell><cell>À1.152</cell><cell>À0.677</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PE3</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.52</cell><cell>0.598</cell><cell></cell><cell>À0.819</cell><cell>À0.312</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PE4</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.70</cell><cell>0.461</cell><cell></cell><cell>À0.852</cell><cell>À1.280</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Effort expectancy</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.72</cell><cell>0.381</cell><cell></cell><cell>À1.001</cell><cell>À0.578</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>EE1</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.64</cell><cell>0.490</cell><cell></cell><cell>À0.713</cell><cell>À1.188</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>EE2</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.74</cell><cell>0.439</cell><cell></cell><cell>À1.095</cell><cell>À0.804</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>EE3</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.77</cell><cell>0.421</cell><cell></cell><cell>À1.286</cell><cell>À0.348</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>EE4</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.76</cell><cell>0.429</cell><cell></cell><cell>À1.210</cell><cell>À0.539</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Social influence</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.02</cell><cell>0.766</cell><cell></cell><cell>À0.278</cell><cell>À0.942</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>SI1</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.00</cell><cell>0.858</cell><cell></cell><cell>À0.267</cell><cell>À1.017</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>SI2</cell><cell></cell><cell>3.93</cell><cell>0.851</cell><cell></cell><cell>À0.249</cell><cell>À0.821</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>SI3</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.14</cell><cell>0.786</cell><cell></cell><cell>À0.450</cell><cell>À0.677</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Perceived security</cell><cell></cell><cell>3.92</cell><cell>0.722</cell><cell cols="2">ÀÀ0.347</cell><cell>À0.396</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PS1</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.26</cell><cell>0.663</cell><cell></cell><cell>À0.346</cell><cell>À0.775</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PS2</cell><cell></cell><cell>3.82</cell><cell>0.843</cell><cell></cell><cell>À0.307</cell><cell>À0.501</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PS3</cell><cell></cell><cell>3.78</cell><cell>0.843</cell><cell></cell><cell>À0.240</cell><cell>À0.549</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PS4</cell><cell></cell><cell>3.89</cell><cell>0.804</cell><cell></cell><cell>À0.358</cell><cell>À0.324</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Promotional activities</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.81</cell><cell>0.315</cell><cell></cell><cell>À1.531</cell><cell>1.073</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PA1</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.77</cell><cell>0.421</cell><cell></cell><cell>À1.286</cell><cell>À0.348</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PA2</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.86</cell><cell>0.349</cell><cell></cell><cell>À2.060</cell><cell>2.255</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PA3</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.82</cell><cell>0.386</cell><cell></cell><cell>À1.659</cell><cell>0.757</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Behavioral intention</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.54</cell><cell>0.573</cell><cell></cell><cell>À1.188</cell><cell>0.669</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>BI1</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.71</cell><cell>0.513</cell><cell></cell><cell>À1.519</cell><cell>1.391</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>BI2</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.51</cell><cell>0.643</cell><cell></cell><cell>À0.968</cell><cell>À0.163</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>BI3</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.44</cell><cell>0.710</cell><cell></cell><cell>À1.039</cell><cell>0.316</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Performance</cell><cell>Effort</cell><cell>Social</cell><cell>Perceived</cell><cell>Promotional</cell><cell>Behavioral</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Variable</cell><cell>expectancy</cell><cell>expectancy</cell><cell>influence</cell><cell>security</cell><cell>activities</cell><cell>intention</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Performance</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Expectancy</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Effort Expectancy</cell><cell>0.564**</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Social Influence</cell><cell>0.364**</cell><cell>0.194**</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Perceived Security</cell><cell>0.223**</cell><cell>0.164**</cell><cell>0.229**</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Promotional Activities</cell><cell>0.350**</cell><cell>0.496**</cell><cell>0.168**</cell><cell>0.052 ns</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Table 6.</cell><cell>Behavioral Intention</cell><cell>0.499**</cell><cell>0.492**</cell><cell>0.353**</cell><cell>0.290**</cell><cell>0.374**</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Correlations</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Note: R 2 = the proportion of the variance of the variable explained by the variables that affect it</figDesc><table><row><cell>Model fit statistic</cell></row></table><note><p>2 : Behavioral Intention (0.463)</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><ref type="url" target="https://www.emerald.com/insight/2053-4620.htm">https://www.emerald.com/insight/2053-4620.htm</ref> </p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Corresponding author</head><p>Lisana Lisana can be contacted at: lisana@staff.ubaya.ac.id For instructions on how to order reprints of this article, please visit our website: www.emeraldgrouppublishing.com/licensing/reprints.htm Or contact us for further details: permissions@emeraldinsight.com Impact of innovation network on regional innovation performance: do network density, network openness and network strength have any influence?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Shuliang Zhao, Jinshuang Li</head><p>With the development of regional economy, innovation network plays an increasingly prominent role in reducing regional innovation cost and enabling information, knowledge… Industrial energy behaviour model: an analysis using the TISM approach Jayaraman Chillayil, Suresh M., Viswanathan P.K., Sushanta Kumar Mahapatra, Sasi K. Kottayil </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Janodia</head><p>The purpose of this study is to assess the intellectual property (IP) policy and innovation practices of higher education institutions    We use cookies to help provide and enhance our service and tailor content. By continuing, you agree to the use of cookies .</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developing a general extended UTAUT model for M-payment adoption</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Al-Saedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Al-Emran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ramayah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Abusham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technology in Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101293</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">What are the core characteristics of Generation Z?</title>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Annie Foundation</orgName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="www.aecf.org/blog/what-are-the-core-characteristics-of-generation-z" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021-01-20">2021. 20 Jan 2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Southeast Asian consumers are driving a digital payment revolution</title>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Boston Consulting Group</orgName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="www.bcg.com/publications/2020/southeast-asian-consumers-digital-payment-revolutions" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-05">2020. May 2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Validation in is research: a state-of-the-art assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Boudreau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gefen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Straub</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MIS Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fintech app revenue and usage statistics (2021)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Apps</forename><surname>Business</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="www.businessofapps.com/data/fintech-app-market/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-05">2020. May 2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generation Z&apos;s sustainable volunteering: motivations, attitudes and job performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bonn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sustainability</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1400</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Are consumers ready for mobile payment? An examination of consumer acceptance of mobile payment technology in restaurant industry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cobanoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shatskikh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Agarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hospitality Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quasi-Experimentation: Design and Analysis Issues for Field Settings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
			<pubPlace>Houghton Mifflin, Boston</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A critical review of mobile payment research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dahlberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ondrus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Electronic Commerce Research and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="284" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Intention of adoption of mobile payment: an analysis in the light of the unified theory of acceptance and use of technology (UTAUT)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>De Sena Abrahão</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Moriguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Andrade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="230" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>RAI Revista de Administração e Inovação</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defining generations: where millennials end and Generation Z begins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dimock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pew Research Center</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of customer behavioral intentions towards mobile payment: Cambodian consumer&apos;s perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Do</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Azam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Khatibia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Accounting</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1391" to="1402" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Crowded Indonesian market: 51 licensed e-money providers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fintechnews</forename><surname>Indonesia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://fintechnews.sg/44001/indonesia/crowded-indonesia-market-51-licensed-e-money-providers-in-indonesia/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-05">2020. May 2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating structural equation models with unobservable variables and measurement error</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Larcker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">True gen&apos;: Generation Z and its implications for companies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Francis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hoefel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>McKinsey and Company</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mallery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">SPSS for Windows Step by Step: A Simple Guide and Reference, 11.0 Update, Allyn and Bacon</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigating consumer intention to accept mobile payment systems through unified theory of acceptance model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Arora</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">South Asian Journal of Business Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gender and mobile payment system adoption among students of tertiary institutions in Nigeria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hamza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Computer and Information Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding proximity mobile payment continuance usage in Indonesia from a habit perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Handarkho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Harjoseputro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Samodra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B P</forename><surname>Irianto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Asia Business Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="420" to="440" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Country comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hofstede-Insights</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="www.hofstede-insights.com/country-comparison/indonesia/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022-01-20">2022. 20 Jan 2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Isnurhadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="www.xendit.co/en/blog/e-wallet-payments-usage-and-trends-in-indonesia/" />
		<title level="m">e-Wallet payments usage and trends in Indonesia</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021-05">2021. May 2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Determining sample size</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Israel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>No. PEOD6</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<pubPlace>FL</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of FL, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Tech. Rep.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consumers&apos; behavioural intention to accept of the mobile wallet in Malaysia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Seong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Khin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Southwest Jiaotong University</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The moderating impact of gender on the acceptance of peer-to-peer mobile payment systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Kalini C</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Liébana-Cabanillas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Muñoz-Leiva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Marinkovi C</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Bank Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="138" to="158" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Technological factors of mobile payment: a systematic literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Karsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Chandra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Juwitasary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Procedia Computer Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">157</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="489" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Principles and Practice of Structural Equation Modeling, 4</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>The Guilford Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>th ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determinants of mobile payment usage and the moderating effect of gender: extending the UTAUT model with privacy risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Rha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Electronic Commerce Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting the determinants of mobile payment acceptance: a hybrid SEM-neural network approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Liébana-Cabanillas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Marinkovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>De Luna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Kalinic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technological Forecasting and Social Change</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="130" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the determinants of intention to use P2P mobile payment in Spain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Jstpm Liébana-Cabanillas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Molinillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Japutra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Systems Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="180" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factors influencing the adoption of mobile payment systems in Indonesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lisana</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Web Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="204" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The acceptance of mobile learning: a case study of 3D simulation android app for learning physics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lisana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Suciadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Interactive Mobile Technologies (iJIM)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="214" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mobile payment: the hiding impact of learning costs on user intentions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Molina-Castillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lopez-Nicolas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>De Reuver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Theoretical and Applied Electronic Commerce Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What drives the adoption of mobile payment? A Malaysian perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Moorthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chun T'ing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Chea Yee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wen</forename><surname>Huey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Joe In</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chyi Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Finance and Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="349" to="364" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mobile payments marketgrowth, trends, COVID-19 impact, and forecasts (2021-2026)</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">available at: www.mordorintelligence.com/industry-reports/mobilepayment-market</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021-05">2021. May 2021</date>
			<publisher>Mordor Intelligence</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How inclusive digital financial services impact user behavior: a case of proximity mobile payment in Korea</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sustainability</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9567</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factors influence consumers&apos; adoption of mobile payment devices in Qatar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Musa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Alshare</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Mobile Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="670" to="689" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Neuman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Social Research Methods, Qualitative and Quantitative Approaches</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Allyn and Bacon</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>th ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mobile payment: understanding the determinants of customer adoption and intention to recommend the technology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Oliveira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Baptista</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Campos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers in Human Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="404" to="414" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">M-payment service: interplay of perceived risk, benefit, and trust in service adoption</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Amendah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hyun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Human Factors and Ergonomics in Manufacturing and Service Industries</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determinants of the adoption of mobile learning systems among university students in Indonesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pramana</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Information Technology Education: Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="398" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mobile payment adoption: a systematic literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pramana</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2021 3rd East Indonesia Conference on Computer and Information Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="269" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of demonetization on diffusion of mobile payment service in India</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sobti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Advances in Management Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="472" to="497" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Validation guidelines for is positivist research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Straub</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-C</forename><surname>Boudreau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gefen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the Association of Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="380" to="427" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effects of convenience and speed in m-payment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Teo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W H</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ooi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Yew</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Industrial Management and Data Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="311" to="331" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Indonesia e-wallet transaction to reach $18.5 billion in 2021 amid fierce competition</title>
		<ptr target="www.theasianbanker.com/updates-and-articles/big-tech-platforms-heat-up-competition-in-indonesias-digital-payments-landscape" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Asian Banker</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-05">2020. May 2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Infografis gen Z dominasi penduduk Indonesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Triyasni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="www.liputan6.com/news/read/4467203/infografis-gen-z-dominasi-penduduk-indonesia" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021-05">2021. May 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Generation Z: technology and social interest</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="113" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">User acceptance of information technology: toward a unified view</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Venkatesh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Information System Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="425" to="478" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring factors affecting the adoption of mobile payment at physical stores</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Dai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Mobile Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Young generation&apos;s mobile payment adoption behavior: analysis based on an extended UTAUT model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Luh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Theoretical and Applied Electronic Commerce Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="618" to="637" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A study of consumer intention of mobile payment in Hong Kong, based on perceived risk, perceived trust, perceived security and technological acceptance model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Mo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Advanced Management Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding consumer&apos;s motivation of adopting mobile payment systems for e-business in China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yunpeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jamal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Entrepreneurship Management Innovation and Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How does the pandemic facilitate mobile payment? An investigation on users&apos; perspective under the COVID-19 pandemic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bacao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1016</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2021. 2011 2013 2015 2017 2019 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
