<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Identi cation of driving factors of land, water, energy and food (LWEF) nexus resources: A perspective of environmental degradation in Gidabo Watershed, Southern Ethiopia</title>
				<funder ref="#_uJWkwJg #_mDhKdDs #_a3e5paG">
					<orgName type="full">International Cooperation and Cultivation Project of Nanjing Agricultural University</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Chinese Government Scholarship Council</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">CSC</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zinabu</forename><surname>Wolde</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">College of Land Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanjing Agricultural University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210095</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">College of Agriculture and Natural Resources</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Dilla University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Dilla</settlement>
									<country key="ET">Ethiopia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wu</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">College of Land Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanjing Agricultural University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210095</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Joint Engineering Research Center for Rural Land Resources Use and Consolidation</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210095</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Haile</forename><surname>Ketema</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">College of Land Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanjing Agricultural University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210095</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">College of Agriculture and Natural Resources</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Dilla University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Dilla</settlement>
									<country key="ET">Ethiopia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Eshetu</forename><surname>Yirsaw</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">College of Agriculture and Natural Resources</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Dilla University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Dilla</settlement>
									<country key="ET">Ethiopia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Habtamu</forename><surname>Temesegn</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">College of Agriculture and Natural Resources</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Dilla University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Dilla</settlement>
									<country key="ET">Ethiopia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Jinling Institute of Technology Eshetu Yirsaw Dilla College</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Nanjing Agricultural University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Nanjing Agricultural University -Weigang Campus</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Nanjing Agricultural University Haile Ketema Nanjing Agricultural Technical College</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Dilla University Habtamu Temesegn Dilla College</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">Dilla University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Identi cation of driving factors of land, water, energy and food (LWEF) nexus resources: A perspective of environmental degradation in Gidabo Watershed, Southern Ethiopia</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.21203/rs.3.rs-234895/v1</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T01:30+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>land-water-energy-food nexus, driving factor, indicators, degradation, path coe cient land-water-energy-food nexus</term>
					<term>driving factor</term>
					<term>indicators</term>
					<term>degradation</term>
					<term>path coefficient</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In Ethiopia, land, water, energy, and food (LWEF)  nexus resources are under pressure, due to population growth, urbanization and economic growth. However, the impact of these factors are less explored at local scale level. As a result, securing nexus resource is becoming a serious challenge. This necessitates identification of driving factors for sustainable utilization of scarce LWEF nexus resources. Our study provides a systemic look at the driving factor indicator that induces nexus resource degradation. We use Analytical Hierarchical Process (AHP) to develop indicator weight and Path Analysis Model(PAM) to quantitatively estimates the effect of driving factor indicators on LWEF nexus resources. The result indicates that, social (48%), economic (19%) and policy and institutional changes (14%) are the major nexus resource driving factor indicators. The path analysis result indicates that from social driving factor indicators population growth, and consumption patterns have significant direct effect on LWEF nexus with the path coefficient of 0.15 and 0.089, respectively. Similarly, the potential of LWEF nexus resources is also influenced by the institutional and policy change drivers such as outdated legislation and poor institutional structure with the path coefficient of 0.46 and 0.39, respectively. This implies that population growth and consumption pattern are the leading social drivers, while outdated legislation and poor institutional structure are institutional and policies change drivers which have potential impact on LWEF nexus resources degradation. Similarly, other driving factor indicators (environmental, economic and technological) also affect nexus resources with varying amount. The finding of our study show the benefits of managing identified driving factors for the protection of LWEF nexus resources, which have close link with human health and the environment. In order to alleviate the adverse effects of driving factors, all stake holders need to show permanent individual and collective commitment. Furthermore, we underline the necessity of applying LWEF nexus approaches to manage these drivers, and optimize environmental and social outcomes.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introductions</head><p>There has been a growing demand of land, water, energy and food (LWEF) nexus resources in the past half-century due to increasing population growth, economy growth and urbanization <ref type="bibr">(Al-Saidi and Elagib, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ringler et al., 2013)</ref>. Today, more than one a billion people are facing shortage of land, water, energy and food due to anthropogenic factors.</p><p>However, there are also natural factors (i.e., climate, topographic feature and resource distribution) that substantially contribute for degradation of nexus resources <ref type="bibr">(Imasiku and Ntagwirumugara, 2020)</ref>. This diminishes the capacity of nexus resources that perform essential function and services in ecosystem <ref type="bibr">(Abel et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr">Bakhshianlamouki et al., 2020)</ref>.</p><p>The concept of nexus has gained increasing attention in the research and policy making communities <ref type="bibr">(Ding et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr">Li et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">van Gevelt, 2020)</ref>. However, there was inadequacy to identify factors that affect pool of LWEF nexus resources which necessitates comprehensive study and critical reflection on existing nexus resources drivers <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Ringler et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">van Gevelt, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zare et al., 2020)</ref>. Identifying driving factors of land, water, energy and food are critical to provide useful information for improving the sustainable utilization of nexus resources <ref type="bibr">(Al-Saidi and Elagib, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ali et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">Imasiku and Ntagwirumugara, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Currently studies focusing on synergies between LWEF nexus resources and individual nexus resources driver from global, national and regional scale are being conducted <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Ringler et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Terrapon-Pfaff et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr">Weitz et al., 2014)</ref> and also on the individual nexus resources driver's from global, national and regional scale <ref type="bibr">(Laspidou et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mabhaudhi et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">Nie et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ringler et al., 2013)</ref>. However, the complex relationship existing among these nexus resources is making it difficult to easily understand the synergies between them and identify their drivers. This complicates the management and leads to nexus resources degradation <ref type="bibr">(Wiegleb and Bruns, 2018)</ref>. Therefore, understanding nexus resource drivers play essential roles for sustainable nexus resource management. However, the driving factors are not distributed uniformly across the region and varies with the patterns of geography, climate, economic development, social and political integration and transformation of the landscape <ref type="bibr">(Duan and Chen, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wang and Zhao, 2018)</ref>. This necessitates site specific action in terms of management which can be achieved by identifying resources driving factor indicators. These indicators are perceived by the public and used as simplified and aggregated forms to present information pertaining to a certain region <ref type="bibr">(Collomb et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Dale and Beyeler, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fraser et al., 2006)</ref>.</p><p>Results of various studies demonstrated that demand for productive land, water, energy and food is driven by common driving factors such as rapid population growth, urbanization and climate change <ref type="bibr">(Dibaba et al., 2020)</ref>. However, there are many other driving factor indicators affecting nexus resources especially at local level. Eventhogh the nexus resource driving factor indicators are varying on the basis of small geographical units, while studies conducted so far were focused at large scale <ref type="bibr">(Ding et al., 2020)</ref>. Hence the existing studies have not developed the nexus resources driver indicators from local level perspective, for which our study area is not exceptional. In the study landscape the existence of LWEF nexus and the prevalence of their drivers appear to be high and vary throughout the area as a result of multifaceted of land-uses, water, energy access, and food insecurity that had been causing the nexus resource degradation <ref type="bibr">(Dibaba et al., 2020)</ref>. Therefore, this study attempts to select nexus resource drivers in relation to the prevailing conditions in the study area and finally use path coefficient analysis to model the causal relationship between LWEF nexus and drivers. With this, the study intended to (i) identify LWEF nexus resources driving factor indicators that affect nexus resource (ii) explore the extent and trends of a driver on four nexus resources (iii) identify the direct and indirect impact of driving factors on LWEF nexus resources.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Material and Methods</head><p>2.1 Study area Gidabo watershed was chosen as the subject of this study to explore the relationship between land, water, energy and food nexus and its driving factors. This watershed is part of central rift valley of Ethiopia, where agricultural expansion and built up land is expanding rapidly <ref type="bibr">(Wolde et al., 2020)</ref>. The expansion of agriculture and built up in this watershed resulted in population growth and increased demand of productive land and water, energy, and food nexus resources.</p><p>In central Ethiopia, the main Ethiopian Rift, divides the Ethiopian highlands into northeastern and southwestern halves. This rift includes the Ethiopian Rift Valley lakes which occupy the floor of the rift valley, with different sub-watersheds. The Gidabo watershed is located from 6 0 9' 4'' to 6 0 56' 4''N latitudes and 37 0 55' to 38 0 35''E longitude (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). It has a peak of 3213 m a.s.l. and the lowest altitude is about 1171m.a.s.l. This watershed is bordered by the catchment of Lake Hawassa to the North, River Bilate to the West, river Galana to the South and Genale-Dawa River basin to the East, which considered as a potential livelihoods sources for Southern Ethiopia. The populations are settled more towards the eastern highland and the population density decreases towards the eastern low lands. There is more population around the eastern highlands and it reduces as one goes down to eastern lowlands. However, the population of the watershed has been growing alarmingly in the last three decades and currently it is more than 1.5 million. The upper part is more populated (&gt;500 inhabitants per square kilometers), and has immense impact on potential nexus resources. The livelihoods of the local community in the study area primarily depend on mixed farming and livestock rearing <ref type="bibr">(Ketema et al., 2020)</ref>, which are sensitive to land, water, energy and food. Therefore, due to the current nexus resource degradation by various driving factors, most farmers in the watershed live with lowest access to electricity, clean water and modern infrastructure and they are vulnerable to frequent food insecurity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Data sources and Techniques</head><p>This study focuses on driving factors indicator of LWEF nexus, which were identified from varied literature sources and deep survey in the history of nexus resources status. Additionally, data were collected from key informants and local community using combination of structured interviews. Secondary data sources were also used for validation of LWEF nexus indicators. Identification of driving factor indicators helps to have common understanding and to easily categorize which LWEF nexus resources directly or indirectly affected by driver.</p><p>The survey was conducted within four-month period from July 2019 to October 2019, following two approaches. First, expert interviews and focus group discussion (N=50) were conducted with respondents from natural resources, agriculture, water and energy sectors in order to characterize driving factors (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). Second, questionnaires were distributed to a total of 434 households, in order to find out how local community perceives identified driving factor indicators. To perform this, the respondents were asked to rank each predefined indicator impact on LWEF nexus from 0 to 4 ranking (4= extreme, 3= high, 2=medium, 1= low, 0= negligible).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Selection of LWEF nexus resources drivers</head><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Taherzadeh and Caro (2019)</ref>, driving factors are defined as driving forces consisting of different components that can affect societal change or natural system.</p><p>Understanding driving factors helps in identifying status, development and management of LWEF nexus resource to ensure equity and sustainability <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Terrapon-Pfaff et al., 2018)</ref>. The driving factor indicator is a variable that describes the status of the nexus resources and its impact on the availability, and distribution trends of nexus resources. In nexus resources management, a single indicator cannot efficiently describe a complex process that affects land, water, energy and food degradation <ref type="bibr">(Spiegelberg et al., 2017)</ref>. Therefore, indicators are combined to create a composite index to monitor the state of the nexus resources. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Sola et al. (2017)</ref> stated that environmental indicators may be considered as a simplified form to present information to a certain region. Therefore, in our current study, we consider nexus resources drivers' indicators to clearly understand area specific driving factors (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</p><p>The nexus resources driving factor variables were selected in relation to the objectives and the prevailing conditions in the case study area from relevant literature and discussed further with expert's. Finally, the researchers and expertise from the four sectors were organized in a group, to provide feedback on interim results of the factors affecting nexus resources. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> provides five main and twenty-five sub driving factors indicators and their explanation. To verify this result we computed multicollinearity for the entire identified indicators using Variance Inflation Factor (VIF) analysis. The finding of the analysis revealed that 22 indicators had strong correlation with each other and removed from the analysis the final result of the analysis shows that the computed mean VIF is 3.4 which is satisfactory to show there is no multicollinearity. Therefore, finally 25 sub-indicators were identified and categorized into five main driving factor indicators. Besides, we also defined each subindicator in order to reduce data-based multicollinearity, which can be removed using subject-area knowledge and factor in the goal, as reported by <ref type="bibr">(Graham, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Shieh, 2010)</ref>  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Analytical Hierarchical Process and Pair wise comparison matrix</head><p>The Analytic Hierarchy Process (AHP) and the Pairwise Comparison Matrix (PCM) were used to normalize indicators and establish the indicators weight from expert's judgment <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Thanh and De Smedt, 2012)</ref>.</p><p>The PCM is constructed by using scores that represent expert's judgment to compare and measure the importance of indicators in relation to all other indicators using Saaty scale <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Saaty, 2016)</ref>, in which the relationships are established using a scale ranging from 1 to 9 and their reciprocals using question "How important is two identified indicators to drive nexus resources?". Appendix table 1 indicates the result of pairwise comparison matrix of the LWEF nexus indicator computed using the following formula. </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">ğ¶ ğ‘£ = âˆ‘ ğ‘‹ ğ‘– ğ¾ ğ‘–ğ‘Ÿ n i=1<label>(</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Technology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lack of input supply TC1</head><p>Technological input supply increase productivity in agriculture, efficient water and land use <ref type="bibr">(Chang et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Chen et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr">Delucchi, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Gulati et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lawford, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lee et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">Li and Ma, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr">Orr et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Rasul, 2016</ref> the highest weight is computed for social, economic and institutional and policy change, while lowest weight is computed for environmental and technological driver indicator (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref>).</p><p>Computing composite weight of driving factor indicator provides a starting point for analysis and used as summary indicators to guide policy makers and other data users <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Thanh and De Smedt, 2012)</ref>. From social driving factors population growth (SC1), poverty (SC2) and lack of public involvement (SC6); and from institutional and policy change inadequate financial capital (IP2) and poor institutional structure(IP3) indicators have strong impact on nexus resources degradation (Appendix Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). Path coefficient can be expressed as standardized coefficient which is typically computed either by first standardizing all variables and then computing the path coefficients from the ratios of the standard deviation of the variable. Standardized coefficients allow direct comparisons of the magnitude of effects of two causal variables measured on different scales <ref type="bibr">(Chouksey et al., 2020)</ref>. A path model may look similar to multiple regression <ref type="bibr">(Maydeu-Olivares et al., 2019)</ref>, where an exogenous variable is analogous to a predictor variable and an endogenous variable is a response; however, the difference is that the endogenous variable can be both a predictor and response in a system of equation. An important assumption is that exogenous variables are measured without error, On the other hand, each endogenous variable is assumed to have error.</p><p>In path analysis, the correlation co-efficient is partitioned in to direct and indirect effect of independent variable (i.e. driving factors) on the dependent variable (i.e. LWEF nexus resources). In order to estimate direct and indirect effects of the correlated characters, let say ğ‘˜ 1, ,ğ‘˜ 2 and ğ‘˜ 3 as driving factor effects on n nexus resources, a set of simultaneous equations is required to be formulated as shown blow;</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">ğ‘Œ ğ‘›ğ¾ 1 = ğ‘ƒ ğ‘›ğ¾ 1 + ğ‘ƒ ğ‘›ğ¾ 2 ğ‘Œ ğ‘˜1ğ‘˜2 + ğ‘ƒ ğ‘›ğ¾ 3 ğ‘Œ ğ‘˜1ğ‘˜3</formula><p>(2)</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">ğ‘Œ ğ‘›ğ¾ 2 = ğ‘ƒ ğ‘›ğ¾ 1 ğ‘Œ ğ‘˜1ğ‘˜2 + ğ‘ƒ ğ‘›ğ¾ 2 + ğ‘ƒ ğ‘›ğ¾ 3 ğ‘Œ ğ‘˜2ğ‘˜3 (3) ğ‘Œ ğ‘›ğ¾ 2 = ğ‘ƒ ğ‘›ğ¾ 1 ğ‘Œ ğ‘˜1ğ‘˜3 + ğ‘ƒ ğ‘›ğ¾ 3 ğ‘Œ ğ‘˜2ğ‘˜3 + ğ‘ƒ ğ‘›ğ¾ 3 (4)</formula><p>Where, ğ‘ƒ denotes path coefficients, ğ‘Œ denotes simple correlation co-efficient. The total correlation between ğ‘˜ 1 and n is thus partitioned as follows ;</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">ğ‘ƒ ğ‘›ğ‘˜ 1 = the direct effect of ğ‘˜ 1 on n, ğ‘ƒ ğ‘›ğ‘˜ 2 ğ‘Œ ğ‘˜1ğ‘˜2 = the indirect effects of ğ‘˜1 via ğ‘˜ 2 on n, ğ‘ƒ ğ‘›ğ‘˜ 3 ğ‘¦ ğ‘˜1ğ‘˜2 = the indirect effects of ğ‘˜1 via ğ‘˜ 3 .</formula><p>Data processing was done by MS excel 2016 and Stata14 statistical package were used for analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Result and Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Analysis of land, water, energy and food (LWEF) nexus driver factor indicators</head><p>This section introduces main and sub-driving factors that affect one or more of the land, water, energy, and food nexus system. We identified twenty-five sub driving factors, which were categorized under five main driving factors. The results of the analysis indicated that from the five main driving factor indicators, social (48%), economic (19%), as well as institutional and policy changes (14%) are the major driving factors that affect nexus resources (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref>). Similarly, the average weight of the main nexus resource driving factor is also computed shows the same trends (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref>). The direct and indirect impacts of these driving factors are explained in the subsequent section. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.1">Social drivers</head><p>Six social driving factor indicators were identified based on the related literature (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref> indicates the path coefficient analysis result of sub-social driving factor indicators that affect nexus resources; population growth (SC1), poverty (SC2), lack of alternative livelihoods (SC3), consumption patterns (SC4), community awareness (SC5) and lack of public involvement (SC6). The result of path co-efficient analysis revealed that population growth (p=0.15), lack of alternative livelihoods (p=0.56) and lack of public involvement (p=0.15) had a positive direct effect on LWEF nexus resources (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>). Population growth also affects LWEF nexus indirectly (p= 0.005) which is mediated by consumption pattern, while poverty had a negative indirect effect (p= -0.16) on LWEF nexus which is mediated by consumption patterns (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>).</p><p>The result of path analysis in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref> revealed that community awareness (SC5) had positive direct effect (p= 0.096) on LWEF nexus degradation in the study area. This implies lack of community awareness in nexus resource management disrupts the planning and execution of nexus resources management. Since, it is important for the success and failure of resource management. The demographic development and characteristics in the study area has implication for high demand on the existing patterns of land, water, energy and food availability and strongly driven nexus resource potential. The rural and urban population in the study area has been increasing from 2005 to 2020, and also expected to increase up to 2035 with increasing demand of nexus resource (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>). This population growth may also increase levels of poverty which results in unwise land use, water, energy and food. The relationship between population growth and nexus resource demand is changing and becoming complex due to increased consumption (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>). It also shows the impact of urban and rural population growth on land, water, energy, and food nexus alongside socioeconomic and political factors. Such kind of population increase needs adopting an integrated method of monitoring the LWEF nexus for the studied landscape.</p><p>The current institutional setup and implementation of policies in land, water, energy and food nexus are still facing challenges in Ethiopia. However, it is the only option to restore degraded nexus resources. The country becomes the second most populated nation in Africa which needs additional food production, which could be obtained by intensive management of LWEF nexus resources. Karlberg et al <ref type="bibr">(Karlberg et al., 2015)</ref> showed that while on-going agricultural intensification require more use of energy, the energy required by the majority of smallholder farmers comes from biomass sources rather than centralized energy infrastructure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2">Economic drivers</head><p>An increase in nexus resource scarcity is linked with economic well-being. Low economic potential declines the quality and quantity of nexus resources which enforces human beings to deplete, convert, pollute or degrade nexus resources (Agboraw and Jones, 2017). Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref> depicts five economic nexus resource driving factor indicator. The weight of the driving factor indicator shows increasing income variability (EC1) and increasing WEF prices (EC3) are the dominant economic driving factors that affect nexus resources in the study area (Appendix table 1). The result of path coefficient analysis indicates that increasing income variability (p= 0.044) and increasing WEF prices (p=0.057) have positive direct impact on LWEF nexus resource (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>).</p><p>Regarding low capital (EC2), it has both direct (p=0.12) and negative indirect (p=-0.003) impacts on LWEF nexus resources (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>). This necessitates governments to set capitals to stimulate economic activity to meet particular sectorial development goal. The low capital, which is the characteristics of low economic potential have taken the brunt of the blame by causing unsustainable use of nexus resources which is caused by low investment.</p><p>Therefore, the identification of pathway of economic driver impacts on LWEF nexus resource degradation, which requires an understanding of direct economic driver and solving it through prioritization. To incorporate this understanding the pathway between LWEF nexus degradation and economic driving factor indicator need to be mapped (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>).</p><p>Increasing land value (EC4) indirectly drives (p=0.015) LWEF nexus resources which are mediated by increasing income variability (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>). The improper land use practices affect the availability of water, energy, and food which have environmental effects. This implies that due to economic development water and energy demand for food production is influenced by past land uses which in turn affect future land use. With this, the economic benefits of nexus resources by the local community have recently changed dramatically because wider forces such as overexploitation and unsustainable use permit them to do so.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.3">Environmental drivers</head><p>A critical challenge for the environment over the coming decades is the demand for food production within the scarce land, water, and energy sources (Cosgrove and Loucks, 2015).</p><p>Decline on those nexus resources will be risky for food production in the future than in the past due to complex driving factors.</p><p>Environmental driving factors have a complex character and they also exhibit different impacts on LWEF nexus resources. As pressure in the environment grows, the nexus resources might change; consequently, there might be an increase in the degradation process.</p><p>According to Rijal et al. ( <ref type="formula">2020</ref>), there may be different environmental driving factor indicator which selected in relation to the objectives and the prevailing condition. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.4">Technology as driver</head><p>Technological developments necessitate higher levels of productivity in terms of the use of land, water, and energy to increase food production. Technology can be expressed in various indicators, however, the current study identified four indicators based on expert's judgment and literature, such as lack of input supply (TC1), inadequate technology adoption and implementation (TC2), attitude towards technology innovation and development (TC3) and lack of infrastructure (TC4).</p><p>Based on the weight of the indicator, lack of input supply (TC1) is ranked as the most important technology driver that imposes LWEF nexus in the study area (Appendix Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</p><p>Lack of access to technological input supply results in unproductive use of land, water, and energy resources <ref type="bibr">(Kanianska, 2016)</ref>. However, the technological processes may also produce unwanted results, such as loss of biodiversity, ecosystem disturbance, increased deforestation which create a trade-off on LWEF nexus. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> exhibits TC1, TC2, TC3 have a significant correlation with LWEF nexus resources, while TC4 does not, which implies TC4 did not have a significant direct impact on LWEF nexus. Similarly, the path coefficient analysis shows that inadequate technology adoption and implementation (p= 0.198) reveals the highest magnitude of a direct impact on LWEF nexus resources, followed by an attitude towards technology innovation and development (p= 0.079) (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>). This implies inadequate technology adoption, implementation and low attitudes towards technology can limit proper use of land, water, and energy resources. Nowadays in Ethiopia due to lack of site-specific technology extension land wastage, irrigation water loss, and energy disruption are becoming serious problems in agreement with study of <ref type="bibr">Bezuneh et al. (2013)</ref>.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> depicts that the attitude towards technology innovation and development has significant indirect impact on nexus resources which is mediated by TC1(p= 0.001), TC2 (p= 0.818) and TC4 (p= 0.012). This implies people are causing environmental changes, notably in the biosphere, hydrosphere, and atmosphere which are associated with a lack of technology-based inputs supply, inadequate technology, and a lack of infrastructure. These changes are the result of human activities linked with time and space, leading to global environmental problems. In general, one of the major causes of prolonged environmental problems is a technology and how humans use it since it can be both source and remedy of environmental problems. It also plays a critical role as an instrument for observing and monitoring the environment on global and local scales, in agreement with the finding of <ref type="bibr">(Ferreira et al., 2020)</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.5">Institutional and policy change as a driver</head><p>Aligned institutional structure and policy help to utilize nexus resources effectively, efficiently, and equitably. However, to date, the institutional structure and policy to integrate and manage the LWEF system as one component in Ethiopia entangled with complex problems of relevance, quality, accessibility and equity <ref type="bibr">(Flintan and Tedla, 2010)</ref>, which results in land, water, energy, and food insecurity.</p><p>Even though institutions and policy are working on Ethiopian forests, in the last three decades, the forest cover of the country drops from 40% to 3% <ref type="bibr">(Gebrehiwot et al., 2014)</ref>. This is linked with unintended institutional and policy change which induce land degradation, results on WEF nexus insecurity across the country.</p><p>The causes of failure in nexus resources insecurity were linked with frequent institutional and policy change. These changes became LWEF resource drivers (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). Based on the literature review and consultation with expert's we consider outdated legislation (IP1), inadequate financial capital (IP2), poor institutional structure (IP3), and poor stakeholder network (IP4) as the common institutional and policy change indicators that affect the LWEF nexus.  <ref type="formula">2002</ref>) the nexus approach is becoming gradually prominent on policymakers' agenda at the global and national level. However, in Ethiopia, particularly, in the case study area, inclusive outdated legislation among land, water, energy and food sectors is challenging. This could be due to those sector applies different concepts and contrasting types of interaction from the budget allocation, management scope, and organogram. Such differences prevent shared understanding which manipulates LWEF resources.</p><p>The result of the analysis indicates that outdated legislation (p= 0.24) and poor institutional structure (p= 0.15) directly affect LWEF nexus resources (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref>). Lack of updating regulation and performing institution on the basis of time and resource use, with the current era of increasing population adequately disrupt the balance between resource and resource usage. Inadequate financial capital indirectly affects LWEF nexus resources through outdated legislation (p= 0.089) and poor institutional structure (p= 0.008). These results depict most programs, projects and activities did not aim to set in place the conditions under which local communities will be economically willing, and able, to conserve LWEF resources, results in nexus resource degradation by placing unsustainable demands on natural resources.</p><p>Poor stakeholder network affects nexus resources indirectly through outdated legislation (p= -0.026) and poor institutional structure (p=0.07) (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref>). In the last two decades many policies and projects designed in the current study area have not achieved LWEF nexus security due to poor stakeholder network. Lack of understanding institutional and policy changes as driving factors influences nexus resources consumption, regulation and management which results in negative externalities across sectors. The result of the path coefficient analysis revealed that economic (p=0.025) and social (p=0.011) driving factors had a positive direct effect on LWEF nexus resource degradation (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">8</ref>). This implies LWEF resource degradation often results from immediate causes such as economic crisis and unsustainable resource management practices, or with underlying causes including population density, poverty, lack of alternative livelihoods, and consumption patterns.</p><p>Institutional and policy change indirectly affect LWEF nexus resources by enhancing or reducing technological advancement. Similarly, social structure and characteristics need a binding policy in order to regulate unsustainable resource utilization activities that contribute to natural degradation. In the study area, there are losses of biological and economic productivity caused by the complexity of land uses, water, energy access, and food insecurity. This could be associated with rapid population increase, urbanization and climate change which will pose a huge pressure on the socio-economic, ecological, and livelihood of the local community <ref type="bibr">(Chung et al., 2011)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Socio-economic impact</head><p>Land, water, energy, and food resources are critical for the development and survival of societies <ref type="bibr">(Liu et al., 2017)</ref>. However, access to these resources is complicated by factors driving nexus resource degradation. According to Mohamed (2017), following the complexity of LWEF nexus resource, more than 18.1 million people in Ethiopia are forced for frequent nexus resource insecurity which will affect different socio-economic components.</p><p>The result shows that access/availability of food (34.6%), overall electric supply (26%), and poor health conditions (10.57%) are key socio-economic characteristics strongly affected by LWEF nexus degradation in the study area (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>). LWEF nexus degradation affects access/availability of food by 34.6% as compared with other socio-economic characteristics (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref>). This implies that land use change, water and energy crisis challenges food security under changing climatic conditions. Understanding sustainable management of land, water and energy is one of the keystones for establishing livelihood security, maintaining the provision of ecosystem services and adaptive capacity against nexus resource degradation.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref>). This causes the population in the study area to continuously depends on food aid, supported by USAID (MOHAMMED, 2016).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">Ecological impact</head><p>Due to resultant nexus resource degradation in the study area ecological balance was disturbed, which characterized by loss of biodiversity and migration of rural people to search for additional land, water and food.</p><p>Land, water, energy and food degradation also interrupts the regulating and provisioning services of the ecosystem, in particular through agro-ecological variations, climate change, forest loss, gully formation, soil erosion, loss of biodiversity, and drying of wetland <ref type="bibr">(Coates et al., 2013)</ref>. During our field investigation, the farming community reported that land use change, water potential reduction, lack of fuel wood, and declining food production was observed in the last four decades. Following this ecological variation in 2017 frost occurrence was observed in the highland part of the study area that affected the major livelihoods of the local community by declining productivity of crops particularly coffee and Enset (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">9</ref>).  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.3">Livelihood impact</head><p>The livelihoods of rural communities entirely depend on the availability and consumption of land, water, energy and food nexus resources, which directly or indirectly affect the livelihoods activities (Table <ref type="table">5</ref>). We used a structured household survey to explore how livelihoods affected by nexus resource degradation. Table <ref type="table">5</ref> summarizes the response of 434 households on how LWEF nexus degradation affects livelihoods.</p><p>As shown in Table <ref type="table">5</ref>, crop production (38.1%), livestock rearing (16.3%), and agroforestry practices (10.4%) were the major livelihood activities affected by LWEF nexus resource degradation in the study area. We are unable to obtain exact details about the size and extent of impacts during the interview. However, crop production and livestock are potential livelihoods are affected by nexus resource degradation. <ref type="bibr">Spiegelberg et al. (2017)</ref> reported that sustainable management of WEF nexus is one of the keystones for establishing livelihood security.</p><p>Beekeeping (5.29%), fishing (9.9%) and fruit production (7.5%) are also an important livelihoods activity affected by the degradation of nexus resources (Table <ref type="table">5</ref>). Therefore, LWEF nexus resource degradation hampered the livelihoods of rural communities and becoming a major challenge for sustainable development.</p><p>Most rural poor are smallholders practicing low-input agricultural production, which need a substantial amount of productive land, water and energy. Lack of these nexus resources could have triggered a reduction in food production, energy, and water access.</p><p>Energy insecurity is a significant challenge in the study area which affects the expansion of the school, health center, institutional structure and other. Furthermore, the lack of available land, water and energy affects small-enterprise by 12.5% (table 5), which is a source of income for the rural community.</p><p>Table <ref type="table">5</ref>. An overview of the livelihoods activities affected by LWEF nexus degradations which were assessed using household surveys (N=434).</p><p>Due to a combination of driving factors and human influences rural livelihoods are characterized by extreme uncertainty and seasonality of land, water, energy and food nexus resources, as reported by <ref type="bibr">(Wolde et al., 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Generally, policymakers in the land, water, energy and food sector need to gauge the influence of the driving factors on LWEF nexus resources in order to identify the problem and carry out effective strategies. In this context, the identification of drivers of LWEF nexus is essential not only for small geographical unity, but also for the sustainable management of basic nexus resource potential in the long run.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusion</head><p>Nowadays in accelerated global socio-environmental change the land, water, energy and food nexus has received increasing attention in academia and policymakers to restore nexus We argue that many nexus discourses focus on population growth and urbanization as a major nexus resource driver. However, these drivers were studied from a macro scale and growing megacities for the last decades, but the variability of these drivers from region to region was under looked at and needs policy attention. Therefore, this study focuses on understanding social, economic, environmental, institutional and policy change, and technology as a driver which induce degradation.</p><p>The result of the analysis indicates that in the study area LWEF nexus resources are significantly influenced by eight direct driving factors (such as SC1, SC2, EC1, EC2, EC4, EN3, EN4, and TC2), while other affects indirectly. These analyzed driving factors and their effects help stakeholders to better plan and design relevant policies to keep synergy and tradeoff for sustainable nexus resources management.</p><p>The finding of this study can also share experiences for nexus resources driving factor from local to a national scale, which can be of interest to the audience of nexus resource managers and planners to provide a better opportunity to reduce pressure on LWEF nexus resources.</p><p>Managing identified driving factor is essential to protect LWEF nexus resources which have a close link with human health and the environment. Addressing the adverse effects of driving factors needs all stakeholders to make a permanent individual and collective commitment which protect the environment and reduce the impact of driving factor on the environment and public health. Furthermore, we underline the necessity of applying LWEF nexus approaches to manage those drivers, in order to optimize environmental and social outcomes. For future research, different driving factor indicators and their impacts can be used to define benchmarks to identify the requirement of sustainable LWEF nexus for different parts of the country.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>21</head><p>Bakhshianlamouki, E., Masia, S., Karimi, P., van der Zaag, P., SuÅ¡nik, J. ( <ref type="formula">2020</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>31</head><p>Chen, B., Han, M., <ref type="bibr">Peng, K., Zhou, S., Shao, L., Wu, X., Wei, W., Liu, S., Li, Z., Li, J. (2018)</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>32</head><p>Global land-water nexus: agricultural land and freshwater use embodied in       The impact of frost due to climatic variability in the highland part of Gidabo watershed Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">10</ref> LWEF nexus resources degradation impact on ecological characteristics</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Map of the case study area.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,89.15,70.85,416.25,286.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>During identification and grouping of indicators, particularly sub-indicators, we tried to reduce overlap and mix up of sub-indicators to reduce multicollinearity of sub-indicators. During our field investigation, the local community choses 47 different driving factor indicators. Following this, a discussion was held among expert from agriculture, water and energy, natural resource and environmental management sectors to score and rank sub-indicator and categorize into the main indicators. After careful evaluation, the experts bring identified 25 sub-driving factor indicators.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1) where ğ¶ ğ‘£ indicates the composite value of indicator, ğ¾ ğ‘–ğ‘Ÿ the relative change index of driving factors indicators, ğ¾ ğ‘– and ğ‘‹ ğ‘– the weight of indicators. Then through further calculation weighting for criteria and indicators within each criterion was computed, as outlined by (Mabhaudhi et al., 2019). Based on the weight value of driving factor indicators,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. The weight of five main nexus resources driving factor indicators (EC= economic, IP= institutional and policy change, SC= social, EN= environmental and TC= technological drivers)2.5 Path coefficient analysis models</figDesc><graphic coords="12,165.65,257.13,264.00,207.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Main LWEF nexus resources driving indicator (Pol &amp; Ins change= policy and</figDesc><graphic coords="14,95.15,70.85,404.25,262.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. The social driving factor indicator (SC1= population growth, SC2=poverty, SC3= lack of alternative livelihoods, SC4= consumption patterns, SC5= community awareness, and SC6= lack of public involvement)</figDesc><graphic coords="15,92.15,112.25,411.00,233.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Population projection in the study area (data source: Central Rift Valley</figDesc><graphic coords="15,111.65,525.41,371.25,188.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. Economic driver indicator of LWEF nexus resources (EC1= increasing income variability, EC2= local capital, EC3= increasing WEF prices, EC4= increasing land value, and EC5= inadequate financial resources)</figDesc><graphic coords="16,76.55,443.42,442.19,251.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. The direct and indirect impact of institutional and policy change driver on LWEF nexus (Outdated legislation (IP1), inadequate financial capital (IP2), poor institutional structure (IP3) and poor stakeholder network (IP4))</figDesc><graphic coords="20,114.65,402.02,366.00,261.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8 reveals comprehensive model fitness statistics for five main LWEF nexus resources driving factors indicators. The result of the analysis indicates that except for institutional and policy change, other main driving factors directly affect LWEF nexus resources. Additionally, economic, social, and environmental driving factors also indirectly affect LWEF nexus resources.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8. The final comprehensive path model which tested how main driving factor indicator affect LWEF nexus. The indices of model fit demonstrated excellent goodness-offit (ğ‘‹ (6) 2 = 7.24, p= 0.31, TLI=0.99; NFI=0.92; RMSEA= 0.03) and all paths in the model are significant at p&lt;0.05</figDesc><graphic coords="22,108.80,112.25,371.25,216.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9. The impact of frost due to climatic variability in the highland part of Gidabo watershed Climate change caused by nexus resource degradation reduces ecological efficiency to supply productive land, sufficient water, safe energy and food (Figure 10). The study area has been subjected to drastic ecological change attributed to climate change, forest loss, loss of biodiversity and low agricultural productivity which affect the overall environment (Figure 10). The threats to ecology arise because of change in the quality and quantity of LWEF nexus which underpin all ecological processes (Wolde et al., 2020), and lack of stakeholders to invest in nexus resources result on low conservation of biological diversity and ecological integrity.</figDesc><graphic coords="24,76.55,236.44,443.25,249.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10. LWEF nexus resources degradation impact on ecological characteristics</figDesc><graphic coords="25,95.90,70.85,403.50,261.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>., Horion, S., Tagesson, T., De Keersmaecker, W., Seddon, A.W., Abdi, A.M., 6 Fensholt, R. (2020) The human-environment nexus and vegetation-rainfall sensitivity 7 in tropical drylands. Nature Sustainability, 1-8. 8 Agboraw, E., Jones, A., (2017) Economics and Natural Resource Constraints, 9 Resource Constraints and Global Growth. Springer, pp. 5-40. 10 Aggrey, N., Wambugu, S., Karugia, J., Wanga, E. (2010) An investigation of the 11 poverty-environmental degradation nexus: a case study of Katonga Basin in 12 Uganda. Research Journal of Environmental and Earth Sciences 2, 82-88.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>13</head><label></label><figDesc>Al-Saidi, M., Elagib, N.A. (2017) Towards understanding the integrative approach of 14 the water, energy and food nexus. Science of the Total Environment 574, 1131-1139. 15 Ali, M.H., Zailani, S., Iranmanesh, M., Foroughi, B. (2019) Impacts of environmental 16 factors on waste, energy, and resource management and sustainable 17 performance. Sustainability 11, 2443. 18 Amenu, B.T. (2017) Assessments of the Effects of Land Degradation on Freshwater 19 and Local Communities Participation in Essera District, Dawro Zone, South Western 20 Ethiopia. American Journal of Natural Sciences 1, 1-20.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>) A system 22 dynamics model to quantify the impacts of restoration measures on the water-23 energy-food nexus in the Urmia lake Basin, Iran. Science of the Total Environment 24 708, 134874. 25 Barbier, E.B., Hochard, J.P. (2018) Land degradation and poverty. Nature 26 Sustainability 1, 623-631. 27 Bezuneh, T., Hailemariam, S., Zeleke, G., Ababa, A. (2013) Science and Technology 28 in Ethiopia. 29 Chang, Y., Li, G., Yao, Y., Zhang, L., Yu, C. (2016) Quantifying the water-energy-food 30 nexus: Current status and trends. Energies 9, 65.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>33 worldwide supply chains. Science of The Total Environment 613, 931-943. 34 Chouksey, N., Mishra, G., Chouksey, R. (2020) Path Analysis in Rice Yield and Yield 35 Attributing Characters by Structural Equation Model. Int. J. Curr. Microbiol. App. Sci 36 9, 3098-3103. 37 Chung, E.S., Park, K., Lee, K.S. (2011) The relative impacts of climate change and 38 urbanization on the hydrological response of a Korean urban watershed.39Hydrological processes 25, 544-560.40Coates, D., Pert, P.L., Barron, J., Muthuri, C., Nguyen-Khoa, S., Boelee, E., Jarvis, D.I.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>41( 2013 )</head><label>2013</label><figDesc>Water-related ecosystem services and food security. Managing water and 42 agroecosystems for food security 10, 29.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>43</head><label></label><figDesc>Collomb, J., Mupeta, P., Barnes, G., Child, B. (2010) Integrating governance and 44 socioeconomic indicators to assess the performance of community-based natural 45 resources management in Caprivi (Namibia). Environmental Conservation, 303-309.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Figures Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figures</figDesc><graphic coords="36,28.00,74.29,416.62,286.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2</figDesc><graphic coords="36,28.00,429.35,264.24,207.94" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>Figure 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4</figDesc><graphic coords="37,28.00,367.05,411.37,233.46" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head>Figure 9</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9</figDesc><graphic coords="40,28.00,36.00,443.65,249.22" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="38,28.00,36.00,371.58,188.42" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="38,28.00,292.73,442.90,252.23" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="39,28.00,36.00,366.33,261.99" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="39,28.00,402.33,371.58,216.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>LWEF nexus resource driving factor indicators in the study area.</figDesc><table><row><cell>S/No</cell><cell>Main</cell><cell>driver</cell><cell>Sub-driver</cell><cell cols="2">Code Description</cell><cell>Literature</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">indicators</cell><cell>indicators</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>Social</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Population growth SC1</cell><cell cols="2">A growing population</cell><cell>(Barbier</cell><cell>and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">will increase the use of natural resources.</cell><cell>Hochard, Helmy, Imasiku</cell><cell>2018; 2020; and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Poverty</cell><cell>SC2</cell><cell cols="2">Poverty is increasingly</cell><cell>Ntagwirumugara,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">recognized as an important</cell><cell>2020; Mohtar and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">driver of forest which affect</cell><cell>Lawford,</cell><cell>2016;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">WEF system.</cell><cell>Pimentel et al.,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Lack of alternative livelihoods</cell><cell>SC3</cell><cell cols="2">Lack livelihoods leads to little of alternative stake in the health and</cell><cell>2010; Rijal et al., 2020; Wolde et al., 2020)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">productivity of natural</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>resources.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Consumption</cell><cell>SC4</cell><cell cols="2">Consumption</cell><cell>patterns</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>patterns</cell><cell></cell><cell>fairly</cell><cell>convincingly</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">explains the dynamics of</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">poor approach to natural</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>resources</cell><cell>and</cell><cell>their</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">resource use behavior.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Community</cell><cell>SC5</cell><cell>Ignorance</cell><cell>of</cell><cell>local</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>awareness</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">community knowledge is</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">becoming both limitation of</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>their</cell><cell>environmental</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">resource and consequence</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">of their using practices.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Lack of Public</cell><cell>SC6</cell><cell cols="2">Evolving technical and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>involvement</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">institutional measure to</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>prevent</cell><cell>over-extractive</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">resource use.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Economic</cell><cell>Increasing income</cell><cell>EC1</cell><cell cols="2">Natural resources provide</cell><cell>(Dogan et al.,</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>variability</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">important services to both</cell><cell>2020; Karlberg et</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">local on-site and off-site</cell><cell>al., 2015; Ringler</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">beneficiary, while most off-</cell><cell>et</cell><cell>al.,</cell><cell>2013;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">site beneficiary are "free</cell><cell>Tanner</cell><cell>and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">rider", this related with</cell><cell>Johnston,</cell><cell>2017;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">income variation.</cell><cell>Terrapon-Pfaff et</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Low capital</cell><cell>EC2</cell><cell cols="2">Lack of allocation of</cell><cell>al., 2018)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>sufficient</cell><cell>capital</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">investment for resource</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">rehabilitation and control</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">leads to degradation, since</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">capital budget provides an</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">important tool for the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">control and evaluation of</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>resources.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>)</figDesc><table><row><cell>Inadequate</cell><cell></cell><cell>TC2</cell><cell cols="3">In developing nations,</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">technology adoption implementation and</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">millions lack access to sanitation services and safe</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">drinking water, modern</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">energy sources and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">optimized land use.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Attitude towards</cell><cell>TC3</cell><cell cols="3">Lack of proactive attitudes</cell></row><row><cell>technology</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>towards</cell><cell></cell><cell>technology</cell></row><row><cell>innovation</cell><cell>and</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">efficiency, adoption and</cell></row><row><cell>development</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">implementation results on</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">unwise resource use.</cell></row><row><cell>Lack</cell><cell>of</cell><cell>TC4</cell><cell>There</cell><cell>is</cell><cell>growing</cell></row><row><cell>infrastructure</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">momentum to address</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">traditional and emerging</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">threats to the LWEF</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>resources</cell><cell></cell><cell>through</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>innovative</cell><cell></cell><cell>technology</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">infrastructure.</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The path coefficient analysis was carried out to estimate the direct and indirect effects of various environmental driving factors. Table2shows that industrial expansion (p= 0.326) exhibits the highest magnitude of direct effects on LWEF nexus, followed by climate change (p= 0.194) and agricultural land expansion (p= 0.172). These driving factors are considered as the principal factors that affect the LWEF nexus. In Table2fuel wood dependence had</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="9">negative direct effect (p= -0.038) and positive indirect effect on LWEF nexus which</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">mediated by charcoal production (p= 0.291), agricultural expansion (p=0.059), land use</cell></row><row><cell cols="8">change (p= 0.12), climate change (p= 0.066) and industrial expansion (p= 0.065).</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">As depicted in Table 2 the use of charcoal as energy sources had a negative direct (p= -0.038)</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">impact on LWEF nexus resources degradation, but it affects indirectly via agricultural</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">expansion (p=0.001), land use change (p=0.018), climate change (p=0.075), and industrial</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">Table 2. Path coefficient analysis showing direct (bold) and indirect effect of six causal</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="7">environmental driving factor indicator on LWEF nexus resources.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Indicator EN1</cell><cell>EN2</cell><cell>EN3</cell><cell>EN4</cell><cell>EN5</cell><cell>EN6</cell><cell>r</cell><cell>R 2</cell></row><row><cell>EN1</cell><cell cols="2">-0.038 0.291</cell><cell>0.059</cell><cell>0.12</cell><cell>0.066</cell><cell>0.065</cell><cell cols="2">0.712* 0.809*</cell></row><row><cell>EN2</cell><cell>0.06</cell><cell cols="2">-0.075 0.001</cell><cell>0.018</cell><cell>0.075</cell><cell>0.018</cell><cell>0.669</cell></row><row><cell>EN3</cell><cell>0.012</cell><cell cols="2">-0.304 0.172</cell><cell cols="2">-0.021 -0.009</cell><cell>0.089</cell><cell>0.876*</cell></row><row><cell>EN4</cell><cell>0.052</cell><cell>0.054</cell><cell cols="3">-0.060 0.147* 0.004</cell><cell>0.120</cell><cell>0.342**</cell></row><row><cell>EN5</cell><cell>0.290</cell><cell>0.038</cell><cell>0.021</cell><cell>0.089</cell><cell cols="2">0.194** -0.04</cell><cell>0.571</cell></row><row><cell>EN6</cell><cell>0.216</cell><cell cols="2">-0.053 0.048</cell><cell>0.073</cell><cell>0.006</cell><cell cols="2">0.326** 0.432</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">** values are significant at p &lt; 0.01; * values are significant at p &lt; 0.05, EN1=fuel wood</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">dependence, EN2= charcoal production, EN3= agricultural land expansion, EN4= land use</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">change, EN5= climate change, EN6= industrial expansion,</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p>Table</p>1</p>shows the environmental driving factor indicator that affects nexus resources. These factors are fuelwood dependencies (EN1), charcoal production (EN2), agricultural expansion (EN3), land use change (EN4), climate change (EN5), and industrial expansion (EN6). expansion (p=0.018). This indicates the use of charcoal as energy sources may affect nexus resources based on the extent of consumption; however, its integration with other factors may result in unintended impact. For example, land cover change induced by massive charcoal production affect land, water, energy and food production potential</p>(Li et al., 2020)</p>.</p>According to</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Sola et al. (2017)</ref> </p>fuel wood collection and charcoal production is the main land resources driver in sub-Sahran Africa, the same is true in the current study area.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Path coefficient analysis for direct (bold) and indirect effect of technology indicator as LWEF nexus resource driver.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Indicator</cell><cell>TC1</cell><cell>TC2</cell><cell>TC3</cell><cell>TC4</cell><cell>r</cell><cell>R 2</cell></row><row><cell>TC1</cell><cell>-0.299**</cell><cell>0.001</cell><cell>0.015**</cell><cell>-0.031</cell><cell>0.907**</cell><cell>0.907*</cell></row><row><cell>TC2</cell><cell>0.014</cell><cell>0.198**</cell><cell>0.002</cell><cell>-0.002</cell><cell>0.147**</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>TC3</cell><cell>0.001*</cell><cell>0.818*</cell><cell>0.079*</cell><cell>0.012</cell><cell>0.316**</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>TC4</cell><cell>0.04</cell><cell>-0.012</cell><cell>0.001</cell><cell>0.023</cell><cell>0.215</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="7">** values are significant at p &lt; 0.01; * values are significant at p &lt; 0.05; TC1= lack of</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">input supply, TC2= inadequate technology adoption and implementation, TC3= attitude</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">towards technology innovation and development, TC4= lack of infrastructure.</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Impact of LWEF nexus degradation on socio-economic characteristics in the</figDesc><table><row><cell>study area</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>In this study, we closely identified land, water, energy and food nexus resource driving factors indicators to show the concept of the current nexus resources trade-off. The analysis of the weight of nexus resources indicators shows that social (such as; population growth, poverty, lack of alternative livelihoods etc.), economic (increasing income variability and WEF prices), and institutional and policy change (outdated legislation) are the major drivers of nexus resource. This indicates a lack of understanding the social, economic, and institutional and frequent policy change induce LWEF nexus resources degradation.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="4">resource degradation. However, identification of nexus driving factor was limited and can</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">result in degradation of nexus resources.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Livelihoods</cell><cell>mean</cell><cell>Standard deviation</cell><cell>Frequency (%)</cell></row><row><cell>activities</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Crop production</cell><cell>23.75</cell><cell>2.97</cell><cell>38.10</cell></row><row><cell>Agroforestry</cell><cell>10.8</cell><cell>2.4</cell><cell>10.40</cell></row><row><cell>Livestock</cell><cell>18.95</cell><cell>4.98</cell><cell>16.30</cell></row><row><cell>Beekeeping</cell><cell>11.29</cell><cell>6.98</cell><cell>5.29</cell></row><row><cell>Fishing</cell><cell>13.21</cell><cell>6.18</cell><cell>9.90</cell></row><row><cell>Fruit production</cell><cell>9.05</cell><cell>4.78</cell><cell>7.50</cell></row><row><cell>Small-enterprise</cell><cell>12.24</cell><cell>4.03</cell><cell>12.50</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Cosgrove, W.J., Loucks, D.P. (2015) Water management: Current and future</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>challenges and research directions. Water Resources Research 51, 4823-4839.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_2"><p>Gooijer, G., Pettigrew, S. (2012) Regional options for addressing the water, energy</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_3"><p>control human population numbers in the future? Human Ecology 38, 599-611.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_4"><p>evidence from China's three regions with varied urbanization levels. Atmospheric</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>We are grateful to the <rs type="funder">Chinese Government Scholarship Council (CSC)</rs> for giving the first author a chance to pursue his Ph.D. study in China. The authors are also indebted to the thanks <rs type="funder">International Cooperation and Cultivation Project of Nanjing Agricultural University</rs> (Fund No. <rs type="grantNumber">X201915</rs>) which enabled to conduct this research.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><head>Funding</head><p>This study is funded by <rs type="funder">International Cooperation and Cultivation Project of Nanjing Agricultural University</rs> (Fund No. <rs type="grantNumber">X201915</rs>) and <rs type="funder">International Cooperation and Cultivation Project of Nanjing Agricultural University</rs> (Fund No. <rs type="grantNumber">X201915</rs>)   </p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_uJWkwJg">
					<idno type="grant-number">X201915</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_mDhKdDs">
					<idno type="grant-number">X201915</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_a3e5paG">
					<idno type="grant-number">X201915</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Availability of data and material</head><p>Not applicable</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflicts of Interest:</head><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethical approval Not Applicable</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Consent to participate Not applicable</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Consent to publish Not applicable</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Authors Contribution</head><p>Conceptualization, Z.W and W.W.; methodology, Z.W&amp;EY.; software, ZW&amp;HT.; validation, Z.W &amp;HT, WW and H.K.; formal analysis, ZW.; investigation, ZW.; resources, ZW.; data curation, Z.W, HK; writing-original draft preparation, Z.W&amp;HT.; writing-review and editing, Z.W and WW; visualization, ZW.; supervision, WW.; project administration, WW.; funding acquisition, WW. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Managing the food, water, and energy nexus for achieving the 173 Sustainable Development Goals in South Asia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rasul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rijal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rimal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Stork</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environmental Monitoring and Assessment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Environmental Development</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The nexus across water, energy, land and 178 food (WELF): potential for improved resource use efficiency? Current Opinion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ringler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bhaduri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lawford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environmental Sustainability</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">179</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="617" to="624" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The analytic hierarchy and analytic network processes for the 181 measurement of intangible criteria and for decision-making, Multiple criteria 182 decision analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Saaty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="363" to="419" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the misconception of multicollinearity in detection of 184 moderating effects: Multicollinearity is not always detrimental</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Shieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behavioral Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">185</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="483" to="507" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Multivariate</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The environmental, socioeconomic, and health impacts 188 of woodfuel value chains in Sub-Saharan Africa: a systematic map</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Cerutti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gautier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Iiyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schure</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chenevoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Dufe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environmental 189 Evidence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Spiegelberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Baltazar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P E</forename><surname>Sarigumba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Orencio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hoshino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date>190</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unfolding livelihood aspects of the 192 water-energy-food nexus in the dampalit watershed, Philippines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hashimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Taniguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Endo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of 193 Hydrology: Regional Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Multi-stakeholder 196 development of a serious game to explore the water-energy-food-land-climate 197 nexus: The SIM4NEXUS approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>SuÅ¡nik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Domingo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mereu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Trabucco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>SaviÄ‡</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Laspidou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Brouwer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">194. 2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">139</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Vamvakeridou-195 Lyroudia</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drivers of water and land use embodied in 199 international soybean trade</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Taherzadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Caro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of cleaner production</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">223</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">198. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of rural electric access on 201 deforestation rates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Tanner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Johnston</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="174" to="185" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energising the WEF nexus 203 to enhance sustainable development at local level</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Terrapon-Pfaff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ortiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dienst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-C</forename><surname>GrÃ¶ne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of environmental 204 management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">223</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="409" to="416" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">202. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application of an analytical hierarchical process 206 approach for landslide susceptibility mapping in A Luoi district, Thua Thien Hue 207 Province</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Thanh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>De Smedt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vietnam. Environmental Earth Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1739" to="1752" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Institutional Factors Affecting Land and Water Development, 209 Lower Rio Grande Valley</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>208 Trock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Texas. Water Resources Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1364" to="1366" />
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The water-energy-food nexus: bridging the science-policy 211 divide</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Van Gevelt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Opinion in Environmental Science &amp; Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Energy security issues in Asia, Routledge Handbook of Energy in 213 Asia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vivoda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="272" to="283" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
