<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Non-agency interventions for causal mediation in the presence of intermediate confounding</title>
				<funder ref="#_qxvdJ33">
					<orgName type="full">Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">PCORI</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2023-04-26">April 26, 2023</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Iván</forename><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
							<email>ivan.diaz@nyu.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Population Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">New York University Grossman School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>New York</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Non-agency interventions for causal mediation in the presence of intermediate confounding</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2023-04-26">April 26, 2023</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2205.08000v4[stat.ME]</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T18:27+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Recent approaches to causal inference have focused on causal effects defined as contrasts between the distribution of counterfactual outcomes under hypothetical interventions on the nodes of a graphical model. In this article we develop theory for causal effects defined with respect to a different type of intervention, one which alters the information propagated through the edges of the graph. These information transfer interventions may be more useful than node interventions in settings in which causes are non-manipulable, for example when considering race or genetics as a causal agent. Furthermore, information transfer interventions allow us to define path-specific decompositions which are identified in the presence of treatment-induced mediator-outcome confounding, a practical problem whose general solution remains elusive. We prove that the proposed effects provide valid statistical tests of mechanisms, unlike popular methods based on randomized interventions on the mediator. We propose efficient non-parametric estimators for a covariance version of the proposed effects, using data-adaptive regression coupled with semi-parametric efficiency theory to address model misspecification bias while retaining √ n-consistency and asymp-</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Statistical causal inference is primarily concerned with quantifying the strength of causal relations through so-called causal effects, which are defined as contrasts between distributions under hypothetical modifications to the data generating mechanisms. These hypothetical modifications are often called interventions, and the variables resulting from the interventions are often called counterfactuals <ref type="bibr" target="#b88">(Woodward, 2003)</ref>. Counterfactual causal effects can be classified into two types according to the interventions that define them: agency and non-agency causal effects. Agency causal effects are defined with respect to interventions that can be carried out in the real world, at least in principle.</p><p>For example, a clinical researcher may be interested in evaluating mortality rates in a hypothetical world where all patients are given a certain treatment, and compare them with mortality rates in a hypothetical world where no patient is given the treatment, resulting in the so-called average treatment effect. On the other hand, non-agency causal effects do not require that interventions are feasible.</p><p>For example, a clinical researcher may be interested in evaluating the strength of the causal relation between a biomarker and mortality through a hypothetical increase of one unit in the biomarker, without regards to whether or how this increase can be brought about. Analyses involving agency causal effects often have the goal of recommending one of the actions under evaluation, and are therefore of high importance to decision makers. This has led to some philosophers (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Menzies and Price, 1993)</ref> and statisticians (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Holland, 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Hernán and Taubman, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Hernán, 2016)</ref> to hold the view that causal inference is only useful if it evaluates agency effects,<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">foot_0</ref> although that view has been vigorously contested, both in philosophy (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b88">Woodward, 2003)</ref> as well as in statistics and related disciplines (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Glymour and Glymour, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Krieger and Davey Smith, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Daniel et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b81">Vandenbroucke et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Glymour and Spiegelman, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Pearl, 2018</ref><ref type="bibr">Pearl, , 2019a,b),b)</ref>.</p><p>In this article we propose a type of non-agency causal effect based on so-called information interventions, which are heuristically defined as modifications to the information transferred through the edges of a causal graph. This view of causality as transfer of information has been advocated in philosophy (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Collier, 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Illari and Russo, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Hausman and Woodward, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Malinsky, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b84">Weinberger, 2021)</ref> and has been previously used in statistics (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Janzing et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Schwartz et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Pearl, 2018</ref><ref type="bibr">Pearl, , 2019a;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Gong and Zhu, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">Pearl, 2019b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Gong and Zhu, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Schölkopf, 2022)</ref>, although causal effects defined using interventions on the information transferred along the edges are far less common than effects that use interventions on the nodes of the causal graph. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">2</ref> In order to distinguish between measures of causality defined through interventions on the nodes vs the edges of a causal graph, we use the expression causal effect to refer to the former and the expression causal influence to refer to the latter.</p><p>The information interventions we develop have roots in stochastic interventions (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Korb et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Robins et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Didelez et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Eberhardt and Scheines, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Díaz and van der Laan, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b91">Young et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Chaves et al., 2015)</ref>, which are defined as interventions where the nodes of a causal graph are intervened on and replaced by random draws from user-given distributions. Examples of stochastic interventions include incremental propensity score interventions <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Kennedy, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b85">Wen et al., 2021)</ref>, and interventions that shift the exposure distribution in an additive or multiplicative scale <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Díaz and van der Laan, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Díaz and Hejazi, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr">Díaz et al., 2021b</ref><ref type="bibr">Díaz et al., , 2022a))</ref>.</p><p>Although we use ideas from the literature on stochastic interventions, we depart from that literature in that we are not interested in intervening on the nodes of the graph, but merely use random draws from a distribution to aid in describing functional dependencies between variables in a structural equation system. We propose to use stochastic interventions as a means to define operations on a causal model that remove or emulate the information transferred by a node along certain edges of interest, while leaving the node unaffected. Measures of causal influence thus defined can be interpreted outside of an agency view of causality, as measures of counterfactual functional dependence. In other words, the causal influence measures we propose may be considered of a descriptive rather than a prescriptive nature in the sense that they unveil causal relations prevalent in the world, but do not tell us about actions that would yield different outcomes.</p><p>Non-agency interventions may be useful for studying causes that are non-manipulable or for which manipulations are difficult to conceptualize or of no substantive interest. A common characteristic of those causes (e.g., race, gender, genetics) is that their effect is often mediated by other attributes which are more amenable to manipulation by intervention. For example, the causal relation between racial discrimination and health disparities in the US population is mediated by socioeconomic factors <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">(Williams and Rucker, 2000)</ref>. Likewise, the causal relation between polygenic risk scores and individual traits or disease is often mediated by physiological or environmental processes that occur in childhood or adulthood. (see e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Elkrief et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b90">Yang et al., 2022)</ref>. Thus, the eventual development of feasible actions to bring about changes (e.g., to reduce discrimination or to mitigate genetic risks) requires an a-priori understanding of the intervening mechanisms. This understanding can be achieved using mediation or path analysis. Natural direct and indirect effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Robins and Greenland, 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Pearl, 2001)</ref> are a popular approach for mediation analysis, but they are not identified in the presence of treatment-induced mediator-outcome confounding <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Avin et al., 2005)</ref>. A solution to this problem which has gained traction in the applied literature is the use of randomized interventional effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">(VanderWeele et al., 2014)</ref>. Recent research <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Miles, 2022)</ref> has uncovered an important limitation of these effects, namely that they fail to satisfy the sharp null mediational criterion, meaning that the effect through the mediator can be non-zero even when there is no structural relation that operates through the mediator for any individual in the population. In this paper we demonstrate how information interventions can be used to define novel path-specific causal influence measures. We prove that the proposed measures have an important property that they satisfy appropriately defined path-specific sharp null criteria, meaning that they take their null value when there is no mechanism operating through the path under consideration. This means that the proposed path-specific measures of causal influence can be used to identify and estimate the strength of causal mechanisms, even in the presence of mediator-outcome confounders affected by treatment.</p><p>The paper is organized as follows. In §2 we introduce the notation and the causal model used in the paper. In §3 we introduce the novel measure of causal influence based on non-agency information transfer interventions. In §5 we discuss a path-analysis method that uses these interventions, and we prove that this method satisfies appropriately defined path-specific sharp null criteria, providing correct tests for mechanisms. In §6 we present a decomposition that uses information interventions to achieve a path-specific decomposition of agency causal effects, specifically the average treatment effect. In §7 we develop non-parametric efficient estimators for some of the causal influence measures proposed, and in §8 we present the results of applying the methods to two publicly available datasets.</p><p>We conclude in §9 with a brief discussion of connections to recent literature and directions of future research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Notation, data, and causal model</head><p>Assume that we observe n independent and identically distributed copies X 1 , . . . , X n of X = (W, A, Z, M, Y ) ∼ P. We use a Structural Causal Model (SCM, <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Pearl, 2000)</ref> to study causal relations. A SCM is a 4-tuple U, X, F , P , where U are exogenous variables, X are endogenous variables, F is a set of functions used to determine the value of X, and P is a set of allowed distributions on U <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Bareinboim et al., 2022)</ref>. The SCM used in this paper assumes the following.</p><p>A1. Assume that X is generated according to:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">W = f W (U W ); A = f A (W, U A ); Z = f Z (A, W, U A ); M = f M (Z, A, W, U M ); Y = f Y (M, Z, A, W, U Y ).<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where the functions f are deterministic but otherwise unrestricted. Furthermore, assume</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">U A ⊥ ⊥(U Y , U M , U Z ) | W , U Z ⊥ ⊥(U Y , U M ) | (A, W ), and U M ⊥ ⊥U Y | (A, W, Z).</formula><p>We simplify the presentation of the model by considering a single W with little loss of generality, but we could split it into several factors according to whether they are confounders of only some of the subsequent relations. We are interested in quantifying the strength of the causal relation between A and Y , and understanding the extent to which that relation operates through the various paths between the endogenous variables X. We illustrate those pathways in the causal graph depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">1</ref>. For illustrative convenience we do not depict the exogenous variables; correlations between them could be depicted through bi-directed arrows (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Pearl (2000)</ref> for the construction of a causal graph from an SCM). </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">A → Y , A → Z → Y , A → Z → M → Y , and A → M → Y .</formula><p>We refer to the former goal as mediation analysis, and to the latter as path-analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Measuring the strength of causal relations</head><p>The concept of causal influence is generally defined as the existence of a directed path between two variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Pearl and Verma, 1995)</ref>. A formal definition of the causal influence of A on Y in terms of the non-parametric structural equation model can be constructed as follows.</p><p>Definition 1 (Causal influence). For fixed a, let the counterfactual variable Y (a) be defined as the solution in Y of the equations (1) under the intervention</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">A = a. That is, Y (a) = f Y (M(a), Z(a), a, W, U Y ) with M(a) = f M (Z(a), a, W, U M ) and Z(a) = f Z (a, W, U Z ). The variable A is said to have a causal influence on Y if and only if sup a,a ′ |Y (a) -Y (a ′ )| &gt; 0 with positive probability.</formula><p>For binary treatments, the concept of causal influence as stated above is related to Fisher's sharp null hypothesis of no individual treatment effect H 0 : Y i (1) = Y i (0) for all i ∈ {1, . . . , n}. Recent approaches to causal inference have focused on quantifying causal influence through causal effects, which are usually understood as changes in the probability distribution of X under hypothetical interventions that modify the value of the variable A. In this paper, we propose an alternative way to quantify causal influence, using an approach based on intervening on the information transferred along edges in the causal graph depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">1</ref>. In general, we will require that measures for causality satisfy the following properties: While this criterion is trivially satisfied by many causal effects, it has been recently uncovered that it is not satisfied by widely adopted approaches to mediation analysis. In §4 we prove that our proposed path-specific causal influence measures satisfy a version of this criterion adapted to pathanalysis. Before we describe our proposed definitions of intervention on information transferred along edges, we review causal effects defined with respect to interventions on nodes.</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">P1 (Sharp null criterion</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Causal effects</head><p>A general definition of causal effect based on node interventions is as follows (adapted from <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Pearl, 2000)</ref>:</p><p>Definition 2 (Causal effect of a node intervention). Given a fixed value a, the causal effect of the intervention A = a is defined as a comparison between the probability distributions of the counterfactual variables Y (a) and Y (a 0 ), for a reference level a 0 .</p><p>As stated in the definition, to define the causal effect of A on Y one needs to specify an intervention to the node corresponding to A in the SCM (1). For example, consider an intervention that removes the equation f A from the SCM and replaces it with assignment to a fixed value A = a. The counterfactual outcome in this hypothetical intervened world is</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">Y (a) = f Y (M(a), Z(a), a, W, U Y ),</formula><p>denoting outcome that would have been observed in a world where, contrary to fact, A had been equal</p><p>to a with probability one. The causal effect of A on Y may then be defined in terms of contrasts of the distribution of the potential outcomes Y (a) : a ∈ A. For example, for binary A, a common choice is to use the average treatment effect ATE = E[Y (1) -Y (0)] as an effect measure.</p><p>The above definition has been generalized in multiple directions, for example to allow dynamic interventions that might depend on W (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Robins, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b79">van der Laan et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Cain et al., 2010)</ref>, modified treatment policies whereby the intervention might depend on both A and W (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Díaz and Hejazi, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr">Díaz et al., 2021b</ref><ref type="bibr">Díaz et al., , 2022a))</ref>, as well as stochastic interventions whereby the post-intervention exposure is a random draw from a user-given distribution (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b85">Wen et al., 2021)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Causal influence based on information interventions</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">A motivating experimental design</head><p>To motivate the definitions that follow, we fist discuss audit studies, which are a type of experiment to study discrimination common in social sciences <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Gaddis, 2018)</ref>. Although there are many types of audit studies, on a basic level they can be described as a research design where the experimenter prompts some type of interaction with the research subjects (e.g., a letter, a job or housing application, a diagnosis, etc.), randomly varying the attributes under evaluation (e.g., gender, race), and then assesses the behavior of the research subject. To ground ideas, consider the following examples. <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Shapiro et al. (2018)</ref> study implicit biases in periviability counseling among neonatologists caring for pregnant women by using implicit association tests <ref type="bibr">(IATs Greenwald et al., 1998)</ref>. The experiment consisted of showing different neonatologists a vignette of a woman in imminent labor, where the patient's race and socioeconomic status in the vignette were randomized. The neonatologists were then asked to indicate how likely they were to recommend comfort care vs intensive care, and the difference in recommendation across randomized races were assessed. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bertrand and Mullainathan (2004)</ref> performed a similar experiment to study the effect of perceived race on labor market discrimination, where they randomized racial cues such in the candidate's resume such as the name. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Cheng and Florick (2020)</ref> assess the value of study abroad experience in the labor market. Their experiment consisted of submitting resumes to job listings posted on a popular online job site, where other resume attributes are held constant but study abroad experience is randomized within job posting.</p><p>A key feature of all of these examples is that the intervention is performed on the information given to a decision-maker (clinicians, recruiters, etc.) rather than the causes (e.g., a person's race, socioeconomic status, study abroad experience), which are left unmodified. The definitions that follow can be seen as a formalization of the interventions intended by these audit studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">Proposed interventions on information transferred along edges</head><p>We propose to measure the causal influence of A on Y based on the impact on the joint distribution of (A, Y ) of intervening on the information transferred along all directed paths from A to Y in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">1</ref>.</p><p>We first define an intervention where no information is transferred along any of these paths. Specifically, let A denote a noise variable defined as a random draw from the distribution of A conditional on W . Note that in some applications it may be more reasonable to define A as a random draw from the conditional distribution of A given a subset of V ⊆ W . In the interest of simplifying notation we pursue a definition based on a random draw conditional on W .</p><p>To remove the information transferred along all paths between A and Y , one possibility is to transfer noise along the edges in S = {A → Y, A → M, A → Z}. which corresponds to the following data generating mechanism:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">W = f W (U W ); A = f A (W, U A ); Z(A) = f Z (A, W, U A ); M(A) = f M (Z(A), A, W, U M ); Y (A) = f Y (M(A), Z(A), A, W, U Y ).</formula><p>(2)</p><p>The above counterfactual represents interventions that remove the influence of A on Y along all edges in the set S and replace it by transferring noise. We will therefore use the alternative notation Y S for Y (A). This notation will be useful when we define counterfactuals that intervene on the information transferred along different sets of edges, such as those required for path analysis.</p><p>Remark 1. The above interventions are stochastic versions of the info-interventions proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Gong and Zhu (2019)</ref>. These interventions are similar to the inflation operation proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b87">Wolfe et al. (2019)</ref>, but are different in at least two aspects. First, our goal is to quantify the effect of a given cause on a given outcome, whereas the goal of inflation operations is to assess whether a particular data distribution is compatible with a given graphical model. Furthermore, our interventions are performed at the individual level, whereas the inflation operation is performed at the population level by altering the probability distribution of the data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>These interventions may be of interest when, instead of considering interventions on an individual's</head><p>A, we consider a hypothetical joint intervention on the mechanisms downstream of A such that the functional dependence on of these variables on their causal parents are modified. For example, Z =</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">f Z (A, W, U Z ) is replaced by Z = f Z (A, W, U Z ).</formula><p>The form of the function f Z remains the same but one of its inputs changes. To further illustrate the relevance of this definition, consider a problem where one is interested in the causal influence of gender A on wages Y , mediated by work sector M and field of study Z. The correlation between gender A and the counterfactual Z(A) is interpreted as the correlation between gender and the field of study that would be observed in a hypothetical world where field of study preferences and opportunities were as if a person's actual gender did not play a role in their field of study preferences and opportunities.</p><p>This information transfer intervention allows us to define causal influence measures as follows:</p><p>Definition 3 (Measure of causal influence). Let P(y, a) denote the distribution of Y conditional on A, and let P S (y, a) denote the distribution of Y S conditional on A. Let D denote any functional contrasting two distributions such that D(P, P) = 0. The strength of the causal influence of A on Y can be defined as any contrast D(P, P S ) between (moments of) P(y, a) and P S (y, a).</p><p>Remark 2. This definition is related to the definition of causal strength given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Sprenger (2018)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Fitelson and Hitchcock (2011)</ref>. The difference with our definition is that we are interested in a system where the information transferred along by the causal agent is changed to be noise, whereas the definition in these works focuses on contrasts where the causal agent is turned on vs off.</p><p>To further see why Definition 3 is a sensible measure of causal influence, consider the original SCM (1) and its associated causal graph in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">1</ref>. In this model A and Y may be associated due to two different types of relations: (i) any of the directed paths from A to Y , or (ii) undirected paths operating through common causes (e.g., W or U). In contrast, in the intervened SCM (2), A and Y S can only be associated due paths operating through to common causes. Therefore, a contrast between the joint distributions P(y, a) and P S (y, a) provides a measure of the information transferred through paths from A to Y . These ideas are formalized in the following property:</p><p>Proposition 1. Any contrast D(P, P S ) between (moments of) P(y, a) and P S (y, a) satisfies the sharp null criterion P1.</p><p>Proof This follows after noticing that Y S = Y whenever A has no causal influence on Y .</p><p>Note, however, that the counterfactual SCM (2) should not be used in general to define individual causal effects, since A may be equal to A by chance for any given individual. Furthermore, contrasting the marginal distributions of Y S and Y may also be misleading, as these distributions may also be equal by study design, e.g., in a completely randomized trial with binary treatment.</p><p>To properly place the definition of the measure of causal influence D(P, P S ) in the context of causality research, it is useful to consider Judea Pearl's "hierarchy (or ladder) of causation" <ref type="bibr">(Pearl and Mackenzie, 2018)</ref>. The hierarchy consists of three layers: associational, agential,<ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">foot_3</ref> and counterfactual, which correspond to "the ordinary human activities of seeing, doing, and imagining, respectively." <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Bareinboim et al., 2022)</ref>. In this hierarchy, the distribution P S (a, y) may be seen as that of the outcome and cause in an imagined world where the cause under evaluation Y does not causally affect any of downstream variables (Z, M, Y ). Although we operationalize this imagined world through the counterfactual distribution P S (a, y) and associated counterfactual variables, there are a multiple other ways in which this imagined world could have been operationalized.</p><p>To illustrate the utility of Definition 3, we now present a number of examples of how these distributions can be contrasted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Example 1 (Covariance decomposition). Consider the covariance decomposition</head><formula xml:id="formula_8">Cov(A, Y ) = Cov(A, Y -Y S ) causal influence + Cov(A, Y S ) confounding .</formula><p>By definition, A does not have a causal influence on Y S . Any association between A and Y S is due to common causes, which means that Cov(A, Y S ) is a measure of confounding. On the other hand,</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">Cov(A, Y -Y S ) = Cov(A, Y ) -Cov(A, Y S ) is a contrast of covariances comparing hypothetical worlds that only differ in the influence through paths from A to Y , which is present in Cov(A, Y ) but not in Cov(A, Y S ). Thus, Cov(A, Y -Y S ) quantifies the causal influence of A on Y . Furthermore, it</formula><p>recovers the sign of the individual effects in the following sense:</p><p>Theorem 1. The above covariance decomposition satisfies the monotonicity criterion P2.</p><p>Example 2 (Regression of residuals). Consider the function</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">f (a) = E[Y -Y S | A = a],</formula><p>where we note that this parameter measures the strength of the association in a hypothetical world where the influence of A on Y is removed (and therefore all association is due to confounding) and compares it to the association observed in the actual world.</p><p>Example 3 (Kullback-Leibler divergence). Another measure of causal influence may be given by the Kullback-Leibler divergence D(P,</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">P S ) = E P log p(Y,A) p S (Y,A)</formula><p>, where p(y, a) is the density of (Y, A)</p><p>and p S (y, a) is the density of (Y S , A).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Remark 3. Janzing et al. (2013) also propose a measure of causal influence based on the Kullback-</head><p>Leibler divergence, but their proposal differs from ours in two ways. First, our interventional densities allow for random draws A conditional on the past, theirs do not. Second, their measure of causal influence is based on a contrast of the distribution of the complete data X with and without an intervention. While using the distribution of the complete data X yields causal influence measures with important properties (see properties P0-P4 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Janzing et al., 2013)</ref>, adopting a definition based on the distribution of (A, Y ) allows the construction of optimal estimators which would not be possible under the definition that contrasts the full data distributions.</p><p>The parameters described in Examples 1-3 have an interesting structural interpretation in terms of a quantification of the dependence of the function f Y in the SCM on the variable A. In other words, these parameters quantify how much nature's causal mechanisms use information on A to assign the outcome value. The following theorem provides an expression that can be used to identify the joint distribution of (Y S , A) under the standard assumption of no unmeasured confounders.</p><p>Theorem 2 (Identification). Under the assumed SCM (A1) we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">P S (Y S ≤ y | A = a) = E[P(Y ≤ y | W ) | A = a].</formula><p>Note that identification of this causal influence parameter does not require the positivity assumption </p><formula xml:id="formula_13">P(g(a | W )) &gt; 0 that is required</formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">θ = E {[A -E(A | W )] [Y -E(Y | W )]}, and τ = Cov {E(A | W ), E(Y | W )}. Furthermore, we have f (a) = E[Y -E(Y | W ) | A = a].</formula><p>Remark 4. The expectation of the conditional covariance θ has been previously used for causal inference as a means to study other causal effects, such as the variance-weighted ATE <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Li et al., 2011)</ref>.</p><p>Furthermore, it forms the basis to construct the partial correlation coefficient, which has a long but non-rigorous history as a measure of causality in applications <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Ellett and Ericson, 1986)</ref>, for example in the context of genomics (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Freudenberg et al., 2009)</ref>. Its role in conditional independence testing has been previously studied by <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Shah and Peters (2020)</ref>. However, we know of no previous result that provides an interpretation of the expected conditional covariance as a causal effect in terms of formal interventions in a causal model. In addition, this result provides a causal interpretation of the well known law of total covariance as a decomposition of the covariance between A and Y in terms of a pure causal influence θ and a pure confounding effect τ . Furthermore, identification of the contrast</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">E[Y -Y S | A = a] involves regressing the orthogonalized outcome Y -E(Y | W ) on the treatment</formula><p>variable A. This is a procedure commonly used in applied studies aiming to estimate causal inference effects (e.g., in genomics) but its interpretation in a formal causal inference framework has not been previously articulated. This illustrates that causal our proposed causal influence measures formalize vague notions of causality that are already present in scientists minds.</p><p>The counterfactual Y S involves information transfer interventions that remove all the information transferred along edges in S. In this article we will also use an information transfer operation that emulates information transferred along certain paths. Consider, for example, the paths</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">A → Z → Y and A → Z → M → Y . Let Z A denote a draw from the distribution of Z conditional on (A, W ),<label>and</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_17">consider the counterfactual variable Y (A, Z A , M(A, Z A )).</formula><p>In this counterfactual variable, we have emulated the information transferred along the paths</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">A → Z → Y and A → Z → M → Y by information transferred along synthetic paths A → Z A → Y and A → Z A → M → Y , respectively.</formula><p>Interestingly, the distribution of this counterfactual variable is identified by</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">P(Y ≤ y | A = a),</formula><p>suggesting that this information transfer intervention preserves the relation that operates through the original paths. While this kind of intervention is not very useful to define total causal influence of A on Y , it will be fundamental in §4 when we present the path analysis methods using causal influence.</p><p>In the next section we discuss a major advantage of the information transfer interventions introduced in this section, namely the ability to provide measures of direct and indirect causal influence.</p><p>We will show that these interventions allow the decomposition of the total causal influence into an influence and an effect that operates through each specific path. Importantly, we show that this decomposition is possible even in the presence of mediator-outcome confounders which are affected by exposure, a problem whose solution has been elusive in the causal inference literature that focuses on the causal effect of actions. We start our presentation with a brief discussion of the problems with existing approaches to mediation analysis using causal effects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Causal effects and implications for path and mediation analysis</head><p>Mediation analysis is the task of decomposing the total causal influence of A on Y into an influence that operates through M and an influence that operates through all other mechanisms. This can be done by decomposing the total causal influence of the previous section into influence that operates the pathways A → Y and A → Z → Y (so-called direct influence), and influence that operates through</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">the pathways A → M → Y and A → Z → M → Y (so-called indirect influence).</formula><p>Definition 4 (Causal influence through a mediator). For fixed ā = (a 0 , a 1 , a 2 ), define the counterfactual variable Y (a 0 , M(a 1 )) as the solution in Y of the equations ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">1</ref>) under the intervention</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">A = a 0 and M = M(a 1 ). That is, Y (a 0 , M(a 1 )) = f Y (M(a 1 ), Z(a 0 ), a 0 , W, U Y ) with M(a 1 ) = f M (Z(a 1 ), a 1 , W, U M ) and Z(a 0 ) = f Z (a 0 , W, U Z ). The variable A is said to have a causal influ- ence on Y through M if and only if sup ā |Y (a 0 , M(a 1 )) -Y (a 0 , M(a 2 ))| &gt; 0 holds with positive probability.</formula><p>For binary exposures, this definition of causal influence is equivalent to the sharp mediation null</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">H 0 : Y (a, M(1)) = Y (a, M(0)) for a ∈ {0, 1}.</formula><p>As before, it will be desirable that parameters that measure the influence of A on Y operating through M satisfy the following properties <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Miles, 2022)</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">P3 (Mediational sharp null criterion). A measure of the causal influence of A on Y through M is said</formula><p>to satisfy the mediational sharp null criterion if it is null whenever there is no causal influence through the mediator M.</p><p>In addition, it may be desirable that mediation analyses that seek to unveil mechanisms satisfy the following property, which we present in an additive scale but can be equivalently stated in a multiplicative or other scales:</p><p>P4 (Total influence decomposition). A pair of measurements of direct and indirect influence are said to decompose a measure of total influence if they add up to the total influence.</p><p>Having established the above desiderata for a measure of influence through a mediator, we now review two of the major mediation frameworks recently proposed: natural direct and indirect effects, and randomized interventional direct and indirect effects. We discuss the lack of identifiability of natural effects in the presence of a mediator-outcome confounder affected by treatment, and discuss the fact that randomized mediational effects do not satisfy the sharp mediational null criterion. These shortcomings were originally described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Avin et al. (2005)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Miles (2022)</ref>, respectively. We then move onto discussing our proposal for mediation analysis based on the causal influence measures proposed in the previous section, and show how our proposal can be used to address those shortcomings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Natural direct and indirect effects</head><p>In the case of a binary exposure A, the average treatment effect E(Y (1) -Y (0)) is a common measure of the effect of the action A = 1 vs the action A = 0. Natural mediation effects decompose the ATE into effects that operate through the mediator M and effects that operate through all other causes.</p><p>Specifically, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">E[Y (1) -Y (0)] = E[Y (1, M(1)) -Y (0, M(0))] = E[Y (1, M(1)) -Y (1, M(0))] Natural indirect effect (NIE) + E[Y (1, M(0)) -Y (0, M(0))) Natural direct effect (NDE)</formula><p>, While the NIE and NDE provide a useful and intuitive decomposition of the ATE into effects that operate through M vs all other mechanisms, and satisfy P3 and P4, these effects are not identified in the causal graph 1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Avin et al., 2005)</ref>. To understand why identification fails, it is useful to consider a simplified model where W = ∅, all the errors U are mutually independent, and the edges A → M and A → Y have been removed. It can be proved that in this model we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">where</formula><formula xml:id="formula_26">E[Y (1, M (0))] = m,z,z ′ E[Y (Z = z, M = m)]P(M (Z = z ′ ) = m)P(Z(A = 1) = z, Z(A = 0) = z ′ ),</formula><p>where we have enriched the notation to add the intervention node in the index of the counterfactual variables. While P(Y (Z = z, M = m) = y) and P(M(Z = z ′ ) = m) are identifiable in this model, and indirect effects, for example using the methods. Along these lines, much of the recent literature on mediation analysis has focused on randomized interventional effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Didelez et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b74">van der Laan and Petersen, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b72">VanderWeele et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Díaz et al., 2021a)</ref>. We discuss the definition, interpretation, and identification of these randomized interventional effects below. and M(0). Specifically, the randomized mediational effects are defined as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">P(Z(A = 1) = z, Z(A = 0) = z ′ ) is not (for a counterexample, see</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Randomized interventional direct and indirect effects</head><formula xml:id="formula_28">E[Y (1, G(1)) -Y (0, G(0))] Total effect = E[Y (1, G(1)) -Y (1, G(0))] Randomized indirect effect + E[Y (1, G(0)) -Y (0, G(0))] Randomized direct effect</formula><p>.</p><p>The first limitation of randomized mediational effects is that they do not satisfy P4 in the sense that they do not decompose the ATE, but rather decompose an alternative treatment effect given by the left hand side of the above expression which is defined in terms of interventions on both A and M.</p><p>Unlike the NIE and NDE, randomized mediational effects are identified in the model in the SCM (1). <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">VanderWeele et al. (2014)</ref> show that the above randomized interventional indirect effect is identified as</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">E[Y (a, G(a ′ ))] = E(Y | m, z, a, w)dP(z | a, w)dP(m | a ′ , w)dP(w)<label>(3)</label></formula><p>under the assumption that there are no unmeasured confounders of the relations A → M, A → Y , and M → Y . However, <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Miles (2022)</ref> has recently uncovered an important limitation of these effects, namely that they fail to satisfy the mediational sharp null criterion P3. One counterexample involves creating an SCM with independent errors, W = ∅, and an exogenous binary variable U Z such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">M(a) = M(a ′ ) in the event U Z = 1 and Y (a, m ′ ) = Y (a, m)</formula><p>in the event U Z = 0 for all a, a ′ , and m, such that there is no causal influence of A on Y operating through M (Definition 1). It is easy to see that the randomized interventional indirect effect in this example equals</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">E(Y | m, z, a)dP(z | a)[dP(m | a) -dP(m | a ′ )],</formula><p>which is generally not null, and would only be null if U Z was observed and conditioned upon in all the above quantities. The interested reader is referred to <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Miles (2022)</ref> for more details and counterexam-</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ples.</head><p>In what follows we propose a mediation analysis strategies based on the information transfer interventions introduced in §3, and show that this approach overcomes the limitations of the interventional effects discussed in this section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Path analysis using causal influence</head><p>In this section, we propose a decomposition of the causal influence of A on Y into influence that operates through each of the paths</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">A → Y , A → Z → Y , A → Z → M → Y , and A → M → Y .</formula><p>We first state the properties that are desirable of measures of such path-specific influence. In this section, we will use counterfactual variables indexed by interventions on (A, Z, M), and define</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">Y (a, z, m) = f Y (m, z, a, W, U Y ), M(a, z) = f M (z, a, W, U M ),<label>and</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_34">Z(a) = f Z (a, W, U Z ).</formula><p>Definition 5 (Path-specific causal influence). For fixed ā = (a 0 , a 1 , a 2 , a 3 , a 4 ), define the counterfactual variable Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M(a 3 , Z(a 4 ))). The variable A is said to have a causal influence on Y through each path P 1 , P 2 , P 3 , P 4 if and only if the following conditions hold with positive probability</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Name Path</head><p>Condition</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">P 1 A → Y sup ā |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 4 , Z(a 3 ))) -Y (a 0 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 4 , Z(a 3 )))| &gt; 0 P 2 A → Z → Y sup ā |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 4 , Z(a 3 ))) -Y (a 1 , Z(a 0 ), M (a 4 , Z(a 3 )))| &gt; 0 P 3 A → Z → M → Y sup ā |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 4 , Z(a 3 ))) -Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 4 , Z(a 0 )))| &gt; 0 P 4 A → M → Y sup ā |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 4 , Z(a 3 ))) -Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 0 , Z(a 3 )))| &gt; 0</formula><p>Table 1: Conditions for causal influence through each path.</p><p>P5 (Path-specific sharp null criterion). For j = 1, 2, 3, 4, a measure of the causal influence operating through path P j satisfies the path-specific sharp null criterion if it is null whenever there is no causal influence through P j .</p><p>In addition, it will be important that the measures of the causal influence through each path recover the direction of the mechanism in some sense. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Miles (2022)</ref> operationalized this idea using the following property:</p><p>P6 (Path-specific monotonicity criterion). For j = 1, 2, 3, 4, a measure of the causal influence operating through path P j satisfies the monotonicity criterion if (i) it is less than its null value whenever Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M(a 4 , Z(a 3 ))) is decreasing in a j almost surely, and (ii) it is greater than its null value whenever Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M(a 4 , Z(a 3 ))) is increasing in a j almost surely, for all a s : s = j.</p><p>Our proposed method for path analysis will require to specify a set of interventions that sequentially remove the information transferred through the paths P 1 , P 2 , P 3 , and P 4 . To construct the interventions, we first define the sets S j = {P 1 , . . . , P j } for j = 1, 2, 3, 4. Then, let A and Z A denote a random draw from the distribution of A and Z conditional on W , respectively. Let Z A denote a random draw from the distribution of Z conditional on (A, W ). The notation Z A indicates that Z A does not transfer information from A onto the descendants of Z, whereas the notation Z A indicates that Z A transfers information from A onto the descendants of Z. In this sense, an intervention that assigns Z as Z A can be thought of as an edge-emulation intervention. Although the emulation of the information transferred along the edge is not perfect (e.g., Z A cannot transfer information from U Z into M), it will be sufficient for purposes of defining path-specific causal influence. Define the following counterfactual variables:</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">Y S 0 = Y (A, Z(A), M(A, Z(A))), Y S 1 = Y (A, Z(A), M(A, Z(A))), Y S 2 = Y (A, Z(A), M(A, Z(A))), Y S 3 = Y (A, Z(A), M(A, Z(A))), Y S 4 = Y (A, Z(A), M(A, Z(A))),</formula><p>A straightforward measurement of the causal influence through path P j could be achieved through a Fortunately, the edge emulation-intervention can be used to solve this problem. Specifically, denote</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">Y S j with Y<label>(0)</label></formula><p>S j , and let</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">Y (1) S 1 = Y (A, Z(A), M(A, Z A )), Y<label>(1)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_39">S 2 = Y (A, Z(A), M(A, Z A )),<label>(4)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Y</head><p>(2)</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">S 2 = Y (A, Z A , M(A, Z(A))), Y<label>(2)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_41">S 3 = Y (A, Z A , M(A, Z(A))).</formula><p>Then we have the following definition.</p><p>Definition 6 (Measure of causal influence through a path). For i = 0, 1, 2, 3, 4 and k = 0, 1, 2, let</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">P (k) S j (y, a) denote the distribution of (Y<label>(k)</label></formula><p>S j , A). Let D denote any functional contrasting two distributions. The strength of the causal influence of A on Y operating through path P j can be defined as any contrast D(P (0)</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">S j-1 , P<label>(0)</label></formula><p>S j ) for paths not involving the recanting witness Z (i.e., P 1 and P 4 ), as</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">D(P<label>(1)</label></formula><p>S 1 , P</p><p>S 2 ) for the path P 2 , and as D(P</p><p>(2)</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">S 2 , P<label>(2)</label></formula><p>S 3 ) for P 3 .</p><p>Remark 5. The above interventions are stochastic versions of those proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Gong and Zhu (2021)</ref>, but are also different in that we vary the information about A transferred along a pathway, using different kinds of interventions depending on the pathway under measurement. This has important implications, as it allows us to prove important desiderata for path-analysis effect decompositions such as path-specific sharp null criteria (Theorem 3), as well as a result stating that the path-specific measures decompose the total effect (Theorem 4).</p><p>In Theorem 3 below we show that the above definition satisfies the path-specific null criterion, meaning that these parameters may be used to test the null hypothesis of no path-specific effect.</p><p>Theorem 3. The contrasts defined in Definition 6 satisfy the path-specific sharp null criterion P5 with respect to each path P j .</p><p>Note that the definitions of the counterfactuals Y</p><p>(1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">S 1 , Y<label>(1)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_48">S 2 , Y<label>(2)</label></formula><p>S 2 , and Y</p><p>(2)</p><p>S 3 , entail intervening on the information that is transferred along certain paths. For example, in Y The above definitions allow us to test the null hypothesis of no causal influence through each path.</p><p>A related goal is to decompose the total influence of A on Y into influences operating through each path. This is achievable only for some contrasts D (e.g., it is not achievable for the Kullback-Leibler divergence of Example 3). Specifically, we have the following result which is presented in an additive scale but could also be proved for a multiplicative scale. </p><p>S 1 ), θ P 2 = D(P</p><p>(1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">S 1 , P<label>(1)</label></formula><p>S 2 ),</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">θ P 3 = D(P<label>(2)</label></formula><p>S 2 , P</p><p>S 3 ), and θ P 4 = D(P (0)</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">S 3 , P<label>(0)</label></formula><p>S 4 ), as well as the parameter θ P 2 ∨P 3 = D(P</p><p>S 1 , P</p><p>S 1 ) +</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D(P</head><p>(1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">S 2 , P<label>(2)</label></formula><p>S 2 ) + D(P</p><p>(2)</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">S 3 , P<label>(0)</label></formula><p>S 3 ). Then we have the following decomposition of the total causal influence θ = D(P S 0 , P S 4 ):</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">θ = θ P 1 + θ P 2 + θ P 3 + θ P 4 + θ P 2 ∨P 3 .</formula><p>Clearly, the covariance contrast and the expectation contrast of Examples 1 and 2 satisfy the assumption of the theorem. In the above decomposition, the parameter θ P 2 ∨P 3 appears as a consequence of the addition of the counterfactuals in Equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_39">4</ref>). As the notation implies, this parameter is equal to zero if there is no influence through the path P 2 , or there is no influence through the path P 3 . This result is proved formally in Proposition 2 below. Intuition for this may be obtained as follows. The contrasts D(P</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">(0) 1 , P<label>(0)</label></formula><p>2 ) and D(P</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">(0) 2 , P<label>(0)</label></formula><p>3 ), which would readily yield measures of the influence through paths P 2 and P 3 , respectively, are not identified because the distribution P (0)</p><p>2 is not identified due to the recanting witness problem. However, the contrast θ P 2 ∧P 3 = D(P</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">(0) 1 , P<label>(0)</label></formula><p>3 ) is identified, and it measures the influence operating through P 2 and P 3 . That is, θ P 2 ∧P 3 = 0 if there is no causal influence operating through P 2 nor P 3 . This highlights the difficulty in measuring the influence through paths P 2</p><p>and P 3 separately. The above theorem decomposes θ P 2 ∧P 3 into an influence measure θ P 2 that operates only through P 2 , an influence measure θ P 3 that operates only through P 3 , and an influence measure θ P 2 ∨P 3 that operates through P 2 or P 3 . This latter parameter is zero if the influence going trough either of these paths is null. Furthermore, as demonstrated in the following lemma, the parameter is null whenever there is no intermediate confounding by Z. • sup z |M(z 1 ) -Z(z 0 )| = 0 in U 2 , and</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">• sup z |Y (z 1 ) -Y (z 0 )| = 0 in U 3 .</formula><p>Then θ P 2 ∨P 3 = 0.</p><p>Importantly, the above proposition implies that whenever there is no intermediate confounding, the path-specific decomposition is exact in the sense that it satisfies property P4. We now illustrate the proposed path-analysis based on the covariance decomposition of Example 1.</p><p>Example 1 (Continued). Let D denote the covariance contrast defined as D(P,</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">P S ) = Cov(A, Y -Y S )</formula><p>for (Y, A) ∼ P and (Y S , A) ∼ P S . Then, for θ = Cov(A, Y -Y S ), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">θ = θ P 1 + θ P 2 + θ P 3 + θ P 4 + θ P 2 ∨P 3 , where θ P 1 = Cov(A, Y<label>(0)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_65">S 0 -Y (0) S 1 ), θ P 2 = Cov(A, Y<label>(1)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_66">S 1 -Y (1) S 2 ), θ P 3 = Cov(A, Y<label>(2)</label></formula><p>S 2 -Y</p><p>(2)</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">S 3 ), θ P 3 = Cov(A, Y<label>(0)</label></formula><p>S 3 -Y</p><p>S 4 ), and</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">θ P 2 ∨P 3 = Cov(A, Y<label>(0)</label></formula><p>S 1 -Y</p><p>(1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">S 1 + Y (1) S 2 -Y (2) S 2 + Y (2) S 3 -Y<label>(0)</label></formula><p>S 3 ).</p><p>(5) Furthermore, we have:</p><p>Theorem 5. The covariance contrasts θ P 1 , θ P 2 , θ P 3 , and θ P 4 satisfy the path-specific monotonicity criterion P6. <ref type="bibr" target="#b89">Wright (1921</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b89">Wright ( , 1923</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b89">Wright ( , 1934) )</ref> proposed a covariance decomposition for Cov(A, Y ) in terms of pathspecific coefficients in the context of linear models and in the absence of an intermediate confounder</p><p>Z. An immediate consequence of the above results is that our covariance decomposition generalizes Wright's approach to a non-parametric model in the presence of intermediate confounding.</p><p>Zhang and <ref type="bibr" target="#b92">Bareinboim (2018)</ref> provide an alternative generalization that is unidentifiable in the presence of intermediate confounders Z.</p><p>We now present identification formulas for the probability distributions involved in computation of the measures of causal influence of Definition 6.</p><p>A2 (Overlap). For a fixed value a, assume the following hold for all w such that p(w) &gt; 0:</p><p>• p(z | a, w) &gt; 0 implies p(z | a ′ , w) &gt; 0 for all a ′ such that p(a ′ | w) &gt; 0.</p><p>• p(m | z, a, w) &gt; 0 implies p(m | z ′ , a ′ , w) &gt; 0 for all (a ′ , z ′ , z) such that p(a ′ | w) &gt; 0, p(z | a, w) &gt; 0, and p(z ′ | a, w) &gt; 0.</p><p>• p(m | z, a, w) &gt; 0 implies p(m | z ′ , a ′ , w) &gt; 0 for all (a ′ , z ′ , z) such that p(a ′ | w) &gt; 0, p(z | a ′ , w) &gt; 0, and p(z ′ | a ′ , w) &gt; 0.</p><p>Theorem 6 (Identification of path-specific causal influence). Under the assumed SCM (A1) plus A2.</p><p>the path-specific counterfactual distributions are identified as follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">P(Y (0) S 0 ≤ y | A = a) = F(y | A = a), P(Y (0) S 1 ≤ y | A = a) = E F(y | a ′ , Z, M, W )dP(a ′ | W ) | A = a , P(Y<label>(1)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_72">S 1 ≤ y | A = a) = E F(y | a ′ , z, M, W )dP(z | a, W )dP(a ′ | W ) | A = a , P(Y (1) S 2 ≤ y | A = a) = P(Y (2) S 2 ≤ y | A = a) = E F(y | a ′ , z, M, W )dP(z, a ′ | W ) | A = a , P(Y (2) S 3 ≤ y | A = a) = E F(y | a ′ , z, m, W )dP(m | a, z ′ , W )dP(z | a ′ , W )dP(z ′ , a ′ | W ) | A = a , P(Y (0) S 3 ≤ y | A = a) = E F(y | a ′ , z, m, W )dP(m | a, z, W )dP(z, a ′ | W ) | A = a , P(Y (0) S 4 ≤ y | A = a) = E [F(y | W ) | A = a] .</formula><p>At this point it is important to note that the ideas of information transfer interventions discussed in this paper can also be used to obtain a decomposition of the average treatment effect into path-specific effects analogous to the decomposition of Theorem 4. We discuss such an extension in §6 of the supplement.</p><p>In the following section, we discuss efficient non-parametric estimation of the covariance influence discussed in Example 1. Efficient non-parametric estimation of the other parameters discussed in this paper is also possible, but we defer the development of such estimators to future work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Extension to path analysis using causal effects</head><p>This section presents results where we use the information transfer interventions introduced to construct a decomposition of the average effect of a binary treatment into path-specific effects that satisfy path-specific null criteria, analogous to the decomposition constructed for measures of causal influence. A decomposition of the ATE is important for questions that require an agency view of causality, as the ATE can be used to quantify the effect of a hypothetical but feasible intervention. The methods we present below decompose the ATE, which can have an agency interpretation of causality, into path-specific effects that do not correspond to an agency interpretation of causality. Readers interested in decompositions that have an agency interpretation are encouraged to consult the literature on so-called separable effects (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Robins and Richardson, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Stensrud et al., 2022a,b;</ref><ref type="bibr">Robins et al., 2022)</ref>. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">4</ref> Briefly, these works achieve identifiability of mediation parameters under an additional structural assumption stating that treatment/exposure can be separated into disjoint components whose ef- </p><formula xml:id="formula_73">Y S 0 = Y (1, Z(1), M(1, Z(1))), Y S 1 = Y (0, Z(1), M(1, Z(1))), Y S 2 = Y (0, Z(0), M(1, Z(1))),<label>(6)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_74">Y S 3 = Y (0, Z(0), M(1, Z(0))), Y S 4 = Y (0, Z(0), M(0, Z(0))),</formula><p>where the causal effect operating through path P j is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">E[Y S j -1 -Y S j ].</formula><p>As before, the probability distribution of Y S 2 is not identified due to the recanting witness Z. However, we can achieve an effect decomposition into path-specific effects using information transfer interventions as follows. Let Z a denote a random draw from the distribution of Z(a) conditional on W . Define</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">Y ′ S 1 = Y (0, Z(1), M(1, Z 1 )), Y ′ S 2 = Y (0, Z(0), M(1, Z 1 )), Y ′′ S 2 = Y (0, Z 0 , M(1, Z(1))), Y ′′ S 3 = Y (0, Z 0 , M(1, Z(0))),</formula><p>where, in comparison to the definitions in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_73">6</ref>), we have emulate the information transferred through some paths by means of the random draws Z 1 and Z 0 . For example, in Y ′ S 2 , the effect of the action</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">A = 1 operating through the path A = 1 → Z(1) → M → Y is emulated by the effect operating through a path A = 1 → Z 1 → M → Y .</formula><p>This allows us to achieve the following identifiable effect decomposition:</p><p>Theorem 7 (Decomposition of the average treatment effect into path-specific effects). Define the pathspecific causal effects as</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">ψ P 1 = E(Y S 0 -Y S 1 ) ψ P 2 = E(Y ′ S 1 -Y ′ S 2 ) ψ P 3 = E(Y ′′ S 2 -Y ′′ S 3 ) ψ P 4 = E(Y S 3 -Y S 4 ),</formula><p>as well as the parameter</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">ψ P 2 ∨P 3 = E(Y S 1 -Y ′ S 1 + Y ′ S 2 -Y ′′ S 2 + Y ′′ S 3 -Y S 3 ).</formula><p>Then we have the following decomposition of the average treatment effect ψ = E(Y S 0 -Y S 4 ):</p><formula xml:id="formula_80">ψ = ψ P 1 + ψ P 2 + ψ P 3 + ψ P 4 + ψ P 2 ∨P 3 .</formula><p>As in the previous section, we have the following result showing that this decomposition of the total causal effect satisfies the path-specific null criterion:</p><p>Theorem 8. The contrasts defined in Theorem 7 satisfy the path-specific sharp null criterion P5 with respect to each path P j .</p><p>Furthermore, in this case ψ P 2 ∨P 3 is also an effect operating through either</p><formula xml:id="formula_81">A → Z → Y or A → Z → M → Y</formula><p>, which is equal to zero whenever there is no effect through at least one of these paths (e.g., if Z is not an intermediate confounder): </p><formula xml:id="formula_82">Proposition 3. Let U denote the range of U = (U W , U A , U Z , U M , U Y ). Assume U can be partitioned in sets U 1 , U 2 ,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_83">• sup z |Y (z 1 ) -Y (z 0 )| = 0 in U 3 .</formula><p>Then ψ P 2 ∨P 3 = 0.</p><p>In order to present identification results for the above decomposition, we will require the following overlap assumption which guarantees that the functionals defined in Theorem 9 are well defined.</p><p>A3 (Overlap assumption for decomposition of the ATE). Assume the following hold for all w such that p(w) &gt; 0</p><p>• p(a | w) &gt; 0 for a ∈ {0, 1}.</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">• p(z | A = 1, w) &gt; 0 implies p(z | A = 0, w) &gt; 0. • p(m | A = 1, z ′ , w) &gt; 0 implies p(m | A = 0, z, w) &gt; 0 for all (z, z ′ ) such that p(z | a ′ , w) &gt; 0</formula><p>and p(z ′ | a ⋆ , w) &gt; 0 and for a ′ , a ⋆ ∈ {0, 1}.</p><p>Theorem 9 (Identification of the path-specific decomposition of the average treatment effect). As-sumeA3. Then, for a ′ = 1 and a ⋆ = 0, we have the following under the assumed SCM:</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">E(Y S 0 ) = E{E(Y | a ′ , W )}, E(Y S 1 ) = E E(Y | a ⋆ , z, m, W )dP(z, m | a ′ , W ) , E(Y ′ S 1 ) = E E(Y | a ⋆ , z, m, W )dP(z | a ′ , W )dP(m | a ′ , W ) , E(Y ′ S 2 ) = E(Y ′′ S 2 ) = E E(Y | a ⋆ , z, m, W )dP(z | a ⋆ , W )dP(m | a ′ , W ) , E(Y ′′ S 3 ) = E E(Y | a ⋆ , z, m, W )dP(z | a ⋆ , W )dP(m | a ′ , z ′ , W )dP(z ′ | a ⋆ , W ) , E(Y S 3 ) = E E(Y | a ⋆ , z, m, W )dP(z | a ⋆ , W )dP(m | a ′ , z, W ) , E(Y S 4 ) = E{E(Y | a ⋆ , W )}.</formula><p>The proofs of the results in this section follow steps identical to the proofs of the results in §5, where we note that for binary A the causal influence parameter θ = Cov(A, Y -Y S ) and the ATE ψ =</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">E[Y (1) -Y (0)] are connected through the relation θ = E{p(W ) 2 (1 -p(W )) 2 E[Y (1) -Y (0) | W ]}, for p(w) = P(A = 1 | W = w).</formula><p>7 Efficient estimation of the path-specific influence using the covariance contrast</p><p>In this section we discuss estimation of the covariance parameters presented in Example 1, and specifically the causal influence decomposition in (5). Note that, to estimate these covariances, it will be sufficient to construct an estimator of the parameter</p><formula xml:id="formula_87">τ k j = E[f (A)Y (k)</formula><p>S j ] for a general function f . Applications to f (A) = A and f (A) = 1 will allow us to obtain estimates of E[AY (k)</p><p>S j ] and E[Y (k)</p><p>S j ], which together with E[A] constitute the basis for computing the covariance parameters E[AY (k)</p><formula xml:id="formula_88">S j ] -E[A]E[Y (k) S j ].</formula><p>Note also that estimation of</p><formula xml:id="formula_89">E[f (A)Y (0) S 0 ] = E[f (A)Y ] and E[A]</formula><p>is straightforward by means of empirical averages. Thus, in the remaining of this section we focus on estimation of τ k j for (k, j) ∈ {(0, 1), (1, 1), (1, 2), (2, 3), (0, 3), (0, 4)}. For the sake of simplicity, we pursue estimators assuming that A, Z, and M are discrete random variables, although some of the efficiency theory results of this section such as Theorem 10 and the efficiency bound hold for arbitrary variables.</p><p>The identification formulas in Theorem 6 provide a relatively easy approach to obtain estimators of τ k j . For example, given any regression estimate of E[Y | A = a, M = m, Z = z, W = w] and an estimate of the probabilities P(M = m, Z = z, A = a | W = w), an estimator may be constructed by plugging in these estimates in the identification formulas. If the models for these regression and probabilities are parametric and correctly specified, a maximum likelihood plug-in estimation strategy is optimal in the sense that the estimators converge to the optimal normal distribution at √ n-rate.</p><p>However, if the model is non-parametric, a plug-in estimation strategy results in first-order bias, which must be corrected.</p><p>The general methods to characterize this first-order bias are rooted in semi-parametric estimation theory (e.g., von <ref type="bibr" target="#b83">Mises, 1947;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Begun et al., 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bickel et al., 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr">van der Vaart, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Robins et al., 2009)</ref>, and in the theory for doubly robust estimation using estimating equations <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Robins, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Robins et al., 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b75">van der Laan and Robins, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bang and Robins, 2005)</ref>. Under this theory, the first-order bias is characterized in terms of the so-called canonical gradient. This canonical gradient also characterizes the efficiency bound in the non-parametric model, and is therefore also known as the efficient influence function. Importantly, knowledge of the canonical gradient allows the development of estimators under slow convergence rates for the nuisance parameters involved. This is important because flexible regression and estimation methods involving model selection must be used when the model is non-parametric, and those flexible estimation methods often fail to be consistent at parametric rate, though they may be consistent at slower rates.</p><p>The following theorem illustrates the sense in which general plug-in estimators are biased in the non-parametric model, and provides a characterization of the bias in terms of the canonical gradient ϕ k j . The specific formulas of the gradient for each duple (k, j) are useful to construct the estimators, but they are cumbersome and somewhat uninformative, so we relegate their presentation to the supplementary materials.</p><p>Theorem 10 (First order von-Mises expansion). Let τ k j (G) denote the τ k j parameter evaluated at a distribution G. Then, for any pair of distributions P and G, we have the following:</p><formula xml:id="formula_90">τ k j (G) -τ k j (P) = -E P [ϕ k j (X; G)] + R k j (G, P),</formula><p>where R k j (G, P) is a second-order term of the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_91">R k j (G, P) = l ω(G, P){κ l (G) -κ l (P)}{ν l (G) -ν l (P)}dP,</formula><p>for functionals ω, κ, and ν that vary with (i, k). The specific form of each canonical gradient ϕ k j and second order term R k j (G, P) is given in the supplement.</p><p>An application of the above theorem with G equal to an estimate P of the true probability distribution P reveals that a plug-in estimation strategy is generally biased in first-order, and provides a representation of the bias as -E P [ϕ k j (X; P)]. Importantly, this theorem also provides an avenue to correct for this first order bias. Specifically, the first order bias may be estimated through the empirical average of ϕ k j (X j ; P) across observations i. If this bias is added back to the plug-in estimator τ k j ( P), one would expect that the resulting estimator is unbiased in first-order. This idea is formalized below in Theorem 11.</p><p>The canonical gradient and the above reasoning are at the center of several recent estimation methods that leverage machine learning and flexible regression, such as the targeted learning framework (van der <ref type="bibr" target="#b78">Laan and Rubin, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">van der Laan and</ref><ref type="bibr">Rose, 2011, 2018)</ref>, and double machine learning <ref type="bibr">(Chernozhukov et al., 2018)</ref>. An important feature of these approaches is the use of cross-fitting, which will allow us to obtain n 1/2 -convergence of our estimators while avoiding entropy conditions that may be violated by data adaptive estimators of the nuisance parameters <ref type="bibr" target="#b93">(Zheng and van der Laan, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Chernozhukov et al., 2018)</ref>. Let P 1 , . . . , P V denote a random partition of the data set into V prediction sets of approximately the same size. That is, P v ⊂ {1, . . . , n}; J j=1 P v = D; and P v ∩P v ′ = ∅.</p><p>In addition, for each v, the associated training sample is given by T v = D \ P v .</p><p>Our proposed estimator only requires estimation of the conditional expectation of Y given (M, Z, A, W ), which will be denoted by m, the probability mass function of M given (Z, A, W ), denoted by p M , the probability mass function of Z given (A, W ), denoted by p Z , and the probability mass function of A given W , denoted by p A . Let η = (m, p M , p Z , p Z ), and note that the canonical gradients ϕ k j can be written as functions ϕ k j (X; η). Let v(i) denote the prediction set to which observation i belongs, and let ηv(i) denote an estimator of η obtained using training data T v(i) . Then, the estimator of τ k j is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_92">τ k j = 1 n n i=1 φ(X j , ηv(i) ),</formula><p>where φ is the uncentered canonical gradient given in the supplementary materials.</p><p>The following theorem provides the conditions under which the above estimator is expected to be efficient and asymptotically normal:</p><p>Theorem 11 (Asymptotic linearity of the proposed estimator). Assume that R k j (η, η) = o P (n -1/2 ) and that</p><formula xml:id="formula_93">• P{p M (M = m | A, Z, W ) &lt; c M } = P{p M (M = m | A, Z, W ) &lt; c M } = 1 for a constant c M</formula><p>and for all m,</p><formula xml:id="formula_94">• P{p Z (Z = z | A, W ) &lt; c Z } = P{p Z (Z = z | A, W ) &lt; c Z } = 1 for a constant c Z ,</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>and that</head><formula xml:id="formula_95">• P{p A (A = a | W ) &lt; c A } = P{p A (A = a | W ) &lt; c A } = 1 for a constant c</formula><p>A and for all a.</p><p>Then</p><formula xml:id="formula_96">τ k j -τ k j = 1 n n i=1 ϕ k j (X i ; η) + o P (n -1/2 ).</formula><p>The proof of this theorem is sketched in the supplementary materials. The arguments are standard in the analysis of estimators in the targeted learning and double machine learning frameworks. The above theorem implies that an estimator θP j of θ P j constructed through an application of the above estimator to f (A) = A and f (A) = 1 is also asymptotically linear. An application of the Delta method and the central limit theorem then yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_97">n 1/2 ( θP j -θ P j ) N(0, σ 2 ),</formula><p>where σ 2 is the non-parametric efficiency bound, which allows the construction of Wald-type confidence intervals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">Illustrations using real data</head><p>In this section we apply the covariance path-specific decomposition analysis proposed in the previous section to estimating path-specific causal relations in two examples using publicly available data. In the first example, we re-analyze the data from a recent study examining gender differences in wage expectations among students at two Swiss institutions of higher education <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Fernandes et al., 2021</ref>). In the second example, we re-analyze data from a nationally representative randomized experiment on how the framing of media discourse shapes public opinion and immigration policy <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Brader et al., 2008)</ref>.</p><p>The datasets are publicly available in the causalweight (Bodory and Huber, 2021) and mediation <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">(Tingley et al., 2014</ref>) R packages, respectively. Code to reproduce our analyses is available at <ref type="url" target="https://github.com">https://github.com</ref> </p><p>All nuisance parameters were estimated with extreme gradient tree boosting where the hyperparameters are chosen from a random grid of size 100 using the caret <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Kuhn, 2021)</ref> library in R.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.1">Gender differences in wage expectations</head><p>In this study, the authors administered a survey to 804 students at the University of Fribourg and the University of Applied Sciences in Bern in the year 2017. The survey contained a number of questions regarding wage expectations, as well as a number of variables related to wages such as the study program (business, economics, communication, and business informatics), job or educational plans after finishing the studies, the intended industry (trade, transport, hospitality, communication, finance, etc.), as well as other variables such as the age, parents education, nationality, and home ownership.</p><p>We study the causal relation between gender (A) and wage expectations three years after graduation (Y ) study program (Z) and whether a student plans to continue obtaining further education or work full time after graduation (M) as mediators. The outcome Y is recorded in a scale of 0-16, where 0 means less than 3500 Swiss Franc (CHF) gross per month, 1 means 3500-4000 CHF, 2=4000-4500 CHF, etc., and 16=more than 11000 CHF. For simplicity and illustration purposes we treat Y as a numerical variable.</p><p>The results of our analysis are presented in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>. We conclude that most of the influence of gender on wages expectation 3 years after graduation operates through pathways independent of degree and plans after study, which is a result similar to the original result of <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Fernandes et al. (2021)</ref>. Unlike the results in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Fernandes et al. (2021)</ref>, which decompose the average treatment effect into direct and indirect effects, the interpretation of the estimates in  <ref type="table">2</ref>: Results in the gender and wage expectation illustrative example along with 95% confidence intervals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.2">Media discourse and public opinion and immigration policy</head><p>In this study, the authors examine whether and how elite discourse affects public opinion and action on immigration policy. They conducted a randomized experiment in which 265 subjects are exposed to different media stories about immigration. They employed a 2 × 2 design in which they manipulate ethnic cues by altering the picture and name of an immigrant featured in a hypothetical New York Times story (white European vs Latin American). They also manipulate the tone of the story, focusing on whether positive or negative consequences of immigration, as well as conveying positive or negative attitudes of governors and other citizens towards immigration. Our treatment variable A will take values 0, 1, or 2, with 0 denoting a positive story about a white European, 1 denoting a negative story about a white European immigrant or a positive story about a Latin American immigrant, and 2 denoting a negative story about a Latin American immigrant. The authors also collected information on age, education, gender, and income of the study participants, which we denote with W . A major hypothesis of the study was that anxiety and is an important mediator of the causal influence of the framing of the story on negative attitude towards immigration. Anxiety M was measured using a numerical scale from 3 to 12 where 3 indicates the most negative feeling. Perceived harm Z caused by immigration was also measured in a scale between 2 and 8. The outcome of interest Y is a four-point scale measuring a subject's attitude towards increased immigration where larger values indicate more negative attitudes.</p><p>The results of the analysis are presented in Table <ref type="table">3</ref>. These results largely agree with the results of the original research article, with the difference that these analyses provide more nuance in the sense that most of the influence of the framing of the story on negative attitudes towards immigration is mediated directly by anxiety through pathways that do not involve perceived harm from immigration.  <ref type="table">3</ref>: Results in the media discourse illustrative example along with 95% confidence intervals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9">Discussion</head><p>Our proposed approach to measuring causal influence by information transfer interventions can be used in algorithmic fairness. As an example, consider the methods proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Nabi et al. (2019)</ref> to learn fair optimal treatment policies. Their approach to fairness relies on constructing a distribution where undesirable causal pathways are "removed" and then learning optimal treatment policies with respect to this fair but unobserved distribution. Their approach to estimating a fair distribution relies on measuring the path-specific effects, and then finding the closest (e.g., in KL-divergence) distribution to the observed data distribution under the constraint that these path-specific effects are null. Because our proposed path-specific measures satisfy sharp null criteria, the approach of <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Nabi et al. (2019)</ref> to fairness could be adapted to use our proposed path-specific effects to learn fair distributions.</p><p>Our proposal also shares connections to the general theory of causal interventions presented by <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">Shpitser and Tchetgen Tchetgen (2016)</ref>. In their work, the authors generalize and unify many interesting targets of causal inference through the use of so-called edge-and path-interventions, defined as interventions on the source node of the edge or path, where the intervention operates only for the purpose of the specific outgoing path. Our approach to achieving identification of path-specific causal influence and path-specific causal effects also entails a type of path-intervention. The difference with the approach of Shpitser and Tchetgen Tchetgen ( <ref type="formula">2016</ref>) is that we do not restrict the path-intervention to the source node, but instead intervene on nodes in the other positions in the path. Specifically, by Our discussion centers around a structural definition of causal influence interpreted as the strength of dependence of the structural functions on their arguments (see, e.g., Definition 1) This criterion for causal influence may be too strong in some cases. For example <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Sprenger (2018)</ref> argues for a probabilistic rather than structural definition of causal influence. We conjecture that our proposed measures of causal influence would also satisfy probabilistic null criteria, but leave the proof of those results to future work.</p><p>Compared to the natural direct and indirect effects available in the literature, our proposal allows for the definition of parameters that are identified in the presence of a recanting witness. While changing the inferential target allowed us to bypass the recanting witness problem, this strategy comes at a price.</p><p>Specifically, our parameters do not exactly decompose the total effect/influence into path-specific pa-rameters. As detailed in Theorem 4, the decomposition we obtain involves an extra parameter that is equal to zero only in the absence of a recanting witness.</p><p>Lastly, there are multiple interesting directions for future work that build on the ideas presented in this paper. The first is that the order of the decomposition we pursue where we proceed sequentially by intervening on the paths P 1 , P 2 , P 3 , and P 4 is arbitrary. Other orderings for these paths can also be considered and may be of more practical relevance in certain applications. The second is that the ideas we present can be generalized to construct path-specific effects for multiple ordered mediators and for situations with time-varying treatments, mediators, and covariates. The definition of path-specific parameters that measure causal influence in those settings remains an open problem. Furthermore, estimation of existing mediational parameters such as interventional effects is notoriously hard in longitudinal settings (see e.g., <ref type="bibr">Díaz et al., 2022b)</ref> and we believe the ideas introduced in this article can be useful to solve problems in that setting.</p><p>Then β ≥ 0. Likewise, if f (•, y) is decreasing for all y, then β ≤ 0.</p><p>Proof By standard arguments of projections in L 2 (P ) spaces, it can be seen that ρ</p><formula xml:id="formula_98">(L) = E[f (X, L)-bX | L]</formula><p>for any b. This yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_99">R(ρ, β) = E{[f (X, L) -E(f (X, L)|L)] 2 } -2βE{(X -E(X | L))(f (X, L) -E[f (X, L) | L])} + β 2 E[E 2 (X | L)] = E{[f (X, L) -E(f (X, L)|L)] 2 } -2βE{(X -E(X | L))(f (X, L) -f (E(X | L), L))} + β 2 E[E 2 (X | L)],</formula><p>where the second equality follows by adding and subtracting f (E(X | L), L) to the second factor of the second term. By monotonicity, the term (</p><formula xml:id="formula_100">X -E(X | L))(f (X, L) -f (E(X | L), L) is positive everywhere. Thus, if β &lt; 0, then R(ρ, |β|) &lt; R(ρ, β)</formula><p>, contradicting the definition of β and proving the lemma.</p><p>We also have the following general result Lemma 2. Let (X, L) ∼ P any random variables, and let f (x, y) be a function such that f (•, y) is increasing</p><formula xml:id="formula_101">for all y. Then E[X(f (X, L) -E(f (X, L) | L))] ≥ 0.</formula><p>Proof Continuing with the definition of β in the above lemma, notice that E(X</p><formula xml:id="formula_102">2 )β = E[X(f (X, L) - E(f (X, L) | L))],</formula><p>which proves the result.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Theorem 2</head><p>Proof We have</p><formula xml:id="formula_103">P(Y S ≤ y | A = a) = P(Y S ≤ y | A = a ′ , W = w, A = a)dP S (a ′ , w | A = a) = P(Y (a ′ ) ≤ y | W = w, A = a)dP(a ′ | W = w)dP(w | A = a) = P(Y (a ′ ) ≤ y | W = w, A = a ′ )dP(a ′ | W = w)dP(w | A = a) = P(Y ≤ y | W = w, A = a ′ )dP(a ′ | W = w)dP(w | A = a) = P(Y ≤ y | W = w)dP(w | A = a),</formula><p>The first line follows by the law of iterated expectation, the second line by independence of A on all other data conditional on W and by the fact that A is distributed as A conditional on W , the third line follows by the assumption of the theorem, the fourth line because Y (a ′ ) = Y in the event A = a ′ , and the last line by definition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3">Theorem 3</head><p>Proof The proof of Theorem 3 proceeds as follows. We will prove the statement of the Theorem for each contrast of path separately.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">For</head><formula xml:id="formula_104">P 1 , assume that P{sup ā |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 3 , Z(a 4 ))) -Y (a 0 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 3 , Z(a 4 )))| = 0} = 1.</formula><p>Then we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_105">Y (0) S 0 = Y (A, Z(A), M (A, Z(A))) = Y (A, Z(A), M (A, Z(A))) = Y (0) S 1</formula><p>almost surely, where the second equality follows by assumption.</p><p>2. For P 2 , assume that P{sup ā, m |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 3 , Z(a 4 ))) -Y (a 1 , Z(a 0 ), M (a 3 , Z(a 4 )))| = 0} = 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Then we have</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>P(Y</head><p>(1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_106">S 2 ≤ y | A = a) = P[Y (1) S 2 ≤ y | U ∈ U 1 , A = a]P(U ∈ U 1 | A = a) + P[Y (1) S 2 ≤ y | U ∈ U 2 , A = a]P(U ∈ U 2 | A = a),</formula><p>where U 1 and U 2 are the sets of the first statement of Lemma 3 given below. We have</p><formula xml:id="formula_107">Y (1) S 2 = Y (A, Z(A), M (A, Z A )) = Y (A, Z(A), M (A, Z A )) = Y (1) S 1</formula><p>a.s. in the event U ∈ U 1 . We also have Z(A) = Z(A) a.s., and therefore Y</p><p>(1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_108">S 2 = Y (1)</formula><p>S 1 in the event U ∈ U 2 .</p><p>3. For P 3 , assume that P{sup ā, m |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 3 , Z(a 4 ))) -Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 3 , Z(a 0 )))| = 0} = 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Then we have</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>P(Y</head><p>(2)</p><formula xml:id="formula_109">S 3 ≤ y | A = a) = P[Y (2) S 3 ≤ y | U ∈ U 1 , A = a]P(U ∈ U 1 | A = a) + P[Y (2) S 3 ≤ y | U ∈ U 2 , A = a]P(U ∈ U 2 | A = a) + P[Y (2) S 3 ≤ y | U ∈ U 3 , A = a]P(U ∈ U 3 | A = a),</formula><p>where U 1 , U 2 and U 3 are the sets of the second statement of Lemma 3. We have</p><formula xml:id="formula_110">Y (2) S 3 = Y (A, Z A , M (A, Z(A))) = Y (A, Z A , M (A, Z(A))) = Y (2) S 2 a.s. in the event U ∈ U 1 . We also have M (A, Z(A)) = M (A, Z(A)) a.s. in the event U ∈ U 2 ,</formula><p>and therefore Y</p><p>(2)</p><formula xml:id="formula_111">S 3 = Y<label>(2)</label></formula><p>S 2 . Lastly, in the event U ∈ U 3 we have Z(A) = Z(A) a.s., and therefore Y</p><p>(2)</p><formula xml:id="formula_112">S 3 = Y (2) S 2 . 4. For P 4 , assume that P{sup ā, m |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 3 , Z(a 4 ))) -Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 0 , Z(a 4 )))| = 0} = 1.</formula><p>Then we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_113">P(Y (0) S 4 ≤ y | A = a) = P[Y S 4 ≤ y | U ∈ U 1 , A = a]P(U ∈ U 1 | A = a) + P[Y S 4 ≤ y | U ∈ U 2 , A = a]P(U ∈ U 2 | A = a),</formula><p>where U 1 and U 2 and U 3 are the sets of the third statement of Lemma 3. We have</p><formula xml:id="formula_114">Y (0) S 4 = Y (A, Z(A), M (A, Z(A))) = Y (A, Z(A), M (A, Z(A))) = Y (0) S 3 a.s. in the event U ∈ U 1 . We also have M (A, Z(A)) = M (A, Z(A)) a.s. in the event U ∈ U 2 , and therefore Y (0) S 4 = Y (0) S 3 .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4">Theorem 5</head><p>Proof The proof of this result follows steps analogous to those in the proof of Proposition 1. Therefore, we will only sketch the arguments of the proof for P 2 . Assume E(A) = 0 and that Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 4 , Z(a 3 ))) is increasing in a 2 for all (a 1 , a 3 , a 4 , u Y , w). This implies that Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 4 , z)) is increasing in a 2 for all (a 1 , z, a 4 , u Y , w). Define v Y = (u Y , u M , u Z ), and let (ρ, β P 2 ) = argmin L P 2 (r, b), where</p><formula xml:id="formula_115">L P 2 (r, b) = E{Y ( Ā, Z(A), M (A, Z A )) -r(W, M (A, Z A ), V Y ) -bA} 2</formula><p>By Lemma 1, β P 2 ≥ 0. The proposition follows because, as before, E[Var(A | W )]β P 2 = θ P 2 , and therefore θ P 2 and β P 2 have the same sign.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.5">Theorem 6</head><p>Proof We will prove the results for each random variable at a time. First, note that</p><formula xml:id="formula_116">P(Y (0) S 1 ≤ y | A = a) = = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | A = a, Z(a) = z, M (a, z) = m, W = w, A = a ′ ]× dP(a ′ | w)dP(Z(a) = z | a, w)dP(M (a, z) = m | Z(a) = z, a, w)dP(w | a) = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | A = a, W = w]dP(a ′ | w)dP(z | a, w)dP(m | z, a, w)dP(w | a) = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | a ′ , z, m, w]dP(a ′ | w)dP(z | a, w)dP(m | z, a, w)dP(w | a) = P[Y ≤ y | a ′ , z, m, w]dP(a ′ | w)dP(z | a, w)dP(m | z, a, w)dP(w | a),</formula><p>where the first equality follows by law of iterated expectation, the second one by the independence assumptions on the errors U and definition of counterfactuals M (a, z) and Z(a), and the fourth one by definition of the counterfactual Y (a, z, m). Note that, to simplify notation, we removed the random variables from the right hand side of the | symbol in the above probabilities.</p><p>We also have</p><formula xml:id="formula_117">P(Y (1) S 1 ≤ y | A = a) = = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | A = a, Z(a) = z, M (a, z ′ ) = m, W = w, Z A = z ′ , A = a ′ ]× dP(a ′ | w)dP(Z(a) = z | a, w)dP(M (a, z ′ ) = m | Z(a) = z, a, w)dP(z ′ | a, w)dP(w | a) = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | A = a, W = w]dP(a ′ | w)dP(z | a, w)dP(m | z ′ , a, w)dP(z ′ | a, w)dP(w | a) = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | a ′ , z, m, w]dP(a ′ | w)dP(z | a, w)dP(m | z ′ , a, w)dP(z ′ | a, w)dP(w | a) = P[Y ≤ y | a ′ , z, m, w]dP(a ′ | w)dP(z | a, w)dP(m | a, w)dP(w | a). Furthermore, P(Y (1) S 2 ≤ y | A = a) = = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | A = a, Z(a ′ ) = z, M (a, z ′ ) = m, W = w, Z A = z ′ , A = a ′ ]× dP(a ′ | w)dP(z ′ | a, w)dP(M (a, z ′ ) = m | Z(a ′ ) = z, a, w)dP(Z(a ′ ) = z | a, w)dP(w | a) = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | A = a, W = w]dP(a ′ | w)dP(z ′ | a, w)dP(m | z ′ , a, w)dP(z | a ′ , w)dP(w | a) = P[Y ≤ y | a ′ , z, m, w]dP(a ′ | w)dP(z ′ | a, w)dP(m | z ′ , a, w)dP(z | a ′ , w)dP(w | a) = P[Y ≤ y | a ′ , z, m, w]dP(a ′ | w)dP(m | a, w)dP(z | a ′ , w)dP(w | a) = P[Y ≤ y | a ′ , z, m, w]dP(z, a ′ | w)dP(m, w | a)</formula><p>and,</p><formula xml:id="formula_118">P(Y (2) S 2 ≤ y | A = a) = = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | A = a, Z(a) = z ′ , M (a, z ′ ) = m, W = w, Z A = z, A = a ′ ]× dP(a ′ | w)dP(z | a ′ , w)dP(M (a, z ′ ) = m | Z(a) = z ′ , a, w)dP(Z(a) = z ′ | a, w)dP(w | a) = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | A = a, W = w]dP(a ′ | w)dP(z | a ′ , w)dP(m | z ′ , a, w)dP(z ′ | a, w)dP(w | a) = P[Y ≤ y | a ′ , z, m, w]dP(a ′ | w)dP(z | a ′ , w)dP(m | z ′ , a, w)dP(z ′ | a, w)dP(w | a) = P[Y ≤ y | a ′ , z, m, w]dP(z, a ′ | w)dP(m, w | a)</formula><p>In addition,</p><formula xml:id="formula_119">P(Y (2) S 3 ≤ y | A = a) = = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | A = a, Z(a ′ ) = z ′ , M (a, z ′ ) = m, W = w, Z A = z, A = a ′ ]× dP(z | a ′ , w)dP(M (a, z ′ ) = m | Z(a ′ ) = z ′ , a, w)dP(Z(a ′ ) = z ′ | a, w)dP(a ′ | w)dP(w | a) = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | A = a, W = w]dP(z | a ′ , w)dP(m | z ′ , a, w)dP(z ′ | a ′ , w)dP(a ′ | w)dP(w | a) = P[Y ≤ y | a ′ , z, m, w]dP(z | a ′ , w)dP(m | z ′ , a, w)dP(z ′ | a ′ , w)dP(a ′ | w)dP(w | a),</formula><p>As well as,</p><formula xml:id="formula_120">P(Y (0) S 3 ≤ y | A = a) = = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | A = a, Z(a ′ ) = z, M (a, z) = m, W = w, A = a ′ ]× dP(a ′ | w)dP(M (a, z) = m | Z(a ′ ) = z, a, w)dP(Z(a ′ ) = z | a, w)dP(w | a) = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | A = a, W = w]dP(a ′ | w)dP(m | z, a, w)dP(z | a ′ , w)dP(w | a) = P[Y ≤ y | a ′ , z, m, w]dP(a ′ | w)dP(m | z, a, w)dP(z | a ′ , w)dP(w | a) = P[Y ≤ y | a ′ , z, m, w]dP(z, a ′ | w)dP(m | z, a, w)dP(w | a), Lastly, P(Y (0) S 4 ≤ y | A = a) = = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | A = a, Z(a ′ ) = z, M (a ′ , z) = m, W = w, A = a ′ ]× dP(a ′ | w)dP(M (a ′ , z) = m | Z(a ′ ) = z, a, w)dP(Z(a ′ ) = z | a, w)dP(w | a) = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | A = a, W = w]dP(a ′ | w)dP(m | z, a ′ , w)dP(z | a ′ , w)dP(w | a) = P[Y (a ′ , z, m) ≤ y | m, a, z, w]dP(a ′ | w)dP(m | z, a ′ , w)dP(z | a ′ , w)dP(w | a) = P[Y ≤ y | m, a ′ , z, w]dP(a ′ | w)dP(m | z, a ′ , w)dP(z | a ′ , w)dP(w | a) = P[Y ≤ y | w]dP(w | a).</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.6">Proposition 2</head><p>First, note that in the event U ∈ U 1 we have Y</p><formula xml:id="formula_121">(0) S 1 = Y (0) S 3 , Y (2) S 2 = Y (2)</formula><p>S 3 , and Y</p><p>(1) <ref type="table"></ref>and<ref type="table">Y</ref> (1) <ref type="table"></ref>and<ref type="table">Y</ref> (2)</p><formula xml:id="formula_122">S 1 = Y (1) S 2 . In the event U ∈ U 2 we have Y (0) S 1 = Y (1) S 1 , Y (2) S 2 = Y (2) S 3 ,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_123">S 2 = Y S 3 . Furthermore, in the event U ∈ U 3 we have Y (0) S 1 = Y (2) S 2 , Y (1) S 1 = Y (1) S 2 ,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_124">S 3 = Y (0) S 3 .</formula><p>We have</p><formula xml:id="formula_125">D(P (0) S 1 , P (1) S 1 ) = D(P (0) S 3 (• | U 1 ), P (1) S 2 (• | U 1 ))P(U 1 )<label>(7)</label></formula><p>+ D(P</p><p>(2)</p><formula xml:id="formula_126">S 2 (• | U 3 ), P<label>(1)</label></formula><p>S 2 (• | U 3 ))P(U 3 ). ( <ref type="formula">8</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_127">D(P<label>(1)</label></formula><p>S 2 , P</p><p>S 2 ) = D(P</p><p>S 2 (• | U 1 ), P</p><p>(2)</p><formula xml:id="formula_130">S 3 (• | U 1 ))P(U 1 )<label>(9)</label></formula><p>+ D(P (0)</p><formula xml:id="formula_131">S 3 (• | U 2 ), P<label>(2)</label></formula><p>S 3 (• | U 2 ))P(U 2 ) (10)</p><formula xml:id="formula_132">+ D(P<label>(1)</label></formula><p>S 2 (• | U 3 ), P</p><p>S 2 (• | U 3 ))P(U 3 ). ( <ref type="formula">11</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_134">D(P<label>(2)</label></formula><p>S 3 , P</p><p>S 3 ) = D(P</p><p>S 3 (• | U 1 ), P</p><p>S 3 (• | U 1 ))P(U 1 )</p><p>+ D(P</p><p>(2)</p><formula xml:id="formula_139">S 3 (• | U 2 ), P<label>(0)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_140">S 3 (• | U 2 ))P(U 2 ).<label>(13)</label></formula><p>By the assumptions of the lemma we have (7)+( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_130">9</ref>)+(12) = 0, (8)+(11) = 0, and (10)+(13) = 0, concluding the proof of the lemma.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Theorem 10</head><p>We first give the form of the canonical gradients, and then prove the result. The canonical gradients are given by ϕ Proof The proof of the theorem proceeds as follows. We prove the result for (i, k) = (0, 1) and (i, k) =</p><p>(1, 1), the other results can be obtained using the same arguments. We assume the distributions G and P have densities g and p dominated by a measure λ. We use f dλ to denote f (x)dλ(x), and use bf ′ g ⋆ h ′⋆ dλ to denote b(m, z, a, w)f (m, z, a ′ , w)g(m, z ⋆ , a, w)h(m, z ⋆ , a ′ , w)λ(m, z, z ⋆ , a, a ′ , w).</p><p>For (i, k) = (0, 1), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_141">τ (0) 1 (G) -τ (0) 1 (P) + E P [ϕ (0) 1 (X; G)] = = f g M g Z g A g ′ M g ′ Z (m ′ P -m ′ G )p ′ M p ′ Z p ′ A p W dλ + f m ′ G g M g Z g A p ′ A p W dλ -f m ′ G g M g Z g A g ′ A p W dλ + f m ′ G p M p Z p A g ′ A p W dλ -f m ′ G p M p Z p A p ′ A p W dλ = f p ′ M p ′ Z g ′ M g ′ Z -1 m ′ P -m ′ G g M g Z g A p ′ A p W dλ + f (g M g Z g A -p M p Z p A ) m P p ′ A -m G g ′ A p W dλ.</formula><p>Likewise, for (i, k) = (1, 1), we have τ The assumption R where m 1 ∈ supp{M (a 3 , Z(a 4 ))}, and m 2 ∈ supp{M (a 0 , Z(a 4 ))}.</p><p>Proof We show the proof for the third statement, assuming a discrete variable M . The other statements can be proved using parallel arguments. The statement is of the form if p then q, we will prove the contrapositive if not q then not p. We have |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 3 , Z(a 4 ))) -Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 0 , Z(a 4 )))| = m =m ′ |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), m) -Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), m ′ )|1{M (a 3 , Z(a 4 )) = m, M (a 0 , Z(a 4 )) = m ′ }.</p><p>Assume there is a set U ⋆ ⊆ U with P(U ⋆ ) &gt; 0 and values ā, m 1 ∈ supp{M (a 3 , Z(a 4 ))}, and m 2 ∈ supp{M (a 0 , Z(a 4 ))} such that Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), m 1 ) = Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), m 2 ) and M (a 3 , Z(a 4 )) = M (a 0 , Z(a 4 ))</p><p>in U ⋆ (i.e., assume not q). Then, |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 3 , Z(a 4 ))) -Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 0 , Z(a 4 )))| ≥ |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), m 1 ) -Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), m 2 )|1{M (a 3 , Z(a 4 )) = m 1 , M (a 0 , Z(a 4 )) = m 2 }.</p><p>The probability that the term in the right hand side is positive is greater than zero in U ⋆ (i.e., not p), concluding the proof of the claim.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>to assess the effect of many node interventions. Furthermore, if A is randomized, this identification result reduces to P(Y ≤ y | A = a), in agreement with the idea that the causal relation between A and Y is not confounded in a randomized experiment. Corollary 1. Under the assumed SCM (A1) we have Cov(A, Y -Y S ) = θ and Cov(A, Y S ) = τ , where</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the first equality follows by definition of Y (a, M(a)) : a ∈ {0, 1} and the second by adding and subtracting E[Y (1, M(0))]. Inspection of the above formulas reveal why the NIE measures the effect through M and the NDE measures the effect through all other mechanisms. The NIE is the result of comparing the outcome in a hypothetical world where A = 1 is fixed while M is varied from what it would have been under A = 1 to what it would have been under A = 0. The NDE is the result of comparing the outcome in a hypothetical world where A is varied from A = 1 to A = 0 while fixing M to what it would have been under A = 0.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Consider a random draw G(a) from the distribution of M(a) conditional on W . Randomized mediational effects are concerned with interventions that set the mediator to G(1) and G(0) instead of M(1)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>contrast of the distributions P(Y S j ≤ y | A = a) and P(Y S i-1 ≤ y | A = a), for j = 1, 2, 3, 4. (A related definition of path-specific influence is proposed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b92">Zhang and Bareinboim (2018)</ref> in terms of a covariance contrast and using atomic interventions.) However, some of these causal influence measures are not identified due to the recanting witness problem outlined in the previous section. Specifically, the probability distribution of Y S 2 is not identifiable because Z operates as a recanting witness through the paths A → Z → Y and A → Z → M → Y . This means that the causal influence through the path A → Z → Y , defined as a contrasts between P(Y S 2 ≤ y | A = a) and P(Y S 1 ≤ y | A = a) is not identified. The same is true for the causal influence through the path A → Z → M → Y , defined as a contrasts between P(Y S 3 ≤ y | A = a) and P(Y S 2 ≤ y | A = a).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>S 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>the influence of A on Y operating through the path A → Z → M → Y operates by means of the random draw Z A , whereas the influence operating through the path A → Z → Y operates through the natural value of Z. These edge emulation interventions substitute a path A → Z → • • • → Y by a synthetic path A → Z A → • • • → Y that transfer the same information as the original path. The edge-emulation intervention is what allow us to do away with the recanting witness problem to obtain causal influence measures that satisfy the path-specific sharp null criterion.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Theorem 4 (</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Decomposition of the total influence into path-specific influences). Assume that the contrast function D is linear in the sense that D(P, F) = D(P, G) + D(G, F) for any distributions F, P, and G. Define the path-specific influences θ P 1 = D(P</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Proposition 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Assume the contrast D is linear as in Theorem 4. In addition, assume that D is such that D(P, F) = S∈S D(P(• | S), F(• | S))P(S) for any partition S of the sample space, and that it satisfies D(F, F) = 0. Let U denote the range of U = (U W , U A , U Z , U M , U Y ). Assume U can be partitioned in sets U 1 , U 2 , and U 3 such that the following hold almost surely • sup ā |Z(a 1 ) -Z(a 0 )| = 0 in U 1 , and</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>fect operate independently through each of the different causal pathways. Agency interventions are then conceptualized on each separable component. Our goal in this section is to define mediation parameters for the common case where such structural information is unavailable, at the expense of abandoning the agency interpretation of the path-specific effects. Consider the ATE ψ = E[Y (1) -Y (0)] introduced in §3.1, and note that under our assumed SCM we have Y (a) = Y (a, Z(a), M(a, Z(a))). Then we could use the following counterfactuals to define path-specific effects:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>and U 3 such that the following hold almost surely • Z(1) = Z(0) in U 1 , and • sup z |M(z 1 ) -Z(z 0 )| = 0 in U 2 , and</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>allowing path-interventions to be defined in terms of the recanting witness node, we are able to define path-specific effects which are non-parametrically identifiable. A general theory for path-intervention that allow for interventions on nodes other than the source node seems to be an important direction of future work. The interventions we propose also share connections with the interventions proposed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Malinsky (2018)</ref>. These general "macro-level" interventions focus on hypothetical worlds where the structural equations had been replaced for alternative, user-given equations. Some of our information transfer interventions can be interpreted in this way, for example by noticing that the distribution of the outcome in a hypothetical world where we set A = A is equal to the distribution of the outcome where the argument a is marginalized out from the structural function f A , where the marginalization is with respect to the distribution P(a | W ).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Z | A, W ) {Y -E(Y | A, Z, M, W )} + f (a)E(Y | A, z, m, W )dP(m, z, a | W ) f (a)E(Y | a ′ , z, m, W )dP(m, z, a | W )dP(a ′ | W ) + f (A) E(Y | a ′ , Z, M, W )dP(a ′ | W ) ϕ , Z, W ) p(M, Z | A, W ) {Y -E(Y | A, Z, M, W )} + f (a)E(Y | A, z, m, W )dP(m | a, W )dP(z | a, W )dP(a | W ) f (a)E(Y | a ′ , z, m, W )dP(m | a, W )dP(z | a, W )dP(a | W )dP(a ′ | W ) + f (A) E(Y | a ′ , Z, m, W )dP(m | A, W )dP(a ′ | W ) f (A) E(Y | a ′ , z, m, W )dP(m | A, W )dP(z | A, W )dP(a ′ | W ) + f (A) E(Y | a ′ , z, M, W )dP(z | A, W )dP(a ′ | W ) W ) p(M | Z, A, W ) {Y -E(Y | A, Z, M, W )} + f (a)E(Y | A, Z, m, W )dP(m | a, W )dP(a | W ) f (a)E(Y | a ′ , z, m, W )dP(m | a, W )dP(a | W )dP(z, a ′ | W ) + f (A) E(Y | a ′ , z, M, W )dP(z, a ′ | W ) , A, W ) p(M | Z, AW ) {Y -E(Y | A, Z, M, W )} + f (a)E(Y | A, Z, m, W )dP(m | a, z ′ , W )dP(z ′ | A, W )dP(a | W ) f (a)E(Y | a ′ , z, m, W )dP(m | a, z ′ , W )dP(z ′ | a ′ , W )dP(z | a ′ , W )dP(a | W )dP(a ′ | W ) + f (A) p(Z | A, W ) E(Y | a ′ , z, M, W )dP(z | a ′ , W )p(Z | a ′ , W )dP(a ′ | W ) -f (A) p(Z | A, W ) E(Y | a ′ , z, m, W )dP(m | A, Z, W )dP(z | a ′ , W )p(Z | a ′ , W )dP(a ′ | W ) + f (a)E(Y | A, z, m, W )dP(z | A, W )dP(m | a, Z, W )dP(a | W ) f (a)E(Y | A, z, m, W )dP(m | a, z ′ , W )dP(z | A, W )dP(z ′ | A, W )dP(a | W ) + f (A) E(Y | a ′ , z, m, W )dP(m | A, z ′ , W )dP(z | a ′ , W )dP(z ′ | a ′ , W )dP(a ′ | W ) | A, W ) E(Y | a ′ , Z, M, W )p(Z | a ′ , W )dP(a ′ | W ) + f (A) p(Z | A, W ) E(Y | a ′ , Z, m, W )dP(m | A, Z, W )p(Z | a ′ , W )dP(a ′ | W ) + f (a)E(Y | A, Z, m, W )dP(m | a, Z, W )dP(a | W ) f (a)E(Y | a ′ , z, m, W )dP(m | a, z, W )dP(z | a ′ , W )dP(a | W )dP(a ′ | W ) + f (A) E(Y | a ′ , z, m, W )dP(m | A, z, W )dP(z | a ′ , W )dP(a ′ | W ) {Y -E(Y | W )} + f (A)E(Y | W ) Z, W ) = f (a)p(M, Z | a, W )dP(a | W ) Z, W ) = f (a)p(Z | a, W )p(M | a, W )dP(a | W ) W ) = f(a)p(M | a, W )dP(a | W ) A, W ) = f (a)p(M | a, z ′ , W )dP(z ′ | A, W )dP(a | W ) h (0) 3 (M, Z, W ) = f (a)p(M | a, Z, W )dP(a | W ) h (0) 4 (W ) = f (a)dP(a | W ).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>v φ(•; ηv ), τ = P φ(•; η).Thus, √ n{ττ } = G n { φ(•; η)τ } + R n,1 + R n,2 , v { φ(•; ηv )φ(•; η)}, R n,2 = √ n J V v=1 P{ φ(•; ηv )τ }.It remains to show that R n,1 and R n,2 are o P (1). Theorem 10 together with the assumption that R(k) j (η, η) = o P (n -1/2 ) shows that R n,2 = o P (1). For R n,1 we use empirical process theory to argue conditional on the training sample T v . In particular, Lemma 19.33 of van der Vaart (1998) applied to the class of functions F = { φ(•; ηv )φ(•; η)} (which consists of one element) yields E G n,v ( φ(•; ηv )φk j (•; η)) T v 2C log 2 n 1/2 + || φ(•; ηv )φ(•; η)||(log 2) 1/2</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>η) = o P (n -1/2 ) can only hold if ηη = o P (1), therefore the right hand side is o P (1). Lemma 6.1 ofChernozhukov et al. (2018)  may now be used to argue that conditional convergence implies unconditional convergence, concluding the proof.3 Auxiliary resultsLemma 3. Let U denote the range of U = (U W , U A , U Z , U M , U Y ). The following statements are true:1. P{sup ā |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 3 , Z(a 4 ))) -Y (a 1 , Z(a 0 ), M (a 3 , Z(a 4 )))| = 0} = 1 implies U can be partitioned into sets U 1 and U 2 such that (a) P{sup ā,z |Y (a 1 , z 1 , M (a 3 , Z(a 4 ))) -Y (a 1 , z 2 , M (a 3 , Z(a 4 )))| = 0 | U ∈ U 1 } = 1, and (b) P{sup ā |Z(a 2 ) -Z(a 0 )| = 0 | U ∈ U 2 } = 1,where z 1 ∈ supp{Z(a 2 )} and z 2 ∈ supp{Z(a 0 )}.2. P{supā |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 3 , Z(a 4 ))) -Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 3 , Z(a 0 )))| = 0} = 1 implies U can be partitioned into sets U 1 , U 2 , and U 3 such that (a) P{sup ā, m |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), m 1 ) -Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), m 2 )| = 0 | U ∈ U 1 } = 1, and (b) P{sup ā,z |M (a 3 , z 1 ) -M (a 3 , z 2 )| = 0 | U ∈ U 2 } = 1, and (c) P{sup ā |Z(a 4 ) -Z(a 0 )| = 0 | U ∈ U 3 } = 1where m 1 ∈ supp{M (a 3 , Z(a 4 ))} and m 2 ∈ supp{M (a 3 , Z(a 0 ))}, and z 1 ∈ supp{Z(a 4 )} and z 2 ∈ supp{Z(a 0 )}.3. P{supā |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 3 , Z(a 4 ))) -Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), M (a 0 , Z(a 4 )))| = 0} = 1 implies U can be partitioned into sets U 1 and U 2 such that (a) P{sup ā, m |Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), m 1 ) -Y (a 1 , Z(a 2 ), m 2 )| = 0 | U ∈ U 1 } = 1,and (b) P{sup ā |M (a 3 , Z(a 4 )) -M (a 0 , Z(a 4 ))| = 0 | U ∈ U 2 } = 1,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Variables such as Z, which are affected by A and are a common cause of the mediator Causal graph associated to the SCM in equation (1), where the interest is in measuring the causal relation between A and Y and quantifying how it operates through M. For illustrative convenience the exogenous variables U.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>W</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>A</cell><cell>Z</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Figure 1:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>and outcome, are often referred to as intermediate confounders. In this causal graph, one may be interested in mediation analysis in the sense of quantifying all paths from A to Y that involve M (indirect paths) vs all other paths (direct paths). An alternative and arguably more complete analysis would involve understanding the causal relation between A and Y as it operates through each path</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>). A causality measure satisfies the sharp null criterion if it is null whenever there is no causal influence.</figDesc><table /><note><p><p>P2 (Monotonicity criterion). A causality measure satisfies the monotonicity criterion if (i) it is less</p>than its null value whenever Y (a) is monotone decreasing in a almost surely, and (ii) it is greater than its null value whenever Y (a) is monotone increasing in a almost surely.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>operates as an direct mechanism through the path A → Z → Y and as an indirect mechanism through the path A → Z → M → Y , leading to the lack of identifiability of either the direct or the indirect effect. Multiple alternatives exist to conduct mediation analysis in the presence of intermediate confounding. For example, if the relation A → Z is monotonic, Tchetgen Tchetgen and VanderWeele (2014) showed that the NDE and NIE are point-identified and Rudolph et al. (2023) developed nonparametric estimators for the identifying functionals. Alternatively, Miles et al. (2015) gave partial identification bounds for the NDE and NIE. A third option is to target a different definition of direct</figDesc><table /><note><p>Table 1 of Avin et al., 2005), leading to lack of identifiability of the NIE and NDE. The variable Z is often referred to as a recanting witness because it</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Table 2 do not require to interpret hypothetical and infeasible interventions that would modify someone's gender. Instead, we compute the causal covariance between gender and wage expectations θ, and decompose it into path-specific covariances.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="4">Parameter Estimate Lower CI Upper CI</cell></row><row><cell>θ</cell><cell>0.330</cell><cell>0.240</cell><cell>0.421</cell></row><row><cell>θ P 1</cell><cell>0.302</cell><cell>0.205</cell><cell>0.398</cell></row><row><cell>θ P 2</cell><cell>0.021</cell><cell>-0.285</cell><cell>0.327</cell></row><row><cell>θ P 3</cell><cell>0.003</cell><cell>-0.004</cell><cell>0.010</cell></row><row><cell>θ P 4</cell><cell>0.003</cell><cell>-0.003</cell><cell>0.010</cell></row><row><cell>θ P 2 ∨P 3</cell><cell>0.001</cell><cell>-0.332</cell><cell>0.335</cell></row><row><cell>Table</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>This view is often called "the interventionist view of causality" (e.g.,Robins et al.,  </p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>2022), although that designation is a misnomer since all counterfactual views of causality, whether they are agency or non-agency, involve interventions<ref type="bibr" target="#b88">(Woodward, 2003)</ref>. A more appropriate label would be "the agency view of causality"<ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Menzies and Price, 1993)</ref>.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_2"><p>Following the cited literature, we use the phrase "information transfer" to refer to the interventions used in the paper. However, our use of the word information does not necessarily correspond its use in the field of "information theory".</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_3"><p>The agential layer is often referred to as "interventional", although this is possibly a misnomer since the counterfactual layer also uses interventions<ref type="bibr" target="#b88">(Woodward, 2003)</ref>.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_4"><p>Some of this work uses the expression "interventionist view of causality" to refer to their methods. The expression "agency view of causality" would have been more appropriate as all counterfactual causal inference involves interventions.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>This work was supported through a <rs type="funder">Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute (PCORI)</rs> <rs type="grantName">Project Program Award</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">ME-2021C2-23636-IC</rs>).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_qxvdJ33">
					<idno type="grant-number">ME-2021C2-23636-IC</idno>
					<orgName type="grant-name">Project Program Award</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary Materials for</head><p>Proof Assume without loss of generality that E(A) = 0. This follows from application of Lemma 2 below to</p><p>Lemma 1. Let (X, L) ∼ P any random variables, and let f (x, y) be a function such that f (•, y) is increasing</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Proof of Theorem 11</head><p>Proof To simplify notation we remove the index j and superindex k from τ k j to simplify notation. Let P n,v denote the empirical distribution of the prediction set P v , and let G n,v denote the associated empirical process</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifiability of path-specific effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chen</forename><surname>Avin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ilya</forename><surname>Shpitser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Judea</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IJCAI International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="357" to="363" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Doubly robust estimation in missing data and causal inference models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Heejung</forename><surname>Bang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="962" to="973" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On pearl&apos;s hierarchy and the foundations of causal inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elias</forename><surname>Bareinboim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Juan</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Correa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Duligur</forename><surname>Ibeling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Icard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Probabilistic and causal inference: the works of judea pearl</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="507" to="556" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information and asymptotic efficiency in parametric-nonparametric models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Janet M Begun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wei-Min</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jon</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wellner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Annals of Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="432" to="452" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Are emily and greg more employable than lakisha and jamal? a field experiment on labor market discrimination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Marianne</forename><surname>Bertrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sendhil</forename><surname>Mullainathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American economic review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="991" to="1013" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Efficient and Adaptive Estimation for Semiparametric Models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Peter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chris</forename><forename type="middle">Aj</forename><surname>Bickel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ya'acov</forename><surname>Klaassen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jon</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ritov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wellner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hugo</forename><surname>Bodory</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=causalweight" />
		<title level="m">Estimation Methods for Causal Inference Based on Inverse Probability Weighting</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>R package version 1.0.2</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What triggers public opposition to immigration? anxiety, group cues, and immigration threat</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ted</forename><surname>Brader</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicholas</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Valentino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename><surname>Suhay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="959" to="978" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">When to start treatment? a systematic approach to the comparison of dynamic regimes using observational data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lauren</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Emilie</forename><surname>Lanoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Roger</forename><surname>Logan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dominique</forename><surname>Costagliola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Miguel</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hernán</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The international journal of biostatistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information-theoretic implications of quantum causal structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rafael</forename><surname>Chaves</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christian</forename><surname>Majenz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Gross</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The value of study abroad experience in the labor market: Findings from a resume audit experiment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Albert</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laura</forename><surname>Florick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Double/debiased machine learning for treatment and structural parameters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Victor</forename><surname>Chernozhukov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Denis</forename><surname>Chetverikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mert</forename><surname>Demirer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Esther</forename><surname>Duflo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christian</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Whitney</forename><surname>Newey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Econometrics Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="C68" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causation is the transfer of information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John D</forename><surname>Collier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Causation and laws of nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="245" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Commentary: The formal approach to quantitative causal inference in epidemiology: misguided or misrepresented?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rhian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bianca L De</forename><surname>Daniel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stijn</forename><surname>Stavola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International journal of epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1817" to="1829" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causal mediation analysis for stochastic interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Iván</forename><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hejazi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B (Statistical Methodology)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="661" to="683" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Population intervention causal effects based on stochastic interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Iván</forename><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="541" to="549" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing the causal effect of policies: an example using stochastic interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Iván</forename><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The international journal of biostatistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonparametric efficient causal mediation with intermediate confounders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Iván</forename><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kara</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hejazi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mark</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rudolph</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="627" to="641" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonparametric causal effects based on longitudinal modified treatment policies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Iván</forename><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicholas</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Katherine</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Edward</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Schenck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Causal survival analysis under competing risks using longitudinal modified treatment policies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Iván</forename><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Katherine</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nima</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hejazi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2202.03513</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Iván</forename><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicholas</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kara</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rudolph</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2203.15085</idno>
		<title level="m">Efficient and flexible causal mediation with timevarying mediators, treatments, and confounders</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct and indirect effects of sequential treatments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vanessa</forename><surname>Didelez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sara</forename><surname>Philip Dawid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Geneletti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Twenty-Second Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the Twenty-Second Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="138" to="146" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interventions and causal inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Frederick</forename><surname>Eberhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Scheines</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophy of science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="981" to="995" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Independent contribution of polygenic risk for schizophrenia and cannabis use in predicting psychotic-like experiences in young adulthood: testing gene× environment moderation and mediation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Elkrief</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bochao</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mattia</forename><surname>Marchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mohammad</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Afzali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tobias</forename><surname>Banaschewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Arun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Erin</forename><surname>Bokde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sylvane</forename><surname>Burke Quinlan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Herta</forename><surname>Desrivières</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hugh</forename><surname>Flor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Garavan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation, partial correlation, and causation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Frederick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ellett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ericson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Synthese</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="173" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gender differences in wage expectations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ana</forename><surname>Fernandes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Giannina</forename><surname>Vaccaro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plos one</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">250892</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Probabilistic measures of causal strength. na</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Branden</forename><surname>Fitelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christopher</forename><surname>Hitchcock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Partial correlation analysis indicates causal relationships between gc-content, exon density and recombination rate in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Freudenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mingyi</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yaning</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wentian</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Audit studies: Behind the scenes with theory, method, and nuance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Gaddis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Commentary: race and sex are causes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Clark</forename><surname>Glymour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Madelyn</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Glymour</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="488" to="490" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating public health interventions: 5. causal inference in public health research-do sex, race, and biological factors cause health outcomes?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><surname>Glymour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Donna</forename><surname>Spiegelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American journal of public health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Heyang</forename><surname>Gong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ke</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1907.11090</idno>
		<idno>arXiv:2106.03178</idno>
		<title level="m">Heyang Gong and Ke Zhu. Path-specific effects based on information accounts of causality</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019. 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring individual differences in implicit cognition: the implicit association test</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Debbie</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Anthony G Greenwald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jordan Lk</forename><surname>Mcghee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of personality and social psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1464</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Manipulation and the causal markov condition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Hausman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophy of Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="846" to="856" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does water kill? a call for less casual causal inferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Miguel</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hernán</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="674" to="680" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does obesity shorten life? the importance of well-defined interventions to answer causal questions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Miguel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sarah</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hernán</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Taubman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International journal of obesity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8" to="S14" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistics and causal inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Holland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">396</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="945" to="960" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Causality: Philosophical theory meets scientific practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Phyllis</forename><surname>Illari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Federica</forename><surname>Russo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>OUP</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantifying causal influences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dominik</forename><surname>Janzing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Balduzzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Moritz</forename><surname>Grosse-Wentrup</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bernhard</forename><surname>Schölkopf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Annals of Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2324" to="2358" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonparametric causal effects based on incremental propensity score interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Edward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">526</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="645" to="656" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Varieties of causal intervention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Korb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lucas</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hope</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ann</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Nicholson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Karl</forename><surname>Axnick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">PRICAI 2004: Trends in Artificial Intelligence: 8th Pacific Rim International Conference on Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Auckland, New Zealand</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">August 9-13, 2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="322" to="331" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The tale wagged by the dag: broadening the scope of causal inference and explanation for epidemiology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nancy</forename><surname>Krieger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">George</forename><surname>Davey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Smith</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International journal of epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1787" to="1808" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Max</forename><surname>Kuhn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=caret" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">caret: Classification and Regression Training</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="0" to="90" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Higher order inference on a treatment effect under low regularity conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lingling</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eric</forename><surname>Tchetgen Tchetgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aad</forename><surname>Van Der</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Vaart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistics &amp; probability letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="821" to="828" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intervening on structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Malinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Synthese</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">195</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2295" to="2312" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causation as a secondary quality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Menzies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Huw</forename><surname>Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The British Journal for the Philosophy of Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="203" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On the causal interpretation of randomized interventional indirect effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Caleb</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Miles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Caleb H</forename><surname>Miles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Phyllis</forename><surname>Kanki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Seema</forename><surname>Meloni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eric J Tchetgen</forename><surname>Tchetgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1509.01652</idno>
		<title level="m">On partial identification of the pure direct effect</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning optimal fair policies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Razieh</forename><surname>Nabi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Malinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ilya</forename><surname>Shpitser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Conference on Machine Learning</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4674" to="4682" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Causality: Models, Reasoning, and Inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Judea</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct and indirect effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Judea</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Seventeenth conference on Uncertainty in artificial intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the Seventeenth conference on Uncertainty in artificial intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="420" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does obesity shorten life? or is it the soda? on non-manipulable causes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Judea</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Causal Inference</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the interpretation of do (x)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Judea</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Causal Inference</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>a</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2019b. Judea Pearl and Dana Mackenzie. The Book of Why</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Judea</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Causal Inference</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Basic Books</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Sufficient causes: On oxygen, matches, and fires</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A theory of inferred causation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Judea</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Verma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Studies in Logic and the Foundations of Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="789" to="811" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quadratic semiparametric von mises calculus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lingling</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eric</forename><surname>Tchetgen Tchetgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aad</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Van Der</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Vaart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Metrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2-3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="247" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal structural nested models for optimal sequential decisions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>James</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the second seattle Symposium in Biostatistics</title>
		<meeting>the second seattle Symposium in Biostatistics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="326" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifiability and exchangeability for direct and indirect effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>James</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sander</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Greenland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">0</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Alternative graphical causal models and the identification of direct effects. Causality and psychopathology: Finding the determinants of disorders and their cures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>James</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="158" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Effects of multiple interventions. Comparative quantification of health risks: global and regional burden of disease attributable to selected major risk factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Miguel</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>James M Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hernán</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Siebert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2191" to="2230" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An interventionist approach to mediation analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>James M Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ilya</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Shpitser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Probabilistic and Causal Inference: The Works of Judea Pearl</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="713" to="764" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust estimation in sequentially ignorable missing data and causal inference models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<meeting>the American Statistical Association</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation of regression coefficients when some regressors are not always observed</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rotnitzky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">427</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="846" to="866" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-09">September 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient and flexible estimation of natural direct and indirect effects under intermediate confounding and monotonicity constraints</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicholas</forename><surname>Kara E Rudolph</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Iván</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causality for machine learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bernhard</forename><surname>Schölkopf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Probabilistic and Causal Inference: The Works of Judea Pearl</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="765" to="804" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causal identification: a charge of epidemiology in danger of marginalization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sharon</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicolle</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gatto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ulka B</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="669" to="673" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The hardness of conditional independence testing and the generalised covariance measure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rajen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonas</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1214/19-AOS1857</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1214/19-AOS1857" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Annals of Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1514" to="1538" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Implicit physician biases in periviability counseling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Natasha</forename><surname>Shapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elena</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Wachtel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sean</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bailey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Espiritu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of pediatrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">197</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="115" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causal inference with a graphical hierarchy of interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ilya</forename><surname>Shpitser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eric</forename><surname>Tchetgen Tchetgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2433</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Foundations of a probabilistic theory of causal strength</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Sprenger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophical Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="371" to="398" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conditional separable effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mats</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stensrud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aaron</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eric</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sarvet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jessica</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tchetgen Tchetgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Separable effects for causal inference in the presence of competing events</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mats</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jessica</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Stensrud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vanessa</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Didelez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Miguel</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hernán</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">537</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="183" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On identification of natural direct effects when a confounder of the mediator is directly affected by exposure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eric</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tchetgen</forename><surname>Tchetgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tyler</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vanderweele</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">282</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">mediation: R package for causal mediation analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dustin</forename><surname>Tingley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Teppei</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kentaro</forename><surname>Hirose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Luke</forename><surname>Keele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kosuke</forename><surname>Imai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.jstatsoft.org/v59/i05/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Statistical Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct effect models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maya</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The international journal of biostatistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Unified Methods for Censored Longitudinal Data and Causality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Targeted Learning: Causal Inference for Observational and Experimental Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sherri</forename><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Targeted Learning in Data Science: Causal Inference for Complex longitudinal Studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sherri</forename><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Targeted maximum likelihood learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Journal of Biostatistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">History-adjusted marginal structural models and statically-optimal dynamic treatment regimens</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maya</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Marshall</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Joffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Journal of Biostatistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Van Der</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Vaart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Asymptotic Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causality and causal inference in epidemiology: the need for a pluralistic approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Vandenbroucke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alex</forename><surname>Broadbent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Neil</forename><surname>Pearce</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International journal of epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1776" to="1786" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect decomposition in the presence of an exposure-induced mediator-outcome confounder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tyler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stijn</forename><surname>Vanderweele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">300</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the asymptotic distribution of differentiable statistical functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mises</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The annals of mathematical statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="348" />
			<date type="published" when="1947">1947</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Signal manipulation and the causal status of race</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Naftali</forename><surname>Weinberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b85">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Intervention treatment distributions that depend on the observed treatment process and model double robustness in causal survival analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lan</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Julia</forename><surname>Marcus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jessica</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2112.00807</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b86">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding and addressing racial disparities in health care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Toni</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health care financing review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">75</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b87">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The inflation technique for causal inference with latent variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elie</forename><surname>Wolfe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Spekkens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tobias</forename><surname>Fritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Causal Inference</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b88">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Making Things Happen: A Theory of Causal Explanation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, US</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b89">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sewall Wright. The theory of path coefficients a reply to niles&apos;s criticism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sewall</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The annals of mathematical statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="1921">1921. 1923. 1934</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Journal of agricultural research</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b90">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Longer screen time utilization is associated with the polygenic risk for attentiondeficit/hyperactivity disorder with mediation by brain white matter microstructure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anyi</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Edmund</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Rolls</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Guiying</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jingnan</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yuzhu</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jianfeng</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wei</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Xing-Ming</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EBioMedicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104039</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b91">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification, estimation and approximation of risk under interventions that depend on the natural value of treatment using observational data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jessica G</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Miguel</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hernán</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiologic methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b92">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-parametric path analysis in structural causal models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Junzhe</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elias</forename><surname>Bareinboim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 34th Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the 34th Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b93">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cross-validated targeted minimum-loss-based estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wenjing</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Targeted Learning</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="459" to="474" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b94">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Double/debiased machine learning for treatment and structural parameters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Victor</forename><surname>Chernozhukov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Denis</forename><surname>Chetverikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mert</forename><surname>Demirer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Esther</forename><surname>Duflo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christian</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Whitney</forename><surname>Newey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Econometrics Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="C68" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b95">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Van Der</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Vaart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Asymptotic Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
