<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of Death Anxiety based on Body Image Concerns Mediated by Disease Perception in Patients with Breast Cancer</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kefayat</forename><surname>Salmanian</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Ahvaz Branch</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Islamic Azad University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ahvaz</settlement>
									<country key="IR">Iran</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Marashian</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Fatemeh</forename><surname>Sadat</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Ahvaz Branch</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Islamic Azad University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ahvaz</settlement>
									<country key="IR">Iran</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Fatemeh</forename><surname>Sadat Marashian</surname></persName>
							<email>fsadatmarashian@gmail.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Nursing Department of Psychology Ahvaz Branch Islamic</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Azad University Ahvaz Iran</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Mageswaari Rajoo Bangkok</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="TH">Thailand</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Gabriela Lezcano San Francisco</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of Death Anxiety based on Body Image Concerns Mediated by Disease Perception in Patients with Breast Cancer</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.22359/cswhi_13_5_12</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T01:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Body Image</term>
					<term>Breast Cancer</term>
					<term>Death Anxiety</term>
					<term>Disease Perception</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The present study aimed to predict death anxiety based on body image concerns mediated by disease perception in patients with breast cancer. In this descriptive correlation study, Templer's Death Anxiety Scale, Littleton's Body Image Concern Inventory, and Broadbent's Brief Illness Perception Questionnaire were used to collect data. The statistical population included all patients with breast cancer in Abadan City in 2020 who were referred to medical centers for six months. A total of 200 of whom were selected as the sample of the study using convenience sampling. The proposed model was evaluated using path analysis with AMOS software. The results showed that there</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Breast cancer is the most common cancer diagnosed among women globally. It is most often seen in the middle of life between the ages of 35 and 55 years <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>. Prognosis improvement and timely diagnosis result in an increased number of women living with the consequences of the disease and complications associated with its treatment. A major consequence of cancer treatment is temporary or permanent changes in the appearance, feelings, and function of the body <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>. Therefore, post-treatment changes in appearance can cause body image concerns (BICs) among many women, which is a warning as BIrelated concerns are accompanied by increased risks of undesired psychological and physical consequences, such as depression, anxiety, concerns related to sexual relations, and intimacy, and reduction of lifespan <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref>. Fear of death and its associated anxiety are among the effective factors of mental health in patients with cancer <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref>. Cancer diagnosis and treatment can be stressful factors <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>. During the medical or surgical interventions, the patients may experience physical symptoms. With an increase in the symptoms and reduction of perceived function, the level of anxiety and distress elevates in these patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>. These concerns are mostly due to death anxiety (DA). Existential concerns accompanied by DA can be very annoying. In patients at the advanced stage of cancer, the interaction between physical symptoms, concerns about family, age, and reduced self-esteem results in the experience of DA <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Lehto &amp; Stein (4)</ref> found that DA is an effective factor in mental health and a significant psychological diagnosis in patients with cancer. Moreover, body image (BI) is an important element of the quality of life of patients with cancer <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9)</ref>. It encompasses beliefs, as well as conscious and unconscious feel-ings. BI is a person's mental image of their physical appearance. In other words, it is a person's negative and positive feelings about their body shape and size <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>.</p><p>When a person is fighting cancer, they may face many goals and challenges, which can be medical, physical, emotional, interpersonal, and spiritual. These goals and challenges, related to the quality of life, have all been threatened and impaired by cancer. Understanding the disease symptoms is among the essential psychological and behavioral variables in cancer treatment, which is based on the acquisition of information from different sources and patient's beliefs and can affect the mental health and capability of the individual in compliance with the disease <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>. Farahbakhsh Beh et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> showed a significant negative correlation between the perception of illness and social support, and between resilience and death anxiety. Sharifi Saki et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> reported a significant relationship between the properties of psychosis and disease perception. Bibi &amp; Khalid (3) showed that there is a significant negative relationship between death anxiety and social support, that the latter contributed to a reduction of death anxiety and an increase in the recovery period. Mikulincer &amp; Florian <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> showed that there is a significant relationship between emotion - and problem-focused coping strategies with death anxiety.</p><p>Based on the literature review, scant studies have been conducted in Iran on the relationship between disease perception and BI with DA in cancer patients. However, none of them has investigated the relationship between disease perception and BI with DA in patients with breast cancer. Given the paucity of studies on patients with breast cancer, the present study sought to investigate a causal association between body image with death anxiety according to the mod-was a significant association between body image and disease perception (β=0.33, P=0.001), and death anxiety (β=0.57, P=0.001), and between disease perception and death anxiety (β= 0.39, P=0.001). There was a relationship between body image and death anxiety through the mediating role of disease perception in patients with breast cancer (P=0.009). According to the results of the study, the relationship of body image with death anxiety through the mediation of disease perception had a good fit and is an important step in identifying the factors affecting death anxiety of patients with breast cancer.</p><p>Clinical Social Work and Health Intervention Vol. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> No. 5 2022 erating role of disease perception in patients with breast cancer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p>The study was a descriptive correlation performed by path analysis. The statistical population included all patients with breast cancer in Abadan city and 200 of which were selected as the sample of the study using convenience sampling. Patients were introduced to the researcher after examination by a specialist physician and receiving a diagnosis of breast cancer. The inclusion criteria were: age range between 30-50 years, having at least a middle school education, and having no mental disorders. The exclusion criteria included failure to completely answer all the questions. Data were analyzed by descriptive and inferential statistics such as mean, standard deviation, and Pearson correlation coefficient. SPSS and AMOS were used for analyzing the data.</p><p>In this study, the following instruments were used to collect data: The Death Anxiety Scale (DAS): This scale was developed and validated by Templer in 1970. This scale is a self-executive questionnaire comprised of 15 correct-incorrect items. The total score of the questionnaire is in the range of 0 and 15, where the higher score indicates a higher degree of anxiety. The Brief Illness Perception Questionnaire (Brief IPQ): Brief IPQ is a 9-item questionnaire designed to rapidly assess cognitive and emotional representations of illness. The Brief IPQ uses a single-item scale approach to assess perception on a 0-10 response scale.</p><p>Body Image Concern Inventory (BICI): BICI was developed by Littleton et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> with 19 items measuring a person's dissatisfaction and concern about their appearance. Littleton et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> investigated the factor structure of the inventory. The results indicated that there are two important factors. The first factor is comprised of 11 items including a person's dissatisfaction with their appearance, as well as examining and hiding perceived defects or flaws in appearance. The second factor contains 8 items measuring the interference of concern about appearance with social function.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>The participants included 200 women with breast cancer. Descriptive statistics including mean and standard deviation (SD) and Pearson correlation coefficient of study variables are presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</p><p>In the proposed model, the 3 variables of body image, disease perception, and death anxiety were evaluated. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> presents the fitting indices for the proposed model. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> shows the proposed model in which the root means square error of approximation (RMSEA= 0.06; χ 2 /df= 2.44; CFI= 0.997; GFI= 0.993), indicated a good model fit.</p><p>Based on the data in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> there was a significant direct association between body image and disease perception (β= 0.33, P= 0.001). The association between disease perception and death anxiety was positive and significant (β= 0.39, P=  Clinical Social Work and Health Intervention Vol. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> No. 5 2022 0.001). We also observed a direct and significant association between body image and death anxiety (β= 0.57, P= 0.001). The indirect path from body image to death anxiety through the mediating role of disease perception was significant (β= 0.271, P= 0.009) (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion and Conclusion</head><p>The present study aimed to investigate a causal association between body image with death anxiety according to the moderating role of disease perception in patients with breast cancer. The results showed that disease perception had a direct effect on DA in patients with breast cancer. Moreover, there was a significant relationship between BI and DA in patients with breast cancer. In other words, DA increases in patients with breast cancer who develop more attention to their BI. According to the results, the proposed model had a good fit and was an important step in identifying the factors affecting the death anxiety of patients with breast cancer. To explain, it can be said that having a disease can affect the patient's relationships. The presence of a disease can lead the patient to use ineffective coping and adaptive mechanisms which, in turn, can increase their level of stress. Increased stress is directly related to physical factors and can exacerbate the disease severity. It has been proved that negative perception and self-esteem are signs of depression <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>. It can be concluded that not only biological mechanisms but also psychological factors can affect psychosomatic diseases, including breast cancer. What makes this chronic disease psychologically important is the broad range of its neuropsychiatric aspects. Many neuropsychiatric disorders are associated with breast cancer, including depression, euphoria, bipolar disorders, abnormal crying and laughing, psychosis, attention deficit, information processing, executive function, concentration, learning, and memory. Emotional disorders (depression, fatigue, and anxiety) are among the most common psychological symptoms in patients with breast cancer and are largely connected to disabilities and poor living conditions in such patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>.</p><p>Adaptation to the present conditions is the best strategy for enhancing the quality of life of patients with breast cancer. Disease perception is an important psychological variable defined as the patient's belief and image of their disease. It can affect their adaptability to the disease and subsequently their quality of life. This perception can show the outlook of their treatment and adaptation of their therapeutic diets <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>. BI is individuals' subjective picture of their own body, specifically from others' eyes. Some people use this term only for physical appearance and some others use it in a broader sense that includes such concepts as bodily actions, movements, and coordination <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>. Humans covet beauty and have long had a natural tendency towards it. A good appearance enhances a person's self-image and self-confidence. As a result, social activities are formed at an acceptable level. Appearance, as the first thing that appears  in social situations while dealing with others, forms an important part of a person's identity. In today's highly dynamic and rapidly-changing society, where the first perceptions and influences on the other side are important, the appearance, symbols, and external signs are gaining considerable value and importance <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1 Proposed model of the research</figDesc><graphic coords="4,53.24,74.32,188.51,74.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="5">Mean, standard deviation (SD), &amp;</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Pearson correlation coefficients of</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">study variables</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Variables</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">1. Body image 32.52 5.91</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2. Disease perception</cell><cell cols="4">76.64 12.79 0.73* 1</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="6">3. Death anxiety 9.25 2.28 0.32* 0.75* 1</cell></row></table><note><p>M: Mean; SD: Standard deviation; *: p &lt;0.05</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Proposed model fit indicators</figDesc><table><row><cell>Fit indicators</cell><cell>x 2</cell><cell>df</cell><cell>(x 2/df )</cell><cell>GFI</cell><cell>AGFI</cell><cell>IFI</cell><cell>TLI</cell><cell>CFI</cell><cell>NFI</cell><cell>RMSEA</cell></row><row><cell>Proposed model</cell><cell>2.44</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2.44</cell><cell cols="6">0.993 0.902 0.997 0.970 0.997 0.996</cell><cell>0.06</cell></row></table><note><p>GFI: Goodness of Fit Index; AGFI: Adjusted Goodness of Fit Index; IFI: Incremental Fit Index; TLI: Tucker Lewis Index; CFI: Comparative Fit Index; NFI: Normalized Fit Index; RMSEA: Root Mean Square Error of Approximation</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Path coefficients of direct and indirect effects between research variables in the proposed model</figDesc><table><row><cell>Path</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p>Clinical Social Work and Health Intervention Vol.</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> </p>No. 5 2022</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of Interest</head><p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The article was published as a Preprint in</head><p>Research Gate under DOI 10.21203/rs.3.rs-718958/v1</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Psychological and sociocultural influences on body image among midlife women with and without a history of breast cancer: Testing the Tripartite Influence Model of Body Image</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lewis-Smith H</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Diedrichs</forename><surname>Pc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Harcourt</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bond R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Body Image</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="114" to="125" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020. 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Body image in older breast cancer survivors: A systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tami</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Davis C</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ramsay</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Melan-Son L</forename><surname>Maclean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nersesian</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychooncology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="823" to="832" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020. 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Death anxiety, perceived social support, and demographic correlates of patients with breast cancer in Pakistan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bibi</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Khalid</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Death Stud</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="787" to="792" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009. 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Death anxiety: an analysis of an evolving concept</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lehto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Stein Kf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Res Theory Nurs Pract</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="41" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009. 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Obesity and Breast Cancer Prognosis: Evidence, Challenges, and Opportunities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jiralerspong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Goodwin</forename><surname>Pj</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4203" to="4216" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Body mass index and clinical benefit of fulvestrant in postmenopausal women with advanced breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gevorgyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bregni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Galli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ganzinelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Martinetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Vullo S</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tumori</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lapatinib with trastuzumab for HER2-positive early breast cancer (NeoALTTO): a randomised, openlabel, multicentre, phase 3 trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Baselga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Bradbury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Eidtmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Cosimo S</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aura</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>De Azambuja E</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">379</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9816</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="633" to="640" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Body mass index and survival in women with breast cancer - systematic literature review and meta-analysis of 82 follow-up studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Chan Dsm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Vieira Ar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Aune</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ban-Dera</forename><surname>Ev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Greenwood</forename><surname>Dc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mctier-Nan A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1901" to="1914" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of body image in cancer patients and its association with clinical variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bahrami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mohamadirizi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mo-Hamadirizi S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hosseini</forename><surname>Sa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Educ Health Promot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">81</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measurements of body image in clinical weight loss participants with and without binge-eating traits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gromel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sargent</forename><surname>Rg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Watkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shoob</forename><surname>Hd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Digioacchino</forename><surname>Rf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Malin</forename><surname>As</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eating Behaviors</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000. 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advanced cancer patients&apos; understanding of prognostic information: Applying insights from psychological research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Reid</forename><surname>Derry Hm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Prigerson</forename><surname>Mc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4081" to="4088" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural Model of Quality of Life in Patients with Breast Cancer: The Role of Psychological Hardiness, Religious Orientation, Perceived Social Protection and Self-Efficacy with Mediation of Resilience and Death Anxiety. The-Neuroscience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Farahbakhsh Beh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mehrinejad</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Moazedian A</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal-of-Shefaye-Khatam</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Relationship Between Attachment Style to God and Depression Among Female Breast-Cancer Patients: The Mediating Role of Illness Perception</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sharifi Saki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alipour A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aghay-Ousefi</forename><surname>Ar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mohammadi</forename><surname>Mr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gho-Bari Bonab B</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nikofar</forename><surname>Ar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Breast-Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018. 2018</date>
			<pubPlace>Iran-Q-J-of</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stress, coping, and fear of personal death: The case of middle-aged men facing early job retirement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mikulincer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Florian</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Death Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="413" to="431" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995. 1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development of the body image concern inventory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Littleton Hl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pury</forename><surname>Cl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behav Res Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="241" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005. 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Depression and Identity: Are Self-Constructions Negative or Conflictual?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Montesano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Feixas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Caspar</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Winter</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">877</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emotional and psychosomatic disorder among female patients undergoing breast cancer diagnosis]</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Strojwąs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Florkowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jeżowska-Smorąg I</forename><surname>Gadek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Zbo-Ralski K</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Macander</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pol Merkur Lekarski</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">233</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="287" to="291" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Health-related quality of life in breast cancer patients: review of reviews from 2008 to 2018</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mokhatri-Hesari P</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Montazeri</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Qual Life Outcomes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">338</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020. 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factors Influencing Body Image in Women with Breast Cancer: A Comprehensive Literature Review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rezaei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Elyasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Janbabai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moosazadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hamzehgardeshi Z</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Iran Red Crescent Med J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">39465</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changed Body Image as Perceived by Jordanian Women Undergoing Breast Cancer Treatment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Alhusban Ry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Asian Pac J Cancer Prev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="767" to="773" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
