<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Science Council</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NSC</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_PxBxpEn">
					<orgName type="full">Taipei, Taiwan</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T19:44+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Risk perception</term>
					<term>rockfall</term>
					<term>revisit intention</term>
					<term>structural equation modeling</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The study aims to explore the relationship between risk perception of rockfall and revisit intention using a Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) analysis. A total of 573 valid questionnaires are collected from travelers to Taroko National Park, Taiwan. The findings show the majority of travelers have the medium perception of rockfall risk, and are willing to revisit the Taroko National Park. The revisit intention to Taroko National Park is influenced by hazardous preferences, willingness-to-pay, obstruction and attraction. The risk perception has an indirect effect on revisit intention through influencing willingness-to-pay. The study results can be a reference for mitigation the rockfall disaster.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>HE Taroko National Park, located in Hualien County, Tawian is a popular scenic spot for domestic and international travelers. There are more than 3300 thousand persons to Taroko National Park in 2012. The geology of Taroko National Park is metamorphic rocks and the terrain is very steep. After the earthquake and heavy rain, rockfall occurs frequently and the accident of travelers injured by rockfall often happens, which affects seriously the travelers' security and impact the local tourism industry. For example, the event of rockfall on July 6, 1987 made 3 persons killed and 7 persons injured. Another event of rockfall on April 3, 2005 made 1 person killed and 7 persons injured. Especially, the rockfall hit a tourist coach and made 26 persons dead, which is the worst travel accident in recently years. In addition, the landslide induced by the earthquake with a magnitude of 6.3 on June 2, 2013 broke the road of Tai-8, which influences the local tourism development again.</p><p>Based on the records of Taroko National Park, Taiwan, there are 42 accidents of rackfall occurred in Taroko National Park during 1986 to 2012 years. Among these rockfall events, there are 19 injury records, in which 3 dead records. The average risk of rockfall is about 0.79×10-7. The triggered factors to rokfall include earthquake (17%), typhoon (14%), heavy rain (19%), and natural wreathing (50%). In these factors, the probability of natural wreathing-induced rockfall is highest and is hard to prevent from rockfall. Nowadays, Taroko National Park management office adopts two strategies including tourists Ya-Fen Lee is with the Department of Leisure Recreation and Travel Management, Toko University, Chiayi, Taiwan (e-mail: 2007LR03@mail.toko.edu.tw).</p><p>Yun-Yao Chi is with the Department of Land Management and Development, Chang Jung Christian University, Tainan, Taiwan (e-mail: yunyao@mail.cjcu.edu.tw).</p><p>streaming and remediation engineering of rockfall to mitigate the rackfall disaster. It is estimated that the engineering cost of rockfall remediation will reach to 0.85 billion, which brings a heavy loading to government finance and obstructs the landscape of Taroko National Park.</p><p>The travelers are the main rockfall-affected elements. In the tourist process, travelers are deeply immersed in the joy atmosphere and are exposed in the rockfall risk <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[3]</ref>. For travelers, the perceived risk of rockfall can be awarded by sight, hearing sense, smelling sense and experience <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[5]</ref>. That is, the perceived risk of traveler is influenced by the psychology, social colure, and so on <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[6]</ref>. Many studies show that the risk perception may influence the travel decisions. Therefore, the travelers' behavior can be predicted by the investigation of risk perception of travelers. The purpose of this paper is to investigate the risk perception of rockfall and the revisit intention by a case study of Taroko National Park, located in North Taiwan. The study results can be a reference for disaster response and strategy for mitigation the rockfall disaster.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. METHOD</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Study Design</head><p>The initial analytical model is designed for understanding the risk perception of rockfall and tourist behavior (see Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>). The tourist behavior is expressed by the variable of revisit intention, which may be affected by variables of willingness to pay and tourist attitude consisted of perception, attraction, obstruction, and hazardous preference <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[7]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[8]</ref>. The causal relationship between variables is presented as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</p><p>A structural equation model analysis is performed in order to check whether the hypothesized model (see Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>) is verified. Various fit indices are used to test a hypothesized model. Assessment of model fit is based on multiple criteria including absolute-fit-indices, incremental-fit-index and parsimony-fit-index. The absolute-fit-indices includes the root mean square error of approximation (RMSEA), Chi-Square ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>x ), and goodness-of-fit index (GFI). The incremental-fit-index includes normal fit index (NFI). The parsimony-fit-index includes NC (= 2</p><p>x /df). The df is the degree of freedom. A model is fit when the indices shows that (i) the less the value of 2  x is, and the more a model fit, (ii) index of GFI is greater than 0.9, (iii) the RMSEA index of 0.08 or less indicates a reasonable error and can be accepted, (iv) the index of NFI is greater than 0.9, and (v) the index of NC ranges between 1 to 3. These indices are used for evaluation of model fit. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Respondents</head><p>Questionnaire is used to collect data in order to investigate the risk perception of rockfall and revisit intention. A total of 600 questionnaires were selected from travelers, who went to Taroko National Park, Taiwan during April to May, 2013. The 573 valid samples were collected with an effective returns-ratio of 95.5%. The people in the sample are 64.4% female. Of the respondents, 22.2% are aged between 30-39 years old, 66.1% are college educated, and 38.9% are from Northern, Taiwan. There are 26.4% respondents, who travel frequency per year is greater than 6 (see Table <ref type="table">I</ref>).   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Questionnaire and Descriptive Statistics</head><p>There are six constructions adopted in this paper, including hazardous preference, tourism attraction, tourism obstruction, risk perception of rockfall, revisit intention and willingness to pay. Every construction is consisted by 3 -7 items (see Table <ref type="table">III</ref>). All items are answered on nine-point Likert response scale ranging from 9 (strongly agree) to 1 (strongly disagree). The mean values are calculated on the basis of the items measuring the agreement level. A high score on an item and construction indicates a high degree of agreement.</p><p>Table <ref type="table">III</ref> shows the mean of all items and constructions. The main tourism attractions are canyon view and pleasant climate. For travelers, the main tourism obstruction is landslide and rockfall. Most respondents also show that they understand fully the rockfall possibility before departure. The majority of travelers has the medium risk perception of rockfall and is willing to revisit the Taroko National Park. The scales of hazardous preference and willingness to pay are above medium level of agreement. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. ANALYSIS AND RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Reliability</head><p>In this paper, a reliability scale test is carried out for all constructs in order to assess the internal consistency of variables. According to document <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[9]</ref>, the value of Cronbach's alpha was classified based on a reliability index in which 0.90 -1.00 is very high, 0.70 -0.89 is high, 0.30 -0.69 is moderate, and 0.00 -0.29 is low. As shown in Table <ref type="table">III</ref>, the resulting alpha values ranged from 0.86 to 0.93, which fall into the classification of high and very high. That is to say, the alpha values in this paper are above the acceptable threshold 0.70 suggested by document <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[9]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Data Analysis</head><p>A structural equation model analysis is implemented to check whether the hypothesized model (see Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>) is fitted the data from 573 samples. The initial findings show that the data from the sample does not fit with the hypothesized model. Therefore, modifications are done to the model according to the guide <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[10]</ref> where some of information is checked. Modifications steps are as follows <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[11]</ref>: a. Review of the factor loading of each item where it must exceed 0.50, and remove the items that do not meet this criterion. b. Review of the standardized residual where the items with value of more than 2.58 will be dropped. c. Review of the modification index to improve the model.</p><p>After modification, some items are dropped. Modified model is tested again and the results of fit indices indicate a better fit. The fit measure indicates that the proposed model fitted the observed data well from 573 samples. The goodness of fit indices show 2 x = 192.10, df = 165, p = 0.073, NFI = 0.99, GFI = 0.97, RMSEA = 0.017, NC = 1.16. The paths between latent variables are statistically significant. The modified model with standardized path coefficients is presented as shown in Appendix. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> is the simplification of the modified model with standardized coefficients.</p><p>Table <ref type="table">IV</ref> shows the results of component fit measures including standardized coefficient, error variance, t-vale, and composite reliability. The values of composite reliability in Table <ref type="table">IV</ref> show every construct has a good inter-consistency. That is, items in every construct are inter-correlated. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Discussion</head><p>Table <ref type="table">V</ref> shows the effects of constructs on revisit intention. Tourism attraction (ABS), tourism obstruction (IMP), hazardous preference (PRE) and willingness-to-pay (PAY) are variables with direct effects on revisit intention (DIS). And risk perception (REC) is not related to revisit intention (DIS) in the path model. The lack of direct effect of risk perception (REC) on revisit intention impels that the effect on revisit intention is generally mediated through willingness to pay. That is, the risk perception has an indirect effect on revisit intention through influencing willingness to pay. The total effect of hazardous preference on revisit intention is greatest (= 0.51) which means the revisit intention is greater as the hazardous preferences is </p><p>To integrate above analysis, some findings are listed as follows: d. Although the worst fear is rockfall occurrence for travelers to Taroko National Park, Taiwan, its degree of fear is medium. e. Under the threat of rockfall, travelers still have high revisit intention. The influence degree on revisit intention is hazardous preference, willingness to pay, risk perception and tourism attraction, in turn. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. CONCLUSIONS</head><p>The rockfall disaster is an important issue for traveler security of Taroko National Park, located in North Taiwan. This paper investigates the relationship between risk perception of rockfall and visit intention from understating the traveler behavior. Through 573 valid respondents, the findings show majority of travelers are composed of persons like outdoor activities and the canyon view is the most popular attraction. The travelers have a medium degree of risk perception of rockfall and are willingness to revisit Taroko National Park. A structural equation model is adopted to develop the relationships between hazardous preference, tourism attraction, tourism obstruction, risk perception of rockfall, revisit intention and willingness to pay. The results indicate that risk perception displays an indirect effect on revisit intention through influencing willingness to pay. The main influence factor on revisit intention is hazardous preferences.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 1 Hypothesized model</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2 Modified model</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="5,99.24,126.00,396.72,250.32" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table</head><label></label><figDesc>II shows the trip status of travelers to Taroko National Park. Of respondents, about 66% are free travel and 62.1% arrange both of hotel and route in advance. The most traffic tool to Taroko National Park is driving by self. And 31.9% is the first time to Taroko National Park and 55.8% stay 1 day.</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>World Academy of Science, Engineering and Technology International Journal of Mathematical and Computational Sciences Vol:8, No:3, 2014 656 International Scholarly and Scientific Research &amp; Innovation 8(3) 2014 scholar.waset.org/1307-6892/9997638 International Science Index, Mathematical and Computational Sciences Vol:8, No:3, 2014 waset.org/Publication/9997638</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</head><p>The authors wish to acknowledge financial support of the <rs type="funder">National Science Council (NSC)</rs>, <rs type="funder">Taipei, Taiwan</rs> through Grant No. <rs type="grantNumber">NSC 102-2221-E-464 -003</rs>. For this assistance, the authors are very grateful.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_PxBxpEn">
					<idno type="grant-number">NSC 102-2221-E-464 -003</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Attraction (ABS)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Obstruction (IMP)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Risk perception of rockfall (REC)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Revisit intention (DIS)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Willingness-to-pay (PAY)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tourist injury</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bentley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Page</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Tourism in Turbulent Times-Towards Safe Experiences for Visitors</title>
		<title level="s">Advances in Tourism Research Series</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Pendergast</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Leggat</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier Ltd</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating the Nature, Scope and Extent of Tourist Accidents-The New Zealand Experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Page</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bentley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Managing Tourist Health and Safety in the New Millennium</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Page</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Pergamon, Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tourist accidents: An exploratory analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Page</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Tourism Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="666" to="690" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing the Risk of Crime Victimization: The Integration of Personal Victimization Experience and Socially-Transmitted Information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Tyler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Social Issue</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unrealistic Optimism about Susceptibility to Health Problems: Conclusions from a Community-Wide Sample</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Behavioral Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="481" to="500" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Environmental Hazards: Communicating Risks as a Social process</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Krimsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Plough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<publisher>Auburn House Publishing Company</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Massachusetts</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Baum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Environmental</forename><surname>Psychology</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Holt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Winston</forename><surname>Rinehart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Reed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Cognition: Theory and Applications</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>California</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Boos/Cole Publishing</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>th ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Practice of Social Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Babbie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<publisher>Wardsworth Publishing Company</publisher>
			<pubPlace>California</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Black</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Babin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Tatha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Multivariate Data Analysis. New Mersey</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>Person International Edition</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">Mohd</forename><surname>Yusof</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ramlee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M S M</forename><surname>Syed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Seri Bunian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Measurement Model of Employability Skills Using Confirmatory Factor Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="348" to="356" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Academy of Science, Engineering and Technology International Journal of Mathematical and Computational Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno>waset.org/1307-6892/9997638</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">657 International Scholarly and Scientific Research &amp; Innovation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2014</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno>waset.org/Publication/9997638</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Science Index, Mathematical and Computational Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
