<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">ORCA -Online Research @ Cardiff</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Fond de Recherche du Québec -Société et Culture</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Aurelia</forename><surname>Durand</surname></persName>
							<email>aurelia.durand@hec.ca</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of International Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Leeds University Business School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">HEC Montréal</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3000 Chemin de la Côte-Sainte-Catherine</addrLine>
									<postCode>H3T 2A7</postCode>
									<settlement>Montreal</settlement>
									<region>QC</region>
									<country>Canada;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hec</forename><surname>Montréal</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of International Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Leeds University Business School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">HEC Montréal</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3000 Chemin de la Côte-Sainte-Catherine</addrLine>
									<postCode>H3T 2A7</postCode>
									<settlement>Montreal</settlement>
									<region>QC</region>
									<country>Canada;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of International Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Leeds University Business School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">HEC Montréal</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3000 Chemin de la Côte-Sainte-Catherine</addrLine>
									<postCode>H3T 2A7</postCode>
									<settlement>Montreal</settlement>
									<region>QC</region>
									<country>Canada;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Ekaterina</forename><surname>Turkina</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of International Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Leeds University Business School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">HEC Montréal</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3000 Chemin de la Côte-Sainte-Catherine</addrLine>
									<postCode>H3T 2A7</postCode>
									<settlement>Montreal</settlement>
									<region>QC</region>
									<country>Canada;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of International Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Leeds University Business School</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>LS2 9JT</postCode>
									<settlement>Leeds</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Matthew</forename><surname>Robson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of International Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Leeds University Business School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">HEC Montréal</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3000 Chemin de la Côte-Sainte-Catherine</addrLine>
									<postCode>H3T 2A7</postCode>
									<settlement>Montreal</settlement>
									<region>QC</region>
									<country>Canada;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Aurélia</forename><surname>Durand</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of International Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Leeds University Business School</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>LS2 9JT</postCode>
									<settlement>Leeds</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Aurelia</forename><surname>Durand</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">HEC Montréal</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3000 Chemin de la Côte-Sainte-Catherine</addrLine>
									<postCode>H3T 2A7</postCode>
									<settlement>Montreal</settlement>
									<region>QC</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">ORCA -Online Research @ Cardiff</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1509/jim.15.0056</idno>
					<note type="submission">This is the author&apos;s version of a work that was submitted to / accepted for publication.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T23:22+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Psychic Distance</term>
					<term>Country Image</term>
					<term>Relational Exchange</term>
					<term>Exporter-Importer Relationships</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Conflicting evidence on the issue of psychic distance (PD) in international business relationships suggests the existence of misunderstood boundary conditions to its effect. This article argues that country image (CI) is a contingent factor to the effect of PD. Expectancyvalue theory provides the theoretical foundations for this argument. Based on structural equation modeling, analyses for a sample of 358 exporter-importer relationships in the global wine industry provide empirical support. Product-related CI mitigates the negative impact of PD on the relational exchange orientation (REO) between firms. Specifically, a high level of PD dampens REO when product-related CI is poor, whereas a strong product-related CI helps firms facing such PD conditions to build REO irrespective. People-related CI has an indirect effect on REO through product-related CI. Our study contributes to explaining the paradox of distance and offers a fresh perspective on how to handle the issue of PD when relevant.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The impact of psychic distance (PD) on market selection and entry, marketing adaptation strategies, and interfirm relationship success is a long-standing area of interest among international marketing scholars <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(Magnusson and Boyle 2009)</ref>. As per the dominant position in the literature, that PD is an individual-level, subjective influence on marketers <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Håkanson and Ambos 2010)</ref>, we define PD as managers' perceived dissimilarity between homeand foreign-country environments <ref type="bibr">(Evans, Mavondo, and Bridson 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Håkanson and Ambos 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Katsikeas, Skarmeas, and Bello 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b91">Sousa and Lages 2011)</ref>. A key reason why PD continues to capture scholars' attention is the contradictory evidence found in empirical studies.</p><p>In the area of exporter-importer relationships-the focus of our study-research has mainly highlighted detrimental effects of PD <ref type="bibr">(Leonidou et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b89">Skarmeas et al. 2008</ref>). Yet, closer inspection of the literature reveals mixed evidence. For instance, studies have invalidated negative effects of PD on relationalism <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Bello, Chelariu, and Zhang 2003)</ref> and trust <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">(Leonidou, Barnes, and Talias 2006)</ref>.</p><p>Scholars have attributed contradictory evidence on the outcomes of PD to O'Grady and <ref type="bibr" target="#b78">Lane's (1996)</ref> paradox of PD. This postulates that while entering low PD markets is supposed to facilitate performance according to classic internationalization theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Johanson and Vahlne 1977)</ref>, firms doing so experience shocks caused by unanticipated differences. In our view, the reason for the paradox and mixed empirical evidence is the existence of misunderstood contingencies under which the impact of PD varies. Indeed, despite <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Magnusson and Boyle's (2009)</ref> call for empirical studies to develop knowledge about boundary conditions (i.e., moderators) to the effect of PD, this remains a gap in the international marketing literature. The gap deserves acute attention as it is preventing researchers from making accurate recommendations guiding managers' efforts to address PD in their firms' relationships.</p><p>Considering the importance of relationships as drivers of competitiveness, innovation, customer satisfaction, and performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b95">(Ulaga and Eggert 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b99">Walter, Ritter, and Gemünden 2001)</ref> in international settings <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Bello et al. 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b105">Zhang, Cavusgil, and Roath 2003)</ref>, it is necessary to identify contingent factors that help reduce the effect of PD in cross-border business relationships, when appropriate.</p><p>In targeting the abovementioned knowledge gap, we focus on the theoretically meaningful contingent factor, country image (CI). A favorable CI figures among the information cues that make products and foreign partners more attractive to industrial buyers and sellers <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Ahmed and D'Astous 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Bradley 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Knight, Holdsworth, and Mather 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b97">Vinhas da Silva, Davies, and Naude 2001)</ref>. As such, CI is a factor that increases valence (worth) in the relationship and can motivate managers to overcome perceived differences between country environments when doing business with foreign partners. The expectancy-value approach from social psychology <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Atkinson 1957;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b98">Vroom 1964)</ref> provides the theoretical foundation for this argument. The objective of the article is to test this argument by considering CI as a moderator of the effect of PD in relational exchanges. Thus, the research question driving this paper is: "Does CI moderate the effect of PD on relational exchange orientation (REO) in international markets?" We test our assumptions using a sample of 358 relationships of wine exporters and importers. The findings provide support for our theoretical arguments and an affirmative answer to our research question. Although we acknowledge the existence of a negative direct effect of PD on REO, we find that product-related CI moderates this effect. The people-related form of CI exerts an indirect influence on REO via product-related CI. We thus observe different roles of people-and product-related CI, with the latter serving as a boundary condition to the effect of PD. Specifically, a high level of PD undermines relational exchanges between partners under conditions of poor, rather than strong, product-related CI.</p><p>From a theoretical perspective, our study enriches research on exporter-importer relationships and potentially other phenomena affected by PD in international markets. To our knowledge, the current study is the first to identify and test empirically CI as a boundary condition to the effect of PD on REO and, in doing so, it contributes to explaining the mixed empirical evidence and deepening insight into the paradox of PD <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Håkanson and Ambos 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Magnusson and Boyle 2009)</ref>. In using expectancy-value theory, the study reconciles research on PD and CI, two constructs that have been studied separately for decades. From a managerial perspective, we reveal that PD should not always be closed in international channel relationships. To handle the effect of PD appropriately with foreign partners, marketing managers should consider the favorability of their product-related CI and, to a lesser extent, their people-related CI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>THEORETICAL BACKGROUND AND HYPOTHESES</head><p>Prior to theorizing the interplay between PD and CI in affecting REO, we provide conceptual background about REO and the way it is driven by PD and CI according to extant research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The REO Concept</head><p>The idea that relationships and transactions are the two extremes of a relational/transactional continuum in interfirm exchange is central to the field of relationship marketing <ref type="bibr">(Anderson and Narus 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr">Dwyer, Schurr, and Oh 1987)</ref>. The nature of exchange along the continuum depends on a variety of norms (e.g., flexibility and solidarity), behaviors (e.g., communication and cooperation), and situations (e.g., time orientation and interdependence) (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Anderson and Narus 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Heide and John 1992)</ref>. In line with <ref type="bibr">Sheth and Shah's (2003)</ref> study, which coined the term exchange orientation, we define REO as repeated and maintained episodes of exchange over time with trust, commitment, communication, and cooperation between the partners. We use the term REO interchangeably with relationships and relational exchanges.</p><p>Our focus is on REO to capture the nature of exchange along the transactional/relational continuum, rather than on relationalism or relationship quality. First, relationalism has been mainly captured by norms alone (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Bello et al. 2003)</ref>. We wanted to go further in capturing the nature of exchange along the transactional/relational continuum by incorporating the central trust-commitment component and key behaviors such as cooperation. Second, relationship quality has been treated as an overarching relational construct, and has mainly been operationalized based on trust, commitment, and satisfaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b89">(Skarmeas et al. 2008)</ref>, with additional components such as cooperation and communication <ref type="bibr">(Leonidou et al. 2014)</ref>.</p><p>Although it is conceptually close to REO, relationship quality often includes a measure of exchange outcomes (e.g., satisfaction). Our conceptual treatment of REO assumes instead that positive exchange outcomes would flow from the relationship <ref type="bibr">(Leonidou et al. 2014)</ref>. To this point, theories of interfirm relationships (e.g., transaction costs and social exchange theories) identify expected outcomes as a core explanatory mechanism underpinning relational exchanges <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Anderson and Narus 1990)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Negative Effect of PD on REO</head><p>In the international marketing literature, competing ways of conceptualizing and operationalizing PD coexist. First, the objective approach relies on secondary data and objective measures of differences between countries (e.g., number of kilometers between countries and GDP/capita) (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Brewer 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Dow and Karunaratna 2006)</ref>. Second, the subjective approach uses perception-based techniques to collect primary, individual-level data on these political, legal, economic, sociocultural, and technological (PEST) differences <ref type="bibr">(Evans et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b91">Sousa and Lages 2011)</ref>. We align ourselves with the vast majority of studies on PD in cross-border relationships that have adopted the subjective approach. As per <ref type="bibr">Evans and Mavondo (2002a, p. 516)</ref>, "… it is the mind's processing, in terms of perception, of cultural and business differences that forms the basis of psychic distance." The development of any interfirm relationship is an informal process influenced by perceptual constructs <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">(Katsikeas et al. 2009)</ref>.</p><p>Notwithstanding the consensual use of perceptual PD in the international relationships literature (cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b105">Zhang et al. 2003)</ref>, we observe marked diversity in the conceptual treatment of PD in the literature (see Table <ref type="table">1</ref>, for empirical studies published since the year 2000).</p><p>Researchers have conceptualized PD by relying on the extent to which managers: perceive degrees of dissimilarity/differences between their home country and their foreign partner's country (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Griffith and Dimitrova 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Johnston et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Katsikeas et al. 2009)</ref>, are familiar with these differences (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Heroux and Hammoutene 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Leonidou et al. 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Leonidou et al. 2011)</ref>, or find these differences problematic <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Bello et al. 2003)</ref>. Some studies focused on differences between countries (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Katsikeas et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b89">Skarmeas et al. 2008)</ref>, while others focused on differences between companies (in regard to business environments, working methods, etc.) (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Leonidou et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Leonidou et al. 2014</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>-Insert Table 1 about here -</head><p>Regarding the unit of analysis, it was occasionally difficult to retrieve precisely which type of relationship respondents were asked to select and answer for. Moreover, variations can again be observed. Studies focused on relationships with reference to their: size (e.g., the largest or third largest partner) <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Griffith and Dimitrova 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b89">Skarmeas et al. 2008)</ref>, representativeness (e.g., the majority of foreign customers) <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">(Leonidou et al. 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Leonidou, Katsikeas, and Hadjimarcou 2002)</ref>, or difficulty (e.g., the most challenging partner) <ref type="bibr" target="#b105">(Zhang et al. 2003)</ref>. The industries of the studied business relationships often were not well reported, and nor were the foreign countries; the home country-where the exporter/importer sample was recruited-was reported. Failure to specify the nationality of both partners may not have been an issue for the purpose of the studies, but it makes it difficult to extrapolate from their findings. For instance, there is no easy way to assess whether observations were made in base conditions of low, moderate, or high PD between the home and foreign countries. The degree of PD could lead to different behaviors and consequences in relationships <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(Magnusson and Boyle 2009)</ref>.</p><p>The empirical studies do not theorize contingent relationships between PD and relational exchanges despite theorists' encouragement to do so. For instance, <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Conway and Swift's (2000)</ref> conceptual study positioned PD as an antecedent to trust and commitment in international relationships, with varying degrees of impact depending on stage of the relationship. <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Magnusson and Boyle (2009)</ref> extended this idea to the PD paradox by positing that when a cross-border relationship is in an early phase of development, the effect of PD could be detrimental in a context of high PD (it increases uncertainty and inhibits trust) but relatively insignificant in a context of low PD (assumed similarity does not threaten effective exchanges).</p><p>When the relationship is at a more advanced stage, PD could be beneficial to firms in a context of high PD (uncertainty is reduced due to ongoing information sharing between partners) but be detrimental in a context of low PD (poor outcomes resulting from inattention to small differences hurt the relationship). This line of conceptual research indicates the importance of documenting both home and foreign countries, and of capturing various degrees of PD to investigate its effects in business relationships.</p><p>Both transaction costs theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b101">(Williamson 1975</ref>) and social exchange theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">(Macneil 1980</ref>) explain why PD is likely to deter relational exchanges. From a transaction costs perspective, all forms of distance (e.g., geographic, cultural, and economic) generated by differences in the PEST environments of countries not only increase direct costs (e.g., tariffs in the absence of regional trade agreements), but indirect costs too. Searching for information abroad takes longer, reaching satisfactory agreements with foreign partners is more difficult, adapting agreements to unexpected contingencies becomes more frequent, and associated monitoring more costly. From a social exchange perspective, the expectation is that a partner will act in a predictable manner to build a foundation of trust and other relational norms and behaviors <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Anderson and Narus 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr">Dwyer et al. 1987)</ref>. PD hinders predictability and, thus, the development of social exchange relations (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Katsikeas et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Leonidou et al. 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b89">Skarmeas et al. 2008)</ref>.</p><p>PD should be a real problem in exporter-importer relationships. <ref type="bibr">Samiee and Walters (2006, p. 594</ref>) noted that: "The international context invariably introduces some additional barriers: time-zone, language, lack of or limited face-to-face contacts, and cultural differences. These barriers impede information flows which are so critical to relational exchanges…" PD emerges from the factors that interfere with the way firms learn about and understand foreign environments and, thus, foreign business partners' behaviors <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Johanson and Vahlne 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b77">Nordstrom and Valhne 1994)</ref>. According to <ref type="bibr">Johanson and Vahlne's (2009)</ref> later retrospective, although the impact of PD on export market entry order has weakened in the intervening years, low levels of PD continue to help exporters recognize and develop relational opportunities abroad.</p><p>In line with transaction costs, social exchange, and internationalization theories, studies have found a negative impact of PD on the level of harmony within export relationships <ref type="bibr">(Leonidou et al. 2002)</ref>, trust and relationship quality between exporters and importers <ref type="bibr">(Leonidou et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b89">Skarmeas et al. 2008)</ref>, and importers' perceived relationship value with foreign suppliers <ref type="bibr" target="#b90">(Skarmeas, Zeriti, and Baltas 2015)</ref>.</p><p>On the other hand, several studies present confounding results that seem to defy straightforward explanation. For instance, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Bello et al. (2003)</ref> invalidated the hypothesized negative relationship between PD and relationalism. To explain this finding, they postulated that PD may incite managers to adopt more of a contractual governance structure rather than a relational one. <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Leonidou et al. (2006)</ref> stopped short of offering an explanation for their results' partial validation of the expected negative impact of PD on the relationship quality components. <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Griffith and Dimitrova (2014)</ref> observed that business distance reduces the positive effect of complementarity of capabilities on exporters' satisfaction with their performance in international markets, while cultural distance enhances it. These authors did not place emphasis on explaining this surprising opposite influence. Finally, <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Johnston et al. (2012)</ref> were unable to confirm that PD moderates the relationship of trust and satisfaction with joint action. They explained this result in the following manner: "… though psychic distance might thwart the positive relational environment built by trust and satisfaction, buyers might still opt for joint action with sellers due to consideration of possible accomplishment of common goals […] Another plausible explanation could be the existence of calculative commitment among buyers, which indicates an economic rationale behind the continuance of a relationship […] Thus, commitment may enable buyers to overcome the detrimental effects of psychic distance and engage in joint action with sellers" <ref type="bibr">(Johnston et al. 2012, p. 45</ref>). As such, these authors point to the role of expected outcomes as a possible offsetting factor to the negative effects of PD.</p><p>We acknowledge discrepancies in the theorization of PD effects within international channel relationships, and the absence of a satisfactory explanation for the mixed empirical evidence. Nonetheless, theory-driven arguments support a detrimental direct effect of PD on relational exchanges in exporter-importer ties. Consequently, we hypothesize that: H1: The larger the PD, the weaker the REO.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Positive Effect of CI on REO</head><p>In the international marketing literature, different conceptualizations of CI also coexist. There is agreement that CI is a subjective (not objective) matter and the term image refers to a mental representation or picture <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Jaffe and Nebenzahl 2001)</ref>. Instead, scholars have debated the macroversus micro-level of analysis of CI and the dimensions of countries that best reflect their international image (environments, people, or products). Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref> illustrates the diversity of approaches and presents a sample of representative studies on CI.</p><p>-Insert Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref> about here -Among the two conceptualizations of country macro image (PEST-environment and people-related CI), we chose to focus on people-related CI for two reasons. First, beliefs about people are likely to play a more significant role in a study of business relationships with foreign partners compared to beliefs about a country's environment. Second, measures used to capture environment-related CI occasionally overlap with measures of PD. For instance, Parameswaran and Pisharodi <ref type="bibr">(1994)</ref>, and other studies extending their work, captured the macro country image (i.e., general country attributes) by measuring perceptions of differences/similarities between home and foreign countries in terms of politics, culture, and economy. In the present study, PD already captures this comparison between home-and foreign-country environments.</p><p>In the literature on the micro image or product-related CI, <ref type="bibr">Roth and Romeo (1992, p. 480)</ref> specified that: "Country image is the overall perception consumers form of products from a particular country, based on their prior perceptions of the country's production and marketing strengths and weaknesses." In this article, we build on <ref type="bibr" target="#b84">Roth and Romeo (1992)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b83">Roth and Diamantopoulos (2009)</ref> to define product-related CI as an individual's beliefs about a country in connection to a specific product category. In turn, we rely on <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Laroche et al. (2005)</ref> and Zeugner- <ref type="bibr" target="#b104">Roth, Diamantopoulos, and Montesinos (2008)</ref> to define people-related CI as an individual's beliefs about a country in connection to its people.</p><p>Another important discussion relates to the way CI should be conceptualized with regard to processes that lead to image formation in individuals' minds. In their extensive review of the CI construct, <ref type="bibr" target="#b83">Roth and Diamantopoulos (2009)</ref> showed that the majority of previous studies have emphasized cognitive processes (e.g., beliefs formed on the basis of information), while only a minority looked into affective processes (e.g., emotions). These authors also highlighted the need for studies to better incorporate normative processes (e.g., pressure from important others) as well as processes related to conation (e.g., behavioral intention). The conative aspect in CI work has been defined as a motivational and volitional component reflecting consumers' desired level of interaction with the sourcing country <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">(Knight et al. 2007</ref>).</p><p>The theories of reasoned action and planned behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Fishbein and</ref><ref type="bibr">Ajzen 1975, 2010)</ref> are commonly used to explain the effect of CI on behaviors. These theories posit that beliefs and norms translate into attitudes that guide behaviors. Considering that CI is accepted as a belief <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">(Martin and Eroglu 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b75">Nagashima 1970)</ref>, the country-of-origin effect is the attitude toward a specific country that derives from its CI. Norms and values related to, for instance, patriotism, ethnocentrism, and attractiveness of a foreign culture, influence the extent to which the country-of-origin effect, as an attitude, is favorable. In turn, the attitude (e.g., like/dislike) toward a specific country determines behaviors (e.g., seek/avoid) in relation to its people or products (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Jaffe and Nebenzahl 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b83">Roth and Diamantopoulos 2009)</ref>.</p><p>We assert that beliefs about a country in connection to its people and their characteristics, such as friendliness, creativity, hard work, and technical skills (Zeugner- <ref type="bibr" target="#b104">Roth et al. 2008</ref>) can shape the relational behaviors of teams of managers. Qualities of interfirm relationships develop from those of interpersonal ties. To this point, <ref type="bibr" target="#b93">Styles, Patterson, and Ahmed (2008)</ref> noted that the likeability of business partners is a driver of affective commitment and goodwill trust in exporter-importer relationships. In a study of importers' relationships, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Barnes et al. (2015)</ref> observed that the combination of personal characteristics and familiarity with the exporting firm's ethnic origins is conducive to interfirm trust. Further, the corporate image of exporters (importers), which is a function of their country image, could be expected to influence the relational preferences of industrial buyers (sellers) (cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Bradley 2001)</ref>. A favorable people-related CI is thus conducive to REO as it contributes to the development of interpersonal ties between the exporting and importing firms' managers, and of a corporate reputation that elevates the overseas partner's sense of sureness in the relationship.</p><p>Extensive research has shown that a favorable CI leads to positive attitudes from endconsumers toward products from a specific country, which, in turn, promote favorable intentions and behaviors <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Jaffe and Nebenzahl 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b81">Pharr 2005)</ref>. In industrial marketing, the topic is seldom studied even if research has established that professional buyers are similarly affected by the image of countries in their product evaluations <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Ahmed and D'Astous 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b96">Verlegh and Steenkamp 1999)</ref> and international sourcing decisions (Vinhas da <ref type="bibr" target="#b97">Silva et al. 2001)</ref>. In a study of CI shaping industrial purchasers' perceived value of food products, <ref type="bibr">Knight et al. (2007, p. 121)</ref> unveiled that: "…the mode of action of a product-country image summary construct is to provide channel members with a shorthand notation for trust. Trust appears to be the central component that enhances perceived quality while minimizing perceived monetary sacrifice-thereby leading to enhanced perceived value…" In a review of the literature on importer behavior, <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Leonidou et al. (2011)</ref> emphasized the importance of product quality criteria in the selection of suppliers. Moreover, it is likely that a firm's beliefs about the partner's country in connection to its understanding and appreciation of product quality and consistency of quality, are important drivers of relationship value and continuance (cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b95">Ulaga and Eggert 2006)</ref>. Hence, we also expect a favorable product-related CI to enhance REO: H2a: The more positive the people-related CI, the greater the REO; H2b: The more positive the product-related CI, the greater the REO.</p><p>Few studies have investigated the effect of the micro image on the macro image of countries, which has been labeled as the reverse country-of-origin effect (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Lee and Lockshin 2012)</ref>. Instead, different theorizations of the effect of the origin cue (i.e., halo, summary, or heuristic default) on product evaluation suggest the existence of a transfer from the macro to the micro image <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Laroche et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b80">Oberecker and Diamantopoulos 2011)</ref>. For instance, <ref type="bibr">Knight et al. (2007, p. 109</ref>) argued that "…it is possible for a product-country image to change over time, sometimes rapidly, either by design or as a result of technological, social or political change. Judgments consumers make about a country and its people transfer to evaluations of the performance of products from that country." Accordingly, we propose that within cross-border relationships the reputation of people from a given country benefits the reputation of its products. Thus: H3: The more positive the people-related CI, the more positive the product-related CI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Moderating Role of CI in the Relationship of PD and REO</head><p>We turn to an established behavioral theory, the expectancy-value approach, in order to theorize the interaction of PD and CI in connection to REO. The approach traces its origins back to the set of theories in psychology developed in the 1940s and 1950s to explain motivation, performance, decision-making, learning, and cognition <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Feather 1959)</ref>. One of the most cited is <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Atkinson's (1957)</ref> risk-taking model and later developments. Another is Fishbein's expectancy-value model, developed in the early 60s to link beliefs to attitudes, which later became a pillar of the reasoned action theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Fishbein and</ref><ref type="bibr">Ajzen 1975, 2010)</ref>.</p><p>Over the decades, the expectancy-value approach has been extended to a variety of domains including, but not limited to, education, health, management, and communications. Other variables have been incorporated but expectancy and value have remained central to the model, albeit under different names. Within this overall approach, expectancy theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b98">(Vroom 1964)</ref> explains that motivation to perform in the workplace depends on expectancy (belief that performing is feasible), instrumentality (belief that performing will lead to expected outcomes), and valence (belief that performing is worth the effort).</p><p>We draw upon the channel relationships literature to understand how the expectancy-value approach can extend to exporter-importer ties. Expectancy theory has been recognized as a valid framework to analyze interfirm relational exchanges <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Dwyer, Dahlstrom, and DiNovo 1995)</ref>. In this context, <ref type="bibr">Frazier (1983, p. 71</ref>) explained that: "The higher the expected rewards and the required investments, the higher a representative will set the firm's goals and the higher the motivation for making the relationship a success…". Following this logic, we propose to situate CI in relation to expected rewards and PD in relation to required investments. Managers expect positive outcomes in international markets (e.g., export performance and competitiveness) and are motivated to develop or maintain relationships with foreign partners to reach these goals. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b98">Vroom's (1964)</ref> terms, relationships are therefore instrumental to success in international markets. For managers, the belief sustaining this view of instrumentality could translate as: Interacting with this specific foreign partner in a relational orientation-that is, trusting them, committing, cooperating, and communicating with them-will lead to positive outcomes.</p><p>As for valence, the concept of relationship value suggests what valence can mean in international relationships. Defined as a trade-off between benefits received and costs incurred in a given relationship, value in relationships can stem from higher product quality and consistency of quality over time, on-time deliveries, know-how improvements, better support services, pleasant personal interactions, lower operation costs, etc. <ref type="bibr" target="#b95">(Ulaga and Eggert 2006)</ref>.</p><p>As such, the belief underlying valence in managers' minds could translate as: A relationship with this foreign partner will bring our firm important cost reductions and benefits in terms of products, services, and much more; thus it is worth the effort developing and maintaining. A favorable CI is likely to increase valence-the belief that interacting in a relational manner with foreign partners is worth the effort. A favorable product-related CI will raise expectations of benefits in terms of product quality and associated know-how. In turn, a favorable peoplerelated CI should raise expectations of benefits in terms of personal interactions and services, for instance.</p><p>Finally, we turn to expectancy, which, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b98">Vroom's (1964)</ref> terms, is the subjective probability that effort leads to performance. The beliefs underlying expectancy in managers' minds could translate as: The efforts we put into exchanges with this foreign partner will allow us to develop/maintain a relationship with them. Exchanges with foreign partners require increased efforts and investments in time and human and financial resources. Examples include trusting people with different values, committing under different legal systems, cooperating across time differences, and overcoming (non)verbal differences in communication. For this reason, we situate PD as a factor decreasing managers' expectancy, or the belief that they can succeed in interacting with foreign partners in a relational manner and, ultimately, seize expected outcomes.</p><p>A pillar of the expectancy-value approach is the multiplicative function between expectancy and valence. For instance, <ref type="bibr">Atkinson (1957, p. 360</ref>) stated that: "The strength of motivation to perform some act is assumed to be a multiplicative function of the strength of the motive, the expectancy (subjective probability) that the act will have as a consequence the attainment of an incentive, and the value of the incentive...". More recently, <ref type="bibr">Nagengast et al. (2011, p. 3</ref>) explained that: "The cornerstone of [Expectancy-Value Theory] EVT was the critical role of the expectancy-by-value interaction (E×V). […] EVT predicted a multiplicative pattern of relations between expectancy, value, and resulting motivation. To achieve a high level of motivation, both expectancy and value had to be high.</p><p>If either expectancy or value were low, high values on the other dimension were of little or no consequence for motivation and behavior." In like manner, we propose that PD and CI interact in a multiplicative way in shaping REO. Specifically, forms of CI serve as moderators of the main PD to REO relationship. The logic is that a favorable CI will raise valence and motivate managers to overcome the detrimental effects of PD in the development of cross-border relationships. In sum, we posit that the effect of PD on REO depends on people-and productrelated CI: H4a: People-related CI moderates the path between PD and REO in such a way that the more positive the people-related CI, the weaker the negative effect of PD on REO; H4b: Product-related CI moderates the path between PD and REO in such a way that the more positive the product-related CI, the weaker the negative effect of PD on REO.</p><p>The theoretical framework comprising the study hypotheses is depicted in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</p><p>-Insert Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> about here -</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Context</head><p>Our study tested the hypotheses using survey data from exporters and importers in the global wine industry, which was selected as a relevant context for the specific purposes and design of this study for three reasons. First, an industry-specific approach lends itself to the variables studied. Product-related CI strongly relates to particular product categories and is commonly studied in the context of specific industries (e.g., cars, clothing, and food). As this study is the first to investigate the role of CI in relation to PD in international channel ties, we required a single industrial context where origin effects are evident. Although prior research in the global wine industry has mainly focused on end-consumer behaviors (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Felzensztein and Dinnie 2005)</ref>, we can assume that industrial buyers are also sensitive to the origin of wines, if only because of its impact on final consumers.</p><p>Second, the global wine industry is conducive to both transactional and relational exchanges. Wines present the advantage of being treated as specialty products (high product involvement) or commodities (low involvement) depending on their price and origin. For highend wines, firms not only derive advantages from the quality and scarcity of raw materials (i.e., grapes) but also from processing skills and craft that accumulate over time. This aspect of the industry encourages long-term relationships between buyers and sellers. For low-end products, an arm's length market trades wine in bulk across borders with prices and quantities as the main criteria for (transactional) exchange. Third, distances between trade partners in the global wine industry have been widening, not shrinking, with new producers and consumers emerging from developed and developing economies. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Bartlett's (2009)</ref> terms, New World wine producers (e.g., USA, Australia, and Argentina) have initiated a global wine war against exporters from the Old World (e.g., France, Spain, and Italy) over the big emerging markets (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Brazil, India, and China)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Operationalization of Constructs</head><p>We used a perception-based approach to operationalize all constructs as we aimed to understand how perceptions and beliefs about foreign countries influence managers' behaviors in exchanges with international partners. After having carefully screened the relevant literature, we chose existing scales for PD <ref type="bibr" target="#b91">(Sousa and Lages 2011)</ref>, people-related CI (Zeugner- <ref type="bibr" target="#b104">Roth et al. 2008)</ref>, and product-related CI <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Felzensztein and Dinnie 2005)</ref>. The latter scale is particularly relevant as it was developed for the chosen product category and measures beliefs about countries in connection to wine, rather than beliefs about wine in connection to countries. We used Sousa and Lages' (2011) 13-item scale for PD as is, but we adapted available scales for people-and product-related CIs in two ways. First, we converted them to five-point semantic differential scales, as per <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">Martin and Eroglu's (1993)</ref> recommendations for the image construct.</p><p>Then, we developed mirroring versions since they had only been developed from the perspective of buyers.</p><p>For REO, we developed a global scale to capture the orientation of exchange along the transactional/relational continuum. Prior research has measured trust, commitment, long-term orientation, communication, and cooperation among firms using a set of multi-item scales (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Anderson and Narus 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Leonidou et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b74">Morgan and Hunt 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b79">Obadia 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b100">Whipple, Lynch, and Nyaga 2010)</ref>; but doing so leads to lengthy questionnaires and lower response rates. To solve this problem, we captured REO using items tapping well-documented behavioral dimensions from the literature as first-order dimensions. Specifically, we used five items that tap each of the trust, commitment, cooperation, information exchange, and time orientation dimensions, and a sixth item assessing from "purely arm's length exchange" to "close and personal relationships". Appendix A presents the items and scales used to measure the study constructs.</p><p>We included four salient variables from the literature as controls: Product price as a proxy for product involvement-situations of high involvement (characterized by intensive prepurchase planning, for instance) could induce more relational exchanges, with trust and communication as uncertainty coping mechanisms (Sheth and Shah 2003); Relationship duration and knowledge of partner country (i.e., knowledge gained from the informant's personal experience of the country)-as these increase, the exchange orientation becomes more relational by virtue of accumulated experience and enhanced trust (cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Barnes et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Katsikeas et al. 2009)</ref>; Role in the supply chain-being in a buying/importing role could increase REO as securing product quality and quantity is of more strategic importance than disposing of goods in a selling/exporting role <ref type="bibr">(Geiger et al. 2012</ref>). Single-item, seven-point scales were used to measure product price ("under 5$" to "over 40$", in US currency) and relationship duration ("under 1 year" to "over 20 years"). A single-item, five-point bipolar scale (with endpoints "very limited knowledge" and "very extensive knowledge") was developed to capture knowledge of partner country. Finally, firm type was recorded and recoded to tap role in the supply chain (i.e., 1 = exporter, 2 = mixed, or 3 = importer roles).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Questionnaire Development and Pretest</head><p>The survey instrument for the study was an online questionnaire built using Unipark's Questback EFS 10.1 software. To ensure content validity, a first version of the questionnaire was discussed with six business managers in the wine industry from the exporting side and three managers from the importing side. The present study is part of a larger research project that looked into role differences in business relationships. For this reason, some decisions made about the survey design (e.g., collecting both buyers' and sellers' opinions) were motivated by the larger project. The one-on-one discussions with wine professionals helped ensure that the items were well understood by people in the wine business and that the provided pre-set list of countries was germane to the setting. In addition, eight academics specializing in international relationship marketing were asked to ensure that the items adequately captured the variables under study. We then refined the questionnaire in light of comments made by both of these groups.</p><p>To obtain as much variation as possible in terms of PD and CI, it was important to make the questionnaire available in several languages. We followed standard procedures for translation and back-translation of the questionnaire, which was initially drafted in English.</p><p>After this procedure, we were able to provide it in six languages: English, French, Spanish, Mandarin, Russian, and Portuguese. We then sent an online survey to 3,629 wine importers and exporters (compiled from a listing purchased from Best Wine Importers and from a manual search of wine association members in the top 10 wine producing countries). This pilot survey yielded 70 questionnaires, a sufficient number to pretest our survey instrument. The validity and robustness checks conducted on this sample led us to drop two items from the PD scale and two items from the people-related CI scale (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">3</ref>). The other scales did not require adjustments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Survey Instrument and Informant Quality</head><p>Structured in three parts, the questionnaire first asked respondents to identify a specific wine category that they were either purchasing or selling in two different foreign countries. For the selection of the product category, respondents were given the choice between red, white, rosé, and sparkling wine, along with seven retail price points (ranging from under US$4.99 to above US$40). For the selection of two countries, we provided a pre-set list of countries among traditional <ref type="bibr">(France, Germany, Italy, Portugal, and Spain)</ref> and emerging (Argentina, Australia, Canada, Chile, New Zealand, South Africa, and the USA) supply markets for buyers; as well as among traditional (Canada, France, Germany, the United Kingdom, and the USA) and emerging <ref type="bibr">(Brazil, China, India, and Russia)</ref> markets for sellers. We designed the questionnaire so that the respondents' answers were automatically incorporated into the remainder of the questionnaire. The next step consisted of asking respondents to think about their largest business partner (in terms of volume purchased or sold) for this specific category in each of the two selected countries. After confirming this mental selection (using a "yes/no" attention control question), respondents were asked to answer the rest of the questionnaire with these two business partners in mind (without naming them).</p><p>In the second part of the questionnaire, respondents were asked to characterize the REO for both partners, the degree of similarity or difference between their country of work and the two partners' respective countries, and the image of each country with regard to people in general and wine in particular. The third part collected data on demographics and controls. We also measured the key informants' competence on a five-point scale in terms of: degree of selfconfidence in portraying the selected business relationships accurately; personal involvement in the relationships; and decision-making power with regard to doing business with the two selected partners-for a similar procedure, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b95">Ulaga and Eggert (2006)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Collection and Survey Response</head><p>For the main data collection, we opted to send the questionnaire through Global Wine &amp; Spirits (GWS), a specialized electronic marketplace in the global wine industry (B2B only). Based in Montreal, this platform connects 6,700 buying and selling companies located in nearly 100 countries. Overall, data collection lasted six weeks. We followed the procedure for online surveys recommended by <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Dillman, Smyth, and Christian (2008)</ref>. The survey was first announced in the GWS' weekly newsletter and then sent via email to members on two separate occasions (at a 10-day interval), along with a cover letter in English. Over this time period, 927 individuals opened the link to the survey included in the email leading to the language selection page. Out of this total, 722 selected the language of their choice, moved on to the introduction page, and started answering the survey. From this effective sampling frame, we received 235 responses. We discarded 13 answers owing to missing data, 34 because informants had chosen partners from their own country instead of foreign ones, and 9 due to low competence (below the scale mid-point) in portraying the relationships with foreign partners. As a result, we obtained 179 valid answers, giving an effective response rate of 24.8% that compares favorably with other studies on international relationships (Griffith and Dimitrova 2014). Since each respondent was asked to report on two business relationships, we collected a sample of 358 relationships.</p><p>The informants worked in 35 countries and answered for foreign partners from 16 countries. The collected sample is characterized by a diversity of country pairings (e.g., an exporter from France assessing the exchange with importers from China and Australia; an importer from Canada assessing the exchange with exporters from the USA and Italy), and thus by high degrees of variation in terms of PD and CI evaluation. Appendix B.1 provides detail on the study participants and Appendix B.2 shows characteristics of the analyzed relationships.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ANALYSIS AND RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measure Validation</head><p>We first conducted tests for sampling adequacy, language bias, and non-response bias. A Kaiser-Meyer-Olkin statistic of .89 demonstrates no issue with sampling adequacy. As the questionnaire was available in various languages, we looked for signs of language bias by testing (t-tests) for differences in the study constructs for English versus non-English responses.</p><p>The test yielded non-significant results (p &gt; .05), indicating the absence of language bias.</p><p>Assuming respondents who answered in the last stage of the data collection are similar to actual non-respondents, we compared (t-tests) laggard respondents with the early ones on the study constructs. Again, no significant differences (p &gt; .05) were noted, suggesting the absence of non-response bias.</p><p>Subsequently, we evaluated the reliability and validity of the constructs <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Hair et al. 2010)</ref>. For reliability, we observed Cronbach's alpha (&gt; .73) and composite reliability (&gt; .70).</p><p>For convergent validity, we found average variance extracted (AVE) (&gt; .57) and standardized factor loadings (&gt; .70). Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">3</ref> shows that the measurement analyses indicated good reliability and convergent validity. Further, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">4</ref> presents correlations among the latent variables in the study-including our controls-together with scale means and standard deviations. Correlations between the independent variables falling below the recommended threshold of .30 <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Hair et al, 2010)</ref> indicate that multicollinearity is not likely to be a problem in the study. There are no discriminant validity issues as every squared correlation exceeds the relevant AVE scores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>-Insert Table 3 and Table 4 about here -</head><p>We also checked for common method bias using the marker variable approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">(Podsakoff et al. 2003)</ref>. We first included a marker variable (i.e., a construct theoretically unrelated to other constructs in the model) in advance, so there is an a priori justification for predicting a zero correlation. Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Leonidou et al. (2011)</ref>, we used experience in position to serve as a marker variable. Second, we adopted post-hoc identification of a marker variable via the second smallest correlation among the variables in the study (i.e., r = .01). To implement the two tests, we computed a method bias-adjusted correlation matrix in line with <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Malhotra, Kim, and Patil (2006)</ref>. In both cases correlations remained stable, indicating the absence of method bias.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Test of Hypotheses</head><p>We deployed structural equation modeling (SEM) to test our hypotheses, via STATA. Specifically, we estimated a parsimonious model in which the control variables were included as drivers of REO. We followed <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Byrne's (2010)</ref> recommendations for model assessment.</p><p>Hence, we considered the chi-square ratio (i.e., to degrees-of-freedom) and a variety of other fit indices. The theorized model indicated good fit:  2 /df = 2.30, GFI = .91, NFI = .92, CFI = .94, TLI = .91, RMSEA = .06. Table <ref type="table">5</ref> presents the path coefficients and their significance for each hypothesis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>-Insert Table 5 about here -</head><p>As per H1, we find that PD negatively affects REO (β = -.22, p &lt; .01). People-related CI does not influence REO (β = -.03, p &gt; .05), leading to the rejection of H2a. On the other hand, we support H2b since product-related CI enhances REO (β = .29, p &lt; .01). The results uphold our expected H3 path that people-related CI impacts product-related CI (β = .32, p &lt; .01). While people-related CI does not moderate the effect of PD on REO (β = .01, p &gt; .05), product-related CI does negatively condition the path (β = .12, p &lt; .05). We thus reject H4a and support H4b, respectively. In sum, our predictions regarding effects of CI on REO are supported in the case of product-related CI, whereas people-related CI affects REO indirectly via product-related CI.</p><p>Results for the control variables show that product price (proxy for involvement) (β = .10, p &lt; .05), relationship duration (β = .46, p &lt; .01), and role in the supply chain (β = .20, p &lt; .01)<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">foot_0</ref> all influence REO, but knowledge of partner country exerts no such effect on REO (β = .04, p &gt; .05). The amount of REO variance explained in the model is 24.23%.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional Analyses</head><p>We validated the hypothesized model by comparing it with two theoretically plausible, alternative approaches to the relationship between PD and CI (including the same controls).</p><p>Both alternatives exclude interaction effects between PD and CI as these were anchored in expectancy-value theory.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Alternative model #1 (CI → PD).</head><p>In relation to decision-makers' cognitive processes, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Bruner, Jacqueline, and Georges' (1956)</ref> categorization theory asserts that categorization is the process by which human beings group pieces of information (e.g., events, objects, and people around them) into classes and respond to them accordingly, in order to reduce complexity in their environment. In like manner, image theory situates CI as a category that helps individuals process and react to the origin cue among other information cues <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Jaffe and Nebenzahl 2001)</ref>.</p><p>Following this logic, individuals form a mental representation of a foreign country that leads them to perceive (dis)similarities with their home country. Thus, alternative model #1 has CI as an antecedent to PD and tests the following relationships: the more positive the peoplerelated CI, the lower the PD; and the more positive the product-related CI, the lower the PD.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Alternative model #2 (PD → CI).</head><p>With respect to decision-makers' affective processes, <ref type="bibr" target="#b103">Zajonc's (1968)</ref> mere-exposure theory proposes that repeated exposure to a stimulus increases the liking of this stimulus. Distance in all its forms impedes exposure, and thus reduces likability. The related theory of propinquity <ref type="bibr">(Festinger, Schachter, and Back 1983)</ref>, documented in the psychology of interpersonal attractiveness (i.e., people that are physically/psychologically similar tend to be attracted to each other), supports the idea that PD reduces the likeability and attractiveness of foreigners. Likewise, international marketing scholars have argued that since PD prevents information flows, it could reduce the attractiveness of foreign partners in relation to domestic ones <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Johnston et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Leonidou et al. 2011)</ref>. Thus, alternative model #2 situates PD as an antecedent to CI and tests the following relationships: the lower the PD, the more positive the people-related CI; and the lower the PD, the more positive the product-related CI.</p><p>As revealed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">6</ref>, the hypothesized model compares favorably against the alternative models in terms of both overall model fit and percentage of variance of the dependent variables (e.g., REO) explained. Therefore, we conclude that the hypothesized model is the best one.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>-Insert Table 6 about here -</head><p>Another post-hoc analysis evaluated the hypothesized model on the basis of OLS regression. The regression results were fully consistent with our structural model testing of the hypotheses. Variance inflation factors from the regressions provided further evidence that multicollinearity is not an issue in the study. They ranged from 1.74 to 5.32, well below the recommended cut-off score of 10 <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Kutner, Nachtsheim, and Neter 2004)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION AND IMPLICATIONS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Contrary Direct Effects of PD and CI</head><p>The results suggest PD and CI are non-negligible drivers of REO in exporter-importer ties that, however, play contrasting roles. On the one hand, we confirm a negative impact of PD on REO (H1 is supported), which reflects prior research on relationship quality in international markets <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">(Katsikeas et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Leonidou et al. 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b89">Skarmeas et al. 2008</ref>). On the other, our findings uncover a positive effect of product-related CI on REO with foreign partners (H2b is supported). This novel result echoes and extends prior research on the role of CI in supplier evaluations <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Bradley 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Knight et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b97">Vinhas da Silva et al. 2001)</ref>. While the hypothesized positive effect of people-related CI on REO is invalidated (H2a is not supported), it does not mean people-related CI is of no importance. Our results confirm the existence of a transfer from the macro image of people to the micro image of products (H3 is supported). The implication is that the image of people can be a powerful tool to enhance the image of goods from specific origins, even in an industrial context. The novelty of this insight for industrial marketing lies in that the transfer is taking place from the macro image conceptualized as a people-related facet and not by the PEST environment-related facet of CI. The finding reflects place branding work on the role played by citizens as brand ambassadors for their country <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Dinnie 2008</ref>) and studies in consumer behavior showing the influence of affect toward people on product evaluations <ref type="bibr" target="#b83">(Roth and Diamantopoulos 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b104">Zeugner-Roth et al. 2008)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A Favorable Micro CI Mitigates the Detrimental Effect of PD on REO</head><p>Our results confirm the negative effect of PD on REO in international markets <ref type="bibr" target="#b89">(Skarmeas et al. 2008</ref>). However, they tell a somewhat different story about the effect of PD when considered in combination with CI. First, we observe that people-related CI does not moderate the PD to REO path (H4a is not supported). By contrast, we find that product-related CI mitigates the negative effect of PD on REO (H4b is supported). The results support our proposition to situate CI as a boundary condition to the effect of PD, but nuances it to the dominant role of productrelated CI.</p><p>The expectancy-value approach underscores that PD is not always highly detrimental in international channel relationships. In fact, PD can be mitigated by the introduction of valence factors. To explore the moderation effect in detail, we plotted the relationship between PD and REO in situations of high and low levels of product-related CI (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref>). A strong productrelated CI (i.e., positive beliefs about a country in connection to the product category) significantly reduces the negative influence of PD on REO. Firms should not be concerned about the negative effect of PD when they can utilize valence beliefs-stemming from a highly favorable product-related CI-that the relationship is worth the effort. Detrimental effects of PD are mainly relevant for firms with poor product-related CI.</p><p>-Insert Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref> about here -When managers hold contradictory perceptions and beliefs about a foreign country (i.e., high PD and high product-related CI), REO with partners from the country can still be achieved. This observation could reflect the attractiveness of exotic business partners. Although the wine industry may appear relatively unique for valuing exotic suppliers, extent research on CI has demonstrated the existence of strong product-country matches in manufacturing sectors, where exoticism is of little importance, such as Germany and cars, the US and computers, and Japan and electronics <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Dinnie 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Jaffe and Nebenzahl 2001)</ref>. Alternatively, an explanation for observing that REO is enhanced in situations of high PD and positive product-related CI may be found in the theory of cognitive dissonance <ref type="bibr">(Festinger 1957)</ref>, which explains that when people hold conflicting beliefs, this creates a psychological discomfort that they try to reduce.</p><p>One mechanism for reducing dissonance is to seek as much new information as possible (e.g., about the foreign country). Increased knowledge and understanding of differences may motivate managers to develop relationships with partners from the country.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theoretical Implications</head><p>The study contributes to theory in three main ways. First, it contributes to explaining the mixed evidence on the effects of PD on exporter-importer relationships. Using a contingency perspective, we believe this study offers the first empirical validation of the role played by product-related CI in moderating the PD to REO association. Given its theoretical foundations in the expectancy-value approach, this result implies that factors increasing the worth of exchange with foreign partners may mitigate PD because they boost managerial motivation and the willingness to create close partnerships.</p><p>Our significant moderation finding extends existing insights in the international channels literature. For instance, <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Johnston et al. (2012)</ref> referred to calculative commitment and expected achievement of common goals to explain unexpected results that PD does not mitigate the relationships of trust and satisfaction with joint action. Studies on the effects of PD on other foreign market entry strategy decisions also show the moderating role of factors increasing valence. For instance, <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">Malhotra, Sivakumar, and Zhu (2009)</ref> have shown that market size moderates the effect of PD on international market selection. More broadly, economics studies based on the gravity theory of international trade <ref type="bibr" target="#b94">(Tinbergen 1962)</ref> have shown that the attractiveness of countries in terms of economic mass (measured with their GDP, for instance) can override the negative impact of geographical distance.</p><p>Product-CI is just one boundary condition that explains why the detrimental effect of PD can be significantly attenuated. Other factors increasing valence in exchange (e.g., market size, market share, corporate and individual reputations of partners, etc.) represent potential boundary conditions to PD and could further explain mixed evidence on the effects of PD.</p><p>The second theoretical implication of the study is that it provides a deeper understanding of the PD paradox. As an explanation for this paradox, O'Grady and Lane <ref type="bibr">(1996, p. 324</ref>) noted that: "The phenomenon we have referred to as the psychic distance paradox seemed to be created by common, but unexplored, assumptions or underlying beliefs about the United States that decision-makers held in Canadian retail companies." Without naming it, O'Grady and Lane <ref type="bibr">(1996)</ref> referred to the concept of CI. They attributed the poor performance of Canadian retailers to an overly favorable CI of the US in Canada, which not only created excessive expectations but also impeded required efforts to successfully enter the country. Our study provides an alternative explanation. We find that in a context of low levels of PD, its effect can be more detrimental if CI is poor (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref>). A lower than expected CI of Canada in the US could thus explain why-despite low PD-Canadian retailers struggled. This view is supported by the fact that the paradox did not hold for US firms that successfully expanded in Canada.</p><p>American firms may have benefited from a better CI in Canada (like PD, CI is asymmetric). In the same way, the ignored role of CI could explain several of the conflicting observations made by <ref type="bibr" target="#b91">Stottinger and Schlegelmilch (1998)</ref>. For instance, they were surprised that US managers overestimated PD with Canada and Mexico but underestimated PD with Hong Kong. In light of our study, Hong Kong may simply have benefitted from a stronger CI. Integrating the role of CI could challenge Stottinger and Schlegelmilch's (1998) conclusions about the lack of relevance of the PD construct.</p><p>Evidently, we wish we could properly revisit conflicting evidence in the exporter-importer relationships literature. For instance, we might argue that <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Bello et al. (2003)</ref> did not observe a negative effect of PD on relationalism, or <ref type="bibr" target="#b105">Zhang et al. (2003)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Leonidou et al. (2006)</ref> on trust, because a favorable CI had offset the effect of PD. Unfortunately, most studies on the role of PD in cross-border relationships have not documented the country-of-origin of foreign partners (see Table <ref type="table">1</ref>), precluding such alternative explanations. Indeed, from a methodological standpoint, studying boundary conditions (e.g., CI and other valence factors) to the effects of PD in international relationships ideally requires: documenting the country-of-origin of business partners; incorporating varying degrees of PD in survey designs; and harmonizing conceptualizations of PD (differences between countries or companies) and relationship selection criteria (size, representativeness, or difficulty) to enhance comparability of results.</p><p>The third theoretical implication lies in that the study reconciles research on PD with research on beliefs, attitudes, and behaviors. It offers the first empirical validation of the interplay between PD and CI and their mutual, yet contrasting, influence on behaviors in international markets (here, REO). Despite Håkanson and Ambos' (2010) call for reuniting the construct of PD with managerial attitudes and beliefs, research has been compartmentalized. We believe this is the case because the accepted definition of PD (as a perception) and theories traditionally used to study PD (i.e., transaction costs and social exchange theories) make it difficult to find common conceptual ground. The current study bridges the conceptual gap by taking a behavioral perspective, using the expectancy-value approach (in particular Vroom's expectancy theory). As a result, this study suggests reconsidering the conceptualization of PD as a belief rather than a perception. A perception is defined as the way individuals select, organize, and interpret intrinsic (e.g., sights, sounds, smells, and tastes) or extrinsic stimuli (e.g., brand, price, country-of-origin) <ref type="bibr" target="#b83">(Roth and Diamantopoulos 2009)</ref>. A belief is defined as the subjective probability that an object (e.g., a country) has specific attributes <ref type="bibr">(Fishbein and Ajzen 2010)</ref>. Shifting from the idea that PD is the perception of differences between countries to the idea that it is the belief that a foreign country has different attributes compared to the home country, does not seem like much, but it would facilitate the use of behavioral theories related to cognition, affect, attitudes, motivation, and decision-making (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Atkinson 1957;</ref><ref type="bibr">Festinger et al. 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fishbein and Ajzen 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b98">Vroom 1964</ref>). Thus, this study is a stepping-stone toward a finer understanding of the way managers develop distance perceptions and beliefs about foreign countries, which are then translated into attitudes and behaviors toward their people and products.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Managerial Implications</head><p>The current study provides managers with new ideas in two main respects. First, we propose alternative coping mechanisms when the effect of PD is detrimental in international channel relationships. Available recommendations have targeted reducing distance by means of, for instance, cross-cultural training, trips abroad, and language courses <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">(Leonidou et al. 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Leonidou et al. 2011)</ref>. Given our finding that subjective PD can attenuate REO in exporterimporter relationships, it is crucial that partners are able to calibrate, assess, and reduce their respective PD perceptions during formative phases of the relationship. These activities to reduce distance could be used to integrate the two sets of managers. In addition, our study encourages consideration of forms of CI in exchange strategies and communications with foreign partners. In this way, managers could work with their governments and trade associations to reinforce their product-CI, as well as the people-CI (for its indirect effect), through participation in and funding of place branding campaigns and promotion activities (international trade fairs, commercial delegations to foreign countries, etc.) <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Dinnie 2008)</ref>.</p><p>Firms might also derive benefit from adapting their communication strategies according to the degree of favorability of their product-related CI. Marketers from countries with a positive micro image that are looking to develop relationships with psychically distant foreign business partners should not hesitate to flaunt the positive image of their country-of-origin for the production or consumption of goods (providing statistics or rankings, associations with positive attributes, etc.). Firms that lack a positive micro image could proactively dampen the presence of an origin cue in their communications, and highlight other cues (e.g., design, brand, and price). This suggestion aligns with strategies described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Deshpandé (2010)</ref> for firms from emerging markets to overcome the provenance paradox (i.e., not having a favorable product-CI in spite of producing quality products, such as Venezuela and chocolate, or Mexico and beer).</p><p>The second important managerial implication of the study is to show that efforts toward reducing PD could be misplaced in situations-such as a high level of product-related CI-</p><p>where it has minimal impact on REO. This invites managers to learn about their foreign business partners' beliefs regarding their home country; to this purpose, they can use direct or indirect inquiries (e.g., through available country brand rankings). 2 Firms may adapt their market selection strategies accordingly. When confronted with an unfavorable product-related CI, managers should target markets where foreign partners have low PD evaluations and avoid high PD contexts. When armed with a favorable product-related CI, firms should not consider PD as a major impediment. They might even target countries where partners have high PD 2 Examples include: www.simonanholt.com/Research/research-the-anholt-gfk-roper-nation-brands-indexsm.aspx, <ref type="url" target="http://www.futurebrand.com/cbi/2014">http://www.futurebrand.com/cbi/2014</ref>, and www.placebrandobserver.com/country-brand-rankings. evaluations, since this set of circumstances could help firms differentiate from competitors with lower PD evaluations and avoid the distance paradox (e.g., shocks caused by unanticipated differences) in relational exchanges. In sum, firms with strong product-related CI should not always attempt to close PD, because they have the option of leveraging high levels of PD in their partnering strategies and still achieving and maintaining REO.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>LIMITATIONS AND AVENUES FOR FUTURE RESEARCH</head><p>The results of the study need to be interpreted while bearing in mind certain limitations. First, although the research design enabled the collection of a high quality sample characterized by large degrees of variation in terms of PD and CI, future studies should work toward the collection of representative samples of narrower portions of an industry's value chain (e.g., exporter-importing distributor), in order to increase specificity and precision of the results.</p><p>Second, the risk of potential selection bias from our unit of analysis (i.e., relationships with the largest business partners in different countries) impacting generalizability of the results should be controlled for. Third, as the wine industry is sensitive to CI, replications of the study in other industry-specific contexts will also help establish the external validity and generalizability of the findings. Finally, the study has other limitations common with research on interfirm relationships (e.g., non-matched relationships and one informant per company), which future studies should tackle when aiming to confirm our results.</p><p>Overall, six avenues for future research are particularly promising in relation to the study implications. It is important that researchers: First, test the effectiveness of place branding activities in reducing or leveraging the effect of PD in international channel relationships; Second, target explaining greater REO variance by using other antecedents in addition to PD and CI (e.g., relationship value, uncertainty/volatility, and interdependence/power); Third, integrate conceptually environment-related CI with product-and people-related CI to unravel their nebulous linkages with PD; Fourth, test the impact of other valence factors (market size, partners' market share, product price and complexity, product involvement, etc.) as moderators to the effect of PD; Fifth, widen the conceptualization of PD as a subjective influence alonealthough our approach is consistent with theories of motivation, both real and perceived distance between markets place added significance on developing cross-border relationships <ref type="bibr">(Samiee, Chabowski, and Hult 2015)</ref>; Sixth, cross-fertilize the expectancy-value approach using related motivation and cognitive/affective theories (e.g., reasoned action theory, categorization theory, and mere-exposure theory) pertinent to PD in international markets.</p><p>Stottinger and Schlegelmilch (2000, p. 172) commented that: "Only when antecedents to and dimensions of the construct of psychic distance are established can strategies to overcome psychic distance be developed." Fifteen years later, significant effort has resulted in a satisfactory understanding of antecedents and dimensions of the PD construct <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Brewer 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Evans and Mavondo 2002b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b91">Sousa and Lages 2011)</ref>. Nevertheless, highly inconsistent results still lead us to question, and defend, the relevance of the psychic and cultural distance constructs (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b88">Shenkar 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b102">Zaheer, Schomaker, and Nachum 2012)</ref>. The relevance of CI is also facing acute criticism as to its theoretical and operational foundations (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Josiassen and Harzing 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b85">Samiee 2011)</ref>. By showing that previously unexplored boundary conditions (i.e., CI) to the effect of PD exist in exporter-importer ties <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(Magnusson and Boyle 2009)</ref>, this study invites researchers to move on from questions concerning what PD is and why it would or would not matter, and to start focusing on when it matters. In order to develop relevant strategies to overcome the effects of PD in international markets, this study strongly suggests that scholars steer their focus toward managers' motivations in future research.     </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2 Plot of the Moderating Role of Product-Related Country Image in the Relationship of Psychic Distance and Relational Exchange Orientation</figDesc><graphic coords="44,78.95,140.99,454.10,264.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="1,0.00,381.30,595.30,460.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="39,152.05,127.20,307.84,200.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 2 Selected Empirical and Conceptual Studies on Country Image Country Image Macro Country Image Micro Country Image Environment-related Country Image People-related Country Image Product-related Country Image</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Conceptualization</cell><cell>An individual's beliefs about a country in</cell><cell>An individual's beliefs about a country</cell><cell>An individual's beliefs about a country in</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>connection to its political, economic,</cell><cell>in connection to its people</cell><cell>connection to a specific product category</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>sociocultural, and technological (PEST)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>environment</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Operationalization</cell><cell>Extent to which a country's environment is</cell><cell>Extent to which people from a specific</cell><cell>Extent to which products from a specific</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>characterized by, for instance: economic</cell><cell>country are characterized by, for</cell><cell>country are characterized by, for instance:</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>development, per capita income, technological</cell><cell>instance: likeability, trustworthiness,</cell><cell>quality, reliability, innovativeness, design,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>research, standard of living, unemployment,</cell><cell>friendliness, creativity, knowledge,</cell><cell>prestige, and workmanship; or extent to</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>labor costs, industrialization, literacy, education,</cell><cell>competence, education, and hard work</cell><cell>which a country is capable of conceiving,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>welfare system, civilian non-military</cell><cell></cell><cell>designing, engineering, or assembling a</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>government, free market, and democracy</cell><cell></cell><cell>given product category</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 3 Measurement Model Results Note</head><label>3</label><figDesc>: AVE = Average variance extracted; CR = Composite reliability; α = Cronbach's alpha  2 (df = 206) = 340.00, p &lt; .01; GFI = .94; NFI = .96; CFI = .98; TLI = .98; RMSEA = .05</figDesc><table><row><cell>Factors</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 4 Correlations among Latent Variables, Means, and Standard Deviations</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Note: correlations greater than .15 or less than -.15 are significant at p = .05 Model fit:  2 (df = 27) = 62.10, p = .02; GFI = .91; NFI = .92; CFI = .94; TLI = .91; RMSEA = .06</figDesc><table><row><cell>Constructs</cell><cell>1.</cell><cell>2.</cell><cell>3.</cell><cell>4.</cell><cell>5.</cell><cell>6.</cell><cell>7.</cell><cell>8.</cell></row><row><cell>1. Relational exchange orientation</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2. Psychic distance</cell><cell cols="2">-.36 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>3. People-related country image</cell><cell cols="3">.17 -.01 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>4. Product-related country image</cell><cell cols="4">.39 -.26 .13 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>5. Product price</cell><cell>.31</cell><cell>.06</cell><cell>.10</cell><cell cols="2">.06 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>6. Relationship duration</cell><cell cols="3">.41 -.18 .13</cell><cell>.20</cell><cell cols="2">.04 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>7. Knowledge of partner country</cell><cell cols="3">.08 -.08 .00</cell><cell>.02</cell><cell>.01</cell><cell cols="2">.12 1</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>8. Role in the supply chain</cell><cell cols="3">.35 -.18 .13</cell><cell>.10</cell><cell cols="4">.04 -.02 .10 1</cell></row><row><cell>Mean</cell><cell cols="8">2.76 3.03 3.18 2.81 2.84 3.15 1.43 1.70</cell></row><row><cell>Standard deviation</cell><cell cols="2">1.18 1.33</cell><cell cols="4">.74 1.09 1.48 1.66</cell><cell>.60</cell><cell>.85</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 6 Comparative Analysis of Alternative Models</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Indices</cell><cell>Hypothesized Model (CI moderates effect of PD)</cell><cell>Alternative Model #1 (CI → PD)</cell><cell>Alternative Model #2 (PD → CI)</cell></row><row><cell>χ2/df</cell><cell>2.30</cell><cell>3.80</cell><cell>5.20</cell></row><row><cell>GFI</cell><cell>.91</cell><cell>0.81</cell><cell>0.73</cell></row><row><cell>NFI</cell><cell>.92</cell><cell>0.71</cell><cell>0.70</cell></row><row><cell>CFI</cell><cell>.94</cell><cell>0.84</cell><cell>0.81</cell></row><row><cell>TLI</cell><cell>.91</cell><cell>0.89</cell><cell>0.80</cell></row><row><cell>RMSEA</cell><cell>.06</cell><cell>0.09</cell><cell>0.12</cell></row><row><cell>R 2 Relational exchange orientation</cell><cell>24.23%</cell><cell>20.11%</cell><cell>19.30%</cell></row><row><cell>R 2 Psychic distance</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>6.21%</cell></row><row><cell>R 2 Product-related country image</cell><cell>17.51%</cell><cell>16.73%</cell><cell>15.42%</cell></row><row><cell>R 2 People-related country image</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>This finding implies firms playing an importer role in the supply chain have greater REO. Role in the supply chain reflects that global wine traders may act as exporters, importers or else combine both roles at the firmlevel (see Appendix B.1), even if the vast majority of our respondents (80.40%) opted to address the relationship-level study constructs with customers in mind (see Appendix B.2).</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>This work was supported by a grant from the <rs type="funder">Fond de Recherche du Québec -Société et Culture</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <ref type="bibr">Leonidou et al. (2002)</ref> <p>Purpose: Comparing harmonious and problematic relationships with foreign customers (degree of satisfaction) on, for e.g., latent (dependence, distance, trust, uncertainty, understanding) and manifest <ref type="bibr">(adaptation, commitment, communication, conflict, cooperation)</ref> atmosphere Conceptualization: Distance refers to the degree of unfamiliarity of one party in a business relationship with the characteristics of the other, with regard to social, cultural, structural, and procedural aspects such as business environment, working methods, structure, etc. Findings: Greater trust, commitment, communication, and cooperation, and lesser distance, between the parties, characterize harmonious relationships</p><p>Companies: Exporting manufacturers Industries: Industrial goods including machine tools, supplies and materials~75%, and consumer goods including household durables, foodstuffs and beverages~25% Home/Foreign countries: US/83, unspecified Relationship: Foreign customers in general <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Bello et al. (2003)</ref> Purpose: Testing the impact of relationalism (information exchange, solidarity, flexibility) and its antecedents (resource inadequacy, manufacturer dependence, market volatility, product complexity, human content, psychic distance) on distributor performance Conceptualization: Psychic distance refers to problems a firm encounters due to its ignorance of sociocultural differences (culture, language, customs and values of the people, business practices) experienced in the foreign market Findings: No significant effect of psychic distance on relationalism</p><p>Companies: Exporting manufacturers Industries: Unspecified Home/Foreign countries: US/Unspecified Relationship: A single, focal export distributor and foreign market <ref type="bibr" target="#b105">Zhang et al. (2003)</ref> Purpose: Testing the impact of trust and manufacturer reliance on relational norms on manufacturer competitiveness in the export market; and cultural distance, hostility of legal/institutional environment, and relative dependence on foreign distributor as antecedents Conceptualization: Cultural distance refers to country differences on <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Hofstede's (1980)</ref>  Purpose: Testing the impact of drivers related to markets (psychic distance, environmental uncertainty) and exporters (role performance, transaction specific investments) on relationship quality (trust, commitment, satisfaction) Conceptualization: Psychic distance refers to the perceived dissimilarity between foreign and domestic operating environments in terms of culture (traditions, values, language), accepted business practices, economic environment, legal system, and communication infrastructure Purpose: Exploring differences in perceptions between US and Canadian managers in terms of dependence, understanding, commitment, communication, uncertainty, conflict, and distance in relationships with foreign partners Conceptualization: Distance is the degree of unfamiliarity of one business party with the other Findings: Trust is the only dimension of relationships on which perceptions differ; psychic distance is relatively small between US and Canada Companies: Exporters (pure exporting~50%, hybrid, also with manufacturing~50%) Industries: Unspecified Home/Foreign countries: US and Canada/The same Relationship: Unspecified</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Johnston et al. (2012)</head><p>Purpose: Testing effects of trust and satisfaction on joint action; communication frequency and bi-directionality as antecedents; and psychic distance as a moderator of these links Conceptualization: Psychic distance refers to buyers' perceptions of the differences between the operating environments of buyers and sellers in an international exchange relationship Findings: Psychic distance reduces positive effects of communication on trust and satisfaction but does not moderate effects of trust and satisfaction on joint action Companies: Importers Industries: Unspecified Home/Foreign countries: Taiwan/China~17%, US~13%, Japan~12%, Singapore~11%, and Hong Kong~9% Relationship: Unspecified <ref type="bibr">Leonidou et al. (2014)</ref> Purpose: Conducting a meta-analysis on the antecedents (opportunism, conflict, communication, cultural distance, adaptation), components (cooperation, trust, commitment), and outcomes (relationship performance, financial performance) of relationship quality Conceptualization: Distance is any prevention, delay, or distortion of information shared between partners in a relationship that keeps them apart Findings: Distance negatively affects cooperation, trust, and commitment and, thus, relationship quality Companies: Exporters~58%, importers~27%, dyads but not necessarily matched~15% Industries: Unspecified (i.e., meta-analysis) Home/Foreign countries: US~27%, UK~13%, China~10%, and Australia~8%/Unspecified Relationship: Foreign partners as a whole or with a particular partner <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Griffith and Dimitrova (2014)</ref> Purpose: Testing effects of business and cultural distance on complementarity of capabilities, which is expected to impact satisfaction with performance (moderated by distance) Conceptualization: Business distance refers to perceived differences in the economic environment, legal and political system, business practices, market structure, and language; cultural distance refers to perceived differences across <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Hofstede's (1980)</ref> dimensions Findings: Business distance negatively affects complementarity; business distance and cultural distance have opposite effects in moderating the complementarity to satisfaction path (the former reduces the effect, while the latter enhances it); and cultural distance negatively impacts satisfaction Companies: Exporters Industries: Unspecified, but manufacturing sector Home/Foreign countries: US/Unspecified Relationship: The primary foreign buyer <ref type="bibr" target="#b90">Skarmeas et al. (2015)</ref> Purpose: Testing effects of relationship-specific assets, knowledge sharing, complementary capabilities, and relational norms, as well as psychic distance (moderated by cultural sensitivity), on relationship value, which is expected to affect relational outcomes (insensitivity to competitive offerings and future purchase expansion </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1 Theoretical Model</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX A Operationalization of Constructs</head><p>Note: Text between brackets is dependent upon early responses given by participants (perspective of the buyer or seller, work country, country of origin of selected partner #1 and #2) and is automatically replaced by the survey software.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scale</head><p>From </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experience in position</head><p>Less than 1 year: 6.1%; 1-3 years: 16.8%; 3-5 years: 16.2%; 5-10 years: 26.3%; 10-15 years: 17.3%; 15-20 years: 9.5%; Over 20 years: 7.8%</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Work country of respondent</head><p>35 Countries: France: 18.4%; Italy: 15.1%; Spain: 12.8%; Portugal: 7.3%; Argentina: 5.0%; Australia: 4.5%; Canada: 3.9%; Chile, Mexico: 2.8% (each); South Africa, USA: 2.2% (each); China, Greece, Netherlands, Norway, Switzerland, UK: 1.7% (each); Cyprus, Georgia, New Zealand, Puerto Rico, Russia: 1.1% (each); Belgium, Bolivia, Croatia, Germany, Hong Kong, Macedonia, Malaysia, Singapore, Slovenia, Togo, Uganda, Uruguay, Venezuela: .6% (each)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Native country of respondent</head><p>39 Countries: France: 19.6%; Italy: 14.0%; Spain: 13.4%; Portugal: 6.1%; Argentina: 4.5%; UK: 3.4%; Canada, Chile: 2.8% (each); Australia, Mexico, Netherlands, South Africa, Switzerland, USA: 2.2% (each); Greece, New Zealand: 1.7% (each); Belgium, China, Cyprus, Germany, Georgia, Puerto Rico: 1.1% (each); Bolivia, Burundi, Croatia, Denmark, Kenya, Macedonia, Malaysia, Mongolia, Romania, Russia, Singapore, Slovenia, Togo, Uruguay, Venezuela: .6% (each)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Firm size</head><p>Under 10 employees: 57.5%; 11-50 employees: 28.5%; 51-100 employees: 6.7%; 101-250 employees: 3.4%; 251-500 employees: 1.1%; 501-1,000 employees: 1.1%; Over 1,000 employees: 1.7%</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Firm type</head><p>Firms with activities located: Upstream of the value chain: 61% (Producer; Exporter; Producer and exporter); Across the whole value chain: 10% (Producer, exporter, and importer; Producer, exporter, and wholesaler; Producer, exporter, and retailer; Producer, wholesaler and retailer; Exporter, importer and wholesaler; Producer, exporter, importer and wholesaler; Producer, exporter, wholesaler, and retailer; Exporter, agent/broker and wholesaler; Exporter, agent/broker, importer and wholesaler); Downstream of the value chain: 29% (Importer; Agent/broker; Wholesaler; Retailer; Importer and wholesaler; Importer and retailer; Importer, wholesaler, and retailer; Agent/broker, importer, and wholesaler; including "other activities" for 2.8%, i.e. consultancy companies, wine school, sommelier, and winemaker association).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Market type</head><p>Do business with partners from: Both traditional and emerging market/supply markets: 67.0%; Traditional market/supply markets only: 27.4%; Emerging market/supply markets only: 5.6%</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX B.2 Sample Description: Interfirm Relationships (n=358) Product type</head><p>Type: Red wine: 80.40%; White wine: 13.40%; Sparkling wine: 4.50%; Rosé wine: 1.70%;</p><p>Retail price (US$)</p><p>Retail price: Under 5$: 15.10%; 5$-9.99$: 30.70%; 10$-14.99$: 24.60%; 15$-19.99$: 15.60%; 20$-29.99$: 7.80%, 30$-39.99$: 2.80%; Over 40$: 3.40%</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Type of relationship</head><p>Selected relationships with: Customers: 80.40%; Suppliers: 19.60%</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Duration of relationship</head><p>Under 1 year: 15.60%; 1-3 years: 31.00%; 3-5 years: 5-10 years: </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>France</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="74" />
			<pubPlace>New Zealand; Greece, Portugal</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Italy: 3.63%; Spain: 1.95%; Argentina: 1.39%</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chile</forename><surname>Canada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Germany</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Uk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bolivia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Georgia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mexico</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Netherlands</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Puerto</forename><surname>Norway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rico</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>16.00%) France: 4.46%; Italy: 2.79%; Spain: 2.23%; Australia: 1.95</idno>
		<title level="m">28% (each) China</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Singapore, Switzerland, Uruguay; Portugal, South Africa; Greece; Argentina, Germany, New Zealand, Croatia, Georgia, Macedonia, Singapore, Switzerland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Germany</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">63% (each); France: 2.23%; Portugal: 1.67%; Greece Argentina</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Spain</forename><surname>Italy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>Chile, South Africa</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Croatia</forename><surname>Usa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Georgia, Macedonia, Netherlands, Norway, Slovenia, Switzerland</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>France: 3.00%; Italy: 1.95%; Spain: 1.39%; Portugal: .84%; Australia: .55%</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">21%) Argentina: 1.95%; Portugal: 1.67%; Spain: .55%</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Brazil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>Chile, France</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Italy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>New Zealand, South Africa, Belgium, Bolivia, Mexico, Norway, Puerto Rico, Switzerland, Uruguay</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">10%) Canada: 1.11%; China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>France</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Portugal, Spain</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Italy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hong</forename><surname>Kong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>Mexico, Netherlands, Norway</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">28% (each) Russia (6.14%) France: 1.67%; Italy: 1.11%; Spain</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Belgium, Cyprus, Togo, Uganda; Argentina, Chile, Portugal</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cyprus</forename><surname>Russia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Georgia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Slovenia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">%; Spain: 1.11%</title>
		<idno>5.60%) Australia: 1.39</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">83%; Portugal</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>France, Italy; Argentina; Chile, Mexico</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Spain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>3.00%) Canada: .83</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>China, Mexico</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Usa</forename><surname>Russia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Puerto</forename><surname>Malaysia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rico</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">28% (each) Italy (2.50%) USA: .83%; Canada</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>China, UK , Cyprus, Netherlands, Switzerland; Chile (2.23%) Canada, Mexico</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>28% (each)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Venezuela</forename><surname>Usa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">28% (each) India (1.11%)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Argentina</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>Australia: .55</idno>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>Canada, Italy, Malaysia, Puerto Rico, Venezuela; France, South Africa</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Africa (1.11%) Spain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>UK, Togo, Uganda</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Zealand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">55%) Canada</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Russia: .28% (each) Portugal (.28%) Netherlands: .28%</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of Country-of-Origin Effects on Household and Organisational Purchasing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sadrudin</forename><surname>Ahmed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alain D'</forename><surname>Astous</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Model of Distributor Firm and Manufacturer Firm Working Partnerships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Narus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="42" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Partnering as a Focused Market Strategy</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">California Management Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="113" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motivational Determinants of Risk-Taking Behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Atkinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="372" />
			<date type="published" when="1957">1957</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interpersonal Factors as Drivers of Quality and Performance in Western-Hong Kong Interorganizational Business Relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bradley</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Leonidas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Leonidou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Noel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Constantinos</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Siu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Leonidou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global Wine War</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christopher</forename><surname>Bartlett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Harvard Business School, 9-910-405</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009. 2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="23" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Antecedents and Performance Consequences of Relationalism in Export Distribution Channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Bello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cristian</forename><surname>Chelariu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Li</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Country-Company Interaction Effects and Supplier Preferences Among Industrial Buyers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Frank</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Industrial Marketing Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="524" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Operationalizing Psychic Distance: A Revised Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Brewer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="66" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Study of Thinking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jerome</forename><surname>Bruner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Goodnow</forename><surname>Jacqueline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Austin</forename><surname>Georges</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1956">1956</date>
			<publisher>John Wiley and Sons</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Barbara</forename><surname>Byrne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Structural Equation Modeling with AMOS: Basic Concepts, Applications, and Programming</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge Academy</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Second edition ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">International Relationship Marketing -The Importance of Psychic Distance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tony</forename><surname>Conway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonathan</forename><surname>Swift</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11/12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1391" to="1414" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why You Aren&apos;t Buying Venezuelan Chocolate</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rohit</forename><surname>Deshpandé</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Harvard Business Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-12">2010. December</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Don</forename><surname>Dillman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jolene</forename><surname>Smyth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Leah</forename><surname>Christian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Internet, Mail, and Mixed-Mode Surveys: The Tailored Design Method</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hoboken, New Jersey</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nation Branding: Concepts, Issues, Practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Keith</forename><surname>Dinnie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developing a Multidimensional Instrument to Measure Psychic Distance Stimuli</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Douglas</forename><surname>Dow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amal</forename><surname>Karunaratna</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Business Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="578" to="602" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Buyer-Seller Relationships -Theoretical Perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Dwyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Dahlstrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Theresa</forename><surname>Dinovo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Business Marketing: An Interaction and Network Perspective</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kristian</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Möller</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developing Buyer-Seller Relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sejo</forename><surname>Schurr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Oh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Psychic Distance and Organizational Performance: An Empirical Examination of International Retailing Operations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jody</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Felix</forename><surname>Mavondo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Business Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="515" to="532" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Psychic Distance: The Construct and Measurers</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">American Marketing Association Conference Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002b</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="308" to="314" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Psychic Distance: Antecedents, Retail Strategy Implications, and Performance Outcomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Felix</forename><surname>Mavondo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kerrie</forename><surname>Bridson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Subjective Probability and Decision under Uncertainty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Feather</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="164" />
			<date type="published" when="1959">1959</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effects of Country of Origin on UK Consumers&apos; Perceptions of Imported Wines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christian</forename><surname>Felzensztein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Keith</forename><surname>Dinnie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A Theory of Cognitive Dissonance</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Leon; Stanford, California</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1957">2005. 1957</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="117" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Festinger</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Spatial Ecology of Group Formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schachter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Back</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Social Pressure in Informal Groups: A Study of Human Factors in Housing</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Leon</forename><surname>Festinger</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stanley</forename><surname>Schachter</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kurt</forename><surname>Back</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Stanford, California</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Fishbein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Icek</forename><surname>Ajzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Belief, Attitude, Intention, and Behavior: An Introduction to Theory and Research</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Reading, Massachussets</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Predicting and Changing Behavior -The Reasoned Action Approach</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Taylor and Francis Group</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exchange Behavior an Marketing Channels: A Broadened Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gary</forename><surname>Frazier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="68" to="78" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Bonding Effects of Relationship Value and Switching Costs in Industrial Buyer-Seller Relationships: An Investigation Into Role Differences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ingmar</forename><surname>Geiger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aurelia</forename><surname>Durand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Samy</forename><surname>Saab</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Kleinaltenkamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Roger</forename><surname>Baxter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yeonhee</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Industrial Marketing Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Business and Cultural Aspects of Psychic Distance and Complementarity of Capabilities in Export Relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Griffith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Boryana</forename><surname>Dimitrova</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Joseph</forename><surname>Hair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">William</forename><surname>Black</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Babin</forename><surname>Barry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rolph</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Multivariate Data Analysis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Upper Saddle River, New Jersey</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Seventh Edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Antecedents of Psychic Distance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lars</forename><surname>Håkanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Björn</forename><surname>Ambos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do Norms Matter in Marketing Relationships?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Heide</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">George</forename><surname>John</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship Marketing in the American and Canadian Export Sectors: A Matter of Trust</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lise</forename><surname>Heroux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ali</forename><surname>Hammoutene</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of American Academy of Business</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Culture and Organizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Geert</forename><surname>Hofstede</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Studies of Management and Organization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eugene</forename><surname>Jaffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Israel</forename><surname>Nebenzahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">National Image and Competitive Advantage</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Copenhagen, Denmark</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Copenhagen Business School Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Internationalization Process of the Firm -A Model of Knowledge Development and Increasing Foreign Market Commitments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Johanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan-Erik</forename><surname>Vahlne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Business Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Uppsala Internationalization Process Model Revisited: From Liability of Foreignness to Liability of Outsidership</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Business Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1411" to="1431" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determinants of Joint Action in International Channels of Distribution: The Moderating Role of Psychic Distance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wesley</forename><surname>Johnston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shadab</forename><surname>Khalil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Megha</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Julian Ming-Sung</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Descending from the Ivory Tower: Reflections on the Relevance and Future of Country-of-Origin Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alexander</forename><surname>Josiassen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anne-Wil</forename><surname>Harzing</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Management Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="264" to="270" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Country-of-Origin Contingencies -Competing Perspectives on Product Familiarity and Product Involvement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bryan</forename><surname>Lukas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gregory</forename><surname>Whitwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Marketing Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="423" to="440" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developing Successful Trust-Based International Exchange Relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Constantine</forename><surname>Katsikeas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dionysis</forename><surname>Skarmeas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Bello</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Business Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="132" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Country-of-Origin and Choice of Food Imports: An In-Depth Study of European Distribution Channel Gatekeepers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Knight</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Holdsworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Damien</forename><surname>Mather</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Business Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="125" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Kutner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christopher</forename><surname>Nachtsheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Neter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Applied Linear Regression Models</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston, Massachussets</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill Irwin</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of National Culture on the Choice of Entry Mode</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bruce</forename><surname>Kogut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Harbir</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Business Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="433" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Country Image Structure on Consumer Evaluations of Foreign Products</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michel</forename><surname>Laroche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicolas</forename><surname>Papadopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Louise</forename><surname>Heslop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mehdi</forename><surname>Mourali</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Marketing Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="115" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reverse Country-of-Origin Effects of Product Perceptions on Destination Image</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Larry</forename><surname>Lockshin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Travel Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="502" to="511" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Leonidas</forename><surname>Leonidou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bradley</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Talias</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Exporter-Importer Relationship Quality: The Inhibiting Role of Uncertainty, Distance, and Conflict</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="576" to="588" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building Successful Export Business Relationships: A Behavioral Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Constantine</forename><surname>Katsikeas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Hadjimarcou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="115" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drivers and Outcomes of Importer Adaptation in International Buyer-Seller Relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dayananda</forename><surname>Palihawadana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Simos</forename><surname>Chari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Constantinos</forename><surname>Leonidou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of World Business</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="527" to="543" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antecedents and Outcomes of Exporter-Importer Relationship Quality: Synthesis, Meta-Analysis, and Directions for Further Research</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Saeed Samiee, Bilge Aykol, and Michael Talias</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="46" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Power, Contract, and the Economic Model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ian</forename><surname>Macneil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Issues</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="909" to="923" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Contingency Perspective on Psychic Distance in International Channel Relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Magnusson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Brett</forename><surname>Boyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Channels</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Common Method Variance in IS Research: A Comparison of Alternative Approaches and a Reanalysis of Past Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Naresh</forename><surname>Malhotra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sung</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ashutosh</forename><surname>Patil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1865" to="1883" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distance Factors and Target Market Selection: The Moderating Effect of Market Potential</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shavin</forename><surname>Malhotra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sivakumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pengcheng</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Marketing Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="651" to="673" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring a Multi-Dimensional Construct: Country Image</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ingrid</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sevgin</forename><surname>Eroglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Commitment-Trust Theory of Relationship Marketing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Morgan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shelby</forename><surname>Hunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Comparison of Japanese and U.S. Attitudes toward Foreign Products</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Akira</forename><surname>Nagashima</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="68" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Who Took the &quot;×&quot; Out of Expectancy-Value Theory? A Psychological Mystery, a Substantive-Methodological Synergy, and a Cross-National Generalization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Benjamin</forename><surname>Nagengast</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Herbert</forename><surname>Marsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Francesca</forename><surname>Scalas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Man</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kit-Tai</forename><surname>Hau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ulrich</forename><surname>Trautwein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1058" to="1066" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is the Globe Shrinking? Psychic Distance and the Establishment of Swedish Sales Subsidiaries During the Last 100 Years</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kjell</forename><surname>Nordstrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan-Erik</forename><surname>Valhne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International trade: Regional and global issues</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="56" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Psychic Distance Paradox</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shawna</forename><surname>O'grady</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Henry</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lane</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Business Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cross-Border Interfirm Cooperation: The Influence of the Performance Context</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Claude</forename><surname>Obadia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Marketing Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="634" to="650" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consumers&apos; Emotional Bonds with Foreign Countries: Does Consumer Affinity Affect Behavioral Intentions?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eva</forename><surname>Oberecker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Adamantios</forename><surname>Diamantopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synthesizing Country-of-Origin Research from the Last Decade: Is the Concept Still Salient in an Era of Global Brands?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Julie</forename><surname>Pharr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Theory and Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Common Method Biases in Behavioral Research: A Critical Review of the Literature and Recommended Remedies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Philip</forename><surname>Podsakoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Scott</forename><surname>Mackenzie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lee</forename><surname>Jeong-Yeon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nathan</forename><surname>Podsakoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="879" to="903" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advancing the Country Image Construct</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Katharina</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Adamantios</forename><surname>Diamantopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="726" to="740" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Matching Product Category and Country Image Perceptions: A Framework for Managing Country-of-Origin Effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jean</forename><surname>Romeo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Business Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="477" to="497" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b85">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Resolving the Impasse Regarding Research on the Origins of Products and Brands</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Saeed</forename><surname>Samiee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Marketing Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="473" to="485" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b86">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">International Relationship Marketing: Intellectual Foundations and Avenues for Further Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Brian</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Chabowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hult</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b87">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supplier and Customer Exchange in International Industrial Markets: An Integrative Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Walters</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Industrial Marketing Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="589" to="599" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b88">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cultural Distance Revisited: Towards a More Rigorous Conceptualization and Measurement of Cultural Differences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Oded</forename><surname>Shenkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Business Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="519" to="536" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b89">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Market and Supplier Characteristics Driving Distributor Relationship Quality in International Marketing Channels of Industrial Products</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dionysis</forename><surname>Skarmeas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Constantine</forename><surname>Katsikeas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stavroula</forename><surname>Spyropoulou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Esmail</forename><surname>Salehi-Sangari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Industrial Marketing Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b90">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship Value: Drivers and Outcomes in International Marketing Channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dionysis</forename><surname>Skarmeas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Athina</forename><surname>Zeriti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">George</forename><surname>Baltas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>In press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b91">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The PD Scale: A Measure of Psychic Distance and Its Impact on International Marketing Strategy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Carlos</forename><surname>Sousa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Luis Filipe Lages ;</forename><surname>Stottinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Barbara</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bodo</forename><surname>Schlegelmilch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Marketing Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="357" to="372" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">2011. 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>International Marketing Review</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b92">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Psychic Distance: A Concept Past Its Due Date?</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Marketing Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="173" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b93">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Relational Model of Export Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chris</forename><surname>Styles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Patterson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Farid</forename><surname>Ahmed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Business Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="880" to="900" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b94">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Shaping the World Economy: Suggestions for an International Economic Policy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Tinbergen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1962">1962</date>
			<publisher>Twentieth Century Fund</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b95">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Value-Based Differenciation in Business Relationships: Gaining and Sustaining Key Supplier Status</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wolfgang</forename><surname>Ulaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Eggert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b96">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Review and Meta-Analysis of Countryof-Origin Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peeter</forename><surname>Verlegh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan-Benedict</forename><surname>Steenkamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="521" to="546" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b97">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Country of Origin and Destination Effects in Buyer Decision Making: A Relationship Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rui</forename><surname>Vinhas Da Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gary</forename><surname>Manuel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pete</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Naude</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business-to-Business Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b98">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Victor</forename><surname>Vroom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Work and Motivation</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1964">1964</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b99">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Value Creation in Buyer-Seller Relationships: Theoretical Considerations and Empirical Results from a Supplier&apos;s Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Achim</forename><surname>Walter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Ritter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hans</forename><surname>Georg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gemünden</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Industrial Marketing Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="377" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b100">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Buyer&apos;s Perspective on Collaborative Versus Transactional Relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Judith</forename><surname>Whipple</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Lynch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gilbert</forename><surname>Nyaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Industrial Marketing Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="507" to="518" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b101">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Oliver</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Williamson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Markets and Hierarchies</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Free Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b102">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distance without Direction: Restoring Credibility to a Much-Loved Construct</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Srilata</forename><surname>Zaheer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Margaret</forename><forename type="middle">Spring</forename><surname>Schomaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lilach</forename><surname>Nachum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Business Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b103">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Attitudinal Effects of Mere Exposure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Zajonc</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b104">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Home Country Image, Country Brand Equity and Consumers&apos; Product Preferences: An Empirical Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Katharina</forename><surname>Zeugner-Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Adamantios</forename><surname>Petra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ma</forename><surname>Diamantopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Montesinos</forename><surname>Ángeles</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management International Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="577" to="602" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b105">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Manufacturer Governance of Foreign Distributor Relationships: Do Relational Norms Enhance Competitiveness in the Export Market?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chun</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tamer</forename><surname>Cavusgil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anthony</forename><surname>Roath</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Business Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="550" to="566" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
