<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of Factors Affecting Youth Motivation in Madura to Improve Education with the Structural Equation Modeling Method</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">St</forename><surname>Kuzairi</surname></persName>
							<email>kuzairi81@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Mathematics and Natural Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Islamic University of Madura</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Pamekasan 69317</addrLine>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">th Ahmad Department of Law</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Law</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Islamic University of Madura</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Pamekasan 69317</addrLine>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics Airlangga University Surabaya</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">MFF Mardianto</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">th H sakdiyah Departement of Account Faculty of Economic</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Islamic University of Madura</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Pamekasan 69317</addrLine>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Mawaddah Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Mathematics and Natural Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Islamic University of Madura</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Pamekasan 69317</addrLine>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">th Faisol Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Mathematics and Natural Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Islamic University of Madura</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Pamekasan 69317</addrLine>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of Factors Affecting Youth Motivation in Madura to Improve Education with the Structural Equation Modeling Method</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T20:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>teenagers in Madura</term>
					<term>Stuctural Equation Modeling</term>
					<term>influence analysis</term>
					<term>education in Madura</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Madura is an area in Indonesia that is still far behind compared to other regions, especially in the field of education. The education system in Madura is dominated by boarding school where boarding school has become a distinctive culture that is still maintained by the Madura community, especially among adolescents who are deciding the future of a country to receive education, it can be a motivation to improve the education system in Madura. In addition there are many things that are the reason for the Madura community that causes the education system in Madura is unstable so it needs to be further analyzed factors that influence the motivation of adolescents to improve education. For this purpose, collected through a survey of adolescents in Madura who became the sample. The survey was conducted online related to the reasons for the interruption of adolescent education in Madura including motivation, environment and poverty data obtained and then processed using Structural Equation Modeling. The method has the advantage of being able to analyze latent variables or variables that cannot be measured such as motivation. Based on the results of the study, it can be seen that the factors that influence motivation to improve education are motivation and poverty. Environmental factors do not affect the improvement of adolescent education in Madura.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>The Indonesian nation as a nation which in its position is still said to be a developing country is looking for forms of how and how to become a developed country, especially in the field of education, because Education is very influential on the progress of a region. education is able to produce good quality Human Resources (HR) in terms of spiritual, intelligence, and skill. Improving the quality of Human Resources through education can reduce poverty because with education can increase employment opportunities, reduce income inequality and welfare and productivity of the poor <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[9]</ref>.</p><p>Education is indeed not an area of life that is separate from other fields of life. Education is often seen as an influential factor of the problems that occur in a strategic environment so that education often receives bad consequences from these changes <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[7]</ref>. Education policy that will be determined must at least be able to anticipate various challenges and problems that occur in a strategic environment, even education must be able to make itself as a factor that can move or direct changes in the environment. therefore it is necessary to have an assessment of several factors that need to be addressed to make Human Resources (HR) in Madura able to be motivated to continue to improve education <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[10]</ref>.</p><p>This study was conducted to determine whether there is a relationship between motivation variables with several factors, namely environmental conditions, education, and poverty found in Madura <ref type="bibr">[1]</ref>. The hypothesis in this study is there a positive relationship between environmental conditions, education, and poverty on the motivation of adolescents in Madura to improve education using the Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) method <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[4]</ref>. SEM is a statistical method that allows testing a series of relatively structured relationships simultaneously. The structural relationship can be built from one or several variables with one or several independent variables. Each dependent and independent variable can be in the form of factors or constructs that are built from several indicators <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[11]</ref>. SEM is widely used in a study because SEM has many advantages including, SEM allows for more flexible assumptions to facilitate users to read the results of the analysis, the possibility of testing the model as a whole rather than the coefficients individually and so on. In addition there are several programs offered by SEM in analyzing factors, one of which is the AMOS program, where the AMOS program can facilitate researchers in SEM completion <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[6]</ref>.</p><p>Based on previous research that is relevant in the use of the Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) method. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[5]</ref> who explained about the application of Structural Equation Modeling on the influence of motivation and trust factors on construction project managers with the conclusion that the model is acceptable, which means there is a match between the model and the data. Motivation and trust have a positive effect on commitment. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[8]</ref> also explained about Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) on the calculation of the customer satisfaction index with the conclusion of data analysis techniques using Structural Equation Modeling (SEM), conducted to explain thoroughly the relationship between variables in the study. SEM is used not to design a theory, but rather is intended to examine and justify a model.</p><p>Based on the above research, no one has examined the Structural Eqution Modeling (SEM) method to analyze the factors that influence the motivation of adolescents in Madura to improve education with endogenous variables of motivation and three exogenous variables in the form of environmental conditions, education, and poverty. Analysis by SEM method aims to determine whether there is an influence of exogenous variables on endogenous variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[4]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. MATERIALS AND METHOD</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Education System in Indonesia</head><p>Education is the main thing that will sustain the progress of a nation. The progress of a nation is measured by the quality and existing education system. Without education, a country will be far behind other countries. The quality of education in Indonesia today is very alarming, especially in Madura, Madura has long been considered a poem as a disadvantaged area, both on a national and regional scale (provincial level). According to the reading indexality of education, the sign of backwardness is so striking, compared to the three regions (Surabaya, Gresik, and Sidoarjo) that are geographically close to the western end of the island <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[9]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Factors Affecting Motivation</head><p>Learning motivation is an impulse or driving force from within an individual that gives direction and enthusiasm to learning activities, so as to achieve the desired goals. In a motivation that does not escape from several influencing factors such as the environment, education and poverty, it is a factor that can be a motivation to keep trying to improve an education. Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) is known by several other names, such as Covariance Structural Analysis (CSA), latent variable analysis and confirmatory factor analysis. The Structural Equation Modeling equation model, hereinafter abbreviated (SEM), is a statistical method that is currently very popular in management research because of its superiority <ref type="bibr">[2]</ref>. Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) is a multivariate statistical technique which is a combination of factor analysis and regression analysis that aims to examine the relationships between variables that exist in a model, be it between indicators with the construct, or relationships between constructs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1) Data and Procedures</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Collection</head><p>The data used in this study are primary data obtained through surveys conducted online using google forms specifically for people in Madura.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hipotesis and Variables hypothesis of this research is:</head><p>H0 : There is no impact from the manifest variables to the latent variables H1 : There is impact from the manifest variables to the latent variables</p><p>The variables used in this study are the factors that influence adolescents in Madura to improve education consisting of dependent variables (endogenous variables) and independent variables (exogenous variables). The dependent factor is motivation which consists of several indicators namely ideals, interests, sincerity, hard work, and not despair. While the exogenous variables in this study are environmental factors, education and poverty which have their respective indicators.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2) Analysis and Procedures</head><p>The steps undertaken for this analysis are given as follows:</p><p> Determine the hypothesis to be tested  Defining latent variables, manifest variables and relationships between variables  Make a path diagram of variables that have been defined </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Descriptive statistics</head><p>This study uses primary data by distributing online questionnaires about factors that influence the motivation of adolescents in Madura to improve education and from the questionnaire obtained 130 respondents from various districts in Madura. General description of the data is displayed in a pie chart and about the number of responses from each district in Madura below: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Analysis of Factors Affecting Youth Motivation in Madura to Improve Education with the SEM method 1) Multivariate detection outlier</head><p>In Appendix 1, it can be seen that the maximum d-squard mahalanobis of 40,962 is smaller than the χ ^ 2 table value of 41,638 so it can be concluded that there is no multivariate outlier.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">Multivariate Normality Test</head><p>Hypothesis: H0: Data is normally distributed H1: Data is not normally distributed The critical area of this test is rejecting H0 if the Multivariate CR (Critical Ratio) value is in the range of -2.58 or +2.58. In Appendix 2, we can know that the Multivariate value of 2.548 is smaller than 2.58 so that it can be concluded that the data is normally distributed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.3.">Reliability Test</head><p>The reliability test received was ≥0.60.</p><p>The following are the results of the reliability test using AMOS 22 on latent variables. Based on the analysis results, it can be concluded that all latent variables have good model reliability because CR.CR 0.60 so that it means that the manifest variable can really explain each latent variable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2) Correlation Analysis</head><p>Following are the results of correlation analysis using AMOS 22 From the results of the analysis, it is known that there is a positive correlation between poverty and motivation, motivation and education. This can be interpreted that poverty and motivation affect the improvement of education.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3) Model Conformity Test</head><p>The results obtained from the AMOS 22 output are as follows: Based on the results of testing using AMOS, it can be seen that the evaluation of the whole model is good, meaning that the conceptual model developed and based on the theory has been supported by facts (empirical data).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. CONCLUSION</head><p>Based on the results of a survey of 3 factors that influence adolescent motivation to improve education, namely motivation, poverty and the environment along with its indicators, it was widely agreed by adolescents in Madura that the statement could be a factor influencing adolescent motivation in Madura to improve education. The results of the analysis of factors that influence the motivation of adolescents in Madura to improve education with the structural Equation Modeling method can be assessed from various aspects. Based on the correlation results it is known that there is an effect of poverty on motivation and motivation on improving education. While for the environment after being tested the significance was not significant so it needed to be modified and the results stated that there was no environmental effect on improving education.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>REFERENCES</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1 SEM Path Diagram 1. Detect the existence of Multivariate Outliers and Multivariate Normality 2. Perform validity tests with SPSS 20 and reliability tests with AMOS 22 on the data that has been collected 3. Estimating the loading factor (λ) for each manifest variable against the associated latent variable 4. Test the significance of each loading factor (λ) 5. Conduct correlation analysis between latent variables to calculate gamma (γ) 6. To test the suitability of the model with the criteria of CMIN / DF, RMSEA, GFI, AGFI, TLI, PNFI 7. Interpreting the output The mean of geometric form from figuren1 is given as follows : = latent variables</figDesc><graphic coords="2,313.20,315.36,230.28,211.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2 Pie Chart of Respondent Data from Four districts in Madura From Figure 2 it can be seen that respondents are representatives of four districts in Madura. With 54 Sampang details, Pamekasan 40 respondents, Sumenep 20 respondents, and Bangkalan 15 respondents are displayed in the form of percent (%).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">RESULTS OF RELIABILITY TESTS WITH AMOS 22</cell></row><row><cell>latent variable</cell><cell>C.R</cell><cell>Information</cell></row><row><cell>Education</cell><cell>0,807</cell><cell>well</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 2 CORRELATION</head><label>2</label><figDesc>ANALYSIS RESULTS WITH AMOS 22</figDesc><table><row><cell>Estimate</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>TABLE 5 MODEL</head><label>5</label><figDesc>CONFORMITY TEST RESULTS WITH AMOS 22</figDesc><table><row><cell>Criteria</cell><cell>AMOS</cell><cell>Cut Of</cell><cell>Model Evaluation</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>results</cell><cell>Value</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>40,962</cell><cell>41,638</cell><cell>Well</cell></row><row><cell>Probability</cell><cell>0,7</cell><cell>0,05</cell><cell>Well</cell></row><row><cell>RMSEA</cell><cell>0,01</cell><cell>0,08</cell><cell>Well</cell></row><row><cell>GFI</cell><cell>0,908</cell><cell>0,90</cell><cell>Well</cell></row><row><cell>AGFI</cell><cell>0,925</cell><cell>0,90</cell><cell>Well</cell></row><row><cell>TLI</cell><cell>1,384</cell><cell>0,95</cell><cell>Well</cell></row><row><cell>CFI</cell><cell>1,445</cell><cell>0,95</cell><cell>Well</cell></row><row><cell>CMIN/DF</cell><cell>1,445</cell><cell>2,00</cell><cell>Well</cell></row><row><cell>PNFI</cell><cell>0,930</cell><cell>0,90</cell><cell>Well</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>[1] Anekawati A, Otok B W. (2017). Structural Equation Modelling with Three Schemes Estimation of Score Factors on Partial Least Square (Case Study: The Quality of Education Level SMA/MA in Sumenep Regency. IOP Conference Series, Journal of Physics, 855 012006.</figDesc><table /><note><p><p>[2] Banerjee, A., &amp; Chaudhury, S. (2010). Statistics without tears:</p>Populations and samples. Industrial Psychiatry Journal, 19(1), 60.</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Blunch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Introduction to structural equation modeling using IBM SPSS statistics and AMOS</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bollen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Structural equations with latent variables</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">210</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The influence of motivation and trust factors on performance through commitment to the Construction Project Manager with the Structural Equation Modeling approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wibowo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Civil Engineering Communication Media</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Structural equation modeling with AMOS: basic concepts, applications, and programming (multivariate applications series)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Byrne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2010. 2009. 2009. 2009</date>
			<publisher>Gazetted Republic Indonesia</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">396</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>New York; Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Poverty and Effects on Motivation and Achievement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Basri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">80</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Nawangsari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Structural Equation Modeling on the calculation of the customer satisfaction index using the AMOS software</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Yogyakarta</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">62</biblScope>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Yogyakarta State University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sistem pendidikan di indonesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Munirah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Auladuna</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">234</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Jurnal Ilmiyah. Rendahnya Kualitas Pendidikan di Indonesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Kulsum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Applied Multivariate Statistic for the Social Science</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Steven</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<publisher>Laurence Erlbaum Assosiates</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
