<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">On Pinpoint Capture Power Management in At-Speed Scan Test Generation</title>
				<funder ref="#_GNKxXnH">
					<orgName type="full">JST-NSC</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_e8d9amb #_7KNjCJu">
					<orgName type="full">JSPS</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Kyushu Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>820-8502</postCode>
									<settlement>Iizuka</settlement>
									<region>Fukuoka</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Nishida</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Kyushu Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>820-8502</postCode>
									<settlement>Iizuka</settlement>
									<region>Fukuoka</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Miyase</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Kyushu Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>820-8502</postCode>
									<settlement>Iizuka</settlement>
									<region>Fukuoka</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kajihara</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Kyushu Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>820-8502</postCode>
									<settlement>Iizuka</settlement>
									<region>Fukuoka</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Girard</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIRMM</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>161 rue Ada</addrLine>
									<postCode>34095</postCode>
									<settlement>Montpellier</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tehranipoor</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Connecticut</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>06296</postCode>
									<settlement>Storrs</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">L.-T</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">SynTest Technologies, Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94086</postCode>
									<settlement>Sunnyvale</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">On Pinpoint Capture Power Management in At-Speed Scan Test Generation</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T00:55+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper proposes a novel scheme to manage capture power in a pinpoint manner for achieving guaranteed capture power safety, improved small-delay test capability, and minimal test cost impact in at-speed scan test generation. First, switching activity around each long path sensitized by a test vector is checked to characterize it as hot (with excessively-high switching activity), warm (with normal/functional switching activity), or cold (with excessively-low switching activity). Then, X-restoration/Xfilling-based rescue is conducted on the test vector to reduce switching activity around hot paths. If the rescue is insufficient to turn a hot path into a warm path, mask is then conducted on expected test response data to instruct the tester to ignore the potentially-false test response value from the hot path, thus achieving guaranteed capture power safety. Finally, X-restoration/X-filling-based warmup is conducted on the test vector to increase switching activity around cold paths for improving their small-delay test capability. This novel approach of pinpoint capture power management has significant advantages over the conventional approach of global capture power management, as demonstrated by evaluation results on large ITC'99 benchmark circuits and detailed path delay analysis.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Delay testing is indispensable for achieving high product quality for deep-submicron (DSM) circuits that are susceptible to timing-related physical defects. Delay test vectors can be generated by using the transition delay or path delay fault model or both <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. There are two issues that are of special importance to delay test vectors.</p><p>The first issue with a delay test set is test quality, which is determined by its capability to expose the existence of delay defects of various sizes. It has been shown that small-delay defects are becoming dominant in DSM chips <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>; thus, the capability of detecting small-delay defects should be improved in order to achieve high timing-related test quality. For this purpose, special care can be taken to sensitize long paths for fault detection in transition delay test generation <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, and/or long paths can be explicitly selected and targeted in path delay test generation <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p><p>The second issue with a delay test set is test power. This is especially true when delay testing is conducted through at-speed scan testing with the launch-on-capture (LOC) clocking scheme as illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. At-speed scan test power includes shift power and capture power <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</p><p>Shift power is caused by shift switching activity in the whole circuit due to the consecutive application of shift clock pulses. Its impact is therefore accumulative, which mostly manifests itself as excessive heat. Effective techniques <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref> are available for effectively reducing shift power through manipulating shift clocking, circuit design, test vector generation, etc.</p><p>Capture power is caused by the launch switching activity (LSA) triggered by the stimulus launch clock pulse T 1 . This leads to IR-drop in the power distribution network (PDN), resulting in delay increase on sensitized paths <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. This IR-drop-induced extra delay can have negative impact and positive impact on the timing of sensitized paths.  Negative Impact: When the IR-drop-induced delay increase is larger than the allowable slack of a sensitized path, a false timing failure will occur at T 2 at the endpoint of the sensitized path even when the circuit is fault-free. This results in over-test and thus undue yield loss, which has become a severe challenge in the industry <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.  Positive Impact: When the IR-drop-induced delay increase is less than the allowable slack of a sensitized path, delay defects of smaller sizes on the path will become more likely to be detected because of the extra delay along the path. This results in enhanced test quality in terms of better small-delay test capability <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</p><p>Conventionally, global capture power management has been widely used in practice, which is for adjusting the whole-circuit capture power that is quantified by a single metric, such as weighted switching activity (WSA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Previous techniques based on this approach mitigate the negative impact of capture power by reducing LSA at T 1 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>. However, the reduction effect is often questionable with respect to capture power safety <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, and its impact on test costs is high <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. Furthermore, the positive impact of capture power has been largely ignored since the global approach is not suitable for adjusting the delay of a particular path. These problems all call for a new approach to capture power management. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Shift Power</head><p>Heat Impact</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Problems of Global Capture Power Management</head><p>The conventional approach of global capture power management tries to control the whole-circuit capture power by adjusting the number of simultaneouslycapturing scan flip-flops (FFs) at T 1 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). This can be achieved by circuit / clock modification or test data manipulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>. However, circuit / clock modification, when applied in capture mode, tends to entail significant changes to automatic test pattern generation (ATPG) algorithms, fault coverage loss, as well as test data inflation. Therefore, test data manipulation is generally considered preferable for capture power management <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>.</p><p>The capture power of a test vector can be manipulated during test generation (in-ATPG) or after test generation (post-ATPG). The former can be realized by disabling clock gators to reduce the number of simultaneouslycapturing scan FFs by low-capture-power ATPG <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>. The latter can be realized by first conducting test relaxation <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> to turn fully-specified test vectors into partiallyspecified test cubes and then applying low-capture-power X-filling <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> to equalize FF input/output values as much as possible to reduce capture transitions at FFs.</p><p>Although many techniques for global capture power management (mostly reduction) have been proposed, they generally suffer from the following serious problems:</p><p> Problem 1 (Unfocused Capture Power Reduction): Most of the previous techniques only reduce capture power in a global or unfocused manner. This is a severe problem since capture power is not evenly distributed across the whole chip. Global or unfocused reduction may end up with reducing the capture power in an area already with low capture power but leaving the capture power in an area with excessively-high capture power intact. As a result, the negative impact of capture power cannot be effectively mitigated by global capture power reduction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Problem 2 (No Guarantee of Capture Power Safety):</head><p>Although previous techniques can reduce capture power to some extent, most of them cannot guarantee that they can always sufficiently reduce capture power below a safe limit <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>. This is a major problem since capture power safety, rather than capture power reduction, is the ultimate goal in mitigating the negative impact of capture power.  Problem 3 (Test Vector Count Inflation): The global/ unfocused approach often results in unnecessary reduction for test vectors or chip regions that need no capture power reduction. This is the cause of severe low-power-testgeneration-induced inflation in test vector count <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref>.  Problem 4 (Compromised Test Quality): Most of the previous techniques only try to mitigate the negative impact of capture power by unconditionally reducing capture power. They ignore the positive impact of capture power, thus missing the chances of improving small-delay test capability. In addition, global capture power reduction also tends to over-reduce the capture power in some regions, which also leads to compromised test quality.</p><p>All the aforementioned problems are essentially caused by the obvious fact that, conducting capture power management in a global manner is fundamentally against the local nature of capture power.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Needs for Pinpoint Capture Power Management</head><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref> illustrates why the impact of capture power is local in nature and largely depends on the sensitization status and lengths of paths, as the motivation of this work. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref> shows three possible scenarios when the test stimulus is launched at T 1 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>), based on whether and what type of capture power impact will occur to a path due to IR-drop-induced delay increase. First, if a path is not sensitized or sensitized but very short, then no matter how much switching activity occurs around it, neither the negative impact nor a significant level of the positive impact of capture power will occur to the path. Such a path is a dead path, and there is no need to manage (reduce or increase) its neighboring switching activity. Second, if a long path is sensitized and its neighboring switching activity is excessively high, there is a risk that IR-dropinduced delay increase along the path may cause a false timing failure at the endpoint of the path. Such a path is a hot path, and clearly it is imperative to eliminate all hot paths for a test vector so as to guarantee capture power safety <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Third, if a long path is sensitized but its neighboring switching activity is considerably low (i.e., significantly below the functional level), there is a possibility to benefit from the positive impact of capture power. Such a path is a cold path, which can be warmed-up by properly increasing its neighboring switching activity so as to improve its small-delay test capability <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref> clearly demonstrates the needs for pinpoint capture power management, whose focused nature completely matches the local nature of capture power. Based on this new approach, the goal of this work is to establish a novel and practical at-speed scan test generation scheme with the following unique advantages:</p><p>( </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Background</head><p>This section first reviews sensitized-path-based capture power analysis, which is indispensable for pinpoint capture power management. A brief review then follows about previous work related to guaranteeing capture power safety and improving small-delay test capability, which helps highlight the novelty of this work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Sensitized-Path-Based Capture Power Analysis</head><p>The impact of capture power for a test vector mostly manifests itself as delay increase along paths sensitized by the test vector <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>. However, it is prohibitively costly to obtain the accurate IR-drop-induced delay increase of a sensitized path in test generation since it requires timingaccurate logic simulation, IR-drop analysis, and delay calculation. A realistic alternative for test generation is to measure logical switching activity in the neighbourhood of a path by normal logic simulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>. The neighbourhood, also referred to as impact area, is defined below <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Definition 1:</formula><p>The aggressor region of a gate G, denoted by AR(G), is composed of aggressor nodes (gates and FFs) whose transitions strongly impact the supply voltage of G.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definition 2:</head><p>The impact area of a path P, denoted by IA(P), consists of the aggressor regions of all of its on-path</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">gates (G 1 , G 2 , . . ., G n ). That is, IA(P) =   n i i G AR 1 ) ( .</formula><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref> illustrates the impact area of a path P. Note that the aggressor region of a gate G can be readily obtained by finding nodes that share the power vias from which G draws most of its current <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>. Such power vias and their related or influenced nodes can be directly identified by using circuit/PDN layout data. Once the impact area of a long sensitized path is obtained, the switching activity level in this area can be estimated with a metric based on the results of logic simulation. For example, the WSA metric <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, calculated as a weighted toggle count for all nodes in the impact area, can be used for this purpose. One can also use more sophisticated metrics <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>, which can provide a more accurate estimation of IR-drop-induced delay increase but usually at a higher computational cost.</p><p>This work uses sensitized-path-based capture power analysis in pinpoint capture power management for guiding its decisions and assessing its effect. The details will be presented in Subsection 3.1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Related Work</head><p>Some representative previous techniques related to pinpoint capture power management are reviewed below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1">Guaranteeing Capture Power Safety</head><p>There is no doubt that capture power safety is more important than capture power reduction. Capture power reduction techniques with capture safety checking <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref> or based on pseudo-functional testing <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> are helpful for this purpose. Recently, we proposed a rescue-and-mask based test generation scheme <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref> for explicitly guaranteeing capture power safety with minimal test data inflation, through the following four steps:</p><p> Step-1 (Initial Test Vector Generation): Conventional test generation is conducted to deterministically generate a test cube C 1 for detecting targeted faults and randomly-fill C 1 into a test vector V 1 for fortuitous detection. Randomlyfilled bits in V 1 are called X-filled logic bits. No capture power reduction is considered in this step.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><p>Step-2 (Capture Safety Checking): Sensitized-pathbased capture power analysis is conducted on V 1 . If there is at least one risky path (i.e., a long sensitized path with excessively-high switching activity in its impact area), go to Step-3; otherwise, V 1 is capture-power-safe and final.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Step-3 (Rescue):</head><p>The rescue operation is conducted by first restoring into X-bits those X-filled logic bits in V 1 that can reach the impact areas of risky paths, resulting in a new test cube C 2 . Then, low-capture-power X-filling <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref> is conducted on C 2 to reduce switching activity in the impact areas of the risky paths, resulting in a modified test vector V 2 . If all risky paths become safe, V 2 is capturepower-safe and final; otherwise, go to Step-4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Step-4 (Mask):</head><p>The mask operation is conducted on V 2 by assigning a special symbol (X for most testers) to the expected test response bit corresponding to the output of each remaining risky path. X instructs the tester not to compare test responses at this output bit so as to avoid the impact of the risky path, thus guaranteeing capture power safety. Note that the masking is only effective for the current test vector. That is, the masked output bit is available for fault detection for other test vectors. In addition, fault coverage loss due to the masking of the current test vector can be fully recovered by other test vectors generated in subsequent ATPG runs.</p><p>Although the above rescue-and-mask scheme <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> can achieve guaranteed capture power safety with minimal test vector count inflation (less than 0.1% for large ITC'99 benchmark circuits as reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>), it only tries to mitigate the negative impact of capture power by reducing switching activity and ignores the positive impact of capture power. In addition, it runs the risk of over-reducing the switching activity in the impact area of a risky path, resulting in compromised small-delay test capability. These problems will be addressed in this paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2">Improving Small-Delay Test Capability</head><p>Previous techniques exist for maximizing IR-drop on critical paths by increasing switching activity around onpath nodes <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. Although being intended for estimating worst-case delay for critical paths, they demonstrate the possibility of making use of the positive impact of capture power for improving small-delay test capability in at-speed scan testing. This possibility will be fully exploited by the new test generation scheme in this work. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Basic Idea</head><p>This section presents the basic idea of this work. First, it shows how to classify paths sensitized by a test vector. Then, based on the results of path classification, a strategy for pinpoint capture power management is established.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Path Classification</head><p>Because the impact of capture power manifests itself as timing failures due to IR-drop-induced delay increase, it can only show up at the endpoints of sensitized paths. Especially, the length of a sensitized path and the switching activity in its impact area determine the characteristic of the path with respect to the impact of capture power. Such characteristics can be revealed through path classification. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> lists the definitions of variables needed for this purpose. The theoretical criteria for path classification are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>(a). First, E 1 (P) is used to determine if a sensitized path P is long or short. For a long path P, E 2 (P) and E 3 (P) are further used to determine if P is hot, warm, or cold. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Criterion 1: E 1 (P) = D n (P) + D d + D i (S max (P))</head><p>E 1 (P) indicates whether the switching activity in the impact area of a sensitized path P can possibly affect the delay fault detection capability of P. E 1 (P) &gt; T means that increasing switching activity in the impact area of P may help in detecting delay faults by P. Such a path is a long path. On the other hand, E 1 (P)  T means that increasing switching activity in the impact area of P cannot help in detecting delay faults by P. Such a path is a short path. It is clear that pinpoint capture power management only needs to be conducted for long sensitized paths. Definition 3: A sensitized path P for a test vector V is long</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">(short) if E 1 (P) = D n (P) + D d + D i (S max (P)) &gt; T ( T).</formula><p> Criterion 2: E 2 (P) = D n (P) + D i (S(P)) E 2 (P) indicates whether the current switching activity under the test vector V in the impact area of a long, sensitized, but defect-free path P, namely S(P), causes an excessivelylarge delay increase on P. E 2 (P) &gt; T means that a false timing failure may occur at the endpoint of P, causing a good chip to fail only in test mode. Such a path is a risky (hot) path. E 2 (P)  T means that the impact of the current switching activity is insufficient to invalidate the test response at the endpoint of P. Such a path is a safe path. Definition 4: A long sensitized path P for a test vector V is risky (safe) if E 2 (P) = D n (P) + D i (S(P)) &gt; T ( T). A risky path is also referred to as a hot path.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Criterion 3: E 3 (P) = D n (P) + D d + D i (S(P))</head><p>E 3 (P) shows whether the current switching activity under the test vector V in the impact area of a safe path P, namely S(P), causes sufficient delay increase to help in detecting a delay defect of the typical size on P. E 3 (P) &gt; T means that the current switching activity induces sufficient delay increase to detect a typical delay defect on P. Such a safe path is a warm path. E 3 (P)  T means that the delay increase caused by the current switching activity is insufficient to help in detecting a typical delay defect on P. Such a safe path is a cold path. Definition 5: A safe path P for a test vector V is warm</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">(cold) if E 3 (P) = D n (P) + D d + D i (S(P)) &gt; T ( T).</formula><p>It is clear that the theoretical criteria of Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4(a)</ref> classify paths sensitized by a test vector from three perspectives: (1) path length, (2) switching activity in the impact area of a path in a defect-free case, and (3) switching activity in the impact area of a path in a defective case. Theoretical path classification can be conducted as follows:  Step-1 (Long / Short): Long paths are identified by E 1 as those sensitized paths on which capture power may help improve their capability for detecting delay defects.  Step-2 (Risky / Safe): Long sensitized paths are further classified into risky (hot) paths and safe paths by E 2 , based on whether the current switching activity in the impact area of a long sensitized path may cause a false timing failure at its endpoint even when the path is defect-free.  Step-3 (Cold / Warm): Safe paths are further classified into warm paths and cold paths by E 3 , based on whether the current switching activity in the impact area of a safe path may cause sufficient IR-drop-induced delay increase to help in detecting delay defects along the path. The theoretical criteria shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>(a) for path classification are accurate but time-consuming for large circuits. In order to classify paths efficiently in an actual ATPG flow, practical criteria shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>(b) can be applied by using easy-to-compute parameters. Practical path classification can thus be conducted as follows:  Step-1 (Long / Short): Each sensitized path P is checked by the criterion F 1 to see whether P is longer than a preset percentage () of the longest structural path. If so, P is a long path; otherwise, P is a short path.  Step-2 (Risky / Safe): Each long sensitized path P is further checked by the criterion F 2 to see whether WSA(P) (the current WSA-measured switching activity in the impact area of P) is higher than a preset percentage () of WSA max (P) (the maximum WSA in the impact area of P). If so, P is a risky (hot) path; otherwise, P is a safe path.  Step-3 ((Cold / Warm): Each safe path P is further checked by the criterion F 3 to see whether WSA(P) (the current WSA-measured switching activity in the impact area of P) is lower than a preset percentage () of WSA max (P) (the maximum WSA in the impact area of P). If so, P is a cold path; otherwise, P is a warm path.</p><p>Practical criteria F 1 ~ F 3 are easy to implement in any ATPG system and less costly to apply. More details about choosing , , and  will be provided in Section 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Strategy for Pinpoint Capture Power Management</head><p>Based on the result of path classification for a test vector V, a strategy for applying pinpoint capture power management on V can be established as follows:</p><p> Eliminating Hot Paths: The impact of any hot path P should be avoided. This is achieved with a similar approach used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> by first reducing the switching activity in the impact area of P. If the reduction effect is insufficient to turn P into a safe (preferably warm) path, the expected test response bit for V at the endpoint of P is masked to instruct the tester to ignore the actual test response for V from P so as to avoid the possible negative impact of P.  Warming-Up Cold Paths: The switching activity in the impact area of a cold path P can be increased in an attempt to turn P into a warm path in order to improve its smalldelay test capability. Even if P eventually remains as a cold path, increased switching activity in its impact area still helps improve its general delay test capability.  Maintaining Warm Paths: A warm path P has a right level of switching activity in its impact area. That switching activity will not cause any false timing failure when P is defect-free but will help fault detection when P has a delay defect of a typical size. Therefore, when dealing with hot or cold paths by pinpoint capture power management, special care should be taken so as not to change the status of any warm path in order to avoid compromising its small-delay test capability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Proposed Test Generation Scheme</head><p>This section presents the proposed test generation scheme based on pinpoint capture power management. First, the general test generation scheme is outlined. After that, individual techniques are described in detail.  In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>, conventional test generation (A~E) starts from initial fault list generation (A). Each test generation run begins with an all-X input vector, and logic values are gradually assigned to them. First, a partially-specified test cube C 1 is deterministically generated to detect a primary fault and dynamic compaction is optionally conducted to </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">General Scheme</head><formula xml:id="formula_4">Test Vector  V Test Cube  C3 Test Vector  V</formula><p>detect secondary faults (B). Note that these primary and secondary faults are explicitly targeted faults in test generation. Since C 1 usually still contains X-bits even after aggressive dynamic test compaction, detection-oriented Xfilling needs to be conducted to turn C 1 into a fullyspecified test vector V (C). Random-fill is widely used for this purpose since its high fortuitous detection capability improves unmodeled-defect detection (thus higher test quality) and reduces test data volume (thus lower test cost). After that, fault simulation is conducted for V to update the fault list (D), and the termination condition is checked to decide whether to continue test generation (E).</p><p>It is clear that the initial test vector V, obtained by conventional test generation (A~E), consists of two types of logic bits, as defined below: Definition 6: A logic bit in a test vector is a deterministic logic bit if it is deterministically generated for detecting explicitly targeted faults (i.e., primary and secondary faults) in conventional test generation. Definition 7: A logic bit in a test vector is an X-filled logic bit if it is obtained by X-filling an X-bit in a partiallyspecified test cube without explicitly targeting any fault.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">6</ref> illustrates the two types of logic bits in a test vector. It is clear that deterministic logic bits are responsible for intentionally detecting explicitly targeted faults, while X-filled logic bits are responsible for unintentionally-achieved fortuitous detection. This classification of paths is important for X-restoration to be described in Subsections 4.2.1 and 4.3.1. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Phase-I: Hot Path Elimination</head><p>A test vector with even one hot path is risky for at-speed scan testing. To eliminate all hot paths in Phase-I, we have significantly improved a technique based on rescue-andmask <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> so that it can not only achieve capture power safety by eliminating all hot paths but also avoid test quality degradation by maintaining warm paths. Phase-I consists of three steps ( ~  in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>) as follows:</p><p> Step- (X-Restoration for Hot Paths) to obtain X-bits that can only affect the impact areas of hot paths.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Step- (X-Filling for Reducing Capture Power) to determine proper logic values for the X-bits obtained by</head><p>Step- so as to reduce capture power around hot paths.  Step- (Remaining Hot Path Masking) to instruct the tester not to use the possibly-false test response bit that corresponds to the endpoint of any remaining hot path.</p><p>Step- and Step- are for rescuing hot paths by trying to turn them into warm paths. On the other hand, Step- is for avoiding the impact of any remaining hot path if the rescue effort fails. By first rescuing and then masking, Phase-I can effectively guarantee capture power safety without causing severe test data inflation. This is because the more test response bits are masked, the more new test vectors usually need to be generated. Therefore, it is preferable to apply masking after rescuing is tried.</p><p>The details of the three steps in Phase-I are as follows. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> for obtaining a partially-specified test cube with X-bits directly from a fully-specified test vector. Its basic idea is to keep all deterministic logic bits in a fully-specified test vector intact and only change some X-filled logic bits back into X-bits for a specific purpose, e.g., hot path elimination in this work. Note that, different from X-relaxation / Xidentification <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, X-restoration adds no additional computational costs since it only utilizes the results of logic bit classification, which are naturally available in any conventional test generation flow.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.1">X-Restoration for Hot Paths X-restoration is a fast and efficient technique</head><p>In X-restoration for hot paths ( in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>), bits that are changed to X-bits are X-filled logic bits that can only affect hot paths by reaching the impact areas of hot paths but not warm paths. This guarantees that X-filling for the resulting test cubes only reduces the switching activity around hot paths (for contributing to capture power safety) while maintaining all warm paths (for keeping test quality).</p><p>X-restoration for hot paths is conducted as follows: (1) The set of X-bit positions for all hot paths of a test vector V, denoted by S X-bit-for-hot-paths (V), is obtained by</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">S X-bit-for-hot-paths (V) = S X-filled-logic-bits (V)  S reach-hot-paths (V)  ) (V S paths warm reach  </formula><p>where S X-filled-logic-bits (V) is the set of all X-filled logic bit positions in V, S reach-hot-paths (V) is the set of all bit positions in V that can reach nodes (including both FFs and gates) in the impact areas of hot paths of V, and S reach-warm-paths (V) is the set of all bit positions in V that can reach nodes in the impact areas of warm paths of V.</p><p>(2) Turning the bits in S X-bit-for-hot-paths (V) into X-bits results in a partially-specified test cube C 2 at  in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>.</p><p>An example of X-restoration for hot paths is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>, where V = &lt;0101101000111&gt; and S X-filled-logic-bits (V) = &lt;b, c, d, e, f, h, j, k, m&gt;. If V has two hot paths P 1 and P 3 and one warm path P 2 , S reach-hot-paths (V) = &lt;a, b, c, d, e, j, k, l, m&gt; and S reach-warm-paths (V) = &lt;e, f, g, h, i, j&gt;. As a result, S X-bit-for-hot-paths (V) = &lt;b, c, d, k, m&gt;. The resulting partiallyspecified test cube C 2 is thus &lt;0XXX101000X1X&gt;.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Deterministic</head><p>Generation Random X-Filling</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">0 1 0 1 1 0 1 0 0 0 X X X X X 1 X 0 C1 V</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Deterministic Logic Bits X-Filled Logic Bits</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C B</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>X-Filling</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Fig. 7. Example of X-restoration for hot paths.</head><p>Different from the previous X-restoration technique <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, the improved technique for X-restoration for hot paths is more sophisticated in that it avoids any impact on warm paths, thus maintaining warm-path-related test quality.</p><p>Note that X-restoration (for hot paths as described in this subsection and for cold paths to be described in Subsection 4.3.1) does not affect the basic fault detection capability of a test vector achieved by its deterministic logic bits. X-restoration may only affect the fortuitous detection achieved by X-filled logic bits since it only changes some X-filled logic bits back into X-bits. As illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>, fault coverage loss due to Xrestoration, if any, will be fully recovered by new test vectors generated in subsequent ATPG runs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.2">X-Filling for Reducing Capture Power</head><p>As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>, after a test cube C 2 is obtained from a test vector V by X-restoration for hot paths (), X-filling for reducing capture power () is conducted on C 2 . Since the X-bits in C 2 only affect the impact areas of hot paths without affecting warm paths, the X-filling is pinpoint in that it only reduces switching activity around hot paths in an attempt to turn them into warm paths, without the risk of increasing switching activity around warm paths that may turn some of them into hot paths. Note that this pinpoint nature exists even when hot paths and warm paths or their impact areas overlap, as illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>.</p><p>There are two basic approaches to reducing capture power by X-filling: FF clock disabling and FF input-output equalizing, as illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">8</ref>. Here, the clock gator signal CG controls two FFs (FF c and FF d ), and disabling the clock gator CG by X-filling will reduce two possible capture transitions from FF c and FF d . On the other hand, although the capture clock pulse cannot be stopped for FF b , no capture transition will occur at FF b if X-filling makes the same logic value to appear on its input and output. A hybrid procedure is used for X-filling for reducing capture power at  in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref> to turn a test cube C 2 to a test vector V. First, FF clock disabling is applied since it is effective even in test compression <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>. After that, FF input-output equalizing is applied by using a fast and highly scalable X-filling technique based on Preferred-fill <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. The details of the procedure are as follows:</p><p>Procedure-A X-Filling for Reducing Capture Power; Input: C2 (a partially-specified test cube); Output: V (a fully-specified test vector); { // FF Clock Disabling A1: Conduct 3-valued logic simulation for C2. A2: For each clock gator with X, disable the clock gator signal by justifying 0 onto it through assigning proper logic values to some X-bits in C2.</p><p>// FF Input-Output Equalizing A3: For all remaining X-bits (input lines) in C2, calculate the logic probabilities of their corresponding output lines in the circuit by assuming 50% 0-probability / 1-probablity for each X-bit in C2. A4: Assign 0 (1) to an X-bit in C2 if the 0probability of its corresponding output line is greater (less) than its 1probability. } Note that a clock gator having X after logic simulation (A1) means that all of its controlled FFs do not contribute to the basic fault detection capability of the initial test vector achieved by its deterministic logic bits; thus the FFs can be stopped by disabling the clock gator (A2). Also note that in the above procedure, the switching activity in the impact area of each hot path can be monitored. If the switching activity is reduced to the level of a warm path, the corresponding hot path is said to be rescued. In this case, further X-filling for its impact area is stopped. This is to avoid turning the path into a cold path due to over-reducing capture power in its impact area.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.3">Remaining Hot Path Masking</head><p>Even after X-filling for reducing capture power ( in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>), some hot paths may remain due to insufficient switching activity reduction in their impact areas. In this case, masking <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> is applied ( in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>) by putting a special symbol (X for most testers) at the expected test response bit for the endpoint of each remaining hot path. This symbol instructs the tester to ignore the test response bit from the path for the test vector since it may be faulted not by a delay defect but by excessive capture power. This guarantees capture power safety for the test vector.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref> shows an example. X-filling for reducing capture power turns a test cube C 2 into a test vector V. As a result, the original hot path P 1 (shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>) becomes a warm (thus safe) path but the other original hot path P 3 remains. Although the expected test response bit from P 3 is 1, it is masked with X (meaning "ignore" on a tester) to avoid the possible negative impact of the remaining hot path P 3 .</p><p>Note that masking-induced fault coverage loss, if any, will be recovered in subsequent ATPG runs as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>. Also note that masking an output bit is only for the current test vector. For other test vectors, the output bit is not masked and available for fault detection.</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">a 0 X X X 1 0 1 0 0 V C 2 Hot Warm Impact Areas P1 P2 0 1 0 1 1 0 1 0 0 X-Filled Logic Bits b c d e f g h i Impact Areas Hot P3 j k l m 0 X 1 X 0 1 1 1 X B C D B C D FFb FFc FFd X X X 1 X Clock Gator CG C2 1 A FFa A 0</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Input Lines</head><p>Output Lines Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref>. Example of remaining hot path masking.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Phase-II: Cold Path Warm-Up</head><p>In the test generation scheme shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>, after Phase-I (Hot Path Elimination) is completed to achieve capture power safety, Phase-II (Cold Path Warm-Up) is conducted to increase switching activity around cold paths in order to improve their small-delay test capability. Phase-II consists of two steps ( and  in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>) as follows:  Step- (X-Restoration for Cold Paths) to obtain X-bits that can only affect the impact areas of cold paths.  Step- (X-Filling for Increasing Capture Power) to determine proper logic values for the X-bits obtained by</p><p>Step- so as to increase capture power around cold paths.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.1">X-Restoration for Cold Paths</head><p>Similar to X-restoration for hot paths described in 4.2.1, Xrestoration for cold paths can be conducted as follows:</p><p>(1) The set of X-bit positions for cold paths of a test vector V, denoted by S X-bit-for-cold-paths (V), is obtained by</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">S X-bit-for-cold-paths (V) = S X-filled-logic-bits (V)  S reach-cold-paths (V)  ) (V S paths warm reach  </formula><p>where S X-filled-logic-bits (V) is the set of all X-filled logic bit positions in V, S reach-cold-paths (V) is the set of all bit positions in V that can reach the impact areas of cold paths of V, and S reach-warm-paths (V) is the set of all bit positions in V that can reach nodes in the impact areas of warm paths of V.</p><p>(2) Turning the bits in S X-bit-for-cold-paths (V) into X-bits results in a partially-specified test cube C 3 at  in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>.</p><p>X-restoration for cold paths is illustrated by an example shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">10</ref>. Here it is assumed that there are a cold path P 5 and a warm path P 6 . In this case, S X-filled-logic-bits (V) = &lt;b, c, d, e, f, h&gt; h, S reach-cold-paths (V) = &lt;a, b, c, d, e&gt; and S reach-warm-paths (V) = &lt;e, f, g, h, i&gt;. The resulting partiallyspecified test cube C 3 is thus &lt;0XXX10100&gt;. Similar to X-restoration for hot paths, the X-bits obtained by X-restoration for cold paths only affect the impact areas of cold paths but not warm paths. Note that some warm paths in Phase-II may be originally hot paths but later rescued in Phase-I. Thus, avoiding impact on warm paths helps in maintaining not only test quality but also capture power safety achieved in Phase-I.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.2">X-Filling for Increasing Capture Power</head><p>In the test generation scheme of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>, after a test cube C 3 is obtained from a test vector V by X-restoration for cold paths (), X-filling is conducted on C 3 for increasing capture power (). Since the X-bits in C 3 only affect the impact areas of cold paths, the X-filling is pinpoint in that it only increases switching activity in the impact areas of cold paths, without running the risk of accidentally increasing switching activity around warm paths that may turn some of them into hot paths. Note that this pinpoint nature exits even when cold paths and warm paths or their impact areas overlap, as illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">10</ref>.</p><p>Generally, X-filling for increasing capture power can be conducted by reversing the operations used for X-filling for reducing capture power (described in 4.2.2). In this work, we use the following procedure for this purpose:</p><p>Procedure-B X-Filling for Increasing Capture Power; Input: C3 (a partially-specified test cube); Output: V (a fully-specified test vector); { // FF Clock Enabling B1: Conduct 3-valued logic simulation for C3. B2: For each clock gator with X, enable the clock gator signal by justifying 1 onto it through assigning proper logic values to some X-bits in C3.</p><p>// FF Input-Output Non-Equalizing B3: For all remaining X-bits (input lines) in C3, calculate the logic probabilities of their corresponding output lines in the circuit by assuming 50% 0-probability / 1-probablity for each X-bit in C3. B4: Assign 1 (0) to an X-bit in C3 if the 0probability of its corresponding output line is greater (less) than its 1probability. } Procedure-B is the reversion of Procedure-A used for Xfilling for reducing capture power (described in 4.2.2). As in Procedure-A, the switching activity in the impact area of each cold path can be monitored. If the switching activity is increased to the level of a warm path, the corresponding cold path is said to be successfully warmed-up. In this case, further X-filling for its impact area is stopped. This is to avoid turning the path into a hot path due to overincreasing capture power in its impact area.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Extension to Test Compression</head><p>The descriptions so far in this paper are focused on the non-test-compression environment. Nonetheless, the proposed ATPG scheme can be readily applied to broadcast-scan-based test compression through simple circuit model extension <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref>. For linear-decompressionbased test compression, the basic idea of this paper still applies. Especially, masking will remain effective for achieving capture power safety, while clock-gator-based direct ATPG <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref> will be needed for the part of Xrestoration/X-filling-based capture power management.</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">a 0 0 0 1 1 0 1 0 0 V HotWarm Warm Impact Areas P1 P2 b c d e f g h i Areas Hot P3 j k l m 0 1 1 1 X 0 X X X 1 0 1 0 0 C2 Masking 0 X 1 X 1 1 0 0 0 1 0 0 1 0 1 1 0 X-Filling for Reducing Capture Power C3 a 0 X X X 1 0 1 0 0 V Cold Warm Impact Areas P5 P6 0 1 0 1 1 0 1 0 0 X-Filled Logic Bits b c d e f g h i</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Experiment Results</head><p>The proposed test generation scheme was implemented in C based on a broadcast-scan-based-test-compression tool (VirtualScan TM ), and evaluated on large ITC'99 benchmark circuits. Circuit statistics, including information on longest structural path lengths (Max. Path Length), are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>. Evaluation experiments were conducted on a workstation with an Intel Xeon  3.33 GHz CPU. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Results</head><p>Table <ref type="table">3</ref> shows the results of conventional ATPG as the baseline for evaluation. A split ratio of 1:8 was used for test compression. Test vector count (# of Vectors) is for evaluating test costs, while transition fault coverage (FC), bridging coverage estimate (BCE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, and statistical delay quality level (SDQL) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> are for evaluating test quality. BCE and SDQL are effective in assessing the detection capability of unmodeled structural defects (e.g., bridging defects) and small-delay defects, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 3. Results of Conventional ATPG</head><p>Path classification was also conducted for test vectors generated by conventional ATPG. First, long sensitized paths (LSPs) were identified by using a fast sensitization checking algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> and the practical criterion F 1 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4(b)</ref>) with  = 70%. That is, a sensitized path whose length was longer than 70% of the longest structural path in a circuit was considered an LSP. After that, a hot path was identified by using the practical criterion F 2 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4(b)</ref>) with  = 30%. That is, an LSP was considered a hot path if the WSA in its impact area was higher than 30% of the maximum WSA in its impact area. Furthermore, a cold path was identified by using the practical criterion F 3 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4(b)</ref>) with  = 10%. That is, an LSP was considered a cold path if the WSA in its impact area was lower than 10% of the maximum WSA in its impact area. These parameters were set by assuming a 20% functional toggle rate. It can be seen that all circuits had some risky test vectors as shown under % of Risky Vectors in Table <ref type="table">3</ref>. This result also clearly demonstrates the needs for guaranteeing capture power safety in at-speed scan testing.</p><p>Table <ref type="table">4</ref> shows the results of applying the proposed ATPG, whose biggest advantage is guaranteed capture power safety achieved by hot path elimination. Another advantage is that the impact of the proposed ATPG on test costs and test quality is minimal as evidenced by the percentage changes in test vector count and three test quality metrics (FC, BCE, SDQL) as shown under # of vectors, FC, BCE, and SDQL, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 4. Results of Proposed ATPG</head><p>Table <ref type="table">5</ref> shows the details of Phase-I (Hot Path Elimination) in the proposed ATPG (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>) for guaranteeing capture power safety. The number of long sensitized paths and the percentage of hot paths are shown under # of LSPs and % of Hot Paths, respectively. The percentage of X-bits obtained by X-restoration ( in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>) is shown under % of Restored X-Bits, and the rescue rate (i.e., the percentage of hot paths becoming warm paths) achieved by X-filling for reducing capture power ( in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>) is shown under Rescue Rate (%); maximum and average WSA reduction rates for impact areas of hot paths are shown under Max. WSA Reduction Rate (%) and Ave. WSA Reduction Rate (%), respectively; the number of test response bits masked for remaining hot paths ( in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>) is shown under # of Masked Test Res. Bits. It can be seen that the powerful masking operation for guaranteeing capture power safety only masks a relatively small number of test response bits with respect to the number of remaining hot paths. This is because many hot paths share the same endpoint.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 5. Details of Phase-I (Hot Path Elimination)</head><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">6</ref> shows the details of Phase-II (Cold Path Warm-Up) in the proposed ATPG (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>) for improving smalldelay test capability. The percentage of cold paths for each circuit is shown under % of Cold Paths. The percentage of X-bits obtained by X-restoration ( in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>) is shown under % of Restored X-Bits; maximum and average WSA increase rates for impact areas of cold paths achieved by X-filling for increasing capture power ( in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>) are shown under Max. WSA Increase Rate (%) and Ave. WSA Increase Rate (%), respectively. % of ColdWarm shows the percentage of cold paths becoming warm paths (i.e., the best result of cold path warm-up).  Note that even if the switching activity around a cold path is not sufficiently increased to turn it into a warm path, its delay test capability may still improve. This has been confirmed by delay analysis on ITC'99 benchmark circuit b19 with VCS  , PrimeRail, and PrimeTime  . Synopsys 90nm Generic Library was used and a test cycle time of 9ns was assumed. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">11</ref> shows the results of 50 cold paths for two test vectors, in terms of the slack change (% Path-Slack-Change) of each path and the WSA change in its impact area (% Impact-Area-WSA-Change). Note that SDQL values shown in Tables <ref type="table">3</ref> and<ref type="table">4</ref> do not reflect power supply noise caused by switching activity of individual test vectors. In this sense, detailed delay analysis provides a better assessment of delay test capability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Discussions</head><p> Table <ref type="table">3</ref> shows that risky vectors are sparse in most cases. In addition, hot paths often cluster together for a risky test vector. This indicates that the conventional approach of reducing capture power unconditionally for all test vectors and globally across the whole chip may be both wasteful (i.e., causing test data inflation) and harmful (i.e., compromising test quality). This fact further highlights the need for a paradigm shift from global capture power management to pinpoint capture power management.  The proposed ATPG scheme is easy to integrate into any ATPG flow. All added processes, including X-restoration, X-filling, and masking, are highly scalable since they only need one pass of structural cone analysis, 3-valued logic simulation, and probability estimation for each risky test vector. In addition, there is no risk of fault coverage loss since masking is only for the current test vector, and faults becoming undetected due to the current masking can be detected by subsequently generated test vectors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Conclusions</head><p>This paper is the first that has proposed pinpoint capture power management and has established a novel at-speed scan test generation scheme based on it. Compared with the conventional (global / unfocused) capture power reduction, the proposed scheme has three significant advantages: guaranteed capture power safety, improved small-delay test capability, and minimal test cost impact. Applicable both in-ATPG and post-ATPG, pinpoint capture power management has the potential of leading to the next-generation capture-power-aware ATPG to meet the industry's growing needs for capture-power-safe, lowcost, and high-quality at-speed scan test vectors. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>% of</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Test power in LOC-based at-speed scan testing.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Motivation for pinpoint capture power management.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Impact area of a path.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>(a)Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Path classification.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Hot</head><label></label><figDesc>Switching Activity S(P) in the ImpactArea of Path P n (P)+D i (S(P)) D n (P)+D d +D i (S(P))  T &gt; T &gt; T D n (P)+D d + D i (S max (P))</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5 shows the outline of the proposed test generation scheme. It consists of conventional test generation steps (A~E) and new steps ( ~ ) for pinpoint capture power management based on the strategy outlined in 3.2. New steps  ~  form Phase-I (Hot Path Elimination) while new steps  and  form Phase-II (Cold Path Warm-Up).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Proposed test generation scheme.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>TestD</head><label></label><figDesc>Cube Generation with Dynamic Compaction Test Cube  C1 Detection-Oriented X-Filling (e.g., Random-Fill) Phase-II (Cold Path Warm-Up)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Two types of logic bits. The new test generation scheme is obtained by enhancing the conventional test generation scheme (A~E) with pinpoint capture power management. The enhancement consists of path classification (), Phase-I (Hot Path Elimination) ( ~ ), and Phase-II (Cold Path Warm-Up) ( and ). The details of path classification have been provided in Subsection 3.1. Phase-I and Phase-II will be described in Subsections 4.2 and 4.3, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Basic approaches to reducing capture power.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Example of X-restoration for cold paths.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. Detailed delay analysis for cold paths.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,68.16,309.12,214.20,99.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 . Variable Definitions E</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note><p>k (P) Total delay of path P for criterion k (k = 1, 2, 3) D n (P) Nominal delay of path P S(P) Switching activity in the impact area of path P S max (P) Maximum amount of S(P) D i (S(P)) Delay increase on path P due to S(P) D d Typical defect delay T Test cycle (as shown in Fig. 1)</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 . Circuit Statistics</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 6 . Details of Phase-II (Cold Path Warm-Up)</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>This work was partly supported by <rs type="funder">JSPS</rs> <rs type="grantName">Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research</rs> (B) #<rs type="grantNumber">22300017</rs>, <rs type="funder">JSPS</rs> <rs type="grantName">Grant-in-Aid for Challenging Exploratory Research #</rs><rs type="grantNumber">24650022</rs>, and <rs type="funder">JST-NSC</rs> <rs type="grantName">Grant-in-Aid for Japan-Taiwan Joint Research</rs> on the <rs type="institution">Testing of Nano Devices</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_e8d9amb">
					<idno type="grant-number">22300017</idno>
					<orgName type="grant-name">Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_7KNjCJu">
					<idno type="grant-number">24650022</idno>
					<orgName type="grant-name">Grant-in-Aid for Challenging Exploratory Research #</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_GNKxXnH">
					<orgName type="grant-name">Grant-in-Aid for Japan-Taiwan Joint Research</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hsiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Delay</forename><surname>Testing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">System-on-Chip Test Architectures: Nanometer Design for Testability</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Morgan</forename><surname>Kaufmann</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">(l.-T</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Francisco, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Invisible Delay Quality -SDQM Model Lights Up What Could Not Be Seen</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Sato</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ITC, Paper</title>
		<meeting>ITC, Paper</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Timing-Aware ATPG for High Quality At-Speed Testing of Small Delay Defects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ATS</title>
		<meeting>ATS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="146" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Power-Aware Testing and Test Strategies for Low Power Devices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Girard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Power Supply Noise: A Survey on Effects and Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tehranipoor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Design &amp; Test of Computers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-04">Mar.-Apr. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Scheme to Reduce Power Consumption during Scan Testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Saxena</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ITC</title>
		<meeting>ITC</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="670" to="677" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Power-Aware Test: Challenges and Solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ravi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ITC, Lecture</title>
		<meeting>ITC, Lecture</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007-02-02">2.2, 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Test Strategies for Low-Power Devices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ravikumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. of Low Power Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="138" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Layout-Aware Pattern Generation for Maximizing Supply Noise Effects on Critical Paths</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. VTS</title>
		<meeting>VTS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="226" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ATPG for Heat Dissipation Minimization during Test Application</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ITC</title>
		<meeting>ITC</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="250" to="258" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On Low-Capture-Power Test Generation for Scan Testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. VTS</title>
		<meeting>VTS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="270" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Power-Aware Test Generation with Guaranteed Launch Safety for At-Speed Scan Testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. VTS</title>
		<meeting>VTS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="171" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://www.itrs.net/Links/2011ITRS/Home2011.htm" />
		<title level="m">International Technology Roadmap for Semiconductors, 2011 Edition</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preferred Fill: A Scalable Method to Reduce Capture Power for Scan Based Designs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Remersaro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ITC, Paper</title>
		<meeting>ITC, Paper</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On Capture Power-Aware Test Data Compression for Scan-Based Testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ICCAD</title>
		<meeting>ICCAD</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="72" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Power Supply Noise Reduction for At-Speed Scan Testing in Linear-Decompression Environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-F</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE TCAD</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1767" to="1776" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Low Peak Power ATPG for n-Detection Test</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ISCAS</title>
		<meeting>ISCAS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1993" to="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why is Conventional ATPG Not Sufficient for Advanced Low Power Designs?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Chakravadhanula</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ATS</title>
		<meeting>ATS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="300" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Low Power Compression Utilizing Clock-Gating</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rajski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ITC, Paper 7.1</title>
		<meeting>ITC, Paper 7.1</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">XID: Don&apos;t Care Identification of Test Patterns for Combinational Circuits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Miyase</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE TCAD</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="326" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pseudo-Functional Testing for Small Delay Defects Considering Power Supply Noise Effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ICCAD</title>
		<meeting>ICCAD</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="39" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Novel Post-ATPG IR-Drop Reduction Scheme for At-Speed Scan Testing in Broadcast-Scan-Based Test Compression Environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Miyase</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ICCAD</title>
		<meeting>ICCAD</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="104" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of Multiple-Detect Test Patterns on Product Quality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Benware</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ITC</title>
		<meeting>ITC</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1031" to="1040" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incremental Techniques for the Identification of Statically Sensitizable Critical Paths</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-C</forename><surname>Ju</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. DAC</title>
		<meeting>DAC</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1641">1991. 1337 1124 1641 1161 1371 2748</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="541" to="546" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>X-Restoration/Filling-Based Warm-Up</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
