<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Topological Semantics for Lumped Parameter Systems Modeling</title>
				<funder ref="#_SFp9Kt5">
					<orgName type="full">National Institute of Standards and Technology</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NIST</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_zghUcqw #_2qgPq9q #_Y8CkVEf">
					<orgName type="full">National Science Foundation</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NSF</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency&apos;s FUNdamental Design Program</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-11-08">November 8, 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Randi</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Spatial Automation Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Wisconsin -Madison</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Vadim</forename><surname>Shapiro</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Spatial Automation Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Wisconsin -Madison</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Topological Semantics for Lumped Parameter Systems Modeling</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-11-08">November 8, 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1811.02666v1[cs.SY]</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T20:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Interoperability</term>
					<term>Algebraic topology</term>
					<term>System modeling languages; Tonti diagrams</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Behaviors of many engineering systems are described by lumped parameter models that encapsulate the spatially distributed nature of the system into networks of lumped elements; the dynamics of such a network is governed by a system of ordinary differential and algebraic equations. Languages and simulation tools for modeling such systems differ in syntax, informal semantics, and in the methods by which such systems of equations are generated and simulated, leading to numerous interoperability challenges. Logical extensions of SysML aim specifically at unifying a subset of the underlying concepts in such languages.</p><p>We propose to unify semantics of all such systems using standard notions from algebraic topology. In particular, Tonti diagrams classify all physical theories in terms of physical laws (topological and constitutive) defined over a pair of dual cochain complexes and may be used to describe different types of lumped parameter systems. We show that all possible methods for generating the corresponding state equations within each physical domain correspond to paths over Tonti diagrams. We further propose a generalization of Tonti diagram that captures the behavior and supports canonical generation of state equations for multi-domain lumped parameter systems.</p><p>The unified semantics provides a basis for greater interoperability in systems modeling, supporting automated translation, integration, reuse, and numerical simulation of models created in different authoring systems and applications. Notably, the proposed algebraic topological semantics is also compatible with spatially and temporally distributed models that are at the core of modern CAD and CAE systems.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction 1.Motivation</head><p>Lumped parameter models are commonly used to describe behaviors of many engineering systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. In such systems, spatially and temporally distributed physical phenomena are approximated by a finite network of abstract components that store, dissipate, or transform energy; the phenomenaspecific constitutive properties of the components (e.g. generalized impedances) are estimated by domain integrals from the actual system by a process of "reticulation" <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. Bond graphs <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, linear graphs <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, Modelica <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> and Simulink/Simscape <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> are commonly used physical modeling languages for creating, editing, and simulating lumped parameter models. These languages may differ widely in their syntax, but have similar (though not identical) semantics that specifies interconnectivity and constitutive relations of individual components in a system; the resulting model of a system created in such languages is then compiled into a system of state equations that may be numerically solved to simulate the system's dynamic response. Formally, the dynamic behavior of a lumped parameter model is described by the state equations, a set of ordinary differential equations (ODEs) or differential algebraic equations (DAEs), whose solutions depend on the initial conditions.</p><p>Generally speaking, all modeling languages can handle the same broad class of problems but with non-trivial differences in system types, representations, state equation derivation and simulation mechanisms <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>. For example, in Simulink, components exchange numeric information uni-directionally and are not subject to conservation laws; by contrast, the energy flow between components is bi-directional in other languages, satisfying conservation laws. While every linear graph model may be represented by a bond graph, the converse statement is not true <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. Furthermore, parallel/serial junctions in a bond graph do not specify ordering of branches in the junctions, which implies that every bond graph in fact corresponds to a family of (dynamically) equivalent graph-based models in other languages. Many languages generate state equations using efforts and flows as variables, but their integral forms may also be used, for example in bond graphs <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. The above and other differences in syntax and semantics of system modeling languages lead to challenges in exchange, translation, and composition of models created in these languages. Such interoperability difficulties are only likely to increase due to ubiquitous and growing adoption of physical modeling languages by industry and standards organizations.</p><p>Conceptually, there are two possible approaches to dealing with semantic interoperability issues: "point-to-point" correspondence<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">foot_0</ref> between models created in different languages, or standardization on a single neutral format that can be translated to/from models in any such languages. The first approach is more practical but is problematic because it requires O(n 2 ) such translators, which is not only expensive, but discourages development of new languages and simulation solutions. The second approach is similar in spirit to STEP for product models, which requires the neutral format to be formally defined and include the superset of models present in any such language. These difficulties can be observed in a recent effort to extend System Modeling Language (SysML) with packages for direct communication with multiple simulation tools <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. Recently proposed Functional Mockup Interface (FMI) <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> attempts to sidestep the semantic interoperability issues by supporting model exchange and integration via standardized XML and C-code interfaces; this approach simply shifts the responsibility for semantic correctness of these tasks to the authoring systems and users.</p><p>Irrespectively of the selected approach, semantic interoperability requires establishing formal correspondence between concepts and constructs in distinct modeling languages. This is the main goal of this paper. Our approach relies on tools from algebraic topology and well known classification of physical theories developed over the years by Tonti <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref>, Roth <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, Branin <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, Kron <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, and others. Importantly, this classification generalizes to higher-dimensional physical models, suggesting that the proposed framework may be extended to include spatially-distributed models represented by three-dimensional solid models, partial differential equations and finite element methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Outline</head><p>Section 2 briefly surveys and compares the main system modeling languages and surveys related work. In Section 3, we summarize the well known algebraic topological model of physical systems; this model serves as the basis for Tonti's diagrams that classify physical variables, laws, and theories <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Tonti's classification is a starting point for the unified semantics proposed in this paper. The main results of the paper are contained in Sections 4 and 5.</p><p>Single domain lumped parameters systems are examined in detail in Section 4. Because all such systems are isomorphic in terms of their physical variables, laws, and Tonti's diagrams, we only discuss the models of electrical systems -with understanding that the discussion also applies to lumped parameters systems in other physical domains. In particular, we show that paths over the corresponding Tonti diagram correspond to all possible ways to generate state equations for an electrical network, including well known node-potential and mesh-current methods that date to Maxwell <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. While the discussion and the semantics proposed in Section 4 apply to any one singledomain lumped-parameter system model, in Section 5 we consider the more general multi-domain systems (that may combine electrical, mechanical, hydraulic, thermal, and other single-domain subsystems). We show that all such systems may be represented by an algebraic topological model in terms of generalized state variables associated with extended and generalized Tonti diagrams. We conclude in Section 6 with discussion of practical applications and consequences of the proposed semantic unification, open issues, and possible extensions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Background</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Brief history of lumped-parameter modeling</head><p>Informally, the significance of lumped-parameter models and languages can be attributed to two main factor factors. Lumped parameter models are the simplest models of system behavior (usually, but not always dynamic) that encapsulate and abstract away all detailed geometric information. This allows modeling behavior of systems without dealing with detailed embodiment of such systems -either because these details are too complex or not known (for example in early design stages). Secondly, the lumped parameter models in different physical domains (electrical, mechanical motion, fluid flow, etc.) have identical mathematical structure that unifies all such models. Below we briefly summarizes the conceptual evolution of these developments.</p><p>The efforts to classify and unify different physical models and theories date back at least to James Clerk Maxwell, who expressed the desire to establish a formal analogy between various physical quantities based on their mathematical form <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, and continued through 20 th century (for example see <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>). Maxwell also introduced the so called mesh and node methods for solving electrical networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref> that we will also use to derive state equations for lumped parameter systems in <ref type="bibr">Section 4.</ref> Advances in analysis and simulation of (analog) electrical systems motivated many to use such analogies in order to leverage the advances in electrical engineering in other physical domains <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref>. In particular, Nickle proposed to predict the response of a mechanical dynamical system by translating it into a dynamically equivalent analog electrical circuit <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. This electrical-network approach to modeling and simulation of mechanical systems became widely used and culminated in the work of Gabriel Kron, an influential and controversial electrical engineer, who showed that most distributed mechanical systems may also be modeled and efficiently simulated by analog electrical networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24]</ref>. Kron's work influenced many others, including F. Branin, P. Roth, E. Tonti, and H. Paynter.</p><p>More specifically, Branin recognized that the versatility of electrical networks is an indication of the combinatorial and topological nature of the classical vector calculus <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. Roth identified specific algebraic topological model for stationary electrical networks in terms of chain and cochain sequences <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, whereas Branin generalized Roth diagram to two dual cochain sequences and revealed that this model underlies general three-dimensional network models. Tonti <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> built on these insights to develop a complete classification of space-time physical theories in terms of their underlying topological structures and codified this classification in terms of concise (Tonti) diagrams. We will review the Tonti diagrams in Section 3 and we will adopt them as a convenient way to describe and visualize models of lumped parameter systems. More details of these developments can be found in Appendix D of <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</p><p>Increasingly, these algebraic topological models are finding applications in computational modeling of engineering systems. For example, several researchers proposed that all geometric and physical computations should be based on a common (co)chain complex model <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29]</ref>, and that a vast majority of physical laws may be enforced as topological invariants of common transformations used in automated design systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>. Algebraic topological structure has been used explicitly in variety of modeling systems spanning diverse areas such interactive physics <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, computer graphics <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>, and manufacturing systems [33].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Languages for lumped parameter modeling</head><p>Paynter's work <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> originally focused on methodology for use of lumped parameters models for design and analysis of engineering systems and culminated in the language of bond graphs. He described a systematic method of converting a general system to a simplified lumped parameter model by a process of "reticulation" (creating a network model through discretization of a spatiallydistributed system) and developed a symbolic language of bond graphs for describing such models. A major conceptual and practical significance of bond graphs is that they model all lumped parameter systems in terms of small number of abstract generalized variables: efforts, flows, their derivatives, integrals, and constitutive relationships. This allowed bond graphs to represent lumped parameter models of complex physically heterogeneous systems that are coupled using abstract transformer and gyrator elements and can be easily translated into a system of ordinary differential equations.</p><p>Arguably, all lumped parameter models and languages are based on concepts similar to those used in bond graphs and are now a standard textbook material <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref>. Lumped parameter models abstract a spatially and temporaly distributed system by a network of components. The purpose of the network is to model the flow of energy through the system's components as a function of time; detailed geometry of the system is accounted for by integral properties of the components. Formally, the lumped parameter model is described in terms of ordinary differential and algebraic equations with variables that are specific to physical phenomena modeled by the network. However, all such models are isomorphic based on the well known 'analogies' between different physical theories, as summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. In each physical domain, the power is a product of two generalized variables that are classified as across or through (in case of Modelica and linear graph models), or effort and flow (in case of bond graphs). The network includes abstract sources of these variables, and transforms the energy by storing or dissipating in three types elements that are commonly described by analogy with electrical networks as generalized resistors, inductances, and capacitors. In addition, the energy may be transformed between different physical domains using transformer and gyrator components in the network. More general components with complex behavior may be incorporated into the network, but all such components may be modeled as a composition of these basic components listed above <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. The formal reason for these analogies is the common underlying algebraic topological structure that we will discuss in Section 3.</p><p>The differences between various modeling languages stem from their approach to describing the basic components, their connectivity in the network, and the method by which the governing system of equations is generated. Thus, bond graph uses 0 and 1 junctions to represent parallel or serial connections of components; linear graph uses directed edges to connect components (nodes), while Modelica/Simulink uses connectors to link library components. Behavior of components is described in terms of state variables that are related by constitutive relations: bond graph associates effort, flow and constitutive relationships to 1-ports; linear graph associates across and through variables to directed edges, while Modelica and Simulink associate these variables with blocks.</p><p>The governing state equations is a system of ODEs (or more generally DAEs) that are generated from such descriptions by methods that differ in the choice of state variables and generation algorithms. Of course, all such equations describe identical dynamical behavior of the modeled system  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> shows how the same circuit would be described in four different languages: bond graphs, linear graphs, Modelica, and Simulink. As we already noted, electrical circuits themselves have also been used as a general purpose modeling language for modeling lumped parameter system, for example in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, but they have been largely superceded by more modern languages in use today.</p><p>The following is a brief summary of steps to generate state equations for the circuit in each of the languages.</p><p>Bond graph : (1) assign causality to the bond graph; (2) select input and energy state variables; (3) generate an initial set of system equations; (4) simplify initial equations to state-space form <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, giving d dt</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">q C p L = 0 1 L -1 C -R L q C p L + 0 V AC<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where, q C is the time integral of the current of capacitor, p L is the time integral of the voltage of inductor. V AC represents the voltage of voltage source. Linear graph: (1) generate a normal tree from the linear graph; (2) select the primary and secondary variables, system order and state variables; (3) formulate constitutive, continuity and compatibility equations then simplify these equations to state equations <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>, giving</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">d dt i L v C = -1 L -R L 0 1 C i L v C + 1 L 0 V AC<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where, i L represents the current of inductor, v C represents the voltage of capacitor. V AC represents the voltage of voltage source. Modelica/Simulink: (1) based on the established model in Modelica/Simulink, extract constitutive equations of each component from library; (2) select dynamic variables; (3) express the problem as the smallest possible ODE system <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>. In case of Modelica, we get</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">der(L.i) der(C.v) = -1 L -R L 0 1 C L.i C.v + 1 L 0 V AC<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where, der( * ) represents the derivative of * in terms of time. L.i is the current of inductor, C.v is the voltage of capacitor. Similarly, for Simulink, we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">L di dt = V AC -Ri - 1 C t -∞ i(t)dt<label>(4)</label></formula><p>It is easy to verify that these equations are equivalent in terms of their solutions, but are distinct in appearance due to the different choices of state variables and procedures by which they are generated in each modeling system. For instance, linear graph uses across (effort) and through (flow) variables, but bond graph uses their integral forms as state variables.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Interoperability of lumped parameter languages and systems</head><p>Broadly speaking, interoperability subsumes the problems of exchange and integration of simulation models created in different systems. The latter often manifests itself as the need for co-simulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> and/or for executable semantics in system modeling tools. For example, system engineering languages, such as SysML <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref> need to integrate with simulation models in order to predict the modelled system behavior; however, each specific tool needs a different interface, as proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39]</ref> for Matlab/Simulink <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39]</ref>, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41]</ref> for Modelica, and for bond graph in <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>. An effort to overcome these challenges was recently described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, where a SysML extension is proposed specifically for the purpose of generating such interfaces automatically. One of our goals in this effort is to provide formal semantics for this and other interoperability efforts. Without such formal semantics, integration of distinct simulation tools requires a non-trivial software development effort that must resolve individual assumptions and differences of distinct models. The purpose of the recently proposed FMI standard <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref> is to streamline and simplify such efforts through generation of uniform C code. Unifying semantics of distinct models would support automatic generation of such FMI interfaces.</p><p>Model to model conversion is an effective method for achieving interoperability between different modeling languages. The conversion between the bond graph and linear graph models has been studied in the 70's. Ort and Martens proposed a topological procedure for converting the bond graph to the linear graph by identifying the correspondence of bonds in a bond graph and edges of a linear graph <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>. While theoretically not every bond graph has a corresponding linear graph <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, Birkett gave a deterministic cut-and-paste method for converting any physical bond graph to the corresponding linear graph model <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>. Bond graphs can also be converted to equivalent models in Simulink or Modelica. Specifically, <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> used bond graphs through Simulink to analyze dynamic systems by transforming bond graphs to equivalent block diagrams; researchers in <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48]</ref> observed that translating non-causal bond graph models to Modelica is in principle a straightforward process, even if causal assignment cannot be specified in Modelica. The reverse conversion from Modelica to bond graphs has been studied in <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>. Strictly speaking, not every Modelica model can be translated into a bond graph, because power continuity (the energy balance) is strictly enforced by the junction structure of bond graph but does not have to be enforced by interconnection of components in Modelica <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>. Similarly, not all Simulink models may be translated into Modelica models, but translation of selective Simulink models to equivalent Modelica models was considered in <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>. Our goal is to identify a subset of physical models that is supported by all of these languages and provide unified semantics that would remove any ambiguities in such conversions and other interoperability tasks.</p><p>A fundamental limitation underlying all of the above approaches is that none of them offer a systematic path towards interoperability with full 3D (spatially distributed) models governed by partial differential equations and discretized by finite element, volume, or difference methods. This area of research is in its infancy and exemplified by rather limited efforts. For example, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref> finite element model of 3D deformable objects are converted to the corresponding lumped mass-spring models by minimizing the difference of stiffness matrices of these two models. Others proposed various methods for associating geometric information with components in the lumped parameter systems. Thus, integral properties from solid models in CAD systems may be mapped to lumped parameters, and mating constraints in assembly models are mapped to transformers in the corresponding Modelica models <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55]</ref>. Such methods also allow translating Adams rigid body simulation models to Modelica code <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref>. Additional constraints and annotations may be introduced in order to explicitly maintain bilateral correspondence between parameters of lumped parameter and three-dimensional models <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[57,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">58,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">59]</ref>. By contrast, the semantics of lumped parameter models proposed in this papers naturally extends to full 3D models of spatially distributed phenomena.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Algebraic topological models of lumped parameter systems</head><p>Algebraic topological interpretations of network models and various types of electrical circuits are well known in literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref> and are now a standard textbook material <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[60]</ref>. We now apply such an interpretation to lumped parameter models and show that it provides a neutral standard semantics for all such systems. Superficially, all algebraic topological formulations are identical, but important semantic difference emerge in details. As a starting point, we adopt Tonti's classification <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> of physical theories in terms of their algebraic topological models; however, specific requirements of the lumped parameter system require significant extensions and modifications that we discuss below. Strictly speaking, a proper setting for physical modeling is 4D spacetime. But, most engineering models are set in space×time, where space and time models are treated separately.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Lumped parameter models as cochains</head><p>In algebraic topological view of physics, physical properties are distributed in spacetime over finite chunks of space called p-dimensional cells, or p-cells, (p = 0, 1, 2...) that fit together to form a cell complex that decomposes the undelying physical space. Many choices of cells are possible; they can be open or closed, p-simplicies, p-balls, or p-manifolds; specific choices are dictated by convenience and applications and define the type of cell complex <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[61]</ref>. All cells are endowed with orientation, or sense of direction, which becomes important in order to properly assign signs to physical properties associated with cells.</p><p>As we already saw, all lumped parameter models are formulated using 2-dimensional cells complexes: 0-cells (nodes), 1-cells (edges), and 2-cells (cycles or "meshes"). These complexes are abstract in the sense that geometric coordinates or shapes of the cells are immaterial; only their connectivity carries important physical information. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">2</ref> The distribution of physical properties is described by assigning their types and quantities to the individual cells in this complex. The formal mechanism for doing so requires discretizing the property g over p-cells e p α as a p-cochain C p , a formal sum</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">C p = np α=1 g α e p α (5)</formula><p>The relation between physical properties is governed by two types of fundamental laws: metric laws and topological laws. Metric laws usually involve measurement while topological laws relate physical properties associated with space and its boundary. Topological laws can be formulated using formal linear coboundary δ operations on cochains. Specifically, coboundary δ p operating on a p-cochain produces a (p + 1)-cochain by transferring and adding the coefficient of the p-cochain to its cofaces (Eq.6). Formally,</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">δ p (C p ) = δ p np α=1 g α e p α = n p+1 β=1 np α=1 h αβ • g α • e p+1 β ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where n p represents the number of cells in the p-cochain. The incidence coefficient h αβ = [e p α , e p+1 β ] ∈ {0, ±1} is determined by relative orientation of p-cell e p α and it cofaces (p + 1)-cell e p+1 β <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. If e p+1 β is not a coface of e p α , then h αβ = 0; otherwise, if the orientations of e p α and e p+1 β are consistent, then h αβ = +1, otherwise, h αβ = -1. If we denote the usual p-incidence matrix as A = [h βα ], then the coboundary operator δ p is commonly represented by its transpose A T .</p><p>Informally, the coboundary operations capture the essence of balance, equilibrium, conservation, compatibility, and other topological laws. For cochains on finite cell complexes, coboundary operators δ p , p = 1, 2, 3 correspond to the usual vector calculus operators of gradient, curl, and divergence respectively. The vector calculus identities ∇ × (∇φ) = 0, and ∇ • (∇ × F) = 0 are simply instances of the Poincare lemma stating that δ p (δ p-1 ()) = 0, where 0 denotes a null cochain. A collection of cochains and coboundary operators on a cell complex form a cochain complex <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[61]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Physical theories as Tonti diagrams</head><p>Every physical theory is conceptualized in terms of relationships between two types of dual physical quantities that are referred to by various authors as configuration/source <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, through/across <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, or effort/flow <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. In what follows we will adopt Tonti's convention and distinguish between configuration type variables, that are modeled as cochains on primary cell complex decomposition of space, and source variables that are modeled as cochains on the dual cell complex decomposition of the same space. This notion is illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref>, where the primal cell complex is shown in blue the dual cell complex is shown in black. (The actual geometry of cells is irrelevant for this discussion.) Each p-dimensional cell in the primal cell complex is dual to a unique (n -p)-dimensional cell in the dual cell complex. By duality, it also follows that the coboundary operator δ p on the dual cell complex can be represented by the transpose of δ p = A T , or simply A.</p><p>This conceptualization of physical quantities in terms cochains on dual cell complexes is not arbitrary: it arises from first principles based on how the postulated quantities are measured. In each case, the measurement process implies the intrinsic dimension of the associated quantity (e.g., displacements are measured at a point, currents are measured across the surface, voltage drop is measured along a path, and so on). The decision whether a particular quantity belongs to the primal or dual complex is determined by the oddness principle that requires change of sign under change of orientation of the relevant cell. The primal cells are are endowed with inner orientation, while the dual cells are oriented relative to the containing (outer) space. The reader is referred to <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> for detailed discussion of these concepts.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> shows the correspondence between the primal and dual cochains of variables and naming conventions used by different authors and lumped-parameter modeling systems. We note that the adopted classification in terms of primal and dual cochains is consistent with the conventions in linear graphs <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, Modelica <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, Simscape <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> and NIST models <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, but differs slightly from that in bond graphs <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Physical laws (topological and metric) relate different types of variables within each physical theory. Tonti proposed a systematic method for representing these laws using a diagram that can be considered an evolved combination of the so-called Roth diagrams <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62]</ref> in terms of cochain sequences and "Maxwell house" diagram to represent all topological and metric relationships in electromagnetism <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[63]</ref>. A simple example of such a diagram is the Tonti diagram of electrical (static) network theory is shown in (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>). It describes the network systems that satisfy Kirchhoff Current Law (KCL) and Kirchhoff Voltage Law (KVL) using a pair of cochains complexes dual to each other <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</p><p>The diagram consists of two vertical sequences corresponding to the primal (left) and dual (right) cochain complexes, ordered by dimension. The vertical arrows correspond to the coboundary operations, going down for primal cochains and going up for dual cochains. Formally, the two sequences are exact<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">foot_2</ref> and form two dual cochain complexes:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">primal : e 0 δ 0 -→ v 1 δ 1 -→ 0 2<label>(7)</label></formula><p>dual :</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">0 2 δ 1 ←-j 1 δ 0 ←-i 0<label>(8)</label></formula><p>The measured relationships between dual quantities are represented by the horizontal links in the diagram. In the case of network theory, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>, the primal variable are node potentials e associated with 0-cells, voltage drops v and sources associated with 1-cells, and voltage drops associated with 2-cells (meshes or cycles) that are identically 0 as the consequence of KVL. The cochains of adjacent dimensions satisfy topological laws expressed by the corresponding coboundary operations depicted as down-facing vertical arrows. Thus, 1-cochain of voltage drops v 1 = A T e 0 is implied by the coboundary operation δ 0 on 0-cochain of node potentials e 0 ; and KVL The constitutive relation between 1-cochain of voltage drops v and 1-cochain of currents j satisfies Ohm's Law (or its inverse). The diagram also reveals two (dual) methods of generating the governing state equations for network models, depending on the choice of state variables. The two methods are indicated by primal and dual 'cycles' which refer to two different ways of composing topological and metric laws. For instance, in the primal cycle, 1-cochain voltage drop v is obtained by coboundary operation on 0-cochain node potential e. Using the Ohm's law, v is converted to 1-cochain branch currents j in the dual cell complex, where coboundary operation A on j equals zero. The physical meaning of the latter coboundary operation A is that the algebraic sum of branch currents of a dual loop equals zero, as required by KCL. Similarly, the dual cycle relies on KVL to generate the dual state equations for the same system.</p><p>Even though the diagram in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> describes a static phenomena, the reader will notice that the configuration and source variables are associated with time instances: primal instances for source variables and dual instances for configuration variables. This distinction becomes critical in dynamic physical models where, once again, the primary time elements (0-dimensional instances and 1-dimensional intervals) are distinguished from the dual time elements based on the oddness principle that requires sign change under reversal of motion <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Strictly speaking, a proper setting for all physical models is a 4D spacetime, which we chose to represent as direct product of space and time. In other words, for each type of spatial variable, we can also consider its behavior in time which is represented by a pair of dual 1-dimensional time complexes, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>. Here 0-cells I * and 1-cells T * represent primal time instances and intervals, while 0-cells I * and 1-cells T * represent the dual time instances and intervals, respectively.</p><p>The introduction of time cell complexes in time has two consequences. First, it identifies the usual time derivative with the corresponding coboundary operator δ t . Thus, if q is a 0-cochain of primal (or dual) time instances, then I (respectively, I) is the 1-cochain of time intervals of q defined 0 q (respectively δ t 0 q). On a finite cell complex, δ t 0 become the time difference operation. Secondly, all space Tonti diagrams now acquire an additional time dimension, giving rise to horizontal sections of the diagram. One such section is shown in Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>, which corresponds to the Tonti diagram of RLC circuit systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Here, the usual differential relations V = dΦ/dt and I = dQ/dt are consequence of topological relations V = δt 0 Φ and I = δ t 0 Q, respectively, where Φ is magnetic flux and Q is electric charge. Two new constitutive equations describe the capacitance relation between electric charge Q and voltage drop v and the inductance relation between magnetic flow Φ and currents j. The second time derivative is the result of composition of two first time derivatives. For instance, the second order equation differential equation V = dΦ/dt =Ld (I)/dt =Ld 2 Q dt 2 in Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref> can be expressed as V = δt 0 Φ = L δt 0 I = δt 0 Lδ t 0 Q <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">64]</ref>. Finally, we note that the vertical space diagram in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> and the horizontal time diagram in Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref> can be combined into a single three-dimensional diagram, as described in Section 4 and shown in Figure <ref type="figure">6a</ref>.</p><p>In addition to physical quantities in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> and 5, the diagram in Figure <ref type="figure">6a</ref> includes magnetic flux potential Ψ and mesh electric charge q that are related by coboundary operators to magnetic flux Φ and electric charge Q respectively. In other words, the extended Tonti diagram includes two additional cochain complexes defined by the two sequences:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">primal : Ψ 0 δ 0 -→ Φ 1 δ 1 -→ 0 2<label>(9)</label></formula><p>dual :</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">0 2 δ 1 ←-Q 1 δ 0 ←-q 0 (10)</formula><p>Additional horizontal arrows indicate the corresponding time coboundary (derivative) operations. With the added constitutive, topological equations and physical variables, the extended Tonti diagram includes all possible quantities, as well as constitutive and topological laws of RLC </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Dual cochain complexes on a single cell complex</head><p>The ultimate goal of physical modeling is numerical simulation which is usually performed on a discretization of spacetime. If one were to accept that every physical theory is formulated in terms of dual cochain complexes, it would be reasonable to expect that most modeling and simulation tools are also formulated in terms of dual discretizations (one for configuration variables and another one for the source variable) as illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref> (on the left). In fact, such dual discretizations are often advocated in literature as more natural and numerically stable alternatives, for example, in mimetic discretization schemes <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref>, cell methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[66,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">64]</ref>, discrete exterior calculus <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67]</ref> and other modeling approaches. However, the vast majority of numerical schemes appear to be based on a single discretization of space, which supports evaluation of both primal and dual cochains. For example, in most finite element, finite difference, and finite volume methods, all configuration and source variables are associated with cells (often nodes) in the underlying mesh, and their duality is hidden within the numerical scheme itself <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[68]</ref>.</p><p>In lumped parameter models, dual discretizations are particularly counter-intuitive, since all spatially distributed properties have already been integrated (lumped) and only connectivity of the underlying cell complex remains visible. That connectivity often directly corresponds to the physical embedding; for example, a single electrical network carries both voltage and current information. Similarly, general network model is a single cell complex where primal and dual cochains are represented. The mapping of dual cochains on the primal cell complex is straightforward and is accomplished by mapping the dual (n -p)-cells to their corresponding primal p-cells, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref>. Consider how this mapping would work for the cochains in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>. With this mapping, node potentials e, voltage drops v and sources, and voltage drops of cycles 0 are still associated with primal 0-cells (e.g. A), 1-cells (e.g. L), and 2-cells (e.g. M ) respectively. However, the dual source (current) variables: mesh currents i, branch currents j, and currents merging at nodes 0 which were originally associated with dual 0-cells (e.g. a), 1-cells (e.g. l ), and 2-cells (e.g. m) are now associated with primal 2-cells (e.g. M ), 1-cells (e.g. L), and 0-cells (e.g. A) respectively. </p><formula xml:id="formula_10">∂ p (C p ) = ∂ p ( np α=1 g α e p α ) = n p-1 β=1 np α=1 h αβ • g α • e p-1 β ,<label>(11)</label></formula><p>which is similar to Eq.6, except that the coefficients are transferred from p-cells to their (p -1)faces. This implies that the coboundary operation δ n-p on the dual cells complex is mapped into the boundary operation ∂ p on the primal cell complex,<ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">foot_3</ref> i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">∂ p = δ n-p<label>(12)</label></formula><p>This explains, for example, why the KCL on the primal complex is described by condition ∂ 1 j 1 = 0, stating that the branch currents must add up to zero at every node.</p><p>The single complex network model is summarized by a new type of Tonti diagram shown in Figure <ref type="figure">6b</ref>. Here the dual (source) cochains have been mapped to the corresponding cochains on the primal cell complex to form the dual cochain complex with boundary ∂ p operators replacing the original dual δ n-p coboundary operators. In other words, the dual cochain sequences ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">8</ref>) and (10) become respectively</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">i 2 ∂ 2 -→ j 1 ∂ 1 -→ 0 0 (<label>13</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">q 2 ∂ 2 -→ Q 1 ∂ 1 -→ 0 0<label>(14)</label></formula><p>In the rest of the report, we will assume that an algebraic topological model of a lumped parameter system is described by such single (primal) cell complex and a corresponding Tonti diagram with four cochain complexes (correspong to the four vertical 'legs' of the diagram) and all relationships between them. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">5</ref> The two primal cochain complex include: (1) 0-cochain node potentials e 0 , 1-cochain voltage drops v 1 , 2-cochain of mesh voltages (which is 0 by KVL); and</p><p>(2) 0-cochain magnetic flux potentials Ψ 0 , 1-cochain magnetic fluxes Φ 1 , and 2-cochain of mesh magnetic fluxes and 2-cochain of mesh voltages (which is 0 by KVL). The cochains in each complex are related by the spatial coboundary operators, while the corresponding p-cochains in the two complexes are related by the time boundary operator. Similarly, the two dual cochain complexes are: (1) 0-cochain of node currents (which is 0 by KCL), 1-cochain currents j 1 , 2-cochain mesh currents i 2 ; and (2) 0-cochain of node electric charges, 1-cochain electric charges Q 1 , 2-cochain mesh electric charges q 2 . The cochains in each of the dual complexes related by the spatial boundary operators, while the corresponding p-chains in the two dual complexes are related by the time coboundary operators.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Single-domain lumped parameter systems</head><p>In this section, we will show how to use Tonti diagrams to describe lumped parameter systems and introduce an automated method of generating system state equations. We will focus on lumped parameter models of a single physical domain, exemplified by classical RLC electrical circuit systems. Application to other physical domains is immediate, since all such models are isomorphic.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Static systems</head><p>Classical single-domain RLC electrical circuits consist of five types of physical elements: resistors, capacitors, inductors, voltage sources and current sources. We will first consider a special case of static resistive circuits that contain only constant resistors, as well as voltage and current sources; later we will extend the approach to general dynamic electrical circuits. The algebraic topological structure of static electrical circuits relies only on the two dual cochain complexes modeled over a single cell complex. The primal cochain complex includes 0-cochain of node potentials e 0 , 1cochain of voltage drops v 1 , and 2-cochain of mesh voltages (which is 0 by KVL), related by the coboboundry operators; the dual cochain complex consists of 0-cochain of node currents (which is 0 by KCL), 1-cochain of branch currents j 1 , and 2-cochain mesh currents i 2 related by the boundary operators. The topological and constitutive relations between these cochains are given by the diagram in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>, and two methods of generating the equations are indicated by primal and dual 'cycles' respectively in the diagram. In the context of the more general model, these cycles correspond to red and blue paths in the extended Tonti diagram as shown in (Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>). Each path is defined by a sequence of the arrows in the diagram indicating composition of the corresponding physical laws.</p><p>For example, if we use the red path in Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>, then the 0-cochain e 0 is selected as the state variable. The system state equation can be generated by composition of three steps starting with a 0-cochain e 0 of node potentials. First, the downward red arrow indicates that the node potentials give rise to voltage drops associated with incident branches using the coboundary operator v 1 = Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>: Paths corresponding to primal and dual cycle in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> δ 0 e 0 . The second lateral red arrow correspond to the constitutive relation</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">j 1 = G v 1 + v 1 f + j 1 f</formula><p>, which accounts for the contribution of 1-cochains of voltage sources v 1 f and source currents j 1 f in each branch of the electrical network. Finally, the upward vertical red arrow indicates the application of KCL ∂ 1 j 1 = 0 requiring that branch currents add up to zero. The composition of the three laws yields:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">∂ 1 G δ 0 e 0 + v 1 f + j 1 f = 0<label>(15)</label></formula><p>Eq.15 is usually written in a more traditional form as</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">∂ 1 G -δ 0 e 0 -v 1 f + j 1 f = 0<label>(16)</label></formula><p>As explained in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, the minus sign in front of δ 0 e 0 is due to the largely historical assumption that the vertices (0-cells) of the primal cell complex are oriented as sinks. The second minus sign in front of v 1 f signifies the fact that a (positive) voltage source should be subtracted from the (positive) voltage drop in every branch.</p><p>An alternative method for generating the system state equations follows the dual blue path in Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>. The process starts with the dual 2-cochain of mesh currents i 2 selected as the state variable and amounts to composition of the analogous three steps: boundary operator ∂ 2 applied to mesh currents in order to generate branch currents, constitutive Ohm's law R that relates the branch currents to voltage drops, and coboundary operator δ 1 applied to the voltage drops in accordance with KVL. Taking into account the voltage and current sources, the process results in:</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">δ 1 R(∂ 2 i 2 -j 1 f + v 1 f ) = 0<label>(17)</label></formula><p>Collecting the terms with known voltage and current sources and moving them to the right hand side, the system state equations Eq.16 and Eq.17 transform to Eq.18 and Eq.19, respectively.</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">∂ 1 Gδ 0 e 0 = ∂ 1 j 1 f -Gv 1 f (<label>18</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_20">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">δ 1 R∂ 2 i 2 = δ 1 -v 1 f + Rj 1 f (<label>19</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">)</formula><p>When boundary and cobounadry operators are replaced by the corresponding incidence matrices describing a cell complex underlying a specific lumped parameter system, the state equations become systems of linear equations that can be solved for the unknown state variables (node potentials e 0 and mesh currents i 2 respectively).  </p><formula xml:id="formula_23">R 1 = 6Ω, R 2 = 3Ω, R 3 = 2Ω, R 4 = 4Ω, two constant current sources C 1 s = 3A, C 4 s = 1A and two constant voltage sources V 1 s = 8V , V 4 s = 4V .</formula><p>Topologically, the network is a 2-dimensional complex shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">9b</ref> and consisting of three 0-cells (A,B,G), four 1cells(l 1 ,l 2 ,l 3 ,l 4 ) and two 2-cells(M 1 ,M 2 ).</p><p>The algebraic topological model of the electrical circuit contains: primal 0-cochain node potentials (e</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">0 = e A •A+e B •B +e G •G), primal 1-cochain voltage drops (v 1 = V 1 •l 1 +V 2 •l 2 +V 3 •l 3 +V 4 •l 4 ), dual 1-cochain of branch currents (j 1 = j 1 •l 1 +j 2 •l 2 +j 3 •l 3 +j 4 •l 4 ), dual 2-cochain of mesh currents (i 2 = i 1 • M 1 + i 2 • M 2 )</formula><p>and two cochains that are always 0: the dual 0-cochain of node currents and the primal 2-cochain of loop voltage drops. In order to get unique solution of the state equations, we consider 0-cell G as the reference node, implying the boundary condition of e G = 0. Following the red path on the Tonti diagram generates equation Eq.18 with individual terms as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">∂ 1 =   -1 -1 -1 0 0 0 +1 -1 +1 +1 0 +1   (<label>20</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_26">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_27">δ 0 = ∂ T 1 (21) G =     R -1 1 0 0 0 0 R -1 2 0 0 0 0 R -1 3 0 0 0 0 R -1 4     =     1/6 0 0 0 0 1/3 0 0 0 0 1/2 0 0 0 0 1/4    <label>(22)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_28">j 1 f = C 1 s 0 0 -C 4 s T = 3 0 0 -1 T (23) v 1 f = V 1 s 0 0 V 4 s T = 8 0 0 4 T<label>(24)</label></formula><p>Substituting Eq.20 ∼ Eq.24 into Eq.18 we obtain a linear system of equations that has the solution of e 0 = [-1/2, 7/3, 0] T . Once the 0-cochain node potentials e 0 is known, it is easy to obtain 1-cochain voltage drops v 1 and 1-cochain branch currents j 1 by using the topological equation v 1 = -δ 0 e 0 and the constitutive equation j 1 -j 1 f = G v 1 -v 1 f . Similarly following the blue path in the Tonti diagram, the generated system state equation Eq.19 would involve:</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">δ 1 = -1 +1 0 0 0 -1 +1 +1<label>(25)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_30">∂ 2 = δ 1 T (26) R =     R 1 0 0 0 0 R 2 0 0 0 0 R 3 0 0 0 0 R 4     =     6 0 0 0 0 3 0 0 0 0 2 0 0 0 0 4    <label>(27)</label></formula><p>Substituting Eq.23 ∼ Eq.27 into Eq.19, we obtain another system of linear equations that yields the solutions for the mesh currents i 2 = -19/12 -17/12</p><p>T . The 1-cochain branch currents j 1 and 1-cochain voltage drops v 1 are immediately obtained by applying the topological relation</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">j 1 = ∂ 2 i 2 and the constitutive equation v 1 -v 1 f = R j 1 -j 1 f .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Dynamic systems</head><p>In this section, we will extend the above approach to general dynamic electrical circuits. The algebraic topological structure of dynamic electrical circuits relies on cochains from all four cochain complexes modeled over a single cell complex. The topological and constitutive relations between these cochains are given by the diagram in Figure <ref type="figure">6b</ref> and eight different methods of generating the state equations are indicated by paths in the diagrams shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">10</ref>. Just as with static systems, each path is a sequence of the arrows indicating composition of the corresponding physical laws. In contrast to static systems, the middle horizontal section of the diagram allows three alternative (pink, purple and blue) paths relating the primal 1-cochain of voltage drops v 1 and the dual 1-cochain of branch currents j 1 corresponding to capacitance, resistance, and inductance constitutive relationship respectively. The presence of alternative paths indicate superposition of the corresponding equations generated by each path.</p><p>For example, if we use the paths in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">10a</ref> to generate the state equations, then the 0-cochain Ψ 0 is selected as the state variable. The system state equation can be generated by composition of five physical laws (two topological and three constitutive) starting with a 0-cochain Ψ 0 . First, coboundary operator in space δ 0 applied to potential magnetic fluxes Ψ 0 in order to generate magnetic fluxes Φ 1 . Now the path splits in two: the blue arrow corresponds to constitutive law L -1 (of the inductor) that relates the magnetic fluxes to branch currents of inductors; the pink arrow takes the magnetic fluxes to generate voltage drops v via the boundary operator in time ∂ t 1 . From here the path splits in two again: the purple arrow corresponds to the constitutive Ohm's law G that relates the voltage drops to branch currents of resistors; continuing along the pink path,  the constitutive capacitance law C relates the voltage drops to electric charges Q 1 of capacitors is followed by the time coboundary operator δ t 0 applied to electric charges of capacitors to generate branch currents of capacitors. Note that the three paths corresponding to the three constitutive laws merge into a single 1-cochain of branch currents j 1 , which is then transformed one more time by the upward green arrow corresponding to KCL ∂ 1 j 1 = 0. Taking into account the voltage and current sources, above processes results in following state equations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">∂ 1 δ t 0 C -∂ t 1 δ 0 Ψ 0 -v 1 f + R -1 -∂ t 1 δ 0 Ψ 0 -v 1 f + L -1 -δ 0 Ψ 0 -δ t 0 v 1 f + j 1 f = 0 (28)</formula><p>Collecting the terms with known voltage and current sources and moving them to the right hand side, the system state equations Eq.28 can be written in a more intuitive form as</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">∂ 1   δ t 0 C∂ t 1 δ 0 Ψ 0 currents of C + R -1 ∂ t 1 δ 0 Ψ 0 currents of R + L -1 δ 0 Ψ 0 currents of L   = ∂ 1         j 1 f current sources -δ t 0 C + R -1 + L -1 δ t 0 v 1 f equivalent current sources generated from voltage sources        <label>(29)</label></formula><p>Other methods for generating the system state equation follow the different paths in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">10b</ref> -Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">10h</ref>. For example, in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">10b</ref>, the process starts with the dual 2-cochain of mesh charge q 2 selected as the state variable and amounts to another composition of the five physical laws indicated by the corresponding paths. The blue, purple, and pink path corresponds to the three constitutive laws (capacitance, resistance, and inductance respectively), relating the branch electric charges to the branch voltage drops. The two green arrows correspond to the ∂ 2 operator transforming mesh charges q 2 to branch charges Q 1 and application of KVL (δ 1 v 1 = 0). Putting it all together and taking into account the voltage and current sources, the composition procedures results in:</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">δ 1 ∂ t 1 L δ t 0 ∂ 2 q 2 -j 1 f + R δ t 0 ∂ 2 q 2 -j 1 f + C -1 ∂ 2 q 2 -∂ t 1 j 1 f + v 1 f = 0 (30)</formula><p>or in a more intuitive form similar to Eq.29:</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">δ 1    ∂ t 1 Lδ t 0 ∂ 2 q 2 voltage drops of L + Rδ t 0 ∂ 2 q 2 voltage drops of R + C -1 ∂ 2 q 2 voltage drops of C    = δ 1        -v 1 f voltage sources + ∂ t 1 L + R + C -1 ∂ t 1 j 1 f equivalent voltage drops generated from current sources       <label>(31)</label></formula><p>It can be observed that Eq.29 and Eq.31 respectively represent the current and voltage equilibrium of the system. The generated system state equations may be viewed as algebraic with coboundary operators interpreted as finite difference operators on a finite cell complex. However, as we already observed, in lumped parameter systems space and time are treated separately, and discretization of time is often delayed until a particular numerical integration scheme is chosen. In this case, viewing boundary ∂ t 1 and coboundary δ t 0 operations as differentiation in time syntactically transforms Eq.29 and Eq.31 to a more familiar form:</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">∂ 1   Cδ 0 Ψ0 currents of C + R -1 δ 0 Ψ0 currents of R + L -1 δ 0 Ψ 0 currents of L   = ∂ 1           j 1 f current sources -C v1 f + R -1 v 1 f + L -1 v 1 f dt equivalent current sources generated from voltage sources          <label>(32)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_37">δ 1    L∂ 2 q2 voltage drops of C + R∂ 2 q2 voltage drops of R + C -1 ∂ 2 q 2 voltage drops of L    = δ 1          -v 1 f voltage sources + L j1 f + Rj 1 f + C -1 j 1 f dt equivalent voltage drops generated from current sources         <label>(33)</label></formula><p>Example 4.2 We will use a very simple example of RLC electrical circuit (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>) to illustrate the derivation of Eq.33. A copy of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref> is shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">11a</ref>. The shown electrical network </p><formula xml:id="formula_38">0 = ψ 1 •P 1 +ψ 2 •P 2 + ψ 3 • P 3 ), primal 1-cochain voltage drops (v 1 = v 1 • L 1 + v 2 • L 2 + v 3 • L 3 ), primal 1-cochain magnetic fluxes (Φ 1 = φ 1 • L 1 + φ 2 • L 2 + φ 3 • L 3 ), dual 1-cochain currents (j 1 = j 1 • L 1 + j 2 • L 2 + j 3 • L 3 ), dual 1-cochain electric charges (Q 1 = Q 1 • L 1 + Q 2 • L 2 + Q 3 • L 3 ), dual 2-cochain mesh currents (i 2 = i • M 1 )</formula><p>, dual 2-cochain mesh electric charges (q 2 = q • M 1 ), and four cochains that are always 0: 2-cochain loop voltage drops, 2-cochain loop magnetic fluxes, 0-cochain node currents and 0cochain of node electric charges. Following the paths in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">10b</ref> generates Eq.33, with individual terms as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">δ 1 = 1 1 1 (<label>34</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_40">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_41">∂ 2 = δ 1 T (35) L =   0 0 0 0 L 0 0 0 0   (36) R =   R 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0  <label>(37)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_42">C -1 =   0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 C -1   (38) v 1 f = -V s 0 0 T (<label>39</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_43">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_44">j 1 f = 0 0 0 T (<label>40</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_45">)</formula><p>Substituting Eq.34 ∼ Eq.40 into Eq.33, we obtain the system state equations as shown in Eq.41 . Since there is only one 2-cell, the mesh current equals the branch current, so Eq.41 is equivalent to the system state equation generated by the Simulink model shown in Eq.4.  </p><formula xml:id="formula_46">Lq + R q + C -1 q = V s<label>(41)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_47">Ψ 0 = ψ A • A + ψ B • B + ψ C • C + ψ G • G), primal 1-cochain voltage drops (v 1 = v 1 • l 1 + v 2 • l 2 + v 3 • l 3 + v 4 • l 4 + v 5 • l 5 ), primal 1-cochain magnetic fluxes (Φ 1 = φ 1 • l 1 + φ 2 • l 2 + φ 3 • l 3 ), dual 1-cochain currents (j 1 = j 1 • l 1 + j 2 • l 2 + j 3 • l 3 + j 4 • l 4 + j 5 • l 5 ), dual 1-cochain electric charges (Q 1 = Q 1 • l 1 + Q 2 • l 2 + Q 3 • l 3 + Q 4 • l 4 + Q 5 • l 5 ), dual 2-cochain mesh currents (i 2 = i 1 • M 1 + i 2 • M 2 ), dual 2-cochain mesh electric charges (q 2 = q 1 • M 1 + q 2 • M 2 )</formula><p>, and four cochains that are always 0: 2-cochain loop voltage drops, 2-cochain loop magnetic fluxes, 0-cochain node currents and 0-cochain of node electric charges. In order to get unique solution of the state equations, we consider 0-cell G as the reference node, implying the boundary condition of e G = 0. Following the paths in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">10a</ref>, generates Eq.32, with individual terms as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">∂ 1 =     +1 +1 0 0 +1 -1 -1 -1 0 0 0 0 +1 -1 0 0 0 0 +1 -1     (<label>42</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_49">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_50">δ 0 = ∂ T 1 (43) C =       C 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 C 5       (44) R -1 =       0 0 0 0 0 0 1/R 2 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0      <label>(45)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_51">L -1 =       0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 1/L 3 0 0 0 0 0 1/L 4 0 0 0 0 0 0       (46) v 1 f = V s 0 0 0 0 T (<label>47</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_53">j 1 f = C s 0 0 0 0 T (<label>48</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_54">)</formula><p>Substituting Eq.42 ∼ Eq.48 into Eq.32, we obtain the system state equations as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">    C 1 + C 5 -C 1 0 -C 5 -C 1 C 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 -C 5 0 0 C 5     Ψ0 +     1/R 2 -1/R 2 0 0 -1/R 2 1/R 2 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0     Ψ0 +     0 0 0 0 0 1/L 3 -1/L 3 0 0 -1/L 3 1/L 3 + 1/L 4 -1/L 4 0 0 -1/L 4 1/L 4     Ψ 0 =     C s -Vs C 1 -C s + Vs C 1 0 0     (49)</formula><p>5 Multi-domain lumped parameter systems</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Interactions of single-domain models</head><p>Engineering systems are usually constructed as compositions of single-domain subsystems in order to perform complex engineering tasks. Representative examples include electric motors (electromechanical systems), ovens (electro-thermal systems), hydraulic pumps (hydraulic-mechanical systems), etc. We will refer to such systems as multi-domain systems, where lumped-parameter behavior of each single-domain is governed by an extended Tonti diagram as described in the previous section. It should be understood that multi-domain systems subsume the special case of homogeneous systems where all single-domain systems are of the same type, e.g. all electrical or all mechanical. Composition of two single-domain systems is associated with the process of energy conversion between the two systems, also called transduction <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Specific means of transduction vary from system to system, but common examples of transducers (devices the perform transduction) include gears and levers, electrical transformers, motors, piezoelectric devices, hydraulic pumps, and so on. Devices used to couple the same type variables of different physical domains are usually called transformers (e.g. electrical transformers), while devices coupling the dual type variables are called gyrators (e.g. electric motors) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Physical transformers and gyrators always have energy loss during the energy transduction, but if the leakage is small enough then the energy loss is usually neglected during modeling. Transformers and gyrators with no energy loss are called ideal transformers and gyrators <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. System modeling languages generally use ideal transformers and gyrators as abstract constructs in order to avoid modeling complex structures of physical transformers and gyrators devices. For instance, bond graphs use abstract 2-port transformers and gyrators which can be used to connect any 1-ports <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">13</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">14</ref> show several transformer and gyrator models from different system modeling languages.  Such abstract transformers and gyrators in each language can represent hundreds of complex transformer and gyrator devices. For example, Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_16">15</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">16</ref> show two examples of multidomain models represented by different modeling languages. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_16">15</ref> is an example of a homogeneous multi-domain system, where all sub-domains are electrical domains. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">16</ref> is an example of a heterogeneous multi-domain system, where one electrical domain and one mechanical domain are connected by a DC motor.</p><p>In our proposed combinatorial model of lumped parameter systems, physical transducer devices can be abstracted by additional relations between primal and dual variables in each of the subsystems; such relations may be governed by additional constitutive, interaction, or conservation constrains imposed on the multi-domain system <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref>. For example, consider the three-domain In principle, such a representation is sufficient for capturing the behavior of a multi-domain system. Each Tonti diagram corresponds to a system of ordinary differential equations that are coupled by the transducer constraints. When the constraints are algebraic, this representation corresponds to the usual system of differential-algebraic equations. More complex transducer relationships may involve multiple physical variables as well as non-linear and differential constraints <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>, resulting in more complex models of behaviors.</p><p>However, this representation neither recognizes nor takes advantage of the fact that all singledomain behaviors are isomorphic, which allows to treat the whole multi-domain system as a collection of four constrained cochain complexes on a single cell complex model. Below we will define such a model, which takes a form of a generalized Tonti diagram. We then show that, in the presence of two most common transducers: ideal transformers and gyrators, the governing equations for such a model may be generated by following the paths on the generalized Tonti diagram. This results extends the result of Section 3 to multi-domain lumped parameter systems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Generalized Tonti diagram for multi-domain systems</head><p>Since lumped parameter models in different physical domain are isomorphic, so are their corresponding Tonti diagrams. In this sense, a single Tonti diagram describes behavior of all lumped parameter systems, provided that the variable of the same space-time type are identified and generalized.</p><p>Two most common generalizations are mechanical (generalized displacement-force model) and electrical (generalized voltage-current model). For the sake of consistency with the discussion in section 4, we will adopt the generalized electrical model. For example, the electrical voltage, mechanical translational velocity and hydraulic pressure difference are all considered to be of the same type called the generalized voltage; the electrical resistors, mechanical dampers and hydraulic resistors are all identified as generalized resistors, and so on. In order to emphasize the generalized nature of all physical quantities and to distinguish them from the actual physical electrical network model, we will choose a different set of symbols. Specifically, the generalized Tonti diagram is defined by four exact cochain sequences on a single cell complex: Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">16</ref>: Different models of a DC motor primal :</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">p 0 δ 0 -→ a 1 δ 1 -→ 0 2<label>(50)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_57">d 0 δ 0 -→ u 1 δ 1 -→ 0 2<label>(51)</label></formula><p>dual :</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">s 2 ∂ 2 -→ t 1 ∂ 1 -→ 0 0<label>(52)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_59">n 2 ∂ 2 -→ m 1 ∂ 1 -→ 0 0 ,<label>(53)</label></formula><p>where p 0 is a 0-cochain generalized potentials, a 1 is a 1-cochain generalized voltages, d 0 is a 0cochain generalized potential magnetic fluxes, u 1 is a 1-cochain generalized magnetic fluxes, s 2 is a 2-cochain generalized mesh currents, t 1 is a 1-cochain generalized currents, n 2 is 2-cochain generalized mesh charges, and m 1 is a 1-cochain generalized electric charges. There are also four cochains that are always 0: 2-cochain of generalized mesh magnetic fluxes, 2-cochain of generalized mesh voltages, 0-cochain of generalized node currents and 0-cochain of generalized node electric charges.</p><p>With such a generalization, all the physical variables of the same space-time type are replaced by their generalized counterparts, effectively transforming model of the heterogeneous multi-domain </p><formula xml:id="formula_60">Q h -flow of volume, f -flow rate, L h -hydraulic inductance, R h -hydraulic resistance, C h -hydraulic capacitance.</formula><p>ht and kt are transformer modulus. kt is the ratio of relative rotational velocity of motor to voltage drop and ht is the ratio of torque to current. hg and kg are gyrator modulus. kg is the ratio of flow rate to relative rotational velocity of motor and hg is the ratio of pressure drop to torque.</p><p>system in an abstract (generalized) homogeneous system. The behavior of this system is governed by the generalized Tonti diagram shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_19">18</ref>. As before, the generalized primal and dual cochains are related by (generalized) constitutive relations: resistance R g , capacitance C g , and inductance L g .</p><p>Furthermore, since all physical quantities are generalized, the actions of ideal transformers and gyrators can be modeled simply as additional constraints on the cochains in the generalized Tonti diagram. Traditionally, a transformer is abstracted as a linear transformation</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">a 1 t 1 = k t 0 0 1/k t a 2 t 2<label>(54)</label></formula><p>where k t is the transformer's modulus measuring the ratio between two (generalized) voltages a 1 and a 2 , as well as the reciprocal ratio between the generalized currents t 1 and t 2 in order to enforce energy balance a 1 t 1 = a 2 t 2 . It is easy to see that the same relationships may be enforced by a pair of linear constraints</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">1 -k t • a 1 a 2 T = 0 1 -k -1 t • t 1 t 2 T = 0<label>(55)</label></formula><p>Generalizing, every ideal transformer can be represented by a pair of linear constraints</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">k t a = 0; k t t = 0</formula><p>on cochains of generalized voltages a and currents t. These constraints are indicated on the generalized Tonti diagram in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_19">18</ref> by two cycles. Similarly, the effect of an abstract gyrator is usually described by a linear transformation</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">a 1 a 2 = 0 k g k g 0 t 1 t 2<label>(56)</label></formula><p>where the modulus k g relates the dual quantities in two interacting domains: generalized voltage a 1 of the first domain is proportional to the generalized current t 2 of the second domain, and vice versa, again satisfying the ideal energy balance law. Equivalently, a generalized gyrator may be represented by a linear transformation k g that relates the cochains of generalized voltages and currents, as indicated by a dotted arrow in the Tonti diagram in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_19">18</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">System state equations of multi-domain systems</head><p>With all physical variables generalized, the heterogeneous multi-domain system now becomes a homogeneous multi-domain system in terms of generalized physical variables. Instead of multiple 2-cochain complexes associated with different types of physical variables, the algebraic topological model of the multi-domain system is now a set of 2-cochain complexes associated with the same (generalized) type of physical variables that are defined over a single cell complex and are constrained by abstract transformers and gyrators. Eight different methods of generating the state equations are indicated by paths in the generalized Tonti diagram shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_21">19</ref>. Just as with the single domain systems, each path is a sequence of the arrows indicating composition of the corresponding physical laws. In contrast to the single domain diagram, the middle horizontal section of the generalized Tonti diagram allows an additional alternative path relating the primal 1-cochain of generalized voltages a 1 and the dual 1-cochain of generalized currents t 1 by gyrators as well as two alternative cyclic paths (shown in red), which respectively constrain the generalized voltages and currents of transformers.</p><p>For example, if we use the paths in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_21">19a</ref> to generate the state equations, then the 0-cochain d 0 is selected as the state variable. The system state equation can be generated by composition  g that relates generalized voltages to generalized currents of generalized resistors; (2) the brown arrow corresponds to the constitutive law k -1 g that relates generalized voltages to generalized currents of gyrators; (3) the left red cyclic arrow corresponds to constitutive law k t that constrains the generalized voltages of generalized transformers; (4) the pink arrow takes the generalized voltages to generate generalized electric charge of generalized capacitors by using constitutive law C g , followed by taking the generalized electric charge to generate generalized currents of generalized capacitors via the coboundary operator in time δ t 0 . Note that these four paths and the right red cyclic path<ref type="foot" target="#foot_5">foot_5</ref> corresponding to five constitutive laws merge into a single 1-cochain of generalized through variables t 1 , which is then transformed one more time by the upward green arrow corresponding to KCL ∂ 1 t 1 = 0. Taking into account the generalized sources, collecting the terms with known generalized sources and moving them to the right hand side, above procedure results in the state equation Eq.57, with Eq.58 and Eq.59 being the constraint equations generated from two cyclic red paths.</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">∂ 1       δ t 0 C g ∂ t 1 δ 0 d 0 generalized currents of generalized C + R -1 g ∂ t 1 δ 0 d 0 generalized currents of generalized R + L -1 g δ 0 d 0 generalized currents of generalized L + k -1 g ∂ t 1 δ 0 d 0 generalized currents of gyrators + t 1 T generalized currents of transformers       = ∂ 1         t 1 f generalized currents sources -δ t 0 C g + R -1 g + k -1 g + L -1 g δ t 0 a 1 f equivalent generalized current sources generated from generalized voltage sources         (57) k t ∂ t 1 δ 0 d 0 -a 1 f = 0 (<label>58</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_66">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_67">k t t 1 -t 1 f = 0<label>(59)</label></formula><p>Assuming that the number of state variables is N and the number of transformers is M, then the system of equations Eq.57 has N+2M unknowns. The two transformer's constraints generate 2M constraint equations, while the other paths generate N state equations. As expected, the number of unknowns equals to the total number of state and constraint equations.</p><p>Other methods for generating the system state equation follow the different paths in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_21">19b</ref> ∼ Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_21">19h</ref>. For example, in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_21">19b</ref>, the process starts with the dual 2-cochain of generalized mesh electric charges n 2 selected as the state variable and amounts to another composition of the seven physical laws indicated by the corresponding paths. The blue, purple, pink and brown path corresponds to the four generalized constitutive laws (generalized capacitance, resistance, inductance and gyrator), relating the generalized currents to generalized voltages. The two green arrows correspond to the ∂ 2 operator transforming n 2 to generalized electric charges m 1 and application of KVL (δ 1 a 1 = 0). The two red cyclic arrows correspond to the constitutive equations of transformers. Putting it all together and taking into account the generalized sources, the composition procedures results in Eq.60 , with Eq.61 and Eq.62 being the constraint equations generated from two cyclic red paths.</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">δ 1       ∂ t 1 L g δ t 0 ∂ 2 n 2 generalized voltages of generalized L + R g δ t 0 ∂ 2 n 2 generalized voltages of generalized R + C -1 g ∂ 2 n 2 generalized voltages of generalized C + k g δ t 0 ∂ 2 n 2 generalized voltages of gyrators + a 1 T generalized voltages of transformers       = δ 1         -a 1 f generalized voltages sources + ∂ t 1 L g + R g + k g + C -1 g ∂ t 1 t 1 f equivalent generalized voltage sources generated from generalized current sources         (60) k t δ t 0 ∂ 2 n 2 -t 1 f = 0 (61) k t a 1 -a 1 f = 0<label>(62)</label></formula><p>As with any dynamic system, interpreting boundary ∂ t 1 and coboundary δ t 0 operations as differentiation in time syntactically transforms Eq. 57 ∼ Eq.59 and Eq.60 ∼ Eq.62 to a more familiar form:</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">∂ 1       C g δ 0 d0 generalized currents of generalized C + R -1 g δ 0 ḋ0 generalized currents of generalized R + L -1 g δ 0 d 0 generalized currents of generalized L + k -1 g δ 0 ḋ0</formula><p>generalized currents of gyrators</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">+ t 1 T generalized currents of transformers       = ∂ 1           t 1 f generalized current sources -C g ȧ1 f + R -1 g a 1 f + k -1 g a 1 f + L -1 g a 1 f dt equivalent generalized current sources generated from generalized voltage sources           (63) k t δ 0 ḋ0 -a 1 f = 0 (<label>64</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_71">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_72">k t t 1 -t 1 f = 0 (65) δ 1       L g ∂ 2 n2 generalized voltages of generalized L + R g ∂ 2 ṅ2 generalized voltages of generalized R + C -1 g ∂ 2 n 2 generalized voltages of generalized C + k g ∂ 2 ṅ2</formula><p>generalized voltages of gyrators</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">+ a 1 T generalized voltages of transformers       = δ 1           -a 1 f generalized voltages sources + L g ṫ1 f + R g t 1 f + k g t 1 f + C -1 g t 1 f dt equivalent generalized voltage sources generated from generalized current sources           (66) k t ∂ 2 ṅ2 -t 1 f = 0 (67) k t a 1 -a 1 f = 0<label>(68)</label></formula><p>Example 5.1 We will use an example of multi-domain electrical-mechanical system in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_23">20a</ref> to illustrate the derivation of Eq.63 and Eq.66 . The shown electrical-mechanical system contains two resistors R 1 , R 2 , one capacitor C 1 , one inductor L 1 , one voltage source V s , one moment of inertia J, one external torque τ , one electrical transformer and one DC motor. The transformer between two electrical domains is an ideal electrical transformer, where the ratio of voltage drops (currents) equals the ratio (inverse ratio) of the winding numbers N 1 /N 2 ; the gyrator between the electrical and the mechanical domain is an ideal DC motor, where the ratio (inverse ratio) of the voltage drop (current) and the rotational velocity (torque) is a constant number k g . Topologically, the system is a 2-cell complex shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_23">20b</ref>, and consisted of nine 0-cells (P 1 ,P 2 ,P 3 ,P 4 ,P 5 ,P 6 ,P 7 ,P 8 ,P 9 ), nine 1-cells</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">(L R 1 ,L C 1 ,L T L ,L T R , L R 2 ,L L 1 ,L GL ,L GR ,L J ) and three 2-cells (M 1 ,M 2 ,M<label>3</label></formula><p>). We use  </p><formula xml:id="formula_75">= u 1 • L R 1 + u 2 • L C 1 + u 3 • L T L + u 4 • L T R + u 5 • L R 2 + u 6 • L L 1 + u 7 • L GL + u 8 • L GR + u 9 • L J ), primal 1-cochain generalized voltages (a 1 = a 1 • L R 1 + a 2 • L C 1 + a T L • L T L + a T R • L T R + a 5 • L R 2 + a 6 • L L 1 + a GL • L GL + a GR • L GR + a 9 • L J ), dual 1-cochain generalized currents (t 1 = t 1 • L R 1 + t 2 • L C 1 + t T L • L T L + t T R • L T R + t 5 • L R 2 + t 6 • L L 1 + t GL • L GL + t GR • L GR + t 9 • L J ), dual 1-cochain generalized electric charges (m 1 = m 1 •L R 1 +m 2 •L C 1 +m T L •L T L +m T R •L T R +m 5 •L R 2 +m 6 •L L 1 +m GL •L GL +m GR •L GR +m 9 •L J ), dual 2-cochain generalized mesh electric charges n 2 = n 1 •M 1 +n 2 •M 2 +n 3 •M 3 , dual 2-cochain generalized mesh currents s 2 = s 1 • M 1 + s 2 • M 2 + s 3 • M 3</formula><p>and four cochains that are always 0: 2-cochain of generalized mesh magnetic fluxes, 2-cochain of generalized mesh voltages, 0-cochain of generalized node currents and 0-cochain of generalized node electric charges. In order to obtain unique solution of the state equations, we consider 0-cells P 1 , P 7 and P 9 as the reference node. Following the paths shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_21">19a</ref>, generates Eq.63 ∼ Eq.65, with individual terms as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">∂ 1 =               -1 0 +1 0 0 0 0 0 0 +1 -1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 +1 -1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 +1 -1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 +1 -1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 +1 -1 0 0 0 0 0 -1 0 0 +1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 +1 -1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 -1 +1              <label>(69)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_77">δ 0 = ∂ T 1 (<label>70</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_78">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_79">C g =              </formula><p>C g 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_80">             <label>(71)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_81">R -1 g =               0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 R -1 g 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 R -1 g 2 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0              <label>(72)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_82">L -1 g =               0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 L -1 g 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 L -1 g 2               (73) k -1 g =              </formula><p>0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 k -1 g 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 k -1 g 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_83">             <label>(74)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_84">k t = 0 0 1 -N 1 /N 2 0 0 0 0 0 (75) k t = 0 0 1 -N 2 /N 1 0 0 0 0 0 (76) t 1 T = 0 0 t T L t T R 0 0 0 0 0 T (77) a 1 f = 0 -a f 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 -a f 2 T (78) t 1 f = [0] 9×1<label>(79)</label></formula><p>Substitute Eq.69 ∼ Eq.79 to Eq.63 ∼ Eq.65, the generated system state equation is as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">                                                                                          </formula><p>C g 1 -C g 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 -C g 1 C g 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">              d0 +                0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 R -1 g 1 -R -1 g 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 -R -1 g 1 R -1 g 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 R -1 g 2 -R -1 g 2 -k -1 g k -1 g 0 0 0 0 0 -R -1 g 2 R -1 g 2 k -1 g -k -1 g 0 0 0 0 0 -k -1 g k -1 g 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 k -1 g -k -1 g 0 0                ḋ0 +               0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 L -1 g 1 -L -1 g 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 -L -1 g 1 L -1 g 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 L -1 g 2 -L -1 g 2 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 -L -1 g 2 L -1 g 2               d 0 +               t T L 0 -t T L t T R 0 0 -t T R 0 0               =               0 -R -1 g 1 a f 1 R -1 g 1 a f 1 0 0 0 0 -L -1 g 2 a f 2 dt L -1 g 2 a f 2 dt               ḋ0 (3) -ḋ0<label>(1)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_87">ḋ0 (7) -ḋ0 (4) = N 1 /N 2 t T L /t T R = N 2 /N 1<label>(80)</label></formula><p>Similarly following the paths in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_21">19b</ref>, generates Eq.66 ∼ Eq.68, with individual terms as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_88">δ 1 =   +1 +1 +1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 +1 +1 +1 +1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 +1 +1   (81) ∂ 2 = δ 1 T (82) δ 1 L g ∂ 2 = δ 1              </formula><p>0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 L g 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_89">L g 2               ∂ 2 =   0 0 0 0 L g 1 0 0 0 L g 2   (83) δ 1 R g ∂ 2 = δ 1              </formula><p>0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 R g 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 R g 2 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_90">              ∂ 2 =   R g 1 0 0 0 R g 2 0 0 0 0  <label>(84)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_91">δ 1 C -1 g ∂ 2 = δ 1               C -1</formula><p>g 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_92">              ∂ 2 =   C -1 g 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0   (85) δ 1 k g ∂ 2 = δ 1              </formula><p>0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 k g 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 k g 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_93">              ∂ 2 =   0 0 0 0 0 k g 0 k g 0   (86) δ 1 a 1 T = δ 1 0 0 a T L a T R 0 0 0 0 0 T =   a T L a T R 0  <label>(87)</label></formula><p>Substitute Eq.75 ∼ Eq.79, Eq.81 ∼ Eq.87 to Eq.66 ∼ Eq.68, the generated system state equation is as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_94">               0 0 0 0 L g 1 0 0 0 L g 2   n2 +   R g 1 0 0 0 R g 2 k g 0 k g 0   ṅ2 +   C -1 g 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0   n 2 +   a T L a T R 0   =   a f 1 0 a f 2   a T L /a T L = N 1 /N 2 ṅ2<label>(1)</label></formula><p>ṅ2</p><p>(2) = N 2 /N 1 (88)</p><p>6 Conclusion</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Summary and significance</head><p>Formal semantics of engineering models is a principal ingredient of rigorous and algorithmic foundations for model-based systems engineering. Standardizing on such a semantics is also a key to solving widespread interchangeability and interoperability challenges that arise with rapid proliferation of model-based engineering language and tools. In this paper, we proposed a formal semantics for a large and important class of lumped-parameter systems that are widely used for systems engineering, physical modeling, and design activities. The proposed semantics relies only on standard tools from algebraic topology and known results in classification of physical theories and systems. The semantics is effectively 'representation free' in that it is independent of specific implementation assumptions, coordinates, linguistic constructs, or numerical simulation schemes. We showed that (extended and generalized) Tonti diagrams provide a canonical method for representing behaviors of lumped parameter systems computationally. Based on known classification of physical theories, behavior of any lumped parameter system may be described either as a collection of interacting single-domain Tonti diagrams or as a single generalized Tonti diagram with energy transduction represented by additional constraints. In other words, a Tonti diagram can be viewed as a representation scheme and a data structure for representing most known physical behaviors. We have also seen that this representation supports algorithmic generation of all possible forms of the governing state equations as paths in the (collection of) Tonti diagrams. The topological and constitutive operators appear as labels on the edges of the diagram and may be interpreted either symbolically, giving differential equations, or numerically (e.g. as finite difference operators), corresponding to executable approximations of such models.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Interchangeability and interoperability</head><p>Achieving greater interoperability of lumped parameter systems tools and languages was the main motivation for developing the proposed canonical semantic model. The existence of common semantics implies that all compliant models become fully interchangeable irrespective of specific syntax or modeling concepts adapted in a particular simulation tool. The representation of this semantics using the corresponding Tonti diagrams can serve as a formal neutral format for exchange of all such models. Furthermore, this representation supports exchange not only of the system models but also of the adapted simulation approaches in individual systems, now represented as paths in the corresponding Tonti diagrams. In practical terms, the existence of the common semantic model also eliminates the need for customized point-to-point translators or new super-languages attempting to subsume and unify currently existing tools. New compatible languages and modeling tools, for example in SysML, could be developed rigorously and rapidly, as long as they adhere to the adapted semantic model.</p><p>While model translation and exchange is a widely adapted and practiced in industry, it is a rather limited form of interoperability. When distinct tools and languages are based on a common reference semantics, they should be able to interoperate directly in a truly object-oriented fashion, where distinct portions of the system models are represented and simulated in different tools. This would allow better protection of proprietary models and fine-tuning selection of tools that are most appropriate for specific modeling tasks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3">Open issues and promising directions</head><p>The semantic model proposed in this paper provides a foundation and a starting point for developing a more general semantic framework for modeling behavior of physical systems. In particular, the strongly-typed classification of physical theories and their representation by Tonti diagrams tacitly assumes that the constructed models are subject to energy balance laws. The majority of lumped-parameter system models satisfy this assumption. However, many modeling systems support numerous additional operations and constructs, such as signal flows and arbitrary mathematical transformations, that are not necessarily based on first principles. Whether and how such constructs should be included in the common semantics model is not entirely clear. In principle, they could be treated as special cases of energetic processes (as, for example, is advocated in bond graph literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>), or they may require introduction of additional types of constraints to the underlying topological model.</p><p>In this paper we focused on lumped parameter systems that are intrinsically two-dimensional and devoid of geometry. However, both classification of physical theories and Tonti diagrams span the entire spectrum of full-dimensional physical models and behaviors. This implies that the proposed formal semantic model can be extended to all spatially distributed models whose behavior is commonly described by integral and partial differential equations. In fact, developing a semantics model for an single-domain physical model whose behavior is described by a known Tonti diagram is a straightforward task that would follow the development in Section 4 of this paper. Different paths on such a diagram would correspond to different methods to generate governing equations; replacing symbolic operators by numerical approximations yields rich variety of standard numerical simulation methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[68,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">72,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">64]</ref>. However, in contrast to lumped parameter systems that are all isomorphic, spatially distributed models are heterogeneous in their dimension, type of variables, and topological structures. Interaction, composition, and transformation of such Tonti diagrams and the systems they represent remain active open research issues.</p><p>Treating the common semantic model and its representation by Tonti diagrams as the first class objects, that explicitly represent physical behaviors, opens up a number of promising and exciting opportunities in computational design and model-based engineering. Algorithmic construction, editing, composition, and transformation of such models would support a broad range of design engineering activities, from concept generation to detailed system modeling. Because many such engineering activities are performed using SysML, it may be reasonable to expect that Tonti diagrams should appear as one of the standard diagrams in SysML in the near future. Such a diagram would provide immediate support for including physical behaviors and their simulation into a broad range of model-based systems engineering activities.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Comparison of different physical modeling languages for a simple electrical circuit problem</figDesc><graphic coords="5,307.82,330.13,187.20,86.62" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Categorization of physical variables category in different approaches to physical modeling</figDesc><graphic coords="10,72.00,72.00,468.00,232.77" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Tonti Diagram of network theory -constitutive equations are modified to account for voltage and current sources</figDesc><graphic coords="11,189.00,72.00,234.00,191.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :Figure 5 :</head><label>45</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Cell complexes model of time</figDesc><graphic coords="12,177.30,72.00,257.41,91.10" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 6: Extended Tonti diagram for RLC network system -with voltage and current sources</figDesc><graphic coords="13,95.40,77.20,187.20,193.23" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7: Dual cochain complexes on a single cell complex</figDesc><graphic coords="14,118.80,151.84,374.40,159.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a) An electrical circuit of pure resistance (b) Topological structure</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9: An electrical circuit of pure resistance and its topological structure</figDesc><graphic coords="17,364.50,138.29,117.00,123.09" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a) State variable: Ψ 0 (b) State variable: q 2 (c) State variable: e 0 (d) State variable: i 2 (e) State variable: j 1 (f) State variable: Φ 1 (g) State variable: Q 1 (h) State variable: v 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10: State equation generation paths on the extended Tonti diagram</figDesc><graphic coords="19,191.86,212.81,112.32,115.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 11 :</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11: A simple RLC electrical circuit and its topological structure</figDesc><graphic coords="21,118.80,72.00,140.40,124.11" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a) An RLC electrical circuit (b) Topological structure</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 12 :</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 12: An RLC electrical circuit and its topological structure</figDesc><graphic coords="22,142.20,163.79,187.19,123.37" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a) A schematic ideal electrical transformer (b) Bond graph model of transformers (c) Linear graph model of transformers (d) Modelica model of the ideal electrical transformer</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure 13 :</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Figure 13: Comparison of transformers of different modeling languages</figDesc><graphic coords="24,307.82,438.56,229.32,62.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Figure 14 :</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Figure 14: Comparison of gyrators of different modeling languages</figDesc><graphic coords="25,133.34,204.58,112.37,88.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Figure 15 :</head><label>15</label><figDesc>Figure 15: Different models of a multi-domain RLC electrical circuit</figDesc><graphic coords="26,74.86,332.23,229.32,128.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a) A schematic DC motor (b) Bond graph model<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> (c) Linear graph model<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> (d) Modelica model (e) Simulink model<ref type="bibr" target="#b68">[69]</ref> </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Figure 17 :</head><label>17</label><figDesc>Figure 17: Behavior of three-domain system, a hydraulic pump driven by electrical motor, is abstracted by relations between three interacting extended Tonti diagrams. Commonly-used physical variables in the Tonti diagram of rotational mechanical networks: θ -angle, θr -relative angle, ω -rotational velocity, ωr -relative rotational velocity, τ -torque, M -angular momentum, K -rotational stiffness, D -rotational damping coefficient and J -moment of inertia. Commonly-used physical variables in the Tonti diagram of hydraulic networks: Ψ h -potential of hydraulic flux, Φ h -hydraulic flux, p -pressure, pr -pressure drop,</figDesc><graphic coords="28,72.00,72.00,468.00,164.51" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Figure 18 :</head><label>18</label><figDesc>Figure 18: Generalized extended Tonti diagram for generalized RLC network system</figDesc><graphic coords="29,331.82,72.00,187.20,198.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a) State variable: d 0 (b) State variable: n 2 (c) State variable: p 0 (d) State variable: s 2 (e) State variable: u 1 (f) State variable: m 1 (g) State variable: a 1 (h) State variable: t 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>Figure 19 :</head><label>19</label><figDesc>Figure 19: State equation generation paths on the generalized extended Tonti diagram</figDesc><graphic coords="30,82.92,208.32,112.32,114.93" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a) A multi-domain electro-mechanical system (b) Topological structure</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23"><head>Figure 20 :</head><label>20</label><figDesc>Figure 20: An electro-mechanical system and its topological structure</figDesc><graphic coords="33,177.30,189.54,257.40,85.53" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Analogy of physical variables is determined by initial conditions. To be concrete, let us briefly compare how such languages would be used to model a simple example of a serial RLC electrical circuit shown in Figure</figDesc><table><row><cell>Variables type</cell><cell>Effort</cell><cell>Flow</cell><cell>Momentum</cell><cell>Displacement</cell></row><row><cell>Mechanical (translation)</cell><cell>Force</cell><cell>Velocity</cell><cell>Momentum</cell><cell>Displacement</cell></row><row><cell>Mechanical (rotational)</cell><cell>Torque</cell><cell cols="2">Angular velocity Angular momentum</cell><cell>Angle</cell></row><row><cell>Electrical</cell><cell>Voltage</cell><cell>Current</cell><cell>Flux linkage variable</cell><cell>Charge</cell></row><row><cell>Hydraulic</cell><cell cols="3">Pressure Volume flow rate Pressure momentum</cell><cell>Volume</cell></row></table><note><p>that</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Such correspondence may take a form of direct translation or using APIs.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>This is in stark contrast to spatially distributed physical phenomena modeled governed by partial differential equation where geometry of cells becomes critical.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_2"><p>The cochain sequence is exact if it satisfies δp • δp-1 = 0 (p ≥ 1)</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_3"><p>This observation also justifies use of ∂p operator, usually reserved for p-chains, on p-cochains</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_4"><p>Strictly speaking, use ∂p operators give rise to chain complexes, but it should be clear that these chain complexes on the primal cell complex are isomorphic to the cochain complexes over the dual cell complex.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_5"><p>Note that the generalized currents of transformers t 1 T cannot be directly obtained from the generalized voltages of transformers a 1 T , so we treat them as additional unknown variables in the system state equation.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors would like to thank <rs type="person">Conrad Bock</rs> for numerous discussions and encouragement. This research was supported in part by the <rs type="funder">National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST)</rs> under cooperative agreement <rs type="grantNumber">70NANB14H248</rs>, by <rs type="funder">NSF</rs> grants <rs type="grantNumber">CMMI-1344205</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">CMMI-1361862</rs>, and <rs type="grantNumber">CMMI-1547189</rs>, and by <rs type="funder">Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency's FUNdamental Design Program</rs>. The responsibility for errors and omissions lies solely with the authors.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_SFp9Kt5">
					<idno type="grant-number">70NANB14H248</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_zghUcqw">
					<idno type="grant-number">CMMI-1344205</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_2qgPq9q">
					<idno type="grant-number">CMMI-1361862</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_Y8CkVEf">
					<idno type="grant-number">CMMI-1547189</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Dynamic systems: modeling, simulation, and control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Craig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kluever</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Analysis and design of engineering systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Paynter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1961">1961</date>
			<publisher>MIT press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Derek</forename><surname>Rowell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Wormley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">System dynamics: an introduction</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An introduction to the physical modeling language modelica</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hilding</forename><surname>Elmqvist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sven</forename><surname>Erik Mattsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 9th European Simulation Symposium</title>
		<meeting>the 9th European Simulation Symposium</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Citeseer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="23" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Modeling and simulation of systems using MATLAB and Simulink</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Devendra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Chaturvedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Donald</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Dean C Karnopp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ronald</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Margolis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rosenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">System dynamics: a unified approach</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modelica -a unified object-oriented language for system modeling and simulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Fritzson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vadim</forename><surname>Engelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ECOOP98 -Object-Oriented Programming</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="90" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dingyü</forename><surname>Xue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yangquan</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">System simulation techniques with Matlab and Simulink</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bond graphs and linear graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alan</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Perelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">George</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Oster</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Franklin Institute</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">302</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="185" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">System dynamics: modeling, simulation, and control of mechatronic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Donald</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Dean C Karnopp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ronald</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Margolis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rosenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An extension of the systems modeling language for physical interaction and signal flow simulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Conrad</forename><surname>Bock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Raphael</forename><surname>Barbau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ion</forename><surname>Matei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mehdi</forename><surname>Dadfarnia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Systems Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="395" to="431" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional mockup interface (fmi) for model exchange</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Otter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Modelica Newsletter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On the formal structure of physical theories. Istituto di matematica del Politecnico di Milano</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Enzo</forename><surname>Tonti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Enzo</forename><surname>Tonti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The mathematical structure of classical and relativistic physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An application of algebraic topology to numerical analysis: On the existence of a solution to the network problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Roth</forename><surname>Paul</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">521</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1955">1955</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The algebraic-topological basis for network analogies and the vector calculus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Franklin H Branin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Symposium on generalized networks</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="453" to="491" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Diakoptics: the piecewise solution of large-scale systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gabriel Kron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1963">1963</date>
			<publisher>MacDonald</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the mathematical classification of physical quantities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Clerk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maxwell</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Scientific Papers of James Clerk Maxwell</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Niven</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1890">1890</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="266" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the geometrical representation of elementary physical objects and the relations between geometry and physics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Van Dantzig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nieuw Archief voor Wiskunde</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="89" />
			<date type="published" when="1954">1954</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>II</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Course in Mathematics for Students of Physics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Bamberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Schlomo</forename><surname>Sternberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988. 1990</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, England</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oscillographic solution of electro-mechanical systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nickle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transactions of the American Institute of Electrical Engineers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="844" to="856" />
			<date type="published" when="1925">1925</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Olson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Dynamical Analogies. Van Nostrand</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Princeton</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1943">1943</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Numerical solution of ordinary and partial differential equations by means of equivalent circuits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gabriel Kron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="172" to="186" />
			<date type="published" when="1945-03">March 1945</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diakoptics -The Piecewise Solution of Large-Scale Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gabriel Kron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A series of 20 articles beginning</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1957-06-07">June 7, 1957</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1957" to="1959" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The algebraic-topological basis for network analogies and the vector calculus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Franklin</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Branin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Symposium on Generalized Networks</title>
		<meeting>the Symposium on Generalized Networks<address><addrLine>Brooklyn, New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="453" to="491" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An application of algebraic topology to numerical analysis: On the existence of a solution to the network problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="518" to="521" />
			<date type="published" when="1955">1955</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chain models of physical behavior for engineering analysis and design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Richard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vadim</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Shapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research in Engineering Design</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3-4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="184" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chain-based representations for solid and physical modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Antonio</forename><surname>Dicarlo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Franco</forename><surname>Milicchio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alberto</forename><surname>Paoluzzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vadim</forename><surname>Shapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="454" to="467" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linear algebraic representation for topological structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Antonio</forename><surname>Dicarlo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alberto</forename><surname>Paoluzzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vadim</forename><surname>Shapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer-Aided Design</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="269" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Combinatorial laws for physically meaningful design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vasu</forename><surname>Ramaswamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vadim</forename><surname>Shapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-03">March 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A multivector data structure for differential forms and equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jeffrey</forename><surname>Chard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vadim</forename><surname>Shapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mathematics and Computers in Simulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chain models in computer simulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Egli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Neil</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stewart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mathematics and Computers in Simulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="468" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manufacturing Systems Theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Oyvind</forename><surname>Bjorke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<publisher>Akademika Pub</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Analysis and Design of Engineering Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Paynter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1961">1961</date>
			<publisher>The M.I.T. Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Analysis of discrete physical systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Herman E Koenig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tokad</forename><surname>Yelmaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hiremaglur K Kesavan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cláudio</forename><surname>Gomes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Casper</forename><surname>Thule</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Broman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Gorm Larsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hans</forename><surname>Vangheluwe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1702.00686</idno>
		<title level="m">Co-simulation: State of the art</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A practical guide to SysML: the systems modeling language</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sanford</forename><surname>Friedenthal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alan</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rick</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Designing mechatronic systems, a model-based perspective, an attempt to achieve sysml-matlab/simulink model integration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ahsan</forename><surname>Qamar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Carl</forename><surname>During</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Wikander</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">AIM 2009. IEEE/ASME International Conference on</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009. 2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1306" to="1311" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Advanced Intelligent Mechatronics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrating sysml with simulink using open-source model transformations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><surname>Sindico</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Marco</forename><surname>Di Natale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gianpiero</forename><surname>Panci</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SIMULTECH</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="56" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Sysml-modelica transformation specification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Omg</forename><surname>Se Dsig Sysml-Modelica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Working</forename><surname>Group</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrating models and simulations of continuous dynamics into sysml</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aleksandr</forename><surname>Kerzhner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Christiaan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Roger</forename><surname>Paredis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Burkhart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computing and Information Science in Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11002</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A sysml extension for bond graphs support</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Skander</forename><surname>Turki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thierry</forename><surname>Soriano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the International Conference on Technology and Automation (ICTA)</title>
		<meeting>of the International Conference on Technology and Automation (ICTA)<address><addrLine>Greece</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Citeseer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The functional mockup interface for tool independent exchange of simulation models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Torsten</forename><surname>Blochwitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Otter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Arnold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Constanze</forename><surname>Bausch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Elmqvist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Junghanns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mauß</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Monteiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Neidhold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Neumerkel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 8th International Modelica Conference</title>
		<meeting>the 8th International Modelica Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Linköping University Electronic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011-03-20">March 20. 2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="114" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Technical Univeristy; Dresden; Germany</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>th-22nd</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A topological procedure for converting a bond graph to a linear graph</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ort</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Martens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Dynamic Systems, Measurement, and Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="307" to="314" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mathematical foundations bond graphsi. algebraic theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Birkett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Roe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Franklin Institute</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">326</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="329" to="350" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Analysis of Dynamic Systems Using Bond Graph Method Through SIMULINK</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">José</forename><surname>Antonio Calvo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Carolina</forename><surname>Álvarez-Caldas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">José</forename><surname>Luis San Román</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>INTECH Open Access Publisher</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bond-graph modeling in modelica</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Broenink</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 9th European simulation symposium</title>
		<meeting>9th European simulation symposium<address><addrLine>Passau Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-10">Oct, 1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="22" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Object-oriented modeling with bond graphs and modelica</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Broenink</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIMULATION SERIES</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="168" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A bond-graph mapping mechanism for m/cd+</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mariana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gabriel</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dabreu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wainer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Bond graph methodology: development and analysis of multidisciplinary dynamic system models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wolfgang</forename><surname>Borutzky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>Springer Science &amp; Business Media</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatic translation of simulink models into modelica using simelica and the advancedblocks library</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mike</forename><surname>Dempsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">3rd International Modelica Conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Citeseer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>In Paper presented at the</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determination of elasticity parameters in lumped element (mass-spring) models of deformable objects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Suriya</forename><surname>Natsupakpong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cenk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>¸avuşoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Graphical Models</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="73" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A design, simulation and visualization environment for object-oriented mechanical and multi-domain models in modelica</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hakan</forename><surname>Vadim Engelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Larsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Fritzson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings. 1999 IEEE International Conference on</title>
		<meeting>1999 IEEE International Conference on</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999. 1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="188" to="193" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Information Visualization</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanical models translation, simulation and visualization in modelica</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Bunus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Vadim Engelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Fritzson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visualization in Modelica. Proc. of Modelica 2000 Workshop</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Citeseer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanical cad with multibody dynamic analysis based on modelica simulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Vadim Engelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lucian</forename><surname>Bunus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Popescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Fritzson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 44th Scandinavian Conference on Simulation and Modeling</title>
		<meeting>the 44th Scandinavian Conference on Simulation and Modeling</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="19" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Feasibility of detailed vehicle modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Bowles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Tiller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hilding</forename><surname>Elmqvist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dag</forename><surname>Brück</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sven</forename><surname>Erik Mattsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Möller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hans</forename><surname>Olsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Otter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>SAE Technical Paper</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maintaining the design intent in the synthesis of 3-d and 1-d system models using constraints</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Arquimedes</forename><surname>Canedo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Zhi</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ahmad</forename><surname>Albaqsami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jiang</forename><surname>Wan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mohammad</forename><surname>Abdullah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Al</forename><surname>Faruque</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Systems Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An easy-to-use generic model configurator for models in multiple tool formats</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Vadim Engelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ulf</forename><surname>Fritzson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sellgren</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">5th EUROSIM Congress on Modeling and Simulation</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Paris, France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design and validation of an annotation-concept for the representation of 3d-geometries in modelica</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Hoeft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Nytsch-Geusen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 6th International Modelica Conference</title>
		<meeting>the 6th International Modelica Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Bamberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shlomo</forename><surname>Sternberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">A course in mathematics for students of physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Algebraic topology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Allen</forename><surname>Hatcher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Existence and uniqueness of solution to electrical network problem via homology sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Paul</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SIAM-AMS Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>American Mathematical Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">III</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="118" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Computational electromagnetism: variational formulations, complementarity, edge elements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alain</forename><surname>Bossavit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The cell method: An overview on the main features</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elena</forename><surname>Ferretti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curved and Layered Structures</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>José</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Guillermo</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Castillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Miranda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Mimetic discretization methods</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why starting from differential equations for computational physics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Enzo</forename><surname>Tonti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computational Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">257</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1260" to="1290" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Discrete exterior calculus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anil</forename><surname>Nirmal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hirani</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>California Institute of Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An analysis of finite volume, finite element, and finite difference methods using some concepts from algebraic topology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Claudio</forename><surname>Mattiussi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computational Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Matlab and simulink for modeling and control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Babuska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stefano</forename><surname>Stramigioli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Delft University of Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A classification diagram for physical variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Enzo</forename><surname>Tonti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Theory of nonlinear transducers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Henry E Singleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1950">1950</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to finite element methods. Course Notes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Carlos</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Felippa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.colorado.edu/engineering/Aerospace/CAS/courses.d/IFEM.d" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Aerospace Engineeing Sciences, University of Colorado at Boulder</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
