<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Factors Mediating the Association Between Drinking in the First Year After Alcohol Treatment and Drinking at Three Years*</title>
				<funder ref="#_ZhHF3Ca">
					<orgName type="full">National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NIAAA</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_Uvbq9ym">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>PH.D</roleName><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Maisto</surname></persName>
							<email>samaisto@syr.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PH.D</roleName><forename type="first">Patrick</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Clifford</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PH.D</roleName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Stout</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Christine</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Health and Behavior</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Syracuse University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>430 Huntington Hall</addrLine>
									<postCode>13244</postCode>
									<settlement>Syracuse</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Dentistry of New Jersey</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Piscataway</settlement>
									<region>NJ</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Dentistry of New Jersey</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Brunswick</settlement>
									<region>NJ</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Factors Mediating the Association Between Drinking in the First Year After Alcohol Treatment and Drinking at Three Years*</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received: November 28, 2007. Revision: April 14, 2008.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T23:10+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Previous research has shown a signifi cant relationship between alcohol consumption in the fi rst year following alcohol treatment admission and longer term functioning. This fi nding is clinically important and pertains to the clinical course of alcohol-use disorders (AUDs). This study investigated mediators of these relationships, focusing on the fi rst year after treatment admission and alcohol consumption 3 years later. Method: Analyses were conducted on the outpatient Project MATCH (Matching Alcohol Treatment to Client Heterogeneity) sample at baseline (N = 952) and at Months 37-39 after treatment admission (n = 802; hereafter referred to as 3 years). Participants were classifi ed as fi rst-year "abstainer," "moderate drinker," or "heavy drinker." A model featuring three latent variables (psychosocial functioning, self-effi cacy, and treatment experiences) whose indicators were collected at 15 months after treatment admission was initially tested for its fi t to the data. The 3year outcomes were percentage of days abstinent and drinks per drinking day. Each model was run on randomly split subsamples and then crossvalidated on the remaining participants. Results: Model tests by use of structural equation modeling methods showed poor model fi t, owing primarily to problems involving the psychosocial-functioning variable.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Consequently, a reduced model was tested that dropped the psychosocial factor. Initial tests of this model showed an excellent fi t to the data that replicated across subsamples and 3-year drinking variables at the overall model and individual path levels. There was strong support for the hypothesis that the total effects of fi rst-year alcohol use on 3-year drinking is mediated in part (31% and 23% for the two drinking outcomes) through self-effi cacy to abstain from alcohol at 15 months. Conclusions: First-year posttreatment admission alcohol use predicts longer term (3year) alcohol use, and a substantial portion of this relationship seems to be mediated through self-effi cacy at 15 months to abstain from alcohol use. The apparent benefi t of sustained abstinence in the fi rst year may be in part the result of facilitation in the rate or strength of the acquisition of self-effi cacy. Discussed are the clinical implications of these fi ndings as well as directions for future research involving longitudinal studies of alcohol use, treatment experiences, psychosocial factors, and their interaction both within the fi rst year and afterward in the determination of the clinical course of alcohol-use disorders. (J. Stud. Alcohol Drugs 69: <ref type="bibr">[728]</ref><ref type="bibr">[729]</ref><ref type="bibr">[730]</ref><ref type="bibr">[731]</ref><ref type="bibr">[732]</ref><ref type="bibr">[733]</ref><ref type="bibr">[734]</ref><ref type="bibr">[735]</ref><ref type="bibr">[736]</ref><ref type="bibr">[737]</ref><ref type="bibr">2008)</ref> A LTHOUGH DRINKING BEHAVIOR in the fi rst year after alcohol treatment has been identifi ed for some time as an important predictor of longer term clinical course <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Miller et al., 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Polich et al., 1980)</ref>, it has been investigated as a primary research topic in only a few studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Maisto et al., 1998</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Maisto et al., , 2002;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Weisner et al., 2003)</ref>. In two recent studies, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Maisto et al. (2006</ref><ref type="bibr">Maisto et al. ( , 2007a) )</ref> conducted secondary analyses on the Project MATCH (Matching Alcohol Treatment to Client Heterogeneity) outpatient sample data set to investigate the relationship between drinking in the fi rst year after treatment initiation and drinking at 3 years. In the 2007 study, participants were classifi ed as abstainers, moderate drinkers, or heavy drinkers based on their drinking in the fi rst year following the initiation of one of the three MATCH treatments. Analyses of the relationship between drinker classifi cation and percentage of days abstinent and drinks per drinking day at the Months 37-39 follow-up (hereafter referred to as the 3-year follow-up) showed that the fi rst-year abstainers had a higher percentage of days abstinent and the fewest drinks per drinking day at 3 years than did either of the other two groups. Furthermore, the drinking outcomes of the moderate drinkers were superior to those of the heavy drinkers. Drinker group was also associated with the frequency of alcohol-related negative consequences at 3 years, because heavy drinkers reported more consequences than did either the moderate drinkers or the abstainers, who did not differ from each other.</p><p>The purpose of this study was to extend the <ref type="bibr">Maisto et al. (2007a)</ref> fi ndings through an investigation of the factors that might mediate the association between fi rst-year drinking behavior and drinking at 3 years. A conceptual model was developed to guide this study of mediation. The development of an initial conceptual model representing mediation processes specifi c to posttreatment drinking behaviors and longer term functioning proceeded from a review of longer term outcomes of alcohol and other drug treatment (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">McKay and Weiss, 2001)</ref>, alcohol research centered on posttreatment functioning (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Maisto et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Moos et al., 1990)</ref>, and relapse research (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Connors et al., 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Marlatt and Gordon, 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Witkiewitz and Marlatt, 2004)</ref>.</p><p>As <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">McKay and Weiss (2001)</ref> noted in their review of alcohol and other drug treatment outcomes, posttreatment factors correlated with longer term functioning are similar to those variables that have been shown to be related to relapse. A popular relapse model that has been researched extensively is that proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Marlatt and Gordon (1985)</ref> and updated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Witkiewitz and Marlatt (2004)</ref>. A main hypothesis of the Marlatt and Gordon model is that relapse can be attributed to both interpersonal and intrapersonal factors and is likely to occur when an individual encounters a stressful situation with which he or she is ill prepared to cope (i.e., skill deficit) and/or experiences affective interference (e.g., anxiety), which reduces the likelihood that effective action (e.g., drink refusal skills) will be implemented. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Connors et al. (1996;</ref><ref type="bibr"></ref> see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Witkiewitz and Marlatt, 2004)</ref> extended the <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Marlatt and Gordon (1985)</ref> model of relapse precipitants to enhance understanding of relapse within the broader context of posttreatment functioning. Their work can be viewed as an extrapolation of the <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Moos and Finney (1983)</ref> "systems model." Within this framework, treatment refl ects a single event among others that interact over time and contribute to posttreatment functioning; several recent articles that Moos and colleagues have published update and integrate this systems approach with elements of four conceptual models of psychosocial factors and alcohol-use disorder (AUD) remission and relapse <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Moos, 2006</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Moos, , 2007;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Moos and Moos, 2007)</ref>.</p><p>The <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Connors et al. (1996)</ref> model was designed to refl ect the associations among fi ve sets of hypothesized factors (i.e., background characteristics, alcohol involvement and symptomatology, treatment, coping skills and responses, and stressors) related to relapse. The recursive path analytic model used by Connors and colleagues included determinants of relapse that varied in temporal proximity to the outcome event. For example, setting variables that are part of the relapse event itself are possible determinants of drinking that are closer in proximity to it than, say, the level of chronic stress. Thus, the Connors et al. model views relapse within the broader context of treatment outcome and highlights the importance of temporal factors.</p><p>Our earlier research in this area <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Maisto et al., 1998</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Maisto et al., , 2002) )</ref> also points to the importance of temporal considerations. This research shows that drinking behaviors during the posttreatment period are related to longer term functioning and that the association between short-term posttreatment drinking behaviors and longer term functioning may be mediated via posttreatment social and personal factors. With this background in mind, the alcohol and other drug treatment outcome literature was reviewed for the identification of potential mediator variables. Emphasis was placed on the identifi cation of variables that studies have shown consistently to be associated with longer term functioning and that are available in the MATCH data sets.</p><p>To (1) remain theoretically consistent across the <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Connors et al. (1996)</ref> relapse model and the <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Maisto et al. (2002)</ref> posttreatment drinking behavior and longer term functioning model and to (2) simultaneously reconcile differences between the two models, the Connors et al. relapse model was revisited. Model changes were such that four broad categories of factors (i.e., alcohol involvement, treatment experiences, personal factors, and social factors) were identifi ed that were hypothesized to be related to longer term functioning among adults receiving AUD treatment.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> presents the initial, full path model that was developed to represent the hypothesized mediation of the association between drinking behaviors in the fi rst 12 months following treatment initiation and longer term alcohol use and other functioning at 37-39 months (the interval covered in the MATCH 3-year follow-up assessment).</p><p>According to Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, the index treatment has direct effects on alcohol use in Months 1-12 as well as social functioning and psychological functioning/self-effi cacy at 15 months after treatment initiation (in Project MATCH's case, 12 months after the termination of the index treatment). Furthermore, alcohol use during the initial posttreatment period infl uences alcohol use at 3 years as well as psychological functioning/self-effi cacy and social functioning at 15 months. Finally, social functioning and psychological functioning/self-effi cacy at 15 months each directly infl uences alcohol use at 39 months, and subsequent treatment (in this case, Alcoholics Anonymous [AA] involvement, number of AA step meetings attended, and number of outpatient alcohol counseling sessions) at 15 months has a direct effect on alcohol use at 39 months. Subsequent treatment at 15 months also is associated with social functioning and psychological functioning/self-effi cacy. However, that is not the focus of the proposed research, because the model is intended to refl ect hypothesized mediation effects.</p><p>Within this framework, therefore, the relationship between short-term (i.e., 12 months) posttreatment drinking behavior and longer term functioning (i.e., 39 months) is mediated by both psychological and social factors at 15 months. The specifi c mediator variables indicators were selected from the MATCH outpatient sample data set. The 15-month indicators are viewed as autocorrelated with later assessments and directly related to alcohol use at 39 months. However, alcohol use (and other functioning) also is viewed as related indirectly to 39-month drinking behavior through the mediator variables at 15 months.</p><p>With this background, the following analysis strategy was used in this study. As is described in more detail in the Method section, the fi rst-year drinker classifi cations and 3-year drinking outcomes were defi ned as in <ref type="bibr">Maisto et al. (2007a)</ref>, and confi rmatory factor analysis procedures were used to defi ne the 15-month mediator latent variables. The MATCH outpatient sample (N = 802 participants with complete 3-year follow-up data) then was randomly split into two equal-sized subsamples. Structural equation modeling methods were used to test the fi t of a model derived from that illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> (described later in the Method section) to the data provided by the fi rst subsample, and then the fi ndings of this fi rst modeling effort were cross-validated on the second subsample of participants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participants</head><p>Project MATCH was designed as two parallel (i.e., aftercare therapy: N = 774 and outpatient therapy: N = 952) but independent randomized, clinical trials. Regardless of study arm, participants were randomly assigned to one of three manual-guided, individually delivered psychosocial treatment conditions (i.e., cognitive-behavioral coping skills therapy, motivational enhancement therapy, or 12-step facilitation therapy). Study participation eligibility criteria were such that potential study participants had to have a current diagnosis of alcohol abuse or dependence according to the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Third Edition, Revised (DSM-III-R; American Psychiatric Association, 1987); be at least 18 years old; be able to read at a sixth-grade level; and agree to be randomized into any of the three treatments. Potential study participants who met any other current DSM-III-R substance dependence criteria (excluding marijuana), used intravenous drugs within the previous 6-month period, manifested acute psychosis or severe organic impairment, were considered a danger to self or others, lacked a place of residence, or did not provide a "locator" person who could be contacted if the subject became lost to follow-up were excluded from study participation <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Project MATCH Research Group, 1998)</ref>.</p><p>In-person follow-up assessment interviews were scheduled at 3-month intervals beginning 3 months after the fi rst therapy session and terminating 15 months after treatment initiation (i.e., 12 months after treatment completion). An additional follow-up interview, covering Months 37-39 after treatment initiation (3 years after MATCH treatment completion), was added later to the outpatient study arm, thereby providing 3-year posttreatment completion outcome data on this study sample. Of the 952 outpatient subjects originally recruited, 806 (84.7%) provided 3-year outcome data. Posttreatment completion data were not collected from this sample during the intervening 2-year period (i.e., the interval between the 1-year and 3-year follow-up interviews).</p><p>This sample of 806 subjects who participated in the outpatient study arm of Project MATCH and provided 3-year outcome data were the primary data source for this study. This sample is 72% male, is 80% white, and had a mean (SD) age of 38.9 (10.7) years at the time of intake. Additionally, 43% of this sample were married or cohabiting and 69% were employed at the time of study intake. A total of 45% of the sample reported at least one episode of prior alcohol treatment at intake. Based on the Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-III-R (SCID) and the Computerized Diagnostic Interview Schedule (C-DIS), 96% of study participants met alcohol dependence criteria and 33% had one or more lifetime Axis I nonsubstance diagnoses, respectively. Based on their series of missing data analyses, the Project MATCH Research Group (1998) concluded that "the 806 participants who completed the Months 37-39 interview were representative of the original outpatient sample" (p.1302).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures</head><p>Project MATCH involved the administration of an extensive battery of measures at the baseline and follow-up assessments. These have been described in detail in several of the major MATCH publications (e.g., Project MATCH Research <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Group, 1997)</ref>. The analyses completed for this study and reported in this article include data from a baseline demographic questionnaire and baseline psychiatric diagnosis measured by the SCID <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Spitzer and Williams, 1985)</ref>. Also used were baseline and 15-month follow-up interview data that included measures of depression <ref type="bibr">(Beck Depression Inventory;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Beck et al., 1961)</ref>; self-effi cacy (Alcohol Abstinence Self-Effi cacy, [AASE]), including both the temptation to drink and confi dence to abstain summary scales <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(DiClemente, 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">DiClemente et al., 1994)</ref>; psychosocial functioning (Psychosocial Functioning Inventory; <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Feragne et al., 1983)</ref>; psychiatric severity (psychiatric composite score of the Addiction Severity Index [ASI]; <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">McLellan et al., 1980)</ref>; anger (trait anger scale, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Spielberger et al., 1983)</ref>; involvement in AA (AA Involvement Scale; <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Tonigan et al., 1996)</ref>; and alcohol counseling, 12-step participation, and alcohol use collected via Form 90 <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Miller, 1996)</ref>.</p><p>As described by the Project MATCH Research Group (1997), Form 90 is administered by personal interview to obtain retrospective self-reports of daily alcohol consumption. The Form 90 data were used to derive two measures of alcohol consumption that were the primary dependent variables in this study. The fi rst, percentage of days abstinent, was defi ned in MATCH as the percentage of the total number of days in an interval during which the individual reported no alcohol consumption (this measure does not refl ect other drug use). It is a measure of the frequency of drinking. Drinks per drinking day is a measure of drinking intensity or severity and, in Project MATCH, was defi ned as the average number of drinks per drinking occasion.</p><p>The 3-, 9-, and 15-month follow-up interviews <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Connors et al., 1994)</ref> and the 3-year follow-up interview (Project MATCH Research <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Group, 1998)</ref> were considered major participant evaluation points and included the majority of baseline assessments, blood and urine samples, and collateral interviews (i.e., interviews with individuals who were familiar with the participants' drinking). Overall, assessments were conducted with more than 90% of the participants across each of the originally scheduled fi ve follow-up points. Extensive testing and data analyses were conducted to ensure the reliability and validity of subject self-reported data.</p><p>The results of these reliability and validity efforts show that "a high degree of confi dence can be placed in the accuracy of the verbal report data obtained in Project MATCH" (Project MATCH Research <ref type="bibr">Group, 1997, p. 12)</ref>. The focus of this study was to develop and test a structural equation model regarding psychosocial factors that predict and explain (i.e., mediate) longer term posttreatment functioning.</p><p>The relationship between shorter term and longer term drinking outcomes was investigated in this study using categorical defi nitions of shorter term alcohol use. As presented in <ref type="bibr">Maisto et al. (2007a)</ref>, drinking in the fi rst year after treatment initiation was defi ned by classifying participants into one of three groups according to their reports of daily alcohol consumption. Abstainers (n = 93) reported no alcohol consumption at all during this time period. Moderate drinkers (n = 157) reported at least one standard drink (0.5 oz ethanol) but fewer than 6 heavy (fi ve or more standard drinks on an occasion for men, four or more for women) drinking days. Heavy drinkers (n = 546) reported drinking during Months 1-12 that included 6 or more heavy drinking days. The resulting N = 796 refl ects insuffi cient drinking data provided by 10 of the 806 outpatient subjects at the 3-year follow-up.</p><p>As <ref type="bibr">Maisto et al. (2007a)</ref> showed, the three drinker groups did not differ signifi cantly on any baseline demographic or alcohol-related variable, including history of alcohol treatment and frequency of alcohol-related problems 90 days before treatment. However, the three groups did differ in age, as moderate drinkers tended to be about 2 years older than either the abstainers or heavy drinkers. Baseline age, however, was not correlated with percentage of days abstinent or drinks per drinking day at 3 years.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis plan</head><p>A two-step approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Kline, 2005)</ref> was taken in planning the analyses. First, the plan was to conduct a confi rmatory factor analysis (CFA) on the 15-month measures (indicators) hypothesized to load on the mediating constructs shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> of social functioning, psychological functioning/self-effi cacy, and treatment experiences. In the CFA, "psychological functioning/self-effi cacy" was split into two separate constructs of psychological functioning and selfeffi cacy. This was done because of the consistent fi nding in research on AUD clinical course that self-effi cacy is related to longer term alcohol use <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(McKay et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Moos and Moos, 2007)</ref>.</p><p>The Project MATCH indicators hypothesized to refl ect the constructs were entered into the CFA measurement model test. Following the CFA, the plan was to use structural equation modeling (SEM) procedures to test the full model depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. A cross-validation strategy was planned in completing the SEM analyses. In this regard, the plan was to randomly divide the full sample into two equalsized subsamples. In this strategy, the hypothesized model's fi t to the fi rst subsample's data was to be tested, and then the results of these analyses was to be replicated on the second subsample's data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measurement model</head><p>The hypothesized 15-month mediating constructs and their associated indicators in the MATCH data set are as follows. The Social Functioning indicators were the three subscales of the Psychosocial Functioning Inventory, which are social behavior, housemate/roommate, and social role performance. Psychological Functioning indicators were the ASI psychiatric functioning severity score, Beck Depression Inventory total score, and Trait Anger Scale total score. Self-effi cacy was indicated by the temptation and confi dence subscales of the Alcohol Abstinence Self-Effi cacy Scale. Finally, treatment experiences were hypothesized to be indicated by the AA Involvement Scale total score; the number of alcohol outpatient counseling sessions attended in the last 90 days, as reported on Form 90; and the number of AA step meetings attended in the last 90 days, also reported on Form 90. In conducting the CFA, all raw data were used, and the measures were reverse-scored as necessary (e.g., Beck Depression, ASI psychiatric severity) so that higher scores refl ected better functioning. The number of participants with suffi cient data to be included in these analyses was 790, and the residual variances were assumed to be uncorrelated. The measurement model is depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>.</p><p>The results of the analyses showed that the hypothesized measurement model was a good fi t to the data (χ 2 = 186.61, 38 df, p &lt; .01; Comparative Fit Index [CFI] = .95; Taylor-Lewis Fit Index [TLI] = .93; standardized root mean square residual [SRMSR] = .036). It is important to note that these four fi t indexes are used as indicators of how well hypothesized models fi t the data in question. Many fi t indexes have been developed and evaluated and often have distinct advantages and disadvantages associated with their use in a given analytic context. The four indexes presented here are commonly used and are technically acceptable to statisticians <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Kline, 2005)</ref>.</p><p>All of the hypothesized indicator-(measure-) construct (latent variable) loadings were statistically signifi cant at the p &lt; .01 level or greater. Despite this good fi t, inspection of the pattern of simple correlations among the indicator Model testing. The difference between the model depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> and the model tested is that the psychological functioning and social functioning indicators were combined to form a "psychosocial functioning" latent variable. In addition, baseline psychosocial functioning and baseline selfeffi cacy were hypothesized to be directly related to alcohol use in Months 1-12 as well as to their respective 15-month values. In addition, the "index treatment" shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> represents random assignment in MATCH to one of three treatment conditions, with a hypothesized direct path to alcohol use in the fi rst 12 months. Baseline psychosocial functioning was hypothesized to be correlated with baseline self-effi cacy but not to MATCH treatment group assignment, because the latter was determined randomly. Finally, two 12month alcohol-use mediated effects were hypothesized, one through 15-month psychosocial functioning and one through 15-month self-effi cacy.</p><p>The results of the analyses showed poor model fi t to the data for both split samples and the full sample for both dependent variables. For the full-sample percentage of days abstinent model, the results were as follows: χ 2 = 1,176.21, 178 df, p &lt; .01; CFI = .83; TLI = .80; SRMSR = .072. The counterpart statistics for the drinks per drinking day model test were χ 2 = 1,190.49, 178 df, p &lt; .01; CFI = .83; TLI = .80; SRMSR = .072. Besides these fi ndings, the model tests showed suppression effects (Maassen and Bakker, 2001) for both percentage of days abstinent and drinks per drinking day. In this context, a suppression effect meant that the psychosocial variable partialed out extraneous variance from the self-effi cacy variable in the prediction of the drinking outcomes. In this regard, the patterns of simple correlations suggested that (1) the psychosocial variable was more highly correlated with self-effi cacy than it was with either drinking outcome and (2) when both self-effi cacy and psychosocial variables suggested that there may be a simpler measurement model that involved combining the psychiatric and social functioning indicators to form a "psychosocial functioning" latent variable. In this regard, the data showed that several of the indicators were more highly correlated with indicators of the other domain (i.e., psychiatric with social) than they were with indicators within their domains. Accordingly, the threelatent variable model was tested for its fi t to the data.</p><p>The CFA of the three-factor model also showed an excellent fi t to the data (χ 2 = 201.32, 41 df, p &lt; .01; CFI = .94; TLI = .93; SRMSR = .037). All of the hypothesized factor loadings were statistically signifi cant. Based on these fi ndings, the three-factor model was tested for its fi t to the data by use of SEM methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SEM testing</head><p>Sample division. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> presents baseline demographic data and alcohol-related information for the full sample (N = 796) and each of the two subsamples (n for each = 398). Analyses showed that the two subsamples did not differ on any of the variables included in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</p><p>Data preparation. As in the procedures used in testing the measurement model and following recommendations of <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Kline (2005)</ref> and others, the raw indicator scores were used in the SEM analyses. The only exceptions were the two 3-year drinking outcome measures: percentage of days abstinent and drinks per drinking day. Both of these measures were transformed, because the transformation substantially improved the distribution of each respective set of scores' approximation to normal. An arc sine/square root transformation was applied to the percentage of days abstinent data, and a square root transformation was applied to the drinks per drinking day data. functioning were in the same model, the direction of the effect of the psychosocial variable with outcome was the opposite (the expected direction was positive for percentage of days abstinent and negative for drinks per drinking day and consistent with the simple indicator-outcome correlations, albeit weak) of that expected and not statistically signifi cant.</p><p>There was additional evidence found for suppression in the three-factor model when a two-factor (including self-effi cacy and treatment experiences at 15 months) model was tested, as we describe later. In this regard, the hypothesized self-effi cacy paths were signifi cant in both the two-and three-factor model, but the magnitude of the effects was larger in the three-factor model. Again, this suggests that the psychosocial variable partialed out extraneous variance from the self-effi cacy variable in the prediction of the drinking outcomes.</p><p>As a result of these fi ndings and their low substantive value beyond confi rming that the 15-month psychosocial indicators were weakly correlated with outcomes and shared extraneous variance with 15-month self-effi cacy, we moved to testing a model that included only self-effi cacy and treatment experiences as the 15-month latent variables. This "reduced" model is presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>.</p><p>As can be seen in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>, the index MATCH treatment assignment, following our original model, was hypothesized to be related to alcohol use in the fi rst year. We also hypothesized that MATCH treatment assignment would be related to treatment experiences at 15 months because of the fi nding that individuals in the 12-step facilitation condition reported more AA involvement in the fi rst year after treatment <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Connors et al., 2001)</ref>. Baseline self-effi cacy was hypothesized to be related both to alcohol use in Months 1-12 and to self-effi cacy at 15 months. Alcohol use and both 15-month constructs were predicted to be related to drinking at 3 years, and treatment experiences at 15 months were expected to be concurrently correlated with self-effi cacy. The model also set to zero the path from alcohol use in Months 1-12 to treatment experiences at 15 months. Finally, the indirect effect of alcohol use at 12 months to self-effi cacy at 15 months to alcohol use at 3 years was included in the model's testing. The residual variance of all measures was assumed to be independent, except in the case of the baseline and 15-month self-effi cacy assessments.</p><p>The model's fi t to the data was tested for each subsample and the full sample on each 3-year drinking measure; means and standard deviations of each of the indicator variables and their intercorrelations for each test may be obtained from the authors by request. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> summarizes the results of the SEM analyses by presenting indexes of model fi t and signifi cance of the unstandardized path coeffi cients. As can be seen in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>, the model showed excellent fi t for both drinking outcomes and across both subsamples, suggesting its robustness. This conclusion is indicated not only by the fi t indexes but also by the signifi cance of the individual path coeffi cients and the consistency of fi ndings across subsamples at the individual path level. It is important to note that Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> shows that about 31% (indirect effect of drinker group on 3-year drinking through self-effi cacy divided by direct effect of drinker group on 3-year drinking + indirect effect of drinker group through self-effi cacy on 3-year drinking) of the total effect of drinker group on percentage of days abstinent in the full sample is the result of its effects through self-effi cacy. The counterpart value for drinks per drinking day is 23%. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>The results of the SEM analyses show that the model depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> fi t the data well, as refl ected by the fi t indexes and the tests of the individual hypothesized paths. The analyses also suggest the stability of the fi ndings both in overall fi t indexes and in individual paths. Because the model was tested with longitudinal data, these fi ndings-while, of course, not giving direct evidence of causal relationshipsgive a stronger approximation to sequences of causal relationships among the constructs. It is important to note that the results of the tests of individual paths took into account variance resulting from important baseline factors, including self-effi cacy and MATCH treatment condition assignment.</p><p>The fi ndings of this study extend <ref type="bibr">Maisto et al.'s (2007a)</ref> study by showing that early alcohol use (i.e., less frequent, lighter volume of drinking) post-AUD treatment is associated with better drinking outcomes at 3 years both directly and in part (31% and 23% for percentage of days abstinent and drinks per drinking day, respectively) through its beneficial effects on an individual's self-effi cacy to abstain from alcohol use. In addition, the data show the benefi cial direct effects of level of self-effi cacy at 15 months and of treatment experiences at 15 months on drinking at 3 years.</p><p>The data also reveal a signifi cant concurrent relationship between treatment experiences and self-effi cacy at 15 months, as predicted. Given the magnitude of the factor loadings of the two AA-related indicators on the treatment experiences construct and the correlations of both AA indicators at 15 months with 3-year drinking, the fi ndings on treatment experiences reaffi rm the literature supporting AA involvement during and post-AUD treatment <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Humphreys, 2004)</ref>.</p><p>Although the model included the initial treatment episode as exerting a direct effect on alcohol use in Months 1-12, none of the model tests showed this path to be statistically signifi cant. This fi nding does not necessarily fail to support the concept that initial AUD treatment episode has no bearing on shorter term alcohol use. In this regard, the fi nding of no overall treatment effects in the MATCH trial is well known; therefore, the results of the model tests in this study are not surprising.</p><p>The "alcohol use at 12 months" construct was represented by the drinker-group categorization. Our earlier research using this classifi cation suggested that the most direct clinical implications of the fi ndings are that the highest likelihood of good functioning in the drinking domain at 3 years is afforded by complete abstinence in the fi rst year after treatment initiation. Additional analyses treating alcohol use in Months 1-12 as a continuous variable suggested that the crucial proportion of days abstinent was at least 180 of the 360 <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Maisto et al., 2006)</ref>. The model tests in this study suggest that the benefi ts of abstinence in the fi rst year operate in part through its effects on building self-effi cacy to abstain from alcohol use.</p><p>It is not that there are no benefi ts in keeping alcohol use in the fi rst year at a moderate level; <ref type="bibr">Maisto et al. (2007a)</ref> showed that individuals classifi ed as moderate drinkers had drinking outcomes at 3 years that tended to be considerably better than did individuals who were in the heavy drinker category. But as far as 3-year drinking outcomes are concerned, abstainers clearly were functioning the best of the three groups, and this study's data suggest that it is in part because complete abstinence facilitates the rate or the strength (or both) of the building of self-effi cacy regarding maintaining abstinence from alcohol use. We conducted supplementary analyses of the indicators of the self-effi cacy construct (AASE scale, confi dence and temptation subscales) to achieve additional insight into the drinker-group-self-effi cacy connection. The mean scores on the two respective AASE subscales were compared (Tukey's honestly signifi cant difference [HSD] test, p &lt; .05) at 15 months. These paired comparisons of means showed that, for confi dence to abstain, the abstainers scored as more self-effi cacious than either the moderate or heavy drinkers, and the moderate drinkers were more self-effi cacious than were the heavy drinkers. For temptation to drink, the abstainers and moderate drinkers were again more self-effi cacious than the heavy drinkers, but the abstainers and the moderate drinkers did not differ. Therefore, the benefi cial effects of complete abstinence from alcohol in the fi rst year seem to be in part the result of a strengthening of two dimensions of self-efficacy, but, for moderate drinkers, the benefi cial effects were more limited. Of course, it also is possible that moderate drinkers not scoring as high as the abstainers in self-effi cacy in confi dence to abstain may refl ect moderate drinkers having nonabstinent drinking goals to begin with. Clearly, additional research is needed for a better understanding of this pattern of fi ndings.</p><p>A major clinical implication of these fi ndings is that it is crucial to work closely with clients and patients to keep alcohol consumption at a minimum in the fi rst year after treatment, because that seems to be an important element of solidifying a personal resource (self-effi cacy to abstain from alcohol in a variety of situations) that predicts longer term maintenance of changes in alcohol consumption. This may operate by providing a foundation for individuals building and strengthening non-alcohol-use coping skills that may be applied in everyday life, and, as success at application of such skills increases, self-effi cacy to use them would tend to increase as well. In this regard, a premise of cognitivebehavioral approaches to treatment is that a primary way of increasing confi dence in application of a skill is past success in applying it in real situations (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Maisto et al., 2007b)</ref>. Therefore, behavioral success at application of coping skills tends to promote confi dence that they can be used effectively, and longer periods of abstinence from alcohol would give the individual more opportunities to use nonalcohol coping behaviors that individuals learn as part of their treatment.</p><p>More generally, this study's fi ndings highlight the need to closely examine the interrelationship between alcohol use and self-effi cacy within the fi rst year, and there is some evidence to suggest that this is crucial to the long-term maintenance of changes in alcohol use <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Connors et al., 2001)</ref>. Moreover, it seems crucial that clinicians monitor and clinical researchers investigate how other psychological and social/environmental factors, as well as treatment experiences, affect and are affected by changes in alcohol use within the fi rst year.</p><p>Unfortunately, this study could not provide information on other psychological or social functioning variables because of the problems in the analyses of those variables, as described earlier. However, evidence from other research <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Moos and Moos, 2007)</ref> suggests strongly that "psychosocial resources" at the end of the fi rst year predict alcohol use and related functioning as long as 16 years later, implying that an understanding of the course of such resources in the fi rst year is a clinically signifi cant issue.</p><p>There are a few limitations in these data that are important to note. The suppressor effects observed in the three-factor model tests did not allow tests of indirect effects of alcohol use in Months 1-12 through psychosocial functioning. As a result, understanding of the components of the total infl uence of alcohol use in the fi rst year following treatment initiation on longer term functioning may have been reduced considerably. Another limitation of this study, as with all analyses involving the core MATCH data set, is that more than 95% of the participants had a diagnosis of alcohol dependence. In addition, they all participated in a trial of interventions that emphasized abstinence from alcohol as the primary outcome goal. Therefore, the applicability of the results of this study to populations of individuals in treatment for less severe alcohol problems or whose treatment is receptive to alternative drinking outcome goals needs to be determined empirically.</p><p>It also is important to note that Project MATCH excluded individuals who met criteria for other substance-use dependence diagnoses (except for marijuana) or who were intravenous drug users. Therefore, the MATCH sample may have been less involved with drug use other than alcohol than is the case for individuals presenting for treatment in many clinical settings. This raises two questions, the fi rst of which is the generalizability of these fi ndings to more druginvolved AUD clinical populations.</p><p>The second question is related to the fi rst and concerns the degree of importance for different clinical populations of whether fi rst-year substance-use patterns can be operationalized as in this study or if they need to take into account both alcohol and other drug use. This currently is an important question for clinical research.</p><p>The results of this study warrant the conduct of an a priori, longitudinal study of posttreatment alcohol use and AUD clinical course. Such research would build on the results of this study, by providing a sensitive test of the model depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> and choosing indicators that are best suited to measuring the constructs proposed and that are sensitive to change over time. Related to this point, future research should consider more frequent longitudinal assessment than was used in Project MATCH, which would allow for a more sensitive and elaborate estimate of mediation effects of interest than was possible in this study. Such an approach would permit investigation of interrelationships among alcohol use, treatment experiences, and psychosocial factors within the fi rst year, which seems crucial. It is important to note that Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> captures major psychosocial constructs prevalent in current conceptualizations of the development and remission of AUDs <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Moos, 2007)</ref>, so that its further evaluation would aid theoretical as well as clinical developments.</p><p>In conclusion, the results of this study replicate and extend earlier research on the association of fi rst-year alcohol use and longer term clinical course and implicate the importance of self-effi cacy to abstain from alcohol in determining part of that association. A major priority for future research is more sensitive analyses of treatment experiences and psychosocial factors in addition to self-effi cacy-both within the fi rst year and following the fi rst year-and their connections to alcohol consumption in determining long-term AUD clinical course.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIGURE 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>FIGURE 1. Initial full path model of the mediation of the association between fi rst-year alcohol use with longer term alcohol use and related functioning</figDesc><graphic coords="3,60.00,74.00,475.20,267.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FIGURE 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>FIGURE 2. Initial measurement model of hypothesized 15-month mediation latent variables. PFI = Psychosocial Functioning Inventory; ASI = Addiction Severity Index; AASE = Alcohol Abstinence Self-Effi cacy scale; AA = Alcoholics Anonymous.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,299.25,60.00,267.07,602.62" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>FIGURE 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>FIGURE 3. Reduced path model</figDesc><graphic coords="7,73.71,73.19,464.29,227.33" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Participant demographic and baseline characteristics</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Full sample</cell><cell>Split A</cell><cell>Split B</cell></row><row><cell>Characteristic</cell><cell>(N = 796)</cell><cell>(n = 398)</cell><cell>(n = 398)</cell></row><row><cell>Drinker group, Mos. 1-12, n</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Abstainer</cell><cell>93</cell><cell>48</cell><cell>45</cell></row><row><cell>Moderate</cell><cell>157</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>79</cell></row><row><cell>Heavy</cell><cell>546</cell><cell>272</cell><cell>274</cell></row><row><cell>MATCH treatment assignment, n (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CBT</cell><cell>259 (32.5)</cell><cell>130 (32.7)</cell><cell>129 (32.4)</cell></row><row><cell>MET</cell><cell>254 (31.9)</cell><cell>113 (28.4)</cell><cell>141 (35.4)</cell></row><row><cell>TSF</cell><cell>283 (35.6)</cell><cell>155 (38.9)</cell><cell>128 (32.3)</cell></row><row><cell>Gender, male, n (%)</cell><cell>72.4</cell><cell>72.1</cell><cell>72.6</cell></row><row><cell>Age, mean (SD)</cell><cell>38.5 (10.69)</cell><cell>39.1 (10.96)</cell><cell>37.96 (10.40)</cell></row><row><cell>Ethnicity, white, %</cell><cell>79.4</cell><cell>81.7</cell><cell>77.1</cell></row><row><cell>Marital, married/cohabit, %</cell><cell>44.2</cell><cell>43.7</cell><cell>44.8</cell></row><row><cell>Prior treatment, yes, %</cell><cell>45.0</cell><cell>44.5</cell><cell>45.5</cell></row><row><cell>SCID, alcohol dependence, %</cell><cell>95.7</cell><cell>94.5</cell><cell>97.0</cell></row><row><cell>Percentage of days abstinent, mean (SD)</cell><cell>34.20 (29.99)</cell><cell>33.89 (30.95)</cell><cell>34.59 (29.04)</cell></row><row><cell>No. of drinks/drinking days, mean (SD)</cell><cell>13.50 (8.05)</cell><cell>13.18 (7.54)</cell><cell>13.81 (8.52)</cell></row></table><note><p>Notes: Split A = subsample A; Split B = subsample B; mos. = months; CBT = cognitive-behavior therapy; MET = motivational enhancement therapy; TSF = twelve-step facilitation therapy; SCID = Structured Clinical Interview for the DSM-III-R.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Unstandardized path coeffi cients results for testing fi t of modifi ed path model (Figure3) to the data for the two subsamples and the full sample</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">% Days abstinent, Mos. 37-39</cell><cell cols="3">Drinks/drinking day, Mos. 37-39</cell></row><row><cell>Effect</cell><cell>Split A</cell><cell>Split B</cell><cell>Full</cell><cell>Split A</cell><cell>Split B</cell><cell>Full</cell></row><row><cell>SEBL -› SE15</cell><cell>.34  †</cell><cell>.64  †</cell><cell>.49  †</cell><cell>.34  †</cell><cell>.66  †</cell><cell>.50  †</cell></row><row><cell>Tx15 -› SE15</cell><cell>.10  †</cell><cell>.04</cell><cell>.07  †</cell><cell>.10  †</cell><cell>.04</cell><cell>.07  †</cell></row><row><cell>DGp -› SE15</cell><cell>-.45  †</cell><cell>-.29  †</cell><cell>-.37  †</cell><cell>-.45  †</cell><cell>-.30  †</cell><cell>-.37  †</cell></row><row><cell>DGp -› Tx15 (fi xed)</cell><cell>.00</cell><cell>.00</cell><cell>.00</cell><cell>.00</cell><cell>.00</cell><cell>.00</cell></row><row><cell>SE15 -› Alc39</cell><cell>.18  †</cell><cell>.18  †</cell><cell>.18  †</cell><cell>-.39  †</cell><cell>-.42  †</cell><cell>-.41  †</cell></row><row><cell>Tx15 -› Alc39</cell><cell>.07  †</cell><cell>.07  †</cell><cell>.07  †</cell><cell>-.20  †</cell><cell>-.20  †</cell><cell>-.20  †</cell></row><row><cell>SEBL -› DGp</cell><cell>-.17*</cell><cell>-.31  †</cell><cell>-.25  †</cell><cell>-.17*</cell><cell>-.31  †</cell><cell>-.25  †</cell></row><row><cell>DGp -› Alc39</cell><cell>-.13  †</cell><cell>-.17  †</cell><cell>-.15  †</cell><cell>.42  †</cell><cell>.61  †</cell><cell>.52  †</cell></row><row><cell>TxBL -› Tx15</cell><cell>.23  †</cell><cell>.07</cell><cell>.15  †</cell><cell>.23  †</cell><cell>.07</cell><cell>.15  †</cell></row><row><cell>TxBL -› DGp</cell><cell>-.05</cell><cell>-.04</cell><cell>-.04</cell><cell>-.05</cell><cell>-.04</cell><cell>-.04</cell></row><row><cell>TxBL with PFBL</cell><cell>.03</cell><cell>.01</cell><cell>.02</cell><cell>.03</cell><cell>.01</cell><cell>.02</cell></row><row><cell>DGp -› SE15 -› Alc39</cell><cell>-.08  †</cell><cell>-.05  †</cell><cell>-.07  †</cell><cell>.18  †</cell><cell>.13  †</cell><cell>.15  †</cell></row><row><cell>R 2 Alc39</cell><cell>.18</cell><cell>.22</cell><cell>.20</cell><cell>.17</cell><cell>.22</cell><cell>.19</cell></row><row><cell>χ 2 , 29 df</cell><cell>57.52  †</cell><cell>54.44  †</cell><cell>91.12  †</cell><cell>57.87  †</cell><cell>56.56  †</cell><cell>93.87  †</cell></row><row><cell>CFI</cell><cell>.97</cell><cell>.97</cell><cell>.97</cell><cell>.97</cell><cell>.97</cell><cell>.97</cell></row><row><cell>SRMSR</cell><cell>.04</cell><cell>.04</cell><cell>.03</cell><cell>.04</cell><cell>.04</cell><cell>.03</cell></row><row><cell>TLI</cell><cell>.95</cell><cell>.96</cell><cell>.95</cell><cell>.95</cell><cell>.96</cell><cell>.95</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">Notes: Mos. = months; Split A = subsample A, Split B = subsample B, Full = full sample; SEBL = self-effi cacy at</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">baseline; SE15 = self-effi cacy at 15 mos.; Tx15 = treatment at 15 mos.; DGp = drinker group (coded 0 = abstainer,</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">1 = moderate, 2 = heavy); Alc39 = respective alcohol use variable, Mos. 37-39; TxBL = MATCH treatment group</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">assignment; PFBL = psychosocial functioning at baseline; CFI = Comparative Fit Index; SRMSR = Standardized</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Root Mean Square Residual; TLI = Taylor-Lewis Fit Index.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>*p &lt; .05;  † p &lt; .01.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div><p>*This research was supported by <rs type="funder">National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</rs> grant <rs type="grantNumber">R21AA14226</rs>. The data were derived from Project <rs type="projectName">MATCH</rs> (<rs type="projectName">Matching Alcohol Treatment to Client Heterogeneity</rs>), which NIAAA also supported.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_ZhHF3Ca">
					<idno type="grant-number">R21AA14226</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">MATCH</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_Uvbq9ym">
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Matching Alcohol Treatment to Client Heterogeneity</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-Revised (DSM-III-R)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>American</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Association</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessment issues and strategies in alcoholism treatment matching research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Beck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mendelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Erbaugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Connors</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Cooney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Diclemente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Tonigan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Anton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stud. Alcohol, Supplement</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="100" />
			<date type="published" when="1961">1961. 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Arch. Gen. Psychiat.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding relapse in the broader context of post-treatment functioning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Connors</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Maisto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Zywiak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>Supple- ment): S173-S189</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Addiction</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A longitudinal model of intake symptomatology, AA participation and outcome: Retrospective study of the Project MATCH outpatient and aftercare samples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Connors</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Tonigan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stud. Alcohol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="817" to="825" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-effi cacy and the addictive behaviors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Diclemente</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Social Clin. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="302" to="315" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Alcohol Abstinence Self-Effi cacy scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Diclemente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Carbonari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Montgomery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stud. Alcohol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Feragne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Longabaugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stephenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Psychosocial Functioning Inventory. Eval. Hlth Prof</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Circles of Recovery: Self-Help Organizations for Addictions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Humphreys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principles and Practice of Structural Equation Modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Guilford Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd Edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conceptual, methodological, and analytical issues in the study of relapse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mckay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Franklin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Patapis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lynch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Psychol. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="127" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A review of temporal effects and outcome predictors in substance abuse treatment studies with long-term follow-ups: Preliminary results and methodological issues</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mckay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eval. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="161" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An improved diagnostic evaluation instrument for substance abuse patients: The Addiction Severity Index</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mclellan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Luborsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Woody</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Brien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Maassen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bakker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Nerv. Ment. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">168</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="270" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980. 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Sociol. Meth. Res.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relationship between abstinence for one year following pretreatment assessment and alcohol use and other functioning at two years in individuals presenting for alcohol treatment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Maisto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Clifford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Longabaugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Beattie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stud. Alcohol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="403" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drinking in the year after treatment as a predictor of three-year outcomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Maisto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Clifford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Stout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stud. Alcohol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="823" to="832" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moderate drinking in the fi rst year after treatment as a predictor of three-year outcomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Maisto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Clifford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Stout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stud. Alcohol Drugs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="419" to="427" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Maisto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Connors</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Dearing</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Alcohol Use Disorders</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>Hogrefe and Huber</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Toronto, Canada</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Twelve-month abstinence from alcohol and long-term drinking and marital outcomes in men with severe alcohol problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Maisto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mckay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Farrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stud. Alcohol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="591" to="598" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Relapse Prevention: Maintenance Strategies in the Treatment of Addictive Behaviors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Marlatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Gordon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<publisher>Guilford Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Form 90: A Structured Assessment Interview for Drinking and Related Behaviors (Test Manual)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NIAAA Project MATCH Monograph Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="4004" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<publisher>DHHS Publication No</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Bethesda, MD</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>ADM)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long-term follow-up of behavioral self-control training</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Leckman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Delaney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tinkcom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stud. Alcohol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="261" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social contexts and substance use</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Moos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Rethinking Substance Abuse: What the Science Shows, and What We Should Do About It</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Car-Roll</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Guilford Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="182" to="200" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theory-based processes that promote the remission of substance use disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Moos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Psychol. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="537" to="551" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The expanding scope of alcoholism treatment evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Moos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Finney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. Psychologist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1036" to="1044" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Alcoholism Treatment: Context, process, and outcome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Moos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Finney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cronkite</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protective resources and long-term recovery from alcohol use disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Moos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Moos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Drug Alcohol Depend</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="54" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patterns of alcoholism over four years</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Polich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Armor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Braiker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stud. Alcohol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="416" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Matching alcoholism treatments to client heterogeneity: Project MATCH posttreatment drinking outcomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Project Match Research</forename><surname>Group</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stud. Alcohol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Matching alcoholism treatments to client heterogeneity: Project MATCH three-year drinking outcomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Project Match Research</forename><surname>Group</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Alcsm Clin. Exp. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1300" to="1311" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessment of anger: The State-Trait Anger Scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Spielberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Jackobs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Russel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Crane</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Advances in Personality Assessment</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Butcher</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Spielberger</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="189" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Mahwah, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Structured Clinical Inerview for DSM-III-R, Patient Version</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Spitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B W</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<publisher>Biometric Research Department</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York; New York Psychiatric Institute</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alcoholics Anonymous Involvement (AAI) Scale: Reliability and norms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Tonigan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Connors</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol. Addict. Behav</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shortterm alcohol and drug treatment outcomes predict long-term outcome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Weisner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Ray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mertens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Satre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Drug Alcohol Depend</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="281" to="294" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relapse prevention for alcohol and drug problems: That was Zen, this is Tao</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Witkiewitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Marlatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="224" to="235" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
