<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Causal Graph Aided Causal Discovery in an Observational Aneurysmal Subarachnoid Hemorrhage Study</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2024-08-14">August 14, 2024</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Carlo</forename><surname>Berzuini</surname></persName>
							<email>carlo.berzuini@manchester.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Manchester</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Oxford Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>M13 9PL</postCode>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Davide</forename><surname>Luciani</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Unitá di Ingegneria della Conoscenza Clinica</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Mario Negri Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Milan</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hiren</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Manchester Centre for Clinical Neurosciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Stott Lane</addrLine>
									<postCode>M6 8HD</postCode>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Causal Graph Aided Causal Discovery in an Observational Aneurysmal Subarachnoid Hemorrhage Study</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2024-08-14">August 14, 2024</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2408.06464v1[stat.ME]</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T18:21+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>causality</term>
					<term>causal directed acyclic graph</term>
					<term>DAG</term>
					<term>randomized clinical trials</term>
					<term>therapeutic decision making</term>
					<term>causal discovery</term>
					<term>aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage</term>
					<term>instrumental variable</term>
					<term>propensity score</term>
					<term>conditional independence</term>
					<term>observational studies</term>
					<term>external ventricular drain</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Causal inference methods for observational data are increasingly recognized as a valuable complement to randomized clinical trials (RCTs). They can, under strong assumptions, emulate RCTs or help refine their focus. Our approach to causal inference uses causal directed acyclic graphs (DAGs). We are motivated by a concern that many observational studies in medicine begin without a clear definition of their objectives, without awareness of scientific potential, and without tools to identify the necessary in itinere adjustments. We present and illustrate methods that provide "midway insights" during study's course, identify meaningful causal questions within the study's reach and point to the necessary data base enhancements for these questions to be meaningfully tackled. The method 1</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>If every discourse originates from an assumption, a postulate we do not engage in proving, enclosed like an embryo in the yolk and the yolk in the egg, let the assumption at the root of the present work be: MEDICAL SCIENCE IS BASED ON CAUSAL KNOWLEDGE.</p><p>Randomized clinical trials (RCTs)-widely regarded as the "gold standard" for establishing causality-are increasingly facing challenges in addressing the complex causal questions that arise in therapeutic contexts. This has led to a growing interest in complementing RCTs with causal inference methods applied to observational data. These methods, under certain strong assumptions, can emulate the effects of RCTs or enhance their design and focus. Our approach to causal inference uses causal directed acyclic graphs (DAGs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> to represent assumptions about the problem. In a causal DAG, nodes represent domain variables and arrows may represent causal relationships. Under the interpretation adopted in this paper, the DAG simultaneously encodes causal and conditional independence assumptions about the variables. Thanks to this dual encoding, the causal graph enables us to efficiently utilize data to address causal questions that extend beyond the scope of purely predictive studies, as a complement, or as an alternative, to RCTs. Within this framework, our method aims to provide "midway insights" during study's course, identifying clinically relevant causal questions within study's reach and the necessary data base enhancements for these questions to be meaningfully tackled. The method hinges on the concepts of identification and positivity. The former ensures that the relationships depicted by the graph entail a unique, unbiased estimate of the unknown causal quantities, irrespective of the model quantitative specification. Positivity ensures that the data contain sufficient information to allow for estimation of the causal parameters of interest. We emphasise the method's applicability as data gradually become available throughout the study, for informed decisions to be made in selecting the study's appropriate direction.</p><p>We are concerned that too many observational studies in medicine begin without a clear definition of their objectives and with lack of awareness of the potential achievements. Hence the risk of wasting resources without a commensurate progress in causal knowledge. Our methodology helps remedying this.</p><p>We illustrate the conceptual points throught their application in an analysis of data from patients with aneurysmal Subarachnoid Hemorrhage (aSAH), within a realistic midway study scenario. For illustrative purposes, we have selected a scientific question concerning the consequences of a clinical intervention known as external ventricular drainage (EVD) in specific strata of the population.</p><p>The next section provides an overview of therapeutic questions in aSAH that remain to be solved. Section "Causal Graph of a Simple aSAH scenario" reviews basic notions of causal graphs with the aid of our SAH study. Next we deal with identification, with positivity and propensity scoring <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Section "Causal analysis of the effect of EVD" does what it promises. Finally, Section "Monitoring" focuses on multicenter studies and expands on instrumental variable (IV) principles to develop a method for tracking the impact of practice changes at an individual center level, as an alternative causality exploration paradigm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background on SAH</head><p>aSAH is a type of stroke due to a ruptured aneurysm, causing bleeding in the brain's subarachnoid space. It affects roughly 9 in 100000 people each year <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. With its tendency to occur early in life, primarily affecting people aged 50 to 60, with mortality rates as high as 40-50% and a quarter of survivors facing lifestyle limitations, aSAH results in a greater overall loss of productive life than other types of stroke.</p><p>A recent report from the Research Guidelines Committee of the National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> highlights the "glaring" absence of an adequate evidence base for managing aSAH patients, also criticising the lack of reliable outcome prediction models, which sometimes leads to specialists withholding treatment from patients who might have recovered well despite initially poor conditions. There is clearly mileage for research to improve aSAH patient outcomes. Well known difficulties of implementing RCTs in this area call for use of observational data. Hence, in the first place, we need tools for identifying which therapeutic questions can be effectively addressed using observational data and under what conditions. This paper proposes methods for such an aim. Purely for purposes of illustration, we shall devote special attention to assessment of the consequences of extraventricular drainage (EVD) in specific strata of the aSAH patient population. Our data base currently contains aSAH patient-level data from a multicenter hospital registry started in 2011, spanning 15 UK centers and Ireland.</p><p>Before tackling the problem, it may be helpful to review the scoring systems that stroke professionals use to measure a patient's consciousness level by condensing multiple aspects of the patient's status into a single score. In our illustrative analysis, for sake of simplicity, we refrained from treating the different aspects as separate variables, although this would allow a more efficient use of the available information.</p><p>There is a significant perceived margin for improvement in aSAH outcomes, as well articulated by a recent report from the Research Guidelines Committee of the National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. The report highlights the "glaring absence of an adequate evidence base for the management of aSAH patients." It also criticizes the lack of a reliable model for predicting outcomes to guide triage decisions, which sometimes leads to specialists unintentionally withholding treatment from patients who, despite initially poor conditions, could have experienced a favorable recovery.</p><p>Randomized clinical trials in aSAH represent a challenge, our require careful pilot observational studies. Progress thus depends on determining which questions in aSAH management can be effectively addressed using observational data and under what conditions. When these conditions are met, we need methods to analyze the data, leading to the development of evidence-based criteria for patient admission to treatment and selection for specific interventions based on individual circumstances. This paper proposes methods to achieve this goal. For illustrative purposes, we denote special attention to assessing the consequences of extraventricular drainage (EVD) in specific strata of the aSAH patient population. Our database currently includes aSAH patientlevel data from a multicenter hospital registry started in 2011, encompassing 15 centers in the UK and Ireland.</p><p>Before addressing the problem, it may be helpful to review the scoring systems that stroke professionals use to measure a patient's consciousness level by condensing multiple aspects of the patient's status into a single score. In our illustrative analysis, for simplicity, we have refrained from treating these different aspects as separate variables, although doing so would allow for a more efficient use of the information. It is defined as an ordinal 5-level factor, where grade 1 corresponds to GCS = 15; grade 2 to 13 ≤ GCS ≤ 14 with focal neurological deficits; grade 3 to 13 ≤ GCS ≤ 14 without focal neurological deficits; grade 4 to 7 ≤ GCS ≤ 12 and grade 5 to 3 ≤ GCS ≤ 6.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GOS</head><p>In our analysis, we redefine WFNS as a 6-level ordered factor (occasionally treated as a continuous variable for analytic convenience), by adding level 6, which we define as corresponding to an orginal WFNS value of 5 in the absence of pupil reaction. GCS provides a basis for the definition of the Glasgow Outcome Scale (GOS) as given in the marginside.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Causal graph for a simple aSAH scenario</head><p>We begin by introducing basic concepts of causal graphs, followed by a simple application to illustrate these ideas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theory</head><p>A DAG defines a conditional independence structure for its variables, thereby determining a family of probability distributions over them. Conditional independence relationships can be read off the graph using several criteria, including the d-separation criterion, which we are now going to summarize <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>.</p><p>d-separation rests on the concept of path along a graph, defined as consisting of a consecutive sequence of edges, regardless of their directions, as for example: B → D ← A. A path may or may not contain a pair of arrows that collide head-to-head, → • ←. If it does, the node between the two arrows is called a collider. We distinguish between "blocked" and "unblocked" paths on the graph in relation to a particular query. A path is blocked if it contains at least one non-collider that is part of the conditioning set in the query, or at least one collider that does not belong to the conditioning set nor has a descendant in that set.  For example let's ask whether, according to the graph in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, variable B is independent of A once we are told the value of D. In Dawid's notation, this assertion is written B ⊥ ⊥ A | D. We find via d-separation that this assertion does not follow from the graph, meaning that conditional on D, variable B is not independent of A. To justify this conclusion, it suffices to consider that when we condition on D the A → D ← B path is unblocked.</p><p>As we stand at this point of the section, the DAG is seen as representing purely conditional independence properties of a set of random variables, ie, a family of probability distributions over the graph. Pearl <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> would, however, imbue the DAG with causal significance in such a way that the same DAG will represent the causal properties of the system (the way the world works) and its conditional independence properties. In Pearl's formulation, this is possible by assuming that the conditional distribution of any given node, given its parents, remains the same when we (hypothetically) switch from the observational setting where we collected the data to a setting where the values of some or all of the variables in the graph are changed by external intervention (interventional setting). Consider the following example. Interpreted causally, the DAG of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> tells us, for example, that the distribution of C, once we know A and B, is unaffected by how the values A and B arose, whether in the same circumstances in which we collected the data, or by external inter-vention. To the extent to which these assumptions concern effects of interventions, they cannot be corroborated by observational data that are by definition collected free from interventions. As claimed by Dawid <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, these considerations impose limits on the machinelearning notion of "causal discovery", which attempts to deduce causal properties solely from conditional independence relationships inferred from observational data. In contrast, our advocated approach makes "causal discoveries" by combining observational data information with pre-existing causal knowledge.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Application</head><p>Now pay attention! Let's illustrate DAG concepts using the straightforward -perhaps overly simplistic -scenario shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>. Imagine an individual who has suffered from aSAH and, as a result, has been referred to a neurosurgical center for treatment. But which center? We know it. That's indicated by the variable labeled Centre. Once the patient arrives, various pieces of information are gathered from them, which we then represent in the graph as part of the node Pre-decision data.</p><p>The gathered information is used by doctors to decide whether the patient should be admitted for treatment. They may not be admitted, or left under observation until perhaps their conditions improve enough to convince the doctors they should be admitted. This is how the triage goes about. And there's so much to say about triage -but let's save that for the next paper! If the patient is admitted, the next step, depending also early in-hospital events, is to evaluate whether an EVD intervention is necessary. This intervention is represented in the graph by node EVD. At a subsequent landmark time or event, such as discharge or a fixed time post-admission, the patient's clinical outcome is observed. Arrows are consistent with the direction of time, but wait for a deeper definition of their meaning. The following variables are involved: EVD: A random binary variable, where 1 indicates that the doctors decide to perform the EVD intervention on the patient, and 0 indicates that the intervention is forgone.</p><p>Centre: A pointer to the surgical center where the patient has been referred for treatment.</p><p>Pre-decision data: everything relevant (excluding Centre) in the patient's history up to EVD decision. A list of these variables is given in Section "Causal analysis of the effect of EVD". Teo variables which will play an important role in the discussion are derived from the patient's brain scan: Devastating scan, which is self-explanatory, and AB, defined as the ratio of the maximum width of the frontal horns of the lateral ventricles to the maximum internal diameter of the skull at the same level.</p><p>Outcome: A binary random variable where 1 indicates an unfavourable clinical outcome (as defined in the study) and 0 otherwise.</p><p>U : The patient's unobserved, deep state of health.</p><p>Admitted: A binary indicator where TRUE indicates that the patient is admitted, and FALSE otherwise. Our illustrative analysis conditions on this node being TRUE in all patients.</p><p>Some nodes represent doctors' decisions. Others characterise the patient's health status. Some could conceivably be intervened upon.</p><p>For instance, Centre decision is "intervenable" since it is possible to imagine intervening in the decision about the centre a patient is referred to. Different centers may vary in their practice styles, not merely due to differences in patient populations but also because of professional preferences or differing opinions on the effects of interventions. Consequently, intervening on center decision may influence subsequent clinical decisions and outcomes, and this is represented in the graph by causal arrows originating from Centre and pointing towards EVD and Outcome.</p><p>Node Pre-decision data contains variables that may inform decisions (admission and or EVD) as well as intervenable variables (eg Hypertension that may be causal to the outcome. If we were to expose the "guts" of node Pre-decision data, we would see details of its internal causal relationships and of its causal/informational relationships with the remaining nodes of the graph. Our model also allows some or all the pre-decision variables to directly correlate with the patient's deep state of health, U.</p><p>Note in our graph that Pre-decision data and Centre are marginally independent but become dependent when conditioning on admission. This aligns with the observation that center-specific catchment areas exhibit similar frequencies of medical variables, while patient groups may differ with respect to them due to differing admission criteria. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EVD Smoking</head><note type="other">Centre Admitted Outcome</note></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Identification Theory</head><p>Consider a causal DAG model G and let V denote the set of variables of the dag that we have observed and made available to the analyst. Let the causal question of interest ask whether X causes Y, with (X, Y) ⊆ V. A crucial step in addressing the question is to determine whether, under the assumptions encoded in G, the information provided by V determines a unique, unbiased, estimate of the effect of X on Y. Pearl's back-door criterion gives a sufficient condition for identifiability. It requires the existence of a (possibly empty) subset Z of V such that no member of Z is a descendant of X and such that Z blocks (in the sense of d-separation) every path between X and Y that contains an arrow into X, so called back-door path.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Application</head><p>This section demonstrates the capability of the DAG machinery, in conjunction with d-separation, to determine whether a causal question is nonparametrically identified in a given analysis situation. We do it through examples.</p><p>Our first example considers the question whether the variables represented in the graph of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> identify the causal effect of antecedent Smoking habit on Outcome, in an admitted patient, under the assumptions represented in the graph. The answer to the question is yes. In fact, once we condition on Admitted= T RU E and Centre, no unblocked back-door paths exist between Smoking and Outcome.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref> represents an elaboration of the graph of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>, involving the addition of node Hypertension. The causal effect of antecedent smoking on outcome is no longer (nonparametrically) identified, whether or not we condition on Hypertension. In fact, in this new scenario, we have two potential back-door paths with respect to the effect of Smoking: The first is Smoking → Admitted = TRUE ← Hypertension ← U → Outcome. The second is Smoking → Hypertension ← U → Outcome. The former is unblocked when we do not condition on Hypertension. The latter is unblocked when we do condition. Luckily, the problem may be successfully tackled via inverse probability weighting <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</p><p>We've just seen that adding the Hypertension node to the graph in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> disrupts the identifiability of the effect of prior smoking. This underscores the fragility of our assumptions when dealing with our uncertainty about the biological universe is challenging. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Under D EVD</head><p>Outc -completeness, ie, when these two variables are available, a regression analysis of the dependence of Outcome on EVD, within a sample of admitted patients, provided the variables Centre, Smoking and Hypertension are adjusted for, will estimate the causal effect of EVD on Outcome.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Positivity</head><p>Let's assume the causal effect of interest is identified by the data we have. This doesn't necessarily guarantee the data contains information about the effect. We are now going to address this issue by introducing and then using the concept of positivity.</p><p>Let the symbol a denote the generic value of the intervention variable A with domain A = (0, 1) say, where 0 indicates "no intervention" and 1 "intervention". Let the symbol pa A denote the set of variables that are parents of A in the graph, including Centre and all those variables in Pre-decision data that inform the EVD decision. Let the symbol S A denote the region of values of pa A in the patient (sub-)population of interest. Let the symbol D denote the data available to the analyst. Then a necessary condition for the effect of the intervention on patients in S A to be estimable from the data is <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>:</p><p>Positivity condition for evaluating the effect of intervention A on patients in S A ): for every configuration pa A = pa * A , with pa * A ∈ S A , and for each a ∈ A, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">p(a | pa * A ; D) &gt; 0,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where the probabilities involved are large enough for the data to provide a sufficient amount of information to estimate the effect of A.</p><p>The above condition tells us that for every possible configuration of the variables that inform the decision about the intervention and of the intervention variable, there is a positive probability of finding a patient with that configuration in the subpopulation of interest. This implies that if we regard the probability b(pa A ) ≡ p(a = 1 | pa A ; D) as a scalar function of pa A , called the balancing score, and we consider, for each intervention group, its probability density profile over this function, the profiles are continuous with respect to each other, meaning, in practice, that each profile rises above zero wherever the other one does so.</p><p>The balancing score, b(pa A ), must be estimated from the data. One possibility is to assign the b(.) function an a priori parametric form with unknown parameters to be estimated from the data. Since estimation will not involve the outcome, no multiple comparisons bias will affect this procedure. Machine learning algorithms to estimate b(.) are welcome.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Causal analysis of the effect of EVD</head><p>The themes we've discussed so far will converge in this section, much like the spokes of an upside-down fan.</p><p>The analysis we are about to present illustrates what can be done midway through an observational study with the aid of a causal graph, as an aid to an effective management. One author (HP) dedicated considerable effort to interviewing key "actors in the scene", specifically, the aSAH professionals responsible for daily triage and EVD decisions. These interviews resulted in a list of variables that stay "on top of the doctors' heads" during their routine. This list was then compared against the existing collection of database variables. A main discrepancy was discovered: the absence of brain scan (BS) information from the database, and, in particular, of the previously mentioned variables Devastating scan and AB ratio.</p><p>The perceived importance of the missing BS variables, affecting both EVD decision-making and the patient's subsequent evolution, generated trepidation. BS information was clearly a potential unobserved confounder in our analysis. We faced two options: either start systematically digitizing and recording BS information on a long series of future patients or, if feasible, retrieve and digitize the brain scans of past patients and add the information to the database. The latter option proved viable. So far, we have added BS data for 258 patients, alongside the other listed variables. Among BS variables, Devastating Scan is self-explanatory, and AB represents the ratio of the maximum width of the frontal horns of the lateral ventricles to the maximum internal diameter of the skull at the same level.</p><p>In the following description of our pilot analysis of the 258 patients, the goal is not to provide an exhaustive report of the results but rather to highlight the "causal discovery" idea.</p><p>A Bayesian logit-linear regression model of the binary intervention variable, EVD, was fitted to the sample of 258 patients considering all the candidate influencing factors (including BS variables). Results from the fitting are summarized in the forest plot shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>.</p><p>In the plot, circles represent point estimates of covariate effects on the log-odds of sustaining EVD, while the extending lines indicate the corresponding 95% Bayesian credible intervals. The plot demonstrates the dominant influence of brain scan variables and Rebleed on the decision to administer EVD, with the contributions of the remaining variables appearing relatively minor in comparison.</p><p>We used the model-predicted probability of EVD, or EVD propensity score, as a balancing score, (b(.) in our previous notation) between the two intervention groups (EVD vs. no-EVD). A stochastic matching algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> was then applied to the original sample of patients to extract two smaller, well-matched intervention groups with respect to this balancing score. Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref> illustrates the density profiles of the two intervention groups along the balancing score, both before (left plot) and after (right plot) matching.</p><p>In both cases, the densities of the two groups do not have identical support, indicating a lack of positivity. The figure suggests that within the aSAH patient population, there are "extreme ends" (very low or very high propensity) where clinicians generally agree on whether or not to perform EVD, but lack of consensus on EVD in the central region of the propensity score profiles. The lack of positivity signals potential challenges in assessing the overall effect of EVD in the aSAH population, even with comprehensive data collection, including BS information, from a large patient cohort.</p><p>Next, we focused on the 158 patients with WFNS grade 1 within the sample of 258 patients, trying to glean from this limited sample an answer to the question whether a comparison of EVD versus no-EVD within this specific patient category is within reach in our observational study. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref> visualizes the balancing of the two intervention groups by juxtaposing their density profiles along the balancing score, calculated specifically for this category. The degree of balancing appears to be poor due to lack of positivity. Most patients in this stratum appear to have a very low propensity to receive EVD, and within this low-propensity group, there appears to be significant disagreement among doctors as to whether EVD should be performed. However, this category also includes a subgroup with extreme propensity for EVD, corresponding to a small density peak at the upper extreme of the horizontal axis. This is likely to correspond to grade 1 patients with poor brain scan results. What we learn from this plot is that evaluating the effect of EVD within a patient stratum not defined by brain scan variables is of limited value. In conclusion, the question of the effect of EVD in grade 1 patients is poorly framed.</p><p>We then moved to considering the question: "is EVD beneficial within grade 1 patients with no rebleeding and an AB ratio greater than 0.12?"</p><p>Out of the 258 patients of our sample, 147 belonged to the category in question. Our analysis of the 147 patients produced the balancing plot of Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>. The degree of balancing is good, thanks to the uniform disagreement among doctors/centres about the best EVD choice for this patient category. The post-matching EVD vs no-EVD balance is, in fact, very good in this category. In conclusion, it may be a good idea to pursue the above question (or even better questions posited by the specialists) once the larger database has been completed with brain scan data. Post-matching we remained with a sample of 68 patients, corresponding to a sampling ratio of 0.46. As uncertain as this ratio is, given the exiguity of the sample, it nevertheless provides a ballpark estimate of the sample size required to emulate the power of a randomized clinical trial of, say, 100 recruits. We would approximately need 100/0.46 = 218 grade 1 patients with no rebleeding and AB ratio greater than 0.12. propensity to EVD, from an analysis of patients with available brain scan information, characterized by a WFNS grade 1, no rebleeding and an AB ratio greater than 0.12.</p><p>The balancing plot from an analysis of the patients with AB ratio greater than 0.5 is shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">9</ref>. The balancing is poor, one reason being that the EVD decision is undisputed at the extremes of the considered interval of AB values, leaving only some uncertainty and disagreement in the central region of the propensity axis.</p><p>As a final example, note in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">10</ref> the good balancing of the EVD intervention groups within the group of patients with AB ratio between 0.1 and 0.5. This plot reveals lack of consensus about the best EVD decision over the entire range of EVD propensity. This is one question we might wosh to pursue with a complete database.</p><p>Some might find the questions raised in this section less compelling. Never mind! We hope we have illustrated the ability of the method to highlight the importance of adding certain variables to the database, and to identify from a large number of potential causal questions, those that are actually feasible to pursue using observational data, once those variables have been incorporated.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Monitoring</head><p>In this final section, we show results from an analysis of the global sample of 18000 patients with WFNS grade 3-5, across 18 participating centres, by omitting brain scan variables due to their huge percentage of missing values. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">11</ref> summarizes the results from a linear regression analysis of the EVD indicator, allowing a nearcomplete collection of EVD influences (bar BS variables) to enter the model. Variable Centre, in particular, contributed 17 unknown parameters into the model, with Centre 1 taken as reference.</p><p>Noteworthy in this figure is the remarkable amount of variation in propensity to EVD introduced by the variable Centre, compared with that of the most important variables characterizing the patient's health status. It is unlikely that this variation is an artifact due to missing brain scan information. A similar observation applies to Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">12</ref>, which summarizes results from fitting a linear model of the probability of an adverse outcome using the same set of ex- planatory variables as the preceding regression. Joint inspection of <ref type="bibr">Figures 11 and 12</ref> suggests proportionality between the effects exerted by each centre on EVD and on outcome. This is important, because evidence that the centre effect on EVD propensity leads to a proportional effects on outcome may, under certain assumptions, be a sign of causality.</p><p>For a closer look into proportionality we have generated the plot in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">13</ref>, where each ith anonymized centre is represented by a circle with coordinates (α i , β i ), where α i denotes the estimated centre effect on EVD propensity, and β i the estimated centre effect on probability of n unfavourable outcome. The horizontal axis in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">12</ref> quantifies the centre's negative propensity (reluctance) to administer EVD, and the vertical axis is the estimated centrespecific probability of adverse outcomes. Centres falling near the upper right corner of the plot are characterised by low propensity to EVD and correspondingly high risk of an adverse outcome.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">13</ref> is, indeed, mildly suggestive that performing EVD is ben-eficial for a poor grade patient. In fact, it suggests a tendency of an unfavourable outcome to occur in centres who are "reluctant" to perform EVD. This interpretation is emphasized by the positive slope of the superimposed line. which is, in fact, Egger's instrumental variable (IV) estimate of the causal effect of avoiding EVD on probability of an unfavourable outcome, and has been calculated by taking precision of estimates into account. In other words, we are leveraging the diversity of preference for EVD across centres as an instrument for probing a possible causal effect of EVD on outcome.</p><p>Validity of this approach depends on untestable assumptions, including the "instrument strength independent of direct effect" (InSIDE) assumption that centre effects on outcome that are not mediated by EVD be uncorrelated with the corresponding effects on propensity to EVD.</p><p>Due to this result having been obtained from data devoid of brain scan patient information, we remain hesitant to offer this as evidence in favour of a causal hypothesis. We are just interested in illustrating the method. Note that this plot offers more than just a numerical effect estimate: it marks the position of each individual centre with respect to the remaing ones in terms of outcome and propensity to EVD, as a basis for centre performance monitoring in relation to the impact of specific aspects of the centres' clinical practices.</p><p>The two regressions were fitted by using a linear link function (a choice made possible by the limited range of values of the probabilities of an unfavourable outcome) rather than a logistic one to avoid problems of collapsibility.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>Unlike conventional machine-learning approaches, our "causal discovery" method makes explicit the necessary assumptions for draw-  ing valid causal conclusions, empowering users to actively manage these assumptions through the use of a causal graph.</p><p>What we refer to as "causal discovery" in this paper is an evolving process. As the study progresses, incoming data are integrated with the causal graph to sharpen the focus on causal questions that can be effectively addressed using observational data. This approach also helps to identify the key areas where the database needs to be expanded to achieve the study's objectives.</p><p>Many clinical observational studies rely on high-quality hospital registries, which initially include only a limited set of clinical variables due to the high cost and time-consuming nature of data collection.</p><p>As the study advances and specific scientific questions emerge, it be-  comes crucial to ensure that the registry contains all the necessary data to address these inquiries. Our method involves conducting "in itinere" pilot studies (such as our study with 258 patients) and using the causal graph to identifying data gaps early on and providing targeted recommendations for selectively enriching the database.</p><p>In Section "Monitoring," we introduce a different approach to the problem. Rather than aiming for a quantitative assessment of causal effects, this approach visualizes the trajectories of individual treatment centers in terms of their propensity for specific interventions and their outcomes. The relative positions of centers on the plot offer insights into different styles of practice and their impacts on outcomes. The case of aSAH serves as a valuable benchmark for applying the proposed methods in a real clinical setting. It is challenging to grasp the potential impact of our method without considering the sociological aspects of how the medical community advances research. aSAH is a fitting example because therapeutic decisions in aSAH are complex, with a lack of an adequate evidence base to guide practice, allowing considerable clinical freedom. In one scenario, clinicians might converge on a particular intervention policy unsupported by evidence, leading to a lack of positivity and research inertia. In another scenario, the medical community may split into different camps, that adopts intervention policies at odds with each other. This also risks a lack of positivity, thereby hampering knowledge advancement through observational studies. This division can also prevent an RCT (randomized controlled trial) from being accepted due to difficulty in reaching consensus on equipoise. Our method allows researchers to use observational data to capture snapshots of the situation and use them to steer the study in the most promising direction.</p><p>One final remark concerns causal questions that are both intriguing and challenging to pursue. One such question is, "Who is expected to benefit from being admitted to treatment?" The question is important in the light of recent criticisms of the current aSAH triage regime. Such a question must be approached using data from individuals referred to various centers for aSAH treatment, where some have been admitted and others have not, with both groups followed up for an appropriate period before measuring outcomes. Randomizing admission is clearly not an option, so we must ask whether observational data can help. The answer is "yes ... but." If all centers use the same admission criteria, there will be insufficient positivity and the data will not suffice to address this question. The challenge lies in whether there is enough variation in admission criteria across centers for the data to yield useful insights. If the amount of "disagreement" is sufficient, analysis will focus on heterogeneity of effects, namely, of studying the way admission changes prospects of a favourable clinical improvement and, potentially, aspects of causative interaction between different decisions along the clinical journey, in the light of a global causal graph representation of the therapeutic process.</p><p>This draft is the first version of a paper waiting for brain scan data to be made available.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Example of a directed acyclic graph (DAG).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Causal DAG representation of a simple aSAH scenario.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: The causal effect of antecedent smoking on outcome is (nonparametrically) identified by the set of variables represented in the graph, with Admitted = TRUE, based on a sample of admitted patients.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Slightly more elaborate version of the preceding figure. The causal effect of antecedent smoking on outcome is no longer (nonparametrically) identified, whether or not we condition on Hypertension.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Forest plot summary of the fitting of a Bayesian logit-linear regression model of the indicator of sustained EVD on all its known influences, based on the sample of 258 patients complete with brain scan information.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7: Assessment of balance between EVD intervention groups with respect to propensity to EVD, from an analysis of grade 1 patients with available brain scan information.</figDesc><graphic coords="20,189.02,131.50,229.90,183.91" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>12 Figure 8 :</head><label>128</label><figDesc>Figure 8: Assessment of balance between EVD intervention groups with respect to</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9: Again, poor balancing of the EVD intervention groups with AB &gt; 0.5.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>5 Figure 10 :</head><label>510</label><figDesc>Figure 10: Good Balancing of the EVD intervention groups within patients with AB ratio between 0.1 and 0.5.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 11 :</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11: Forest plot summary of the fitting of a Bayesian linear regression model of the indicator of sustained EVD on its influences, including the 18-level factor Centre.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 12 :</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 12: Forest plot summary of the fitting of a Bayesian linear regression model of the binary outcome variable on all known pre-decision patient variables, including the 18-level factor Centre.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 13 :</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Figure 13: Results from an analysis of patients with poor WFNS grade. Participating centers are represented by circles, with horizontal coordinate corresponding to the centre's negative propensity (reluctance) to perform EVD, and the vertical one representing the estimated centre-specific probability of adverse outcomes. The slope of the superimposed line equals Egger's IV estimate of the effect of administering EVD in a poor grade patient, calculated by taking precision of estimates into account.</figDesc><graphic coords="27,169.06,128.40,269.29,251.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Glasgow Outcome Scale (GOS) Categories</figDesc><table><row><cell>Category</cell><cell>Description</cell></row><row><cell>5 -Death</cell><cell>Death due to the initial brain damage. It may be categorized</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>based on whether it occurred before or after regaining conscious-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ness, distinguishing initial recovery.</cell></row><row><cell>4 -Persistent Vegetative</cell><cell>Unresponsive and speechless for weeks or months post-injury, with</cell></row><row><cell>State</cell><cell>sleep-wake cycles emerging after 2-3 weeks.</cell></row><row><cell>3 -Severe Disability (con-</cell><cell>Requires daily support due to physical and/or mental disabilities.</cell></row><row><cell>scious but disabled)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2 -Moderate Disability (dis-</cell><cell>Independent in daily life, able to manage self-care and daily ac-</cell></row><row><cell>abled but independent)</cell><cell>tivities, though possibly with significant family disruption.</cell></row><row><cell>1 -Good Recovery</cell><cell>Resumption of normal life with possible minor neurological or</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>psychological deficits. Return to work could be influenced by so-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>cioeconomic factors and personal circumstances.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">The Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS) is a composite of assessments across</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">three response categories: eye (1 to 4 from no eye opening to open-</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">ing eyes spontaneously), verbal (1 to 5 from no verbal response to</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">oriented and conversational), and motor (1 to 6 from no motor re-</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">sponse to obeying commands). A score at the upper limit of 15 de-</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">notes normal consciousness, whereas the lower threshold of 3 reflects</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">a profound unconscious state. Next we have the World Federation</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">of Neurosurgical Surgeons (WFNS) score, used in the figure above.</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causal diagrams for epidemiologic research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Greenland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dawid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2402.09429</idno>
		<ptr target="https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.09429" />
		<title level="m">What is a causal graph? arXiv preprint</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The central role of the propensity score in observational studies for causal effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rosenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Rubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Subarachnoid hemorrhage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Lawton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Vates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/NEJMcp1605827</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">New England Journal of Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">377</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="266" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">NICE Guideline for Subarachnoid Haemorrhage: Evidence Review for Severity Scoring Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>National Guideline Centre</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Developed by the National Guideline Centre, hosted by the Royal College of Physicians</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conditional independence in statistical theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dawid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.2517-6161.1979.tb01052.x</idno>
		<ptr target="https://academic.oup.com/jrsssb/article/41/1/1/7027599" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B (Methodological)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Probabilistic Reasoning in Intelligent Systems: Networks of Plausible Inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann</publisher>
			<pubPlace>San Mateo, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Causality: Models, Reasoning and Inference</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beware of the DAG</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dawid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>PMLR</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Workshop on Causality: Objectives and Assessment at NIPS 2008</title>
		<meeting>Workshop on Causality: Objectives and Assessment at NIPS 2008</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="86" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Marginal structural models and causal inference in epidemiology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hernán</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Brumback</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="550" to="560" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying the consequences of dynamic treatment strategies: A decision-theoretic overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dawid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Didelez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1214/10-ss081</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistics Surveys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimum distance matched sampling with fine balance in an observational study of treatment for ovarian cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rosenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">477</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
