<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Homopositivity Across Europe: Predictors, Pathways, and Moderators</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2023-01-20">20 January 2023</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Adam</forename><surname>Whitworth</surname></persName>
							<email>adam.whitworth@strath.ac.uk</email>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0001-6119-9373</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Work, Employment and Organisation</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Strathclyde Business School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Strathclyde</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>G4 0QU</postCode>
									<settlement>Glasgow</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Angelo</forename><surname>Moretti</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Methodology and Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Utrecht University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Utrecht</settlement>
									<country key="NL">Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Homopositivity Across Europe: Predictors, Pathways, and Moderators</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2023-01-20">20 January 2023</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10508-023-02531-8</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 28 October 2020 / Revised: 4 January 2023 / Accepted: 4 January 2023 /</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T22:21+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Homopositivity</term>
					<term>Homonegativity</term>
					<term>Structural equation modelling</term>
					<term>Mediation</term>
					<term>European Social Survey</term>
					<term>Sexual orientation</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Although homopositivity, the attitudinal acceptance of homosexuality, has generally increased across Western societies, there remains considerable homonegativity across certain regions of the world as well as certain demographic and socioeconomic groups. Although previous cross-national research has successfully identified the key factors affecting homopositive attitudes, the literature neglects both potentially key mediation pathways and moderating interactions between those factors that may unlock more nuanced understanding of these variations in homopositive attitudes across individuals and places. In response, the present study innovatively applied a multivariate structural equation modelling approach to the latest Wave 9 (2018 data) of the large-scale cross-national European Social Survey data in order to shed new light on these currently neglected predictors, pathways, and moderating influences on homopositive attitudes. It used a three-item latent variable to measure the homopositive attitudes outcomes construct. Its explanatory variables were focused across three key sets of factors identified in theoretical and empirical literature (socioeconomics, religiosity, and values) alongside various wider controls. Our analyses made several innovative methodological and empirical contributions to existing debate. Key innovative findings include the original identification of important indirect effects of religious beliefs on homopositive attitudes via religious practices, important indirect effects of education on homopositive attitudes via household income, and the role of national welfare regimes to homopositive attitudes (and with its effects interestingly not moderated by household income).</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Although homopositivity, the attitudinal acceptance of homosexuality, has generally increased across Western societies there remains considerable homonegativity across certain regions of the world including Africa, Eastern Europe, and parts of Asia <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Alozie et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">IGLA Europe, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Roberts, 2019)</ref>. In addition, there is evidence to suggest that legal and policy protections for homosexuality are far from inevitable, with several eastern European nations showing reversals in previous progress towards homopositivity between 2018 and 2019 <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(IGLA Europe, 2019)</ref>. Within nations too, there remains widespread variation in homopositive attitudes across individuals. Several cross-national quantitative studies have examined the reasons for variation in homonegative attitudes across Europe <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Gerhards, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Hooghe &amp; Meeusen, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kuntz et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Slenders et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Takacs et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">van den Akker et al., 2013)</ref>, "Western" nations <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Hildebrandt et al., 2017)</ref> and globally <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Hadler &amp; Symons, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hildebrandt et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Kenny &amp; Patel, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Redman, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Roberts, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Souza &amp; Cribari-Neto, 2015)</ref>. A range of further studies have posed similar questions of specific regions and individual nations including Taiwan <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Cheng et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Zhou &amp; Hu, 2020)</ref>, Korea <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Youn, 2018)</ref>, China <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Zhou &amp; Hu, 2020)</ref>, Singapore <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Zhou &amp; Hu, 2020)</ref>, the USA <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Haney, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Worthen et al., 2019)</ref>, Netherlands <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Haney, 2016)</ref>, Italy <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Worthen et al., 2019)</ref>, Spain <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Worthen et al., 2019)</ref>, Africa <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Alozie et al., 2017)</ref>, and Eastern Europe <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Bolzendahl &amp; Gracheva, 2018)</ref>.</p><p>Taken together these studies have successfully identified many of the key predictors of homopositive attitudes including age, religiosity, gender, education, and income as well as the country's level of economic development and general level of religiosity. Analysing recently released survey data for 36,015 individuals across 19 European nations, the present article takes as its basic starting point a similar multiple regression modelling strategy to previous studies including these and further explanatory factors as a reflection of the current state of the art in cross-national understanding of homopositive attitudes. From this basic starting point, the paper advances in a series of ways to make three main contributions to the existing literature.</p><p>Firstly, while previous cross-national research has successfully identified the key factors affecting homopositive attitudes, current literature neglects possible mediation pathways between those explanatory factors. For the first time in the literature, the present paper embraces the flexibility around path analysis within a multivariate structural equation modelling (SEM) framework to bring the exploration of key mediation pathways to the heart of the analysis. The exploration of such mediation pathways is important to understand the indirect as well as direct effects of key explanatory variables as well as to shine a light on the processes at play in shaping homopositive attitudes.</p><p>Secondly, previous research pays relatively little attention to the potential moderation of key explanatory factors, with some notable exceptions <ref type="bibr">(Hildebrand et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kuntz et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Worthen et al., 2017)</ref>. As such, the current evidence base for the most part assumes that the effects found on key explanatory variables such as religiosity, income, and values simply apply equally, which may not be the case empirically. In contrast, the present study examines the potential for important interaction effects. Specifically, novel within our analyses is the examination of how the effect of religious beliefs may vary by religious denomination-two key and related factors not previously examined in terms of their potential moderation. Also novel is our attention to how the effects of household income might vary by national welfare regime-a factor found in various strands of welfare scholarship to be important to explaining cross-national differences in a range of cultures and outcomes (Esping- <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Andersen, 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Pierson, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Powell et al., 2020)</ref>, but that is largely neglected in previous scholarship into homopositivity.</p><p>Thirdly, although the idea of homopositivity is widely understood in general terms its practical measurement as an outcome indicator lacks attention or debate in the literature, despite the clear importance of its specification to findings. Previous studies select one outcome indicator to capture the concept, often (though by no means always) a general question asking to what extent respondents agree with the statement that gay and lesbian individuals should be free to live their life as they wish. Instead, the present study acknowledges that homopositivity should instead be treated as a latent concept with multiple dimensions and whose nature and strength of feeling may vary dependent upon the specific dimension in question <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Preuss et al., 2020)</ref>. To enable this, our analyses measure homopositivity as a latent outcome comprised of three conceptually distinct indicators of support for homosexuality.</p><p>The existing body of theory and evidence highlights four main sets of factors key to shaping homopositive attitudes, even if individual studies frequently do not incorporate all four: religiosity; socioeconomics; basic human values; and country-level contexts. These blocks of explanatory factors form the basis of the present article's theoretical and empirical structure and contributions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Religiosity</head><p>Religiosity is consistently found to be a major determinant of homonegativity, with the strength of religious belief, the degree of regular participation in religious practices, and religious denomination each playing a role <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Gerhards, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Herek, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hildebrandt et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Hooghe &amp; Meeusen, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kuntz et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Slenders et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">van den Akker et al., 2013)</ref>. As would be expected, the greater the level of religiosity the less inclined individuals tend to be towards homopositivity, in terms of both the strength of religious belief and the frequency of religious practices. Variation can also be seen across religious denominations, with individuals of Muslim faith tending to be somewhat more homonegative than other religious denominations, even after having controlled for levels of religious belief and participation alongside other factors <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Hooghe &amp; Meeusen, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Slenders et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">van den Akker et al., 2013)</ref>. At a wider societal level, research also finds that the general level of religiosity can affect individual's attitudes towards homosexuality <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Kollman, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Slenders et al., 2014)</ref>. This may be due to religious institutions as anchor institutions of social messaging and education or the increased likelihood of social interactions with people of religious faith <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Moore &amp; Vanneman, 2003)</ref>.</p><p>However, despite religious beliefs, practices, and denominations each being found to be important factors in shaping homopositive attitudes, previous studies do not consider the theoretical or empirical possibilities of either mediation pathways or moderation effects between them. Our analyses provide two original contributions for the literature in these regards. Firstly, the modelling explores the potential indirect effect of religious beliefs on homopositive attitudes through its mediation with religious practices. Secondly, our later modelling includes an interaction effect between religious beliefs and religious denomination in order to explore whether there is any evidence that the effects of these religious beliefs vary across different faith groups.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Socioeconomics</head><p>Research consistently finds a positive association between higher levels of education and more tolerant attitudes towards homosexuality <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Alozie et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bolzendahl &amp; Gracheva, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Gerhards, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Haney, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hadler &amp; Symons, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Hooghe &amp; Meeusen, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kuntz et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Redman, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Slenders et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Takacs et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">van den Akker et al., 2013)</ref>, although the trend towards greater acceptance of homosexuality is visible at all educational levels <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Treas, 2002)</ref>. Equally, although less widely analysed, previous studies also find a positive association between higher levels of household income and more homopositive attitudes <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Slenders et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Zhou &amp; Hu, 2020)</ref>. Our SEM models similarly examine the direct effects of both education and household income on homopositive attitudes. However, our analyses go further than current scholarship in also exploring the potential indirect effects of education on homopositivity through household income, a mediation pathway justified by evidence of the financial returns to education and training <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Oreopolous &amp; Gunderson, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Psacharopoulos &amp; Patrinos, 2018)</ref>.</p><p>Finally, while household income is found to shape attitudes towards homosexuality <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Slenders et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Zhou &amp; Hu, 2020)</ref>, the possible role of the national welfare regime in moderating those links is neglected in previous research, with notable exceptions <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Takacs et al., 2016)</ref>. This is surprising given the demonstration in welfare regimes scholarship of the relevance of welfare regimes to shaping a range of crossnational differences in expectations, behaviours, and outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Esping-Andersen, 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Pierson, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Powell et al., 2020)</ref>. Specific to our analyses, the nature of the national welfare regime has been found to be of relevance to explaining attitudes towards other social cleavages such as immigration <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Crepaz &amp; Damron, 2009)</ref> and plays an important role in shaping and mediating low income in notably differing ways <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Esping-Andersen, 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Powell et al., 2020)</ref>. In later analyses, our modelling advances to explore the potential role of welfare regime both as a direct effect on homopositive attitudes as well as a possible moderator of the effect of household income on homopositive attitudes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Basic Human Values</head><p>Research into the content, structure, and consequences of basic human values has grown rapidly since Schwartz's pioneering work around three decades ago <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Schwartz, 1992)</ref>. A recent review article summarises that "values predict a large variety of attitudes, preferences and overt behaviors" <ref type="bibr">(Sagiv et al., 2017, p. 630)</ref>. In brief, Schwartz's value theory presents a circle of ten basic human values that cover four main domains of openness to change, self-transcendence, conservation, and self-enhancement that relate to one another in complementarity as well as tension. In doing so, Schwartz's value theory resonates with Herek's influential research into homonegative values and attitudes, in particular the call to complement the focus on homophobia with a broader recognition of the constructs and processes of sexual stigma, heterosexism, and sexual prejudice argued to underlie the structures, ideologies, and power relations that perpetuate hostility towards homosexuals <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Herek, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Herk &amp; McLemore, 2013)</ref>.</p><p>The relevance of human values to homopositive attitudes has been well demonstrated in the existing research literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Fitzgerald et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Gerhards, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">van den Akker et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Vicario et al., 2005)</ref>. Our modelling approach advances these studies by analysing the effects of a more detailed set of values than previous studies as well as by exploring the potential role of a country's LGBT-friendly legislative arrangements in moderating the effects of those basic human values. In doing so, our analyses unpack potentially hidden heterogeneity in effects and moderations as compared with previous key studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Kuntz et al., 2015)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Further Controls</head><p>Further controls at both the individual and country level are also included in the modelling. Older individuals and males are, on average, found in previous studies to be less tolerant of homosexuality than younger individuals <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Alozie et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Fitzgerald et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Haney, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Herek, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Hooghe &amp; Meeusen, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kuntz et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Redman, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Slenders et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Zhou &amp; Hu, 2020)</ref>. Three further individual-level control variables-poor health, presence of dependent children, and general life satisfaction-are included. These factors are not included in previous studies, and their potential relevance is therefore unclear. It is hypothesized that having children and being generally more satisfied may relate positively to tolerance for homosexuality because of a desire for one's child to be accepted unconditionally by others and due to a greater ease with others flowing from greater ease with oneself. At the country leve,l further controls are added relating to the level of economic development <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Gerhards, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Kenny &amp; Patel, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Roberts, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Slenders et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Souza &amp; Cribari-Neto, 2015)</ref> and the general level of religious affiliation <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Hadler &amp; Symons, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kuntz et al., 2015)</ref> based on previous findings demonstrating their relevance. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures and Procedure</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Basic SEM Modelling Strategy</head><p>Although not used in previous in studies in the literature, SEM offers a flexible statistical framework to incorporate our theoretical innovations around the examination of homopositivity as a latent concept, mediation pathways, moderation, and moderated mediation <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Edwards &amp; Lambert, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Kline, 2011)</ref>. All models are conducted using the "sem" command in Stata. The final model employs moderated multiple regression and given the advice to use unstandardized coefficients in such models <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Kline, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Whisman &amp; McClelland, 2005)</ref>; all models are interpreted using unstandardized coefficients throughout for consistency. All analyses are stratified by country and survey weighted as per the ESS guidance <ref type="bibr">(ESS, 2014)</ref>.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref> provides a visual summary of the basic SEM modelling strategy with the selection of variables guided by existing research as outlined above. As is standard in SEM notation, the homopositivity outcome is visualized as an oval to denote its incorporation as a latent factor while variables in rectangles denote single indicators. The modelling strategy is oriented around the three main theoretical blocks of religiosity, socioeconomics, and basic human values, with wider controls also included.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Latent Homopositivity Outcome</head><p>As noted above, in contrast to previous research our analyses recognize the potentially multi-dimensional nature of the homopositivity concept and as such measure it via confirmatory factor analysis as a latent factor made up of three indicator variables that capture distinct attitudinal dimensions: "gay and lesbians should be free to live their life as they wish?"; "would you be ashamed if a close family member was gay or lesbian?"; and "gay and lesbian couples should have the right to adopt children?" Each question was recoded 1 to 5 such that higher values relate to more positive attitudes towards homosexuality and goodness of fit statistics support </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Explanatory Variables</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref> summarizes the range of explanatory variables included for each survey respondent. Regards religiosity, literature highlights the relevance of religious beliefs, practices and denomination. Religious beliefs are measured on a 0-10 scale where higher scores relate to stronger religious beliefs. Religious practices are captured by the frequency with which individuals attend routine religious services outside of special occasions such as weddings. This variable is coded 1 to 7 where higher scores relate to greater frequencies of religious practice. Finally, religious denomination is included as dummy variables relating to being of Catholic, Protestant, Eastern Orthodox, Islamic or Other faith, and where No Religion as used as the reference group.</p><p>In the socioeconomic theoretical block, explanatory variables relating to education, income and, in later modelling, national welfare regimes. 1 Education is coded into categories of "low," "medium," and "high" with "low" used as the reference category. Household income is classified into deciles with one being the poorest decile and ten being the wealthiest decile. A final model incorporates national welfare systems as categorized into five commonly used regime types <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Powell et al., 2020)</ref>: Eastern European (Bulgaria, Hungary, Poland, Serbia, Slovenia, Czech Republic) as the reference group; Nordic (Finland, Norway, Netherlands); Liberal (Ireland, United Kingdom); Corporatist (Austria, Belgium, France, Germany, Switzerland); and Southern (Spain, Italy, Cyprus).</p><p>A final theoretical block relates to basic human values and, in later modelling, its potential moderation by the national legislative and policy framework regards homosexuality. Basic human values of universalism, conformity, tradition, self-direction, hedonism, and power are included in our analyses. Each is coded one to six where higher scores correspond to a greater reporting of that value by the individual. The country's legal and policy regulation of homosexuality is incorporated as the 2019 Rainbow Europe Country Index (RECI) score (IGLA Europe, 2019). The scores are a composite index of 46 criteria across the six domains of equality and non-discrimination, family, hate crime and hate speech, legal gender recognition and bodily integrity, civil society space, and asylum. National scores range from zero to one hundred where higher scores denote greater support for homosexuality.</p><p>A range of wider relevant controls are included at the individual and country level. At the individual level, sex is included as a binary variable with male as the reference category. Health condition is included as a binary variable with good health as the reference category and poor health as the dummy. 2 The presence of dependent children is included as a binary variable with no dependent children as the reference category and having dependent children as the dummy. Life satisfaction is included as a binary variable with poor life satisfaction as the reference category and high life satisfaction as the dummy. 3 At the country level, GDP per capita (expressed in 2018 US dollars) and the percentage of the population expressing a religious affiliation in 2018 are included. GDP data are sourced from the World Bank (World Bank, 2020) and national religious affiliation data from the Pew Research Center <ref type="bibr">(Pew Global Research Center, 2018</ref><ref type="bibr">, 2020)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Understanding Homopositive Attitudes Across Europe</head><p>To provide some baseline context for the analyses, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref> shows national survey means for all three indicators of attitudes of homosexuality within our latent outcome measure. All three indicators are measured on a five-point scale where higher values relate to greater tolerance of homosexuality. Acceptance of homosexuality varies widely across Europe from widespread acceptance across Western European and Scandinavian nations to relatively widespread disapproval across Eastern Europe. Variation in support for homosexuality is also evident, with the rights of homosexuals to adopt and raise children seeming more challenging for individuals to accept compared to the rights of homosexuals to live freely with their sexuality or whether a sibling's homosexuality would be a source of shame.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Initial SEM Modelling</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref> moves on to show the results of our initial SEM model of homopositive attitudes in Europe. All coefficients are unstandardized and can therefore be interpreted as the expected change in homopositive attitudes along its fivepoint scale (where higher values denote more positive attitudes towards homosexuality) for every unit change in the 1 "low" = lower secondary and below; "medium" = upper secondary; "high" = advanced vocational and tertiary. 2 "good health" = values 1 and 2 on the underlying health variable; "poor health" = values 3 to 5 on the underlying health variable.</p><p>3 "poor life satisfaction" = values 0 to 6 on the underlying variable; "high life satisfaction" = values 7 to 10 on the underlying variable.</p><p>1 3 explanatory variable. Asterisks denote effects that are statistically significant at the 5% level. It will be noted that the individual-level explanatory factors benefit from a large sample size from which to detect even modest effect sizes with statistical significance while the country-level explanatory factors rely on a far smaller analytic sample size with which to detect the statistical significance of those country-level effects. The overall model fit is good with an R-squared of 69%.  In the religiosity block, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref> highlights that religious attitudes, practices, and denomination all play statistically significant roles in accounting for variation in homopositive attitudes across survey respondents. Other things equal, each point increase in religious beliefs associates with a 0.02 decrease in homopositive attitudes while each point increase in religious practices scale is expected to associate with a 0.09 point decrease in homopositive attitudes. Thus, across their full scales these factors associate with large total effects in attitudes towards homosexuality. These analyses additionally advance previous research in drawing attention to the potential indirect effect of religious beliefs on homopositivity mediated through religious practices. These are two factors identified as important but modelled without connection in previous research. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref> shows that each point increase in religious beliefs associates on average with a 0.29 point increase in religious practices, other things equal. As such, in addition to their direct effects religious beliefs also have notable indirect effects on homopositive attitudes through their association with religious practices. Finally, some variation is seen across different religious denominations. Most notably, individuals of Eastern Orthodox and Islamic faith on average show less positive attitudes towards homosexuality, other things equal.</p><p>Across the socioeconomic factors, the potential effects of education and household income are summarized in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref>. There are two notable differences to previous research. Firstly, while education and income have both been identified as important to homopositivity in previous research they have been treated as unconnected factors. In contrast, our modelling strategy examines the potential for additional indirect effects of education on homopositivity mediated through household income. Other things equal, having either medium or high level education associates positively with homopositive attitudes compared to the reference category of low education, although these effects are modest in magnitude. Other things equal, for each decile wealthier that a household is there is an expected direct increase of 0.02 points on the homopositivity outcome. Education also shows marked indirect effects on homopositive attitudes mediated through household income, which are roughly one third to one half again the size of the direct effects between education and homopositivity.</p><p>As for basic human values, each shows statistically significant estimates and runs in its expected direction. Controlling for other factors, universalism shows the strongest association with homopositivity with a one point increase in the universalism value score expected on average to associate with a 0.25 increase in homopositive attitudes. Tradition, self-direction, and hedonism show smaller positive associations with homopositivity, other things equal, while tradition, conformity, and power show smaller negative associations with homopositivity. The country's RECI score for LGBTfriendly legislative and policy frameworks shows a small but statistically significant relationship with homopositivity.</p><p>Of the wider controls, as expected females tend to show slightly higher scores than males and homopositive attitudes tend to decrease somewhat with every extra year in age, other </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Advancing the SEM Modelling: Exploring Moderation and Moderated Mediation</head><p>Stepping back and reflecting on the SEM modelling above highlights the original insights that are able to be gained through its incorporation of key mediation pathways and latent concepts when compared to the standard regression modelling techniques that dominate the current literature. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref> advances these analyses further by the addition of potentially important yet currently neglected moderation effects and moderated mediation pathways across each of the three core theoretical blocks. Moderated mediation refers to a mediated effect that varies across the of a moderator variable <ref type="bibr">(Edwards &amp; Lambert, 2007:6)</ref>. In the analyses presented in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>, for example, we allow the mediation pathway between household income and homopositivity to be moderated by welfare regime. In doing so the modelling offers a level of detail and sophistication in theoretical explorations not seen within current scholarship in the field. The overall model fit is good with a slightly increased R-squared value of 72%.</p><p>Looking first at the religiosity block, included now in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref> is an interaction between religious beliefs and religious denomination in order to examine for the first time in the literature whether there is any evidence of varying effects of religious belief across faith group. To the centre-right are the main effects of religious denomination flowing directly into the homopositive attitudes outcome. Unlike Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref>, given the presence of the interaction terms these main effects relate now only to the situation where religious beliefs take the value zero (which are reported in the data by individuals across all religious denominations, perhaps surprisingly) on its 0-10 scale. At this low level of religious belief individuals with Catholic, Protestant, or Other faiths show no significant difference in homopositive attitudes compared to the reference category of individuals with no denomination. In contrast, individuals of Eastern Orthodox and especially Islamic faith show notably less positive attitudes towards homosexuality, other things equal. These main effects can be considered a starting point in this more subtle understanding of the relationship between the strength of religious beliefs and homopositive attitudes across different faith groups. The path between religious beliefs and homopositive attitudes to the left then shows how the effects of religious belief vary for each religious denomination as the strength of religious belief increases. It will be remembered that the reference category for the religious denomination variable is those with no religious denomination. Other things equal, for these individuals with no stated denomination each point increase on the religious beliefs scale associates with a small but statistically significant decrease in homopositive attitudes. Individuals of Catholic and Islamic faith are suggested to share that same effect while individuals of Protestant, Eastern Orthodox, and Other denominations show somewhat stronger negative associations between increased religious beliefs and homopositive attitudes, other things equal. Finally, religious beliefs continue to show the same positive association with religious practices and those religious practices in turn continue to show the same negative association with homopositive attitudes, other things equal.</p><p>Regards socioeconomic factors, new to Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref> is the exploration of whether the positive association between household income and homopositive attitudes found in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref> shows variation across different welfare regimes. Given the presence of this interaction effect between household income and welfare regime, the welfare regime main effects in the top section of the socioeconomic block in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref> gives the expected effects of welfare regime for the poorest household income decile only. At this lowest decile of household income, all welfare regimes show large and statistically significant positive associations with homopositive attitudes compared with their Eastern European regime reference group, controlling for other factors. As expected, the Nordic regime shows the largest effect size with a whole point increase in the homopositivity attitudes score expected compared to the reference Eastern welfare regime, other things equal, with Liberal and Corporatist showing slightly smaller but still meaningful effect sizes. The more traditional familialistic and Catholic Southern European welfare regime shows at 0.53 a positive effect around half the size of that seen in the Nordic regime. The welfare regime effects shown on the pathway between household income and homopositive attitudes then reflect the potentially varying effects of household income on homopositive attitudes in each welfare regime type. There is no evidence of varying household income effects across welfare regimes. Taken together, these findings suggest that welfare regime does matter to the shaping of homopositive attitudes but, and perhaps contrary to initial expectations, that it does so less as a moderator of material financial pathways between lower income and homopositive attitudes and instead more as a reflection of their differing cultural and ideological regimes.</p><p>For basic human values, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref> progresses to explore whether the effects of those values seem to be moderated by the country's legal and policy framework around homosexuality as captured by its RECI score. To the far right are shown the main effects of these basic human values when RECI scores are equal to zero. All but one of these values are statistically significant and effect sizes remain in line with those found previously without the interaction term. There remains limited evidence for the importance of national legislative and policy frameworks on homopositve outcomes, with the direct effect of RECI on homopositive outcomes being statistically insignificant and with a zero effect size. There is also not strong evidence of any variation in the effects of basic human values on homopositivity according to the national framework of LGBT support: half of the human values do not show statistically significant effects and none of the values show effect sizes notably different to zero.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>A body of cross-national quantitative studies have built up a valuable picture of the key explanatory factors that explain variation in homopositive/homonegative attitudes across individuals and nations. The present study makes several original contributions to that current understanding through its original use of theoretically guided structural equation modelling.</p><p>An initial contribution concerns the specification of the homopositivity outcome variable. While current studies select a (frequently different) single indicator to measure its outcome indicator, the present study encourages greater explicit consideration and debate of this key specification. The present study embraces its ability to readily incorporate latent factors into its SEM framework to instead measure the inherently latent concept of homopositivity from three distinct yet equally plausible underlying indicators. Model comparisons show that the main messages from the findings remain broadly consistent across all specifications of the outcome indicator. However, differences in effect sizes and in reduced model power are evident when single indicators as used as the outcome measure.</p><p>Religiosity has been found in numerous previous studies to be a key factor in explaining homopositive attitudes in terms of religious beliefs, practices, and faith groups. Our analyses include all three and findings make two main contributions in this area. Firstly, our models allow a mediation pathway between religious beliefs and religious practices for the first time in the literature and this highlights the strong role of religious beliefs in driving religious practices. This illustrates a key process through which beliefs affect homopositive attitudes via their influence on religious behaviours. It also highlights that the total effect of religious beliefs on homopositive attitudes-by which is meant its direct effects plus its indirect effects mediated via religious practices-are notably larger than previous studies have identified via direct effects alone. Secondly, our analyses include detailed interaction terms between religious beliefs and religious denomination in order to explore the potential for varying effects of beliefs across denominations, in contrast to existing scholarship which assumes uniform effects. Our analyses show that although religious beliefs are important to homopositive attitudes in all faith groups their effect size differs across denominations. Specifically, other things equal Eastern Orthodox and especially Islamic faith show notably less positive attitudes towards homosexuality at low levels of religious belief while individuals of Protestant, Eastern Orthodox, and Other denominations show larger expected increases homonegative attitudes as strength of belief increases compared to other faith groups.</p><p>In terms of the socioeconomic drivers of homopositive attitudes our findings make three contributions to the literature. Firstly, they newly illustrate that education has marked indirect effects on homopositive attitudes mediated through household income in addition to the direct effects of both education and household income on homopositivity evidenced in previous research. Secondly, our analyses bring new insights into the role of welfare regimes in affecting homopositive attitudes directly as well as in moderating the effects of low income. The Nordic regime shows the largest positive association with homopositive attitudes and the Eastern European regime the least positive association, other things equal, with Liberal, Corporatist, and Southern European regimes falling in between those extremes. Thirdly, our analyses highlight that household income shows a positive association with homopositve outcomes and that this effect does not vary across welfare regimes despite their markedly differing propensities to mitigate financial risks and losses, particularly at lower income levels. Taken together these findings suggest that welfare regimes do matter to the shaping of homopositive attitudes and hence should be included into future research in the field. However, and perhaps contrary to initial expectations, these findings suggest that they do so less as a moderator of material financial and instead as a reflection of their differing cultural and ideological regimes.</p><p>Finally, our analyses confirm the relevance of key basic human values to homopositive attitudes, with Universalism showing a particularly strong positive association with homopositive attitudes. Compared to previous research findings however <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Kuntz et al., 2015)</ref>, our modelling casts doubt on the substantive importance of a country's legal and policy framework regards homosexuality in either affecting homopositive attitude directly or in moderating the effects of basic human values on homopositivity.</p><p>Taken together the analyses add a range of valuable new insights to our understanding of the key predictors, pathways and moderators of homopositive attitudes. Despite general strides towards greater acceptance of homosexuality homonegativity continues to be a challenge in many regions of the world and within certain demographic groups of all nations. It is our hope that this development in the literature of these richer understandings of homopositive attitudes beyond the identification of headline predictors can help to support continued progress towards equality and acceptance of homosexuality across all people and places.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Participants</head><label></label><figDesc>Our empirical work makes use of the latest round (Round 9) of the European Social Survey (ESS) released in late 2019 and relating to data collected during 2018. The ESS has been collected bi-annually since 2001 and has well-established survey sampling, data collection, and weighting procedures as well as detailed documentation (ESS, 2021). The Round 9 survey wave contains data for 36,015 individuals based on strict random probability methods from 19 European countries (Austria, Belgium, Bulgaria, Cyprus, Czech Republic, Estonia, Finland, France, Germany, Hungary, Ireland, Italy, Netherlands, Norway, Poland, Serbia, Slovenia, Switzerland, UK). National samples are representative of the population aged fifteen and over resident within private households, regardless of their nationality, citizenship, or language.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1 Basic SEM starting point</figDesc><graphic coords="4,85.06,57.76,425.16,289.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2 Variation in attitudes towards homosexuality across and within European nations</figDesc><graphic coords="6,204.17,57.76,340.08,241.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3 Initial SEM model of homopositive attitudes in Europe</figDesc><graphic coords="6,85.06,320.46,425.16,288.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4 Final SEM model of homopositive attitudes in Europe</figDesc><graphic coords="7,53.86,57.76,487.56,254.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Availability of Data and Material</head><p>The ESS data are available publicly to download at: <ref type="url" target="https://www">https:// www</ref>. europ eanso cials urvey. org/ data/ Code Availability The full Stata code is available on request from the corresponding author.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Author Contributions All authors contributed to the study conception and design. Material preparation, data collection, and analysis were performed by Whitworth. The first draft of the manuscript was written by Whitworth. All authors read, revised, and approved the final manuscript.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>The analyses in this article were supported by no particular research funding.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Declarations</head><p>Conflict of interest There are no known conflicts of interest to declare.</p><p>Ethical apporval Ethical approvals were not required for these analyses given their reliance on anonymised secondary survey data that are publicly available for research use.</p><p>Informed consent All analyses use anonymised secondary survey data that are publicly available for research use without the need for further informed consents from survey participants.</p><p>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ref type="url" target="http://creat">http:// creat</ref> iveco mmons. org/ licen ses/ by/4. 0/.</p><p>Publisher's Note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global liberalization on homosexuality: Explaining the African gap</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Alozie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Akpan-Obong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Science Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rejecting the West? Homonegative attitudes and political orientations in contemporary Eastern Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bolzendahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gracheva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Gender and Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="345" to="366" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Changing attitudes towards homosexuality in Taiwan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Adamczyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">2016. 1995-2012</date>
			<publisher>Chinese Sociological Review</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="317" to="345" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Constructing tolerance: How the welfare state shapes attitudes about immigrants</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Crepaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Damron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comparative Political Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="437" to="463" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Methods for integrating moderation and mediation: A general analytical framework using moderated path analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lambert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The three worlds of welfare capitalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Esping-Andersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<publisher>Polity Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Weighting European social survey data</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.europeansocialsurvey.org/docs/round9/survey/ESS9" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ESS9-2018 Documentation report: The ESS data archive edition</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ESS European Social Survey</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014. 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>weigh ting_ data_1. pdf ESS European Social Survey. data_ docum entat ion_ report_ e03_1. pdf</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Searching for evidence of acculturation: Attitudes towards homosexuality among migrants moving from eastern to Western Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fitzgerald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Winstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Prestage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Public Opinion Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="323" to="341" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-discrimination towards homosexuality: The European Union&apos;s policy and citizens&apos; attitudes towards homosexuality in 27 European countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gerhards</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Sociology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">World society divided: Divergent trends in state responses to sexual minorities and their reflection in public attitudes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hadler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Symons</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Forces</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1721" to="1756" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predictors of homonegativity in the United States and the Netherlands using the fifth wave of the world values survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Haney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Homosexuality</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1355" to="1377" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heterosexuals&apos; attitudes toward bisexual men and women in the United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Herek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Sex Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="264" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beyond &quot;homophobia&quot;: Thinking about sexual prejudice and stigma in the twenty-first century</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Herek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sexuality Research &amp; Social Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sexual prejudice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Herek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mclemore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="333" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sooner or later: The influence of public opinion and religiosity on the enactment of laws recognizing same-sex unions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hildebrandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Trudinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jackle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of European Public Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1191" to="1210" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The missing link? Modernization, tolerance and legislation on homosexuality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hildebrandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Trudinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wyss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Research Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="553" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is same-sex marriage legislation related to attitudes toward homosexuality?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hooghe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Meeusen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sexuality Research and Social Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="258" to="268" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Annual review of the human rights situation of lesbian, gay, bisexual, trans and intersex people</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Igla Europe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IGLA Europe</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Norms and reform: Legalizing homosexuality improves attitudes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kenny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Center for Global Development</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Washington</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Working paper 465</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principles and practice of structural equation modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>The Guilford Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Same-sex unions: The globalization of an idea</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kollman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Studies Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="329" to="357" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human values, legal regulation, and approval of homosexuality in Europe: A cross-country comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kuntz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Davidov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Context matters: Effects of the proportion of fundamentalists on gender attitudes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Vanneman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Forces</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="139" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Returns to education in developed countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Oreopolous</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gunderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The economics of education: A comprehensive overview</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="64" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The age gap in religion around the world</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Pew Global Research Center</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Global religious futures project: Country profiles</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.globalreligiousfutures.org/countries" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>Pew Global Research Center</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three worlds of welfare state research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pierson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comparative Political Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="791" to="821" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thirty years of the &quot;Three worlds of welfare capitalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Powell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Yoruk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bargu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A review of reviews. Social Policy &amp; Administration</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="87" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using scenarios for measuring the affective and behavioural components of attitudes toward lesbians and gay men: Validation of the SABA scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Preuss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ottenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kachel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Steffens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Archives of Sexual Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1645" to="1669" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Returns to investment in education: A decennial review of the global literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Psacharopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Patrinos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>World Bank</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Policy Research Working Paper No. 8402</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of same-sex legislation on attitudes toward homosexuality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Redman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Research Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="628" to="641" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changing worldwide attitudes toward homosexuality: The influence of global and region-specific cultures, 1981-2012</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Science Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="114" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Review article: Personal values in human life</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sagiv</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Roccas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cieciuch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Human Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="630" to="639" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Are there universal aspects in the context and structure of values</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Social Issues</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Tolerance towards homosexuality in Europe: Population composition, economic affluence, religiosity, same-sex union legislation and HIV rates as explanations for country differences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Slenders</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sieben</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Verbakel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="348" to="367" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Intimate Relations</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intelligence, religiosity and homosexuality non-acceptance: Empirical evidence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Souza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cribari-Neto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social attitudes toward adoption by same-sex couples in Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Takacs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Szalma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bartus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Archives of Sexual Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1787" to="1798" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How cohorts, education, and ideology shaped a new sexual revolution on American attitudes toward nonmarital sex, 1972-1998</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Treas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Perspectives</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="283" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disapproval of homosexuality: Comparative research on individual and national determinants of disapproval of homosexuality in 20 European countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Van Den Akker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Van Der Ploeg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Scheepers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Public Opinion Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="86" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of values in understanding attitudes to lesbians and gay men</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Vicario</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liddle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Luzzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Homosexuality</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="159" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Designing, testing, and interpreting interactions and moderator effects in family research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Whisman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mcclelland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Family Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">GDP per capita</title>
		<ptr target="https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/NY.GDP.PCAP.CD" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>World Bank</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The roles of politics, feminism, and religion in attitudes toward LGBT individuals: A cross-cultural study of college students in the USA</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Worthen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Lingiardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Caristo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Italy and Spain. Sexuality Research and Social Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="258" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social contact, social distancing and attitudes toward LGT individuals: A cross-cultural study of college students in the United States, Italy and Spain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Worthen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tanzilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Caristo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Lingiardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Homosexuality</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1882" to="1908" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Attitudinal changes towards homosexuality during the past two decades (1994-2014) in Korea</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Youn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Homosexuality</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="116" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social tolerance of homosexuality: A quantitative comparison of Mainland China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Singapore and Taiwan. Chinese Sociological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
