<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Augmented probability simulation for adversarial risk analysis in general security games</title>
				<funder ref="#_AeG9W9k">
					<orgName type="full">STARLIGHT H2020</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_J9tqqDu">
					<orgName type="full">EOARD-AFOSR</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_DQg72ty">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Roi</forename><surname>Naveiro</surname></persName>
							<email>roi.naveiro@icmat.es</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Mathematical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">ICMAT-CSIC)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>C/ Nicolás Cabrera 13-15</addrLine>
									<postCode>28049</postCode>
									<settlement>Madrid</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Rios</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Mathematical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">ICMAT-CSIC)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>C/ Nicolás Cabrera 13-15</addrLine>
									<postCode>28049</postCode>
									<settlement>Madrid</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jose</forename><forename type="middle">Manuel</forename><surname>Camacho</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Mathematical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">ICMAT-CSIC)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>C/ Nicolás Cabrera 13-15</addrLine>
									<postCode>28049</postCode>
									<settlement>Madrid</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Augmented probability simulation for adversarial risk analysis in general security games</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.46354/i3m.2022.dhss.002</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T19:05+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Security games</term>
					<term>adversarial risk analysis</term>
					<term>augmented probability simulation</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Although widely used, standard game-theoretic approaches to security games face severe shortcomings, being the common knowledge assumption a critical one. Adversarial Risk Analysis (ARA) is an alternative modeling framework that mitigates such limitations. However, from a computational perspective, ARA is much more involved than its game theoretical counterparts. We propose an approach for finding ARA solutions to security games represented as bi-agent influence diagrams that is based on augmented probability simulation. We motivate this approach using two simple cases: sequential and simultaneous defend-attack models. We next provide the general framework and illustrate it in handling risks in a cybersecurity setting.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Security games provide a flexible and strong modeling framework for strategic and operational defense and homeland security problems, as argued in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Brown et al. (2006)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Zhuang and Bier (2007)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Brown et al. (2008)</ref> or <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Hausken (2011)</ref>. These authors illustrate the analysis of security games from a standard game theoretic perspective based on approximating Nash equilibria and related refinements.</p><p>The common knowledge assumptions underlying such game theoretic approaches, critically reviewed in e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Raiffa et al. (2002)</ref> or <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hargreaves-Heap and Varoufakis (2004)</ref>, constitute a shortcoming in the security domain.</p><p>In most games, it is assumed that agents know not only their own payoffs, preferences, beliefs and possible actions, but also those of their opponents. In games of incomplete information <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Harsanyi, 1967)</ref>, it is typically assumed that each agent has a joint probability distribution over their opponents' types which is known by all the players. Such assumptions allow for a symmetric joint normative analysis in which players maximise their expected utilities, and expect other players to do the same. However, in defense and homeland security, agents will not generally have so much knowledge about their opponents as players try to hide information. Adversarial Risk Analysis (ARA), <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Rios Insua et al. (2009)</ref>, is an alternative modeling framework which mitigates these common knowledge assumptions. Rather than addressing the problem simultaneously for all agents, ARA provides prescriptive support to one of the decision makers, which we shall refer to as the defender (she), seeking for actions that maximize her expected utility: Nash equilibria notions are abandoned and the defender's problem is viewed as a decision analytic one instead. However, procedures which employ the game theoretic structure are used to estimate the probabilities of the opponent's (referred to as the attacker, he) actions. ARA thus make operational the Bayesian approach to games, as sketched in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Kadane and Larkey (1982)</ref> or <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Raiffa (1982)</ref>.</p><p>A main motivation for ARA comes from security and counter-terrorism analysis. Since its introduction, it has been used to model a variety of problems such as network routing for insurgency <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Wang and Banks, 2011)</ref>, international piracy <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Sevillano et al., 2012)</ref>, urban security resource allocation <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Gil et al., 2016)</ref>, adversarial classification <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Naveiro et al., 2019)</ref>, counter-terrorist online surveillance <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Gil and Parra-Arnau, 2019)</ref>, cyber-security <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Rios Insua et al., 2019)</ref>, insider threat modelling <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Joshi et al., 2020)</ref> and combat modeling enhancement <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Roponen and Salo, 2015)</ref>, to name but a few.</p><p>However, a major problem with the implementation of ARA refers to its computational issues since it essentially entails a two-stage approach in which we first simulate the attacker's problem to compute a probabilistic forecast of the adversary's actions and then use that forecast to optimize the defender's problem. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Ekin et al. (2022)</ref>, augmented probability simulation (APS, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bielza et al. (1999)</ref>) was explored as a solution method for simple sequential defend-attack games from an ARA perspective. In particular, it was shown that APS could be more efficient than standard Monte Carlo based techniques in situations in which the cardinality of the decision sets of the agents intervening in the security game is very big.</p><p>We present here how APS may be used to solve general security games described through bi-agent influence diagrams (BAIDs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Banks et al., 2015)</ref> from an ARA perspective. For this, we first provide a brief introduction to APS (Section 2), and explain how this solution approach can be utilized for solving sequential defend-attack (Section 3) and simultaneous defend-attack (Section 4) games. Section 5 sketches the analysis for general BAIDs. We end up with an experiment illustrating the proposed approach (Section 6) and a brief discussion (Section 7).</p><p>Our aim is thus to support the defender in her decision making. For this, we need to forecast the attacker's intentions. Many different attacker rationalities may be considered in the ARA framework, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Rios Insua et al. (2016)</ref>. However, we circumscribe here the defender to be a level-2 thinker, in the <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Stahl and Wilson (1995)</ref> sense: she will ponder how the attacker's strategy would adapt to her own strategy but presume that he will not conduct likewise. Thus, we assume that the attacker is an expected utility maximiser. We could predict his actions by finding his maximum expected utility policy; however, the uncertainty in our assessments about the attacker's probabilities and utilities propagates to his optimal decision that becomes random, providing us with the required probabilistic forecast over the attacks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Augmented Probability Simulation</head><p>In decision analysis settings, the goal is usually to find an action or set of actions that maximize the expected utility of the decision maker. In general, expected utility cannot be computed analytically and needs to be approximated. Most solution methods proceed by first estimating the expected utility for every possible action (usually through Monte Carlo integration) and then optimizing such estimate. Instead, APS solves for expected utility maximization by converting the tasks of estimation and optimization into simulation from an augmented distribution over the joint space of decisions and outcomes. Suppose that we aim to maximize the expected utility ψpdq " ş upd, θq ¨ppθ|dq dθ, where θ is a random outcome whose distribution is ppθ|dq and upd, θq is the utility perceived when choosing d and obtaining outcome θ. APS stems from the observation that if the utility is nonnegative and integrable, we can define the augmented distribution πpd, θq9upd, θq ¨ppθ|dq on the augmented space of decisions and outcomes. Then, under mild conditions, the mode of the marginal augmented distribution in d coincides with the maximum expected utility solution. This suggests a strategy to compute the optimal decision based on simulating from the augmented probability distribution (for which Markov chain Monte Carlo simulation methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">French and Insua (2000)</ref> are instrumental) and, then, assessing the marginal mode using mode estimation methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Chacon (2020)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Sequential Defend-Attack games</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Basic template</head><p>Drawing on <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Ekin et al. (2022)</ref>, this section sketches how APS-based methods can be utilized for finding optimal defenses in sequential defend-attack games under incomplete information. For illustration purposes, we briefly sketch also the complete information case.</p><p>Assume a Defender (D, she) who chooses her defense d P D, where D is her set of feasible alternatives. After having observed it, an Attacker (A, he) chooses his attack a P A, with A being his set of available alternatives. The consequences of the interaction for both agents depend on a random outcome θ P Θ, with Θ the space of outcomes. Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> displays a template for the corresponding BAID <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Banks et al., 2015)</ref>. Arc D-A reflects that the Attacker observes the Defender's decision. As a motivating example, suppose that a defending organisation decides its protection level against, say, a cyber-attack. An attacking organisation observes such protection level and decides its attack intensity. The attack may be successful or not depending on its intensity and the protection level chosen by the defender. Increasing protection level (attack intensity) entail higher costs for the defender (attacker).</p><p>The agents have their own assessment of the probability of the random outcome, respectively modeled through p D pθ|d, aq and p A pθ|d, aq. The Defender's utility u D pd, θq is a function of her chosen defense and the outcome. Similarly, the Attacker's utility function is u A pa, θq.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Complete information. Game theoretic solution</head><p>In the standard complete information setup, the basic game-theoretic solution does not require A to know D's probabilities and utilities, as he observes her actions. However, the Defender must know pu A , p A q, the common knowledge assumption in this case. Then, both agents' T , a ˚pd GT q ˘is a Nash equilibrium and, indeed, a sub-game perfect equilibrium <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Hargreaves-Heap and Varoufakis, 2004)</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Θ D A U D U A Figure 1.</formula><p>In case of multiple best responses for the attacker given some defender action d, a ˚pdq becomes a set. Ties are generally broken either choosing the most favorable attack for the defender, leading to a strong Stackelberg equilibrium (SSE) or choosing the worst attack for the defender, leading to a weak Stackelberg equilibrium. In what follows, whenever necessary, we shall assume that ties are broken in favor of the defender, the standard solution in security games <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Korzhyk et al., 2011)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Incomplete information. ARA solution</head><p>As discussed in the introduction, the complete information assumption will not hold in many security scenarios. When this is the case, the problem may be handled as an incomplete information game. The most common approach in such context approximates Bayes-Nash equilibria, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hargreaves-Heap and Varoufakis (2004)</ref> for details. Alternatively, we use a decision analytic approach based on ARA, that facilitates the defender to acknowledge the uncertainty she might have about the attacker's judgements pu A , p A q. The Defender's problem is depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2a</ref> as an influence diagram, where A's action appears as an uncertainty. With this, D's expected utility is ψ D pdq " ş ψ D pd, aq p D pa|dq da. Computing this requires estimating p D pa|dq, D's assessment of the probability that the Attacker will choose a after having observed d. Then, her optimal decision is d ÅRA " arg max dPD ψ D pdq.</p><p>Eliciting p D pa|dq is complex, as it possesses a strategic element. It is facilitated by analyzing A's problem from D's perspective (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2b</ref>). In order to accomplish this, the defender would use all information and judgment available about A's utilities and probabilities. However, instead of using point estimates for u A and p A to find A's best response to d, as in Secion 3.2, her uncertainty about the attacks would derive from modeling pu A , p A q  through a distribution F " pU A , P A q on the space of utilities and probabilities. With no loss of generality, assume that U A and P A are defined on a common probability space pΩ, F, Pq with atomic elements ω P Ω <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Chung, 2001)</ref>. This induces a distribution over the Attacker's expected utility ψ A pd, aq, where the random expected utility would be Ψ ω A pd, aq " ş U ω A pa, θqP ω A pθ|d, aq dθ. In turn, this leads to a random optimal alternative defined through A ˚pdq ω " arg max xPA Ψ ω A pd, xq. Then, the Defender would find p D pa|dq " P F " A ˚pdq " a ‰ " P ␣ ω : A ˚pdq ω " a ( in the discrete case (and, similarly in the continuous one).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Computation through APS</head><p>Computationally, ARA models entail integration and optimization procedures that can be challenging in many cases. Therefore, we explore the APS-based methods sketched in the introduction.</p><p>An augmented distribution for the Defender's problem is introduced as π D pd, a, θq9u D pd, θq p D pθ|d, aq p D pa|dq. Its marginal π D pdq " ş ş π D pd, a, θq da dθ is proportional to the expected utility ψ D pdq and, consequently, d ÅRA " mode pπ D pdqq. Thus, one just needs to sample pd, a, θq " π D pd, a, θq and estimate its mode in d. In ? a Metropolis Hastings sampling procedure is introduced to provide a Markov chain with states (d, a, θ) whose stationary distribution is π D pd, a, θq. Under mild conditions, a convenient mode estimate of the d samples generated converges to the ARA solution of the sequential game. Constructing this Markov chain, requires the ability to sample from p D pa|dq. To perform this sampling, an APS in the space of the Attacker's random utilities and probabilities is constructed. For a given d, the random augmented</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">distribution built is Π ω A pa, θ|dq9U ω A pa, θqP ω A pθ|d, aq, its marginal Π ω A pa|dq " ş Π ω</formula><p>A pa, θ|dq dθ being proportional to A's random expected utility Ψ ω A pd, aq. Then, the random optimal attack A ˚pdq ω almost surely coincides with the mode of the marginal Π ω A pa|dq. Consequently, by sampling u A pa, θq " U A pa, θq and p A pθ|d, aq " P A pθ|d, aq, one can build π A pa, θ|dq9u A pa, θqp A pθ|d, aq which is a sample from Π A pa, θ|dq. Then, modepπ A pa|dqq is a sample of A ˚pdq, whose distribution is P F " A ˚pdq ď a ‰ " p D pA ď a|dq, thus providing a mechanism to sample from it.</p><p>The type of computations underlying APS-based solution methods for ARA are illustrated in an example in Section 6.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Simultaneous Defend-Attack Games</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Basic template</head><p>The simultaneous defend-attack game template is depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>, with the same semantics as that of Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>. Observe that arc D Ñ A is lacking, reflecting that both agents act simultaneously in this case. As an example, consider a national aviation security organisation that randomly assigns undercover security guards on planes to deter terror acts. In turn, a terrorist organisation might board a member on certain planes to implement their malicious actions. The security consequences on a given plane would depend on both agents' decisions (presence of security guard and terrorist on the plane). In this case, the ARA approach would support D by solving d ÅRA " arg max dPD ş ψ D pd, aq ¨pD paq da where p D paq represents D's beliefs about what action a will the attacker implement. In order to forecast it, consider the attacker's problem a ˚" arg max aPA ş ψ A pd, aq ¨pA pdq dd. Since we lack knowledge about the attacker's utilities and probabilities, we adopt a Bayesian approach and model our uncertainty through prior distributions (over possible utilities and probabilities) U A pa, θq, P A pθ|d, aq and P A pdq defined over a common probability space pΩ, F, Pq with atomic elements ω P Ω. Then, the random optimal attack is</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">A ˚" arg max xPA ż Ψ ω A pd, xq ¨Pω A pdq dd (1)</formula><p>and make p D pA ď aq " PpA ˚ď aq. This defines p D paq, the missing ingredient in the Defender problem. Clearly, the above requires the specification of U A pa, θq, P A pθ|d, aq, and P A pdqs. Of these three ingredients, eliciting P A pdq has a recursive component as we need to think about how the attacker thinks about the defender, which in turn begs for thinking about how the defender thinks about how the attacker thinks about the defender, and so on. This leads to a recursion similar to the level-k scheme described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Rios and Insua (2012)</ref>. As mentioned in the Introduction, we shall only focus on level-2 thinking, although the scheme described extend to higher levels in the thinking hierarchy.</p><p>As in the sequential case, ARA models may be solved through APS constructing augmented distributions. The distribution corresponding to the Defender's problem is π D pd, θ, aq9u D pd, θq ¨pD pθ|d, aq ¨pD paq</p><p>(2) its marginal being π D pdq " ş ş u D pd, θq ¨pD pθ|d, aq pD paq dθ da which is proportional to the expected utility ψ D pdq and, consequently, d ÅRA " modepπ D pdqq. As in the sequential case, we can solve the problem sampling d, θ and a from π D pd, θ, aq, and computing the mode of the dsamples. This sampling is performed using MCMC methods. In particular, a Metropolis-Hastings is illustrated in Algorithm 1. Notice that this approach requires the ability to sample a " p D paq. To produce those samples, consider now the attacker random APS model, defined for each ω through</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">Π ω A pd, θ, aq9U ω A pa, θq ¨Pω A pθ|d, aq ¨Pω A pdq<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Then, the random mode of the marginal of Π ω pd, θ, aq in a coincides with A ˚, whose distribution is p D paq. Consequently, by sampling u A pa, θq " U A pa, θq, p A pθ|d, aq " P A pθ|d, aq and p A pdq " P A pdq one can build π A pa, θ|dq9u A pa, θqp A pθ|d, aqp A pdq which is a sample from Π A pa, θ, dq. Then, modepπ A paqq is a sample of A ˚, whose distribution is P F " A ˚pdq ď a ‰ " p D pA ď a|dq, thus providing a mechanism to sample from such distribution. This procedure is illustrated in the sample_attack function of Algorithm 1. Under mild conditions, we can prove the convergence of the Algorithm to the ARA solution when using a consistent mode estimator, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Chacon (2020)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">General Games</head><p>The previous sections dealt with relatively simple ARA templates with basic sequences of defense and attack movements. However, such stylized settings may not be sufficient to cope with the complexities of many actual defense and homeland security problems.</p><p>As an illustration, consider the BAID in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>. In it, the incumbent authorities decide how to allocate a given number of patrols to prevent land access to a place of interest (e.g. an airport) by a certain terrorist organization. This decision is referred to as D 1 . The terrorists observe the patrols' display over a certain period and thus have function sample_attack(M, K, g A , U A , P A ):</p><p>initialize : a p0q Draw u A pa, θq " U A pa, θq Draw p A pθ|d, aq " P A pθ|d, aq Draw p A pdq " P A pdq Draw d p0q " p A pdq Draw θ p0q " p A pθ|d p0q , a p0q q for i " 1 to M do Ź Inner APS Propose new attack ã " g A pã|a pi-1q q Draw d " p A pdq Draw θ " p A pθ| d, ãq Evaluate acceptance probability</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">α " min # 1, u Ap ã,θq¨g A ´api-1q |ã ūAp a pi-1q ,θ pi-1q q¨gApã|a pi-1q q +</formula><p>With probability α set pd piq , a piq , θ piq q " p d, ã, θq. Otherwise, set pd piq , a piq , θ piq q " pd pi-1q , a pi-1q , θ pi-1q q. Discard first K samples and record the mode of interest of the rest of draws ta pK`1q , ..., a pMq u as a ˚.</p><p>return a input:</p><p>U A , P A , M, K, N, R, g D and g A proposal distributions initialize : d p0q Draw a p0q " p D paq using sample_attack( M, K, g A , U A , P A ) Draw θ p0q " p D pθ|d p0q , a p0q q for i " 1 to N do Ź Outer APS Propose new defense d " g D p d|d pi-1q q Draw ã " p D paq using sample_attack(M, K, g A , U A , P A ) Draw θ " p D pθ| d, ãq Evaluate acceptance probability</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">α " min # 1, u D ´d,θ ¯¨g D ´dpi-1q | dū D pd pi-1q ,θ pi-1q q¨gD ´d|d pi-1q</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>¯+</head><p>With probability α set pd piq , a piq , θ piq q " p d, ã, θq. Otherwise, set pd piq , a piq , θ piq q " pd pi-1q , a pi-1q , θ pi-1q q. Discard first R samples and estimate mode of the rest of draws td pR`1q , ...,</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">d pNq u as p d ÅRA Record p d ÅRA .</formula><p>Algorithm 1: MH based APS to approximate ARA solution in the simultaneous defend-attack game.</p><p>knowledge of D 1 . Based on this, the terrorists decide when to access the place of interest with the intention of committing an attack. This decision is referred to as A 1 . Whether the terrorists manage to access the airport without being detected by the patrols is modeled through variable S 1 . Provided that the terrorist have a successful access, their vehicles can still be detected before the attack is committed (for instance, via helicopters supervising the area). Whether or not the terrorists' vehicles are detected after land access is modeled with the variable S 2 . If the terrorists are indeed detected, they choose to change their attacking strategy (for instance, modify their target). The new attacking decision is denoted as A 2 . Simultaneously, the authorities decide to allocate reinforcement patrols to further protect the airport. Based on these two decisions, the outcome S 3 models the (random) consequences of an eventual attack. For each agent, there is a utility node which assesses their consequences, respectively represented by u D and u A in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>. In particular, the defender's utility u D (respectively, the attacker's utility u A ) will depend on her decisions D 1 and D 2 (respectively, his decisions A 1 and A 2 ) and the results S 1 , S 2 and S 3 . Moreover, this, or similar sequences of defense-attack movements, could be repeated across time, spanning over several planning periods.</p><p>Note that within the general layout of the BAID in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>, we identify patterns of defence and attack moves as those earlier described as basic templates. In particular, nodes D 1 -A 1 correspond to the Seq D-A template. Similarly, nodes D 1 -A 2 reproduce the backbone structure of a Sim D-A template. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">González-Ortega et al. (2019)</ref>, a scheme for dealing with these structures was introduced adapting strategic relevance concepts from computational game theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Koller, 2003)</ref>, ARA methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Banks et al., 2015)</ref>, and classic influence diagram reductions from <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Shachter (1986)</ref>. However, the basic reduction operations, were essentially analytic. Inspired by the reasoning in Appendix B, we replace here such operations with APS schemes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Simulation based BAID reduction operations</head><p>The methods in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">González-Ortega et al. (2019)</ref> assess analytically a BAID from an ARA perspective. First, they are used to decide whether we deal with a sequential or a simultaneous block. Once such decision is made, we decide which ID reduction to implement, according to Shachter (1986)'s conditions. At a third level, we then implement the required ID reductions until the incumbent block is reduced. In such case, we start again finding the next block to be treated, until all the Defender's decision nodes are reduced.</p><p>ID reductions in the Defender problem (D-reductions) are as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Shachter (1986)</ref>. On the contrary, ID reductions in the Attacker problem (A-reductions) need to be modified to take into account the uncertainty about the attacker's probabilities and utilities. As before, without loss of generality, assume that all involved random utilities U A and probabilities P A are defined over a common probability space pΩ, F, Pq with atomic elements ω. Thus, when invoking them in reference to ω, we designate them U ω A and P ω A , respectively. The remaining notation is adapted from <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Shachter (1986)</ref> where: superscripts old and new refer to an element, respectively, before or after a BAID transformation; and, for any node i, Cpiq designates its conditional predecessors (chance and value nodes), Ipiq its informational predecessors (decision nodes) and Spiq its direct successors. Initially, we denote Ψ ω A px Cpvq q " U ω A px Cpvq q, where v refers to the value node. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">González-Ortega et al. (2019)</ref> provided their theoretical analytical descriptions which we briefly recall:</p><p>• A-Arc inversion. An arc pi, jq between chance nodes i and j (for the attacker), satisfying <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Shachter (1986)</ref> conditions may be reduced with node inheritance as in conventional IDs. (Random) probability assessments are changed by applying Bayes' formula parametrically so that</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">P ω A new px j |x C new pjq q " ż P ω A old px j |x C old pjq q P ω A old px i |x C old piq q dx i ,<label>(4)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_8">P ω A new px i |x C new piq q " P ω A old px j |x C old pjq q P ω A old px i |x C old piq q P ω A new px j |x C new pjq q .</formula><p>(5)</p><p>• A-Chance node removal. A chance node i (for the attacker) satisfying <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Shachter (1986)</ref> conditions may be removed with node inheritance as in conventional IDs. Note, however, that expectations have to be taken parametrically so that we obtain (random) expected utilities.</p><p>Prior to node i reduction, we have a (random) expected utility Ψ ω A old px C old pvq q associated with each combination x C old pvq of values for predecessors of v. After the reduction, we associate with v a new (random) expected utility defined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Shachter (1986)</ref> conditions, we may remove a decision node i (for the attacker) with node inheritance as in conventional IDs, by computing the expected utility of the (random) optimal alternatives, conditional on the values of its predecessors. (Random) optimal alternatives are stored through</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">Ψ ω A new px C new pvq q " ż Ψ ω A old px C old pvq q P ω A px i |x Cpiq q dx i . (6) • A-Decision node removal. Under</formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">A ω i ˚px C new pvq q " arg max x i Ψ ω A old px i , x C new pvq q,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>whereas their (random) expected utilities are</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">Ψ ω A new px C new pvq q " max x i Ψ ω A old px i , x C new pvq q. (<label>8</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_12">)</formula><p>Now the crucial observation is that for expected utility optimization purposes, the denominator in Bayes' formula operates as a constant and we can just use the potential on the right of the proportionality condition</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">P ω A new px i |x C new piq q9P ω A old px j |x C old pjq q P ω A old px i |x C old piq q, .<label>(9)</label></formula><p>thus avoiding the costly arc inversions. Then, we can group all arc inversions and chance node removals prior to a decision node removal conceptually and, operationally, by multiplying the corresponding parameterized potentials and distributions. Next, we just multiply them by the parameterized utility function to obtain the parameterized augmented probability distribution, from which we may sample to obtain a forecast of the attacker's action as required.</p><p>In a similar fashion, we can determine all arc inversions and decision nodes prior to a defender decision node removal, multiply her utility function by the product of potentials and distributions to obtain an augmented probability distribution from which to sample the defender's optimal decision at such stage.</p><p>These APS modified operations would be integrated in the operation and block scheduling scheme in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">González-Ortega et al. (2019)</ref> to provide an APS approach to general BAIDs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Example</head><p>An example illustrates the type of computations undertaken in APS for ARA in a simple sequential Defend-Attack game. Consider an organization (D) that has to choose among ten security protocols: d " 0 (no extra defensive action); d " i (level i protocol with increasing protection), i " 1, . . . , 8; d " 9 (safe but cumbersome protocol). A has two alternatives: attack (a " 1) or not (a " 0). Successful (unsuccessful) attacks are denoted as θ " 1 (θ " 0). When there is no attack, θ " 0.   Attacker judgments. The average attack cost is 0.03Me. The average attack benefit is 2Me. An unsuccessful attack has an extra cost of 0.5M e. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">1c</ref> presents the Attacker's net benefit c A pa, θq. D thinks that A is constant risk prone over benefits, with utility strategically equivalent to u A pc A q " exp pe ˆcA q, with e ą 0.</p><p>Defender strategic judgments. D's beliefs over A's judgments are described through P A and U A . Assume A's random probability of success is modeled as P A pθ " 1|d, a " 1q " Betapα d , β d q with α d and β d in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">1d</ref> (with expected values the p D pθ " 1|d, aq in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">1b</ref>). In addition, A's risk coefficient e is uncertain, with e " Up0, 2q, inducing the random utility U A pc A q.</p><p>In this case, for APS, as the cardinality of D is small, one can estimate the value of p D pa|dq for each d sampling from this distribution and counting frequencies of different attacks. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5a</ref> presents such estimates pD pa|dq. Next, the ARA solution for the Defender is computed. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5b</ref> presents the frequency of samples from the marginal For this same example, the game theoretic solution under the complete information assumption is d GT " 8. Both solutions differ as the informational assumptions are different in both settings: the ARA decision appears to be more conservative, as it suggests a safer but more expensive defense.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Discussion</head><p>APS based methods have already been proven successful in sequential Defend-Attack games <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Ekin et al. (2022)</ref>. In this paper, we have extended APS to deal with general games represented as BAIDs from an ARA perspective. Sequential and simultaneous defend-attack models paved the way to deal with general problems modeled as bi-agent influence diagrams. In Appendix A, we sketch how this methodology could be extended to work with n-stages sequential games. However, in this setting, APS is likely to suffer from the typical computational shortcomings of dynamic programming. Thus, studying scalable methods for solving n-stage sequential games under the ARA perspective is an interesting avenue for future research. In addition, exploring the use of Hamiltonian Monte Carlo methods for APS in situations in which gradients of the utilities are available is also a promising future research line.</p><p>We would like to finish acknowledging that the proposed approach will become specially relevant in a recent class of security game theoretic models, especially under incomplete information, appearing in the emergent field of adversarial machine learning (Ríos <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Insua et al., 2020)</ref>. Efficient scalable algorithmic approaches to solve typical problems in this new domain are essential. Moreover, ARA solutions of such games turns out to be important, as common knowledge assumptions rarely hold in AML. natural disasters-defensive strategy with endogenous attacker effort. Operations Research, 55(5):976-991.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. The n-stage Sequential Game</head><p>The proposed scheme for the two stage sequential Defend-Attack game extend to multiple stage games, informing our general approach in Section 4. Consider a general nstage sequential game under incomplete information in which the defender moves first by choosing decision d 1 P D 1 . After observing d 1 , the attacker selects a 2 P A 2 . Subsequently, the defender observes a 2 , and decides d 3 P D 3 . Interactions between players continue until stage n. After all actions have been chosen, the uncertainty θ is resolved. In general, the distribution of θ depends on all actions taken. For simplicity, denote by S i the sequence of actions taken from stage i. For instance, if the defender moves at stage i, S i " td i , a i`1 , d i`2 , . . . u, and S i-1 " S i Y a i-1 . Then, the defender's beliefs about θ, given the sequence S 1 , are encoded in the distribution p D pθ|S 1 q. In addition, denote the Defender's (Attacker's) utility at the i-th stage as u D i pd i , θq (u A i pa i , θq).</p><p>With this, at the first stage, the defender needs to solve for d 1 " arg max d1 ş u D1 pd 1 , θq ¨pD pθ|S 1 q ¨pD pS 2 |d 1 q dθ dS 2 , where p D pS 2 |d 1 q encodes the Defender's beliefs about the sequence of actions starting at the second stage, given that she chooses d 1 at the first stage. We define an augmented distribution over the space of decisions and uncertainties π D pd 1 , θ, S 2 q9u D1 pd 1 , θq ¨ppθ|S 1 q ¨pD pS 2 |d 1 q: its mode in d 1 coincides with d 1 . Thus, we could solve the problem generating samples d 1 , θ, S 2 " π D pd 1 , θ, S 2 q and computing the mode of the d 1 samples.</p><p>This requires generating sequences of actions given decision d 1 , S 2 " p D pS 2 |d 1 . Note that we can write p D pS 2 |d 1 q " p D pa 2 |d 1 q ¨pD pd 3 |d 1 , a 2 q ¨¨¨Thus, S 2 can be sampled sequentially, by first sampling a 2 " p D pa 2 |d 1 q, then d 3 " p D pd 3 |d 1 , a 2 q, and so on. Note also that:</p><p>1. For every i, p D pd i |d 1 , a 2 , . . . , a i-1 q is a point mass centered at the solution of the i-th stage problem, which can be computed using APS, as we did in the first stage problem. 2. For every i, sampling a i " p D pa i |d 1 , a 2 , . . . , d i-1 q, requires solving the Attacker's i-th stage problem. Let us illustrate how this could be done leveraging the ARA methodology with the Attacker's second stage problem. In such stage, after observing d 1 , a expected utility maximizer attacker would choose a 2 " arg max a2 ż u A2 pa 1 , θq ¨pA pθ|d 1 , a 2 , S 3 q ¨pA pS 3 |d 1 , a 2 q dθ dS 3 .</p><p>However, the Defender is uncertain about the Attacker's utilities and probability judgments. As we did in the 2 stage game, for a given d 1 , the random augmented distribution built is Π ω A2 pa 2 , S 3 θ|d 1 q9U ω A2 pa 2 , θqP ω A pθ|d 1 , a 2 , S 3 qP ω A pS 3 |d 1 , a 2 q, its marginal on a 2 is proportional to A's random expected utility.</p><p>Consequently, by sampling u A1 pa 2 , θq " U A2 pa 2 , θq, p A pθ|d 1 , a 2 , S 3 q " P A pθ|d 1 , a 2 , S 3 q and p A pS 3 |d 1 , a 2 q " P A pS 3 |d 1 , a 2 q one can build π A2 pa 2 , S 3 θ|d 1 q which is a sample from Π A2 pa 2 , S 3 θ|d 1 q. Then, the mode of its marginal in a 2 is distributed as p D pa 2 |d 1 q, thus providing a mechanism to sample from such distribution. Notice that modeling the Defender's uncertainty about p A pS 3 |d 1 , a 2 q, entails constructing a hierarchy of decision-making problems.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Defender analysis of Attacker problem.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Influence diagrams for Defender and Attacker problems.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Template for basic two player simultaneous defend-attack game.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. ARA modeling of general BAID example.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Estimation of p D pa|dq through ARA</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>pd, θq p D pθ|d, aq dθ can be computed. The Attacker's best response to D's action d, is a ˚pdq " arg max aPA ψ A pd, aq. Such response is used to find the Defender's optimal game-theoretic action d GT " arg max dPD ψ D pd, a ˚pdqq. The pair `dG</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">Template for basic two player sequential defend-attack game</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">BAID. White nodes affect solely the Defender; grey nodes affect only the</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Attacker; striped nodes affect both agents.</cell></row><row><cell>expected utilities ψ A pd, aq " ψ D pd, aq " ş u D</cell><cell>ş</cell><cell>u A pa, θq p A pθ|d, aq dθ and</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>a Def. net costs; b Successful attack probs.; c Att. net benefits; d Beta dist. parameters</figDesc><table><row><cell>Defender non strategic judgments. Table 1a presents costs</cell></row><row><cell>c D associated with each decision and outcome, based on a</cell></row><row><cell>7Me business valuation; and 0.05Me base security cost</cell></row><row><cell>plus 0.05Me per each security level increase. Upon suc-</cell></row><row><cell>cessful attack, D loses the entire business value. The proba-</cell></row><row><cell>bility p D pθ " 1|d, aq of successful attack is in Table 1b (com-</cell></row><row><cell>plementary values for unsuccessful attacks). D is constant</cell></row><row><cell>risk averse in costs, with utility strategically equivalent to</cell></row><row><cell>u D pc D q " -exp p0.4 ˆcD q.</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head n="8.">Funding</head><p>Research supported by the <rs type="projectName">AXA-ICMAT Chair in Adversarial Risk Analysis(PI David Rios Insua</rs>), the <rs type="funder">EOARD-AFOSR</rs> project <rs type="grantNumber">RC2APD</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">GRANT 13324227</rs> (<rs type="grantName">PIs David Rios Insua and Tahir Ekin</rs>) and the <rs type="funder">STARLIGHT H2020</rs> project <rs type="grantNumber">101021797</rs> (<rs type="projectName">PI Nizar Touleimat</rs>). None of the funding bodies influenced on the design of this research and the writing of the manuscript.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_J9tqqDu">
					<idno type="grant-number">RC2APD</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">AXA-ICMAT Chair in Adversarial Risk Analysis(PI David Rios Insua</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_AeG9W9k">
					<idno type="grant-number">GRANT 13324227</idno>
					<orgName type="grant-name">PIs David Rios Insua and Tahir Ekin</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_DQg72ty">
					<idno type="grant-number">101021797</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">PI Nizar Touleimat</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Adversarial Risk Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Banks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Aliaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Insua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decision analysis by augmented probability simulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bielza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Insua</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="995" to="1007" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defending critical infrastructure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Carlyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Salmerón</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Interfaces</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="530" to="544" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Optimizing Department of Homeland Security defense investments: Applying Defender-Attacker(-Defender) optimization to terror risk assessment and mitigation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Carlyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>National Academies Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Appendix E.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The modal age of statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chacon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Statistical Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="122" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">A Course in Probability Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Augmented probability simulation methods for sequential games</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ekin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Naveiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Insua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Torres-Barrán</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Operational Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>French</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Insua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Statistical decision theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Adversarial-Risk-Analysis Approach to Counterterrorist Online Surveillance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Parra-Arnau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sensors</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adversarial Risk Analysis for Urban Security Resource Allocation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rios Insua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rios</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Risk Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="727" to="741" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adversarial risk analysis for bi-agent influence diagrams: An algorithmic approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>González-Ortega</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Insua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Operational Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">273</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1085" to="1096" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Game theory: a critical introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hargreaves-Heap</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Varoufakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Games with incomplete information played by &quot;Bayesian&quot; players, I-III Part I. the basic model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Harsanyi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="182" />
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strategic defense and attack of series systems when agents move sequentially</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hausken</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IIE Transactions</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="483" to="504" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Insider threat modeling: An adversarial risk analysis approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Joshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Aliaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Insua</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics and Security</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1131" to="1142" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Subjective probability and the theory of games</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kadane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Larkey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-agent influence diagrams for representing and solving games</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Koller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Milch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Games and Economic Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="221" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stackelberg vs. Nash in security games: An extended investigation of interchangeability, equivalence, and uniqueness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Korzhyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Yin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kiekintveld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Conitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tambe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jour. Art. Intell. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="297" to="327" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adversarial classification: An adversarial risk analysis approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Naveiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Redondo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Insua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ruggeri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Approximate Reasoning</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The art and science of negotiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Raiffa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982. 2003</date>
			<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Negotiation analysis: The science and art of collaborative decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Raiffa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Metcalfe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002. 2002</date>
			<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adversarial risk analysis for counterterrorism modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rios</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Insua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rios Insua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Banks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rios</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Risk Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="742" to="755" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Risk Analysis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An adversarial risk analysis framework for cybersecurity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rios Insua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Couce-Vieira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rubio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Pieters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Labunets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rasines</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Risk Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ríos</forename><surname>Insua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Naveiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gallego</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Poulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1908.06901</idno>
		<title level="m">Adversarial Machine Learning: Perspectives from adversarial risk analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>arXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adversarial risk analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rios Insua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ríos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Banks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">486</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="841" to="854" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adversarial risk analysis for enhancing combat simulation models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Roponen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Salo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Military Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="103" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adversarial Risk Analysis: The Somali Pirates Case</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sevillano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Insua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rios</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Decision Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating influence diagrams</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Shachter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Operations research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="871" to="882" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On players&apos; models of other players: Theory and experimental evidence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Stahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Games and Economic Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="218" to="254" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network routing for insurgency: An adversarial risk analysis framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Banks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Naval Research Logistics (NRL)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="595" to="607" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Balancing terrorism and</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
