<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Semiparametric Estimation for Causal Mediation Analysis with Multiple Causally Ordered Mediators *</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2021-11-10">10 Nov 2021</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Xiang</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Sociology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Harvard University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Harvard University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>33 Kirkland Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>02138</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Sociology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Harvard University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Harvard University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>33 Kirkland Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>02138</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Semiparametric Estimation for Causal Mediation Analysis with Multiple Causally Ordered Mediators *</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2021-11-10">10 Nov 2021</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2011.12751v2[stat.ME]</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T01:12+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>causal inference</term>
					<term>mediation</term>
					<term>path-specific effects</term>
					<term>multiple robustness</term>
					<term>semiparametric efficiency</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Causal mediation analysis concerns the pathways through which a treatment affects an outcome.</p><p>While most of the mediation literature focuses on settings with a single mediator, a flourishing line of research has examined settings involving multiple mediators, under which path-specific effects (PSEs) are often of interest. We consider estimation of PSEs when the treatment effect operates through K(≥ 1) causally ordered, possibly multivariate mediators. In this setting, the PSEs for many causal paths are not nonparametrically identified, and we focus on a set of PSEs that are identified under Pearl's nonparametric structural equation model. These PSEs are defined as contrasts between the expectations of 2 K+1 potential outcomes and identified via what we call the generalized mediation functional (GMF). We introduce an array of regressionimputation, weighting, and "hybrid" estimators, and, in particular, two K +2-robust and locally semiparametric efficient estimators for the GMF. The latter estimators are well suited to the use of data-adaptive methods for estimating their nuisance functions. We establish the rate conditions required of the nuisance functions for semiparametric efficiency. We also discuss how our framework applies to several estimands that may be of particular interest in empirical applications. The proposed estimators are illustrated with a simulation study and an empirical example.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Causal mediation analysis aims to disentangle the pathways through which a treatment affects an outcome. While traditional approaches to mediation analysis have relied on linear structural equation models, along with their stringent parametric assumptions, to define and estimate direct and indirect effects (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baron and Kenny 1986)</ref>, a large body of research has emerged within the causal inference literature that disentangles the tasks of definition, identification, and estimation in the study of causal mechanisms. Using the potential outcomes framework <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Neyman 1923;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Rubin 1974)</ref>, this body of research has provided model-free definitions of direct and indirect effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Robins and Greenland 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Pearl 2001)</ref>, established the assumptions needed for nonparametric identification <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Robins and Greenland 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Pearl 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Robins 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Petersen et al. 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Imai et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hafeman and VanderWeele 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">VanderWeele 2015)</ref>, and developed an array of imputation, weighting, and multiply robust methods for estimation (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Goetgeluk et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Albert 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Tchetgen Tchetgen and Shpitser 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Vansteelandt et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Zheng and van der Laan 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Tchetgen Tchetgen 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">VanderWeele 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Wodtke and Zhou 2020)</ref>.</p><p>While the bulk of the causal mediation literature focuses on settings with a single mediator (or a set of mediators considered as a whole), a flourishing line of research has studied settings that involve multiple causally dependent mediators, under which a set of path-specific effects <ref type="bibr">(PSEs)</ref> are often of interest <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Avin et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Albert and Nelson 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Shpitser 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">VanderWeele and Vansteelandt 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">VanderWeele et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Daniel et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Lin and VanderWeele 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Miles et al. 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Steen et al. 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Vansteelandt and Daniel 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Miles et al. 2020)</ref>. In particular, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Daniel et al. (2015)</ref> demonstrated a large number of ways in which the total effect of a treatment can be decomposed into PSEs, established the assumptions under which a subset of these PSEs are identified, and provided a parametric method for estimating these effects (see also <ref type="bibr">Albert and Nelson 2011)</ref>. More recently, for a particular PSE in the case of two causally ordered mediators, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Miles et al. (2020)</ref> offered an in-depth discussion of alternative estimation methods, and, utilizing the efficient influence function of its identification formula, developed a triply robust and locally semiparametric efficient estimator. This estimator, by virtue of its multiple robustness, is well suited to the use of data-adaptive methods for estimating its nuisance functions.</p><p>To date, most of the literature on PSEs has focused on the case of two mediators, and it remains underexplored how the estimation methods developed in previous studies, such as those in <ref type="bibr">VanderWeele et al. (2014)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Miles et al. (2020)</ref>, generalize to the case of K(≥ 1) causally ordered mediators. This article aims to bridge this gap. First, we observe that despite a multitude of ways in which a PSE can be defined for each causal path from the treatment to the outcome, most of these PSEs are not identified under Pearl's nonparametric structural equation model. This observation leads us to focus on the much smaller set of PSEs that can be nonparametrically identified. These PSEs are defined as contrasts between the expectations of 2 K+1 potential outcomes, which, in turn, are identified through a formula that can be viewed as an extension of <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Pearl's (2001)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Daniel et al.'s (2015)</ref> mediation formulae to the case of K causally ordered mediators. Following Tchetgen Tchetgen and <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Shpitser (2012)</ref>, we refer to the identification formula for these expected potential outcomes as the generalized mediation functional (GMF).</p><p>We then show that the GMF can be estimated via an array of regression, weighting, and "hybrid" estimators. More important, building on its efficient influence function (EIF), we develop two multiply robust and locally semiparametric efficient estimators for the GMF. Both of these estimators are K + 2-robust, in the sense that they are consistent provided that one of K + 2 sets of nuisance functions is correctly specified and consistently estimated. These multiply robust estimators are well suited to the use of data-adaptive methods for estimating the nuisance functions.</p><p>We establish rate conditions for consistency and semiparametric efficiency when data-adaptive methods and cross-fitting <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Zheng and van der Laan 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Chernozhukov et al. 2018</ref>) are used to estimate the nuisance functions.</p><p>Compared with existing estimators that have been proposed for causal mediation analysis, the methodology proposed in this article is distinct in its generality. In fact, the doubly robust estimator for the mean of an incomplete outcome <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Scharfstein et al. 1999)</ref>, the triply robust estimator developed by Tchetgen Tchetgen and <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Shpitser (2012)</ref> for the mediation functional in the one-mediator setting (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Zheng and van der Laan 2012)</ref>, and the estimator proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Miles et al. (2020)</ref> for their particular PSE, can all be viewed as special cases of the K + 2-robust estimators -when K = 0, 1, 2, respectively. Yet, our framework also encompasses important estimands for which semiparametric estimators have not been proposed. To demonstrate the generality of our framework, we show how our multiply robust semiparametric estimators apply to several estimands that may be of particular interest in empirical applications, including the natural direct effect (NDE), the natural/total indirect effect (NIE/TIE), the natural path-specific effect (nPSE), and the cumulative path-specific effect (cPSE). In Supplementary Material E, we discuss how our framework can also be employed to estimate noncausal decompositions of between-group disparities that are widely used in social science research <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Fortin et al. 2011)</ref>.</p><p>Before proceeding, we note that in a separate strand of literature, the term "multiple robustness" has been used to characterize a class of estimators for the mean of incomplete data that are consistent if one of several working models for the propensity score or one of several working models for the outcome is correctly specified (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Han and Wang 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Han 2014)</ref>. In this paper, we use "V -robustness" to characterize estimators that require modeling multiple parts of the observed data likelihood and are consistent provided that one of V sets of the corresponding models is correctly specified, in keeping with the terminology in the causal mediation literature. This definition of "multiple robustness" does not imply that a "K + 2-robust" estimator is necessarily more robust than, for example, a "K + 1-robust" estimator. First, they may correspond to different estimands that require modeling different parts of the likelihood. For example, the doubly robust estimator of the average treatment effect only involves a propensity score model and an outcome model; it is thus less demanding than Tchetgen Tchetgen and <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Shpitser's (2012)</ref> triply robust estimator of the mediation functional, which involves an additional model for the mediator. Second, for our semiparametric estimators of the GMF, the "K + 2-robustness" property is not "sharp" because it can be tightened in various special cases. As we demonstrate in Section 4 and Supplementary Material E, such a tightening may result in a lower V (as in the case of NDE, NIE/TIE, nPSE, and cPSE), or a higher V (as in the case of noncausal decompositions of between-group disparities).</p><p>The rest of the paper is organized as follows. In Section 2, we define the PSEs of interest, lay out their identification assumptions, and introduce the GMF. In Section 3, we introduce a range of regression-imputation, weighting, "hybrid," and multiply robust estimators for the GMF, and present several techniques that could be used to improve the finite sample performance of the multiply robust estimators. In Section 4, we discuss how our results apply to a number of special cases such as the NDE, NIE/TIE, nPSE, and cPSE. A simulation study and an empirical example are given in Section 5 and Section 6 to illustrate the proposed estimators. Proofs of Theorems 1-4 are given in Supplementary Materials A, C, and D. Replication data and code for the simulation study and the empirical example are available at <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.7910/DVN/5TBUM3">https://doi.org/10.7910/DVN/5TBUM3</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">X A M 2 M 1 Y (a) A M 2 M 1 Y (c) A M 2 M 1 Y (b) A M 2 M 1 Y (d) A M 2 M 1 Y</formula><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">1</ref>: Causal relationships with two causally ordered mediators.</p><p>Note: A denotes the treatment, Y denotes the outcome of interest, X denotes a vector of pretreatment covariates, and M 1 and M 2 denote two causally ordered mediators.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Notation, Definitions, and Identification</head><p>To ease exposition, we start with the case of two causally ordered mediators before moving onto the general setting of K mediators.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">The Case of Two Causally Ordered Mediators</head><p>Let A denote a binary treatment, Y an outcome of interest, and X a vector of pretreatment covariates. In addition, let M 1 and M 2 denote two causally ordered mediators, and assume M 1 precedes M 2 . We allow each of these mediators to be multivariate, in which case the causal relationships among the component variables are left unspecified. A directed acyclic graph <ref type="bibr">(DAG)</ref> representing the relationships between these variables is given in the top panel of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">1</ref>. In this DAG, four possible causal paths exist from the treatment to the outcome, as shown in the lower</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">panels: (a) A → Y ; (b) A → M 2 → Y ; (c) A → M 1 → Y ; and (d) A → M 1 → M 2 → Y .</formula><p>A formal definition of path-specific effects (PSEs) requires the potential-outcomes notation for both the outcome and the mediators. Specifically, let Y (a, m 1 , m 2 ) denote the potential outcome under treatment status a and mediator values M 1 = m 1 and M 2 = m 2 , M 2 (a, m 1 ) the potential value of the mediator M 2 under treatment status a and mediator value M 1 = m 1 , and M 1 (a) the potential value of the mediator M 1 under treatment status a. This notation allows us to define nested counterfactuals in the form of Y a, M 1 (a 1 ), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (a 12 )) , where a, a 1 , a 2 , and a 12 can each take 0 or 1. For example, Y 1, M 1 (0), M 2 (0, M 1 (0)) represents the potential outcome in the hypothetical scenario where the subject was treated but the mediators M 1 and M 2 were set to values they would have taken if the subject had not been treated. Further, if we let Y (a) denote the potential outcome when treatment status is set to a and the mediators M 1 and M 2 take on their "natural" values under treatment status a (i.e., M 1 (a) and</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">M 2 (a, M 1 (a))), we have Y (a) = Y a, M 1 (a), M 2 (a, M 1 (a)</formula><p>) by construction. This is sometimes referred to as the "composition" assumption (VanderWeele 2009).</p><p>Under the above notation, for each of the causal paths shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">1</ref>, its PSE can be defined in eight different ways, depending on the reference levels chosen for A for each of the other three paths <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Daniel et al. 2015)</ref>. For example, the average direct effect of A on Y , i.e., the portion of the treatment effect that operates through the path A → Y , can be defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">τ A→Y (a 1 , a 2 , a 12 ) = E[Y 1, M 1 (a 1 ), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (a 12 )) -Y 0, M 1 (a 1 ), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (a 12 )) ],</formula><p>where a 1 , a 2 , and a 12 can each take 0 or 1. In particular, τ A→Y (0, 0, 0) corresponds to the natural direct effect (NDE; Pearl 2001) or pure direct effect (PDE; <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Robins and Greenland 1992)</ref> if the mediators M 1 and M 2 are considered as a whole. In a similar vein, the PSEs via</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">A → M 2 → Y , A → M 1 → Y , and A → M 1 → M 2 → Y can be defined as τ A→M 2 →Y (a, a 1 , a 12 ) = E[Y a, M 1 (a 1 ), M 2 (1, M 1 (a 12 )) -Y a, M 1 (a 1 ), M 2 (0, M 1 (a 12 )) ], τ A→M 1 →Y (a, a 2 , a 12 ) = E[Y a, M 1 (1), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (a 12 )) -Y a, M 1 (0), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (a 12 )) ], τ A→M 1 →M 2 →Y (a, a 1 , a 2 ) = E[Y a, M 1 (a 1 ), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (1)) -Y a, M 1 (a 1 ), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (0)) ].</formula><p>In addition, if we use</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">A → M 1 Y to denote the combination of the causal paths A → M 1 → Y and A → M 1 → M 2 → Y</formula><p>, the corresponding PSE for this "composite path" can be defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">τ A→M 1 Y (a, a 2 ) = E[Y a, M 1 (1), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (1)) -Y a, M 1 (0), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (0)) ].</formula><p>This quantity reflects the portion of the treatment effect that operates through M 1 , regardless of whether it further operates through M 2 or not. In particular, τ A→M 1 Y (0, 0) is often referred to as </p><formula xml:id="formula_7">(a 1 ), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (a 12 )) ],</formula><p>are identified. Below, we review the assumptions under which these expected potential outcomes are identified from observed data.</p><p>Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Pearl (2009)</ref>, we use a DAG to encode a nonparametric structural equation model (NPSEM) with mutually independent errors. In this framework, the top panel of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">1</ref> implies no unobserved confounding for any of the treatment-mediator, treatment-outcome, mediator-mediator, and mediator-outcome relationships. Formally, we invoke the following assumptions.</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">Assumption 1. Consistency of A on M 1 , (A, M 1 ) on M 2 , and (A, M 1 , M 2 ) on Y : For any unit and any a, m 1 , m 2 , M 1 = M 1 (a) if A = a; M 2 = M 2 (a, m 1 ) if A = a and M 1 = m 1 ; and Y = Y (a, m 1 , m 2 ) if A = a, M 1 = m 1 , and M 2 = m 2 .</formula><p>Assumption 2. Conditional independence among treatment and potential outcomes: for any</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">a, a 1 , a 2 , m 1 , m * 1 , m 2 , M 1 (a 1 ), M 2 (a 2 , m 1 ), Y (a, m 1 , m 2 ) ⊥ ⊥ A|X; M 2 (a 2 , m 1 ), Y (a, m 1 , m 2 ) ⊥ ⊥ M 1 (a 1 )|X, A, and Y (a, m 1 , m 2 ) ⊥ ⊥ M 2 (a 2 , m * 1 )|X, A, M 1 . Assumption 3. Positivity: p A|X (a|x) &gt; &gt; 0 whenever p X (x) &gt; 0; p A|X,M 1 (a|x, m 1 ) &gt; &gt; 0 whenever p X,M 1 (x, m 1 ) &gt; 0, and p A|X,M 1 ,M 2 (a|x, m 1 , m 2 ) &gt; &gt; 0 whenever p X,M,M 2 (x, m 1 , m 2 ) &gt; 0,</formula><p>where p(•) denotes a probability density/mass function.</p><p>Note that Assumption 2 involves conditional independence relationships between the so-called cross-world counterfactuals, such as</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">M 2 (a 2 , m 1 ), Y (a, m 1 , m 2 ) ⊥ ⊥ M 1 (a 1 )|X, A.</formula><p>This assumption is a direct consequence of Pearl's NPSEM with mutually independent errors. It implies, but is not implied by, the sequential ignorability assumption that <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Robins (2003)</ref> invokes in interpreting causal diagrams (see Robins and Richardson 2010 for an in-depth discussion). In addition, we note that Assumption 2 does not rule out all forms of unobserved confounding for the causal effects of X on its descendants. For example, unobserved variables are permitted (although not shown) in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">1</ref> that affect both X and Y .</p><p>Under Assumptions 1-3, it can be shown that E[Y a, M 1 (a 1 ), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (a 12 )) ] is identified if and only if a 12 = a 1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Avin et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Albert and Nelson 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Daniel et al. 2015)</ref>. Consequently, none of the PSEs for the path</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">A → M 1 → Y is identified because given a 12 , ei- ther E[Y a, M 1 (1), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (a 12 )) ] or E[Y a, M 1 (0), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (a 12</formula><p>)) ] is unidentified. Similarly, none of the PSEs for the path A → M 1 → M 2 → Y is identified. Interestingly, the PSEs for the composite path A → M 1 Y are all identified, even if a = a 2 . These results echo the recanting witness criterion developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Avin et al. (2005)</ref>, which implies that the PSE for a (possibly composite) path from A to Y when A is set to 0 (or 1) for all other paths is identified if and only if the path of interest contains no "recanting witness" -a variable W that has an additional path to Y that is not contained in the path of interest. Thus the PSE τ A→M 1 →Y (0, 0, 0) is not identified because M 1 has an additional path to</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">Y (M 1 → M 2 → Y ) that is not contained in A → M 1 → Y , but the PSE τ A→M 1 Y (0, 0) is identified because all possible paths from M 1 to Y is contained in A → M 1 Y . Because E[Y a, M 1 (a 1 ), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (a 12</formula><p>)) ] is identified if and only if a 1 = a 12 , we restrict our attention to cases where a 1 = a 12 and use the following notation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">ψ a 1 ,a 2 ,a ∆ = E Y a, M 1 (a 1 ), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (a 1 )) .</formula><p>Under Assumptions 1-3, ψ a 1 ,a 2 ,a is identified via the following formula:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">ψ a 1 ,a 2 ,a = E[Y |x, a, m 1 , m 2 ]dP (m 2 |x, a 2 , m 1 )dP (m 1 |x, a 1 )dP (x).<label>(1)</label></formula><p>For a proof of the above formula, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Daniel et al. (2015)</ref>. Equation (1) can be seen as an extension of <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Pearl's (2001)</ref> mediation formula to the case of two causally ordered mediators.</p><p>It should be noted that Assumptions 1-3 constitute a sufficient set of conditions that allow us to identify ψ a 1 ,a 2 ,a for arbitrary combinations of a 1 , a 2 , and a. For specific combinations of a 1 , a 2 , and a, Assumption 2 can be relaxed. For example, ψ 100 is still identified via equation (1) when unobserved confounding exists for the M 2 -Y relationship, and ψ 010 is still identified via equation (1) when unobserved confounding exists for the M 1 -Y relationship <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Shpitser 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Miles et al. 2020</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">The Case of K(≥ 1) Causally Ordered Mediators</head><p>We now generalize the preceding results to the setting where the treatment effect of A on Y operates through K causally ordered, possibly multivariate mediators, M 1 , M 2 , . . . M K . We assume that for</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">any k &lt; k , M k precedes M k , such that no component of M k causally affects any component of M k .</formula><p>In a DAG that is consistent with this setup, a directed path from the treatment to the outcome can pass through any combination of the K mediators, resulting in 2 K possible paths. Among the 2 K paths, each can be switched "on" or "off," creating 2 2 K potential outcomes. Also, for each of the 2 K paths, the corresponding PSE can be defined in 2 2 K -1 different ways, depending on whether each of the other 2 K -1 paths is switched "on" or "off." For example, when K = 3, for each causal path from A to Y , its PSE can be defined in 2 2 3 -1 = 128 different ways.</p><p>As we will see, despite the exponential growth of possible causal paths and the double exponential growth of possible PSEs, most of these PSEs are not identified under the assumptions associated with Pearl's NPSEM. To fix ideas, let an overbar denote a vector of variables, so that</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">M k = (M 1 , M 2 , . . . M k ), m k = (m 1 , m 2 , . . . m k ), and a k = (a 1 , a 2 , . . . a k ), where M l = m l = a l = ∅ if l ≤ 0.</formula><p>In addition, let [K] denote the set {1, 2, . . . K}, and let a K+1 , instead of a, denote the treatment status set to the path A → Y . Assumptions 1-3 can now be generalized as below.</p><p>Assumption 1 * . Consistency: For any unit,</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">M k = M k (a k , m k-1 ) if A = a k and M k-1 = m k-1 , ∀k ∈ [K]; and Y = Y (a K+1 , m K ) if A = a K+1 and M K = m K . Assumption 2 * . Conditional independence among treatment and po- tential outcomes: M 1 (a 1 ), M 2 (a 2 , m 1 ), . . . Y (a K+1 , m K ) ⊥ ⊥ A|X; and M k+1 (a k+1 , m k ), . . . M K (a K , m K-1 ), Y (a K+1 , m K ) ⊥ ⊥ M k (a k , m * k-1 )|X, A, M k-1 , ∀k ∈ [K]. Assumption 3 * . Positivity: p A|X (a|x) &gt; &gt; 0 whenever p X (x) &gt; 0; p A|X,M k (a|x, m k ) &gt; &gt; 0 whenever p X,M k (x, m k ) &gt; 0, ∀k ∈ [K].</formula><p>Before giving the identification results, we introduce the following notational shorthands:</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">M k (a k ) ∆ = M k-1 (a k-1 ), M k (a k , M k-1 (a k-1 )) , ∀k ∈ [K], ψ a ∆ = E[Y (a K+1 , M k (a k ))],</formula><p>where M k (a k ) is defined iteratively, with the assumption that M 0 (a 0 ) = ∅. For example, when</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">K = 3, ψ a = E Y a 4 , M 1 (a 1 ), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (a 1 )), M 3 (a 3 , M 1 (a 1 ), M 2 (a 2 , M 1 (a 1 ))) .</formula><p>Theorem 1 states that ψ a is identified under Assumptions 1*-3*.</p><p>Theorem 1. Under Assumptions 1*-3*, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">ψ a = x m K E[Y |x, a K+1 , m K ] K k=1 dP (m k |x, a k , m k-1 ) dP (x). (<label>2</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">)</formula><p>The above equation extends <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Pearl's (2001)</ref>  </p><formula xml:id="formula_22">τ A→M k Y (a k-1 , •, a k+1 ) = ψ a k-1 ,1,a k+1 -ψ a k-1 ,0,a k+1 ,</formula><p>where a k+1 ∆ = (a k+1 , . . . a K+1 ). The notation ψ a makes it clear that the average total effect (ATE) of</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">A on Y can be decomposed into K +1 identifiable PSEs corresponding to A → Y and A → M k Y (k ∈ [K]): ATE = ψ 1 -ψ 0 = ψ 0 K ,1 -ψ 0 K+1 A→Y + K k=1 ψ 0 k-1 ,1 k -ψ 0 k ,1 k+1 A→M k Y . (<label>3</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_24">)</formula><p>To be sure, equation (3) is not the only way of decomposing the ATE. Depending on the order in which the paths A → Y and</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">A → M k Y (k ∈ [K]</formula><p>) are considered, there are (K + 1)! different ways of decomposing the ATE. In the above decomposition, ψ 0 K ,1 -ψ 0 K+1 corresponds to the NDE if the mediators M K are considered as a whole.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Estimation</head><p>In this section, we focus on the estimation of the GMF, i.e., the right-hand side of equation (2).</p><p>When Assumptions 1*-3* hold, the GMF is equal to the causal parameter ψ a , but otherwise, it is still a well-defined statistical parameter of potential scientific interest. To distinguish it from the causal parameter ψ a , we henceforth denote the GMF by θ a .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">MLE, Regression-Imputation, and Weighting</head><p>Equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_20">2</ref>) suggests that θ a can be estimated via maximum likelihood (MLE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Miles et al. 2017)</ref>. Specifically, we can fit a parametric model for each</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">p(m k |x, a k , m k-1 ) (k ∈ [K]) and for E[Y |x, a K+1 , m K ],</formula><p>and then estimate the GMF via the following equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">θmle a = P n m K Ê[Y |X, a K+1 , m K ] K k=1 p(m k |x, a k , m k-1 )dν(m k ) ,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">P n [•] = n -1 i [•] i and ν(•)</formula><p>is an appropriate dominating measure. This approach works best when the mediators M 1 , M 2 , . . . M K are all discrete and the covariates X are low-dimensional, in which case the working models for p(m k |x, a k , m k-1 ) are simply models for the conditional probabilities of M k that can be reliably estimated. When some of the mediators are continuous/multivariate or when the covariates X are high-dimensional, estimates of the corresponding conditional density/probability functions can be unstable and sensitive to model misspecification. This problem could be mitigated by imposing highly constrained functional forms on the conditional means of the mediators and the outcome. For example, when</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">E[M k |x, a k , m k-1 ] and E[Y |x, a K+1 , m K ] are</formula><p>all assumed to be linear with no higher-order or interaction terms, θmle a will reduce to a simple function of regression coefficients (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alwin and Hauser 1975</ref>). Yet, the assumptions of linearity and additivity are unrealistic in many applications, which may lead to biased estimates of θ a . Below, we describe several imputation-and weighting-based strategies for estimating θ a .</p><p>First, we observe that the GMF can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">θ a = E X E M 1 |X,a 1 . . . E M K |X,a K ,M K-1 E[Y |X, a K+1 , M K ] ∆ =µ K (X,M K ) ∆ =µ K-1 (X,M K-1 ) ∆ =µ 0 (X)</formula><p>.</p><p>(5)</p><p>This expression suggests that θ a can be estimated via an iterated regression-imputation (RI) approach (Zhou and Yamamoto 2020):</p><p>1. Estimate µ K (X, M K ) by fitting a parametric model for the conditional mean of Y given (X, A, M K ) and then setting A = a K+1 for all units;</p><p>2. For k = K -1, . . . 0, estimate µ k (X, M k ) by fitting a parametric model for the conditional mean of µ k+1 (X, M k+1 ) and then setting A = a k+1 for all units;</p><p>3. Estimate θ a by averaging the fitted values μ0 (X) among all units:</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">θri a = P n μ0 (X) .<label>(6)</label></formula><p>The regression-imputation estimator can be seen as an extension of the imputation strategy proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Vansteelandt et al. (2012)</ref> for estimating the NDE and NIE in the one-mediator setting.</p><p>Since this approach requires modeling only the conditional means of observed/imputed outcomes given different sets of mediators, it is more flexible to use with continuous/multivariate mediators than MLE. Nonetheless, because µ k (x, m k ) is estimated iteratively, correct specification of all of the outcome models is required for θri a to be consistent. Thus, in practice, when parametric models are used to estimate µ k (x, m k ), care should be taken to ensure that the outcome models used to estimate these functions are mutually compatible. For example, if µ 1 (X, M 1 ) follows a linear model that includes X and X 2 as predictors, then the model used to estimate µ 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">(X) = E[µ 1 (X, M 1 )|X, A = a 1 ]</formula><p>should also include X and X 2 in the predictor set.</p><p>The GMF can also be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">θ a = E I(A = a K+1 ) p(a K+1 |X) K k=1 p(M k |X, a k , M k-1 ) p(M k |X, a K+1 , M k-1 ) Y .</formula><p>This expression suggests a weighting estimator of θ a : θw-m</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">a = P n I(A = a K+1 ) p(a K+1 |X) K k=1 p(M k |X, a k , M k-1 ) p(M k |X, a K+1 , M k-1 ) Y .<label>(7)</label></formula><p>This estimator can be seen as an extension of the weighting estimator proposed in VanderWeele et al.</p><p>(2014) for the case of two mediators. It shares a limitation of θmle a in that it requires estimates of the conditional densities/probabilities of the mediators, which tend to be noisy if the mediators are continuous or multivariate. This problem, however, can be sidestepped by recasting the mediator density ratios, via Bayes' rule, as odds ratios in terms of the treatment variable:</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">p(M k |X, a k , M k-1 ) p(M k |X, a K+1 , M k-1 ) = p(a k |X, M k )/p(a K+1 |X, M k ) p(a k |X, M k-1 )/p(a K+1 |X, M k-1 )</formula><p>.</p><p>This observation leads to an alternative weighting estimator based on estimates of the conditional probabilities of treatment given different sets of mediators: θw-a</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">a = P n I(A = a K+1 ) p(a 1 |X) K k=1 p(a k |X, M k ) p(a k+1 |X, M k ) Y .<label>(8)</label></formula><p>In applications where the mediators are continuous/multivariate, θw-a The regression-imputation approach and the weighting approach can be combined to form various "hybrid estimators" of θ a . For example, in the case of K = 2, one can use regressionimputation to estimate µ 2 (x, m 1 , m 2 ), another regression-imputation step to estimate µ 1 (x, m 1 ), and weighting to estimate θ a , yielding an "RI-RI-W" estimator:</p><p>θri-ri-w</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">a = P n I(A = a 1 ) p(a 1 |X) μ1 (X, M 1 ) .<label>(9)</label></formula><p>One can also use regression-imputation to estimate µ 2 (x, m 1 , m 2 ) and then employ appropriate weights to estimate θ a , which leads to an "RI-W-W" estimator:</p><p>θri-w-w</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">a = P n I(A = a 2 ) p(a 2 |X) p(M 1 |X, a 1 ) p(M 1 |X, a 2 ) μ2 (X, M 1 , M 2 ) .<label>(10)</label></formula><p>In fact, with K mediators, there are 2 K+1 different ways to combine regression-imputation and weighting, each of which involves estimating K +1 nuisance functions, which entail a choice between p(a|x) and µ 0 (x) and a choice between p(m k |x, a, m k-1 ) and µ k (x, m k ) for each k ∈ [K] (see Supplementary Material B for detailed expressions of these hybrid estimators in the case of K = 2). As with θmle a , θri a , θw-m a , and θw-a a , each of these hybrid estimators will be consistent only if the corresponding nuisance functions are all correctly specified and consistently estimated. In applications where the pretreatment covariates X and/or the mediators have many components, all of the above estimators will be prone to model misspecification bias.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Multiply Robust and Semiparametric Efficient Estimation</head><p>Henceforth, let O = (X, A, M K , Y ) denote the observed data, and P np a nonparametric model over O wherein all laws P satisfy the positivity assumption described in Section 2.2. In addition, define µ k (X, M k ) iteratively as in equation ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>):</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">µ K (X, M K ) ∆ = E[Y |X, a K+1 , M K ] µ k (X, M k ) ∆ = E[µ k+1 (X, M k+1 )|X, a k+1 , M k ], k = K -1, . . . , 0.</formula><p>Theorem 2. The efficient influence function (EIF) of θ a in P np is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">ϕ a (O) = K+1 k=0 ϕ k (O),<label>(11)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">ϕ 0 (O) = µ 0 (X) -θ a , ϕ k (O) = I(A = a k ) p(a k |X) k-1 j=1 p(M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) p(M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) µ k (X, M k ) -µ k-1 (X, M k-1 ) , k ∈ [K], ϕ K+1 (O) = I(A = a K+1 ) p(a K+1 |X) K j=1 p(M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) p(M j |X, a K+1 , M j-1 ) Y -µ K (X, M K ) .</formula><p>The semiparametric efficiency bound for any regular and asymptotically linear estimator of θ a in</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">P np is therefore E ϕ a (O) 2 .</formula><p>We now present two estimators of θ a based on the EIF. First, consider the factorized likelihood </p><formula xml:id="formula_43">of O: p(O) = p(X)p(A|X) K k=1 p(M k |X, A, M k-1 ) p(Y |X, A, M K ).</formula><formula xml:id="formula_44">=P n I(A = a K+1 ) π0 (a K+1 |X) K j=1 fj (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) fj (M j |X, a K+1 , M j-1 ) Y -μK (X, M K ) + K k=1 I(A = a k ) π0 (a k |X) k-1 j=1 fj (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) fj (M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) μmle k (X, M k ) -μmle k-1 (X, M k-1 ) + μmle 0 (X) ,<label>(12)</label></formula><p>where μmle</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">K (X, M K ) = μK (X, M K ) and μmle k (X, M k ) is iteratively constructed as μmle k (X, M k ) = μmle k+1 (X, M k , m k+1 ) fk+1 (m k+1 |X, a k+1 , M k )dν(m k+1 ), k = K -1, . . . 0. (<label>13</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_46">)</formula><p>When M k+1 involves continuous components, equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_45">13</ref>) can be evaluated via Monte Carlo simulation.</p><p>When some of the mediators are continuous/multivariate, it can be difficult to estimate the conditional distributions p(m k |x, a, m k-1 ). In such cases, it is often preferable to estimate the mediator density ratios using the corresponding odds ratios of the treatment variable, and estimate the functions µ k (x, m k ) using the regression-imputation approach. Specifically, suppose we have estimated 2(K + 1) nuisance functions: π0 (a|x) for p(a|x), πk (a|x,</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">m k ) for p(a|x, m k ) (k ∈ [K]), and μk (x, m k ) for µ k (x, m k ) (k ∈ {0, 1, . . . K}), where for k &lt; K, µ k (x, m k ) is estimated iteratively</formula><p>by fitting a model for the conditional mean of μk+1 (X, M k+1 ) given (X, A, M k ) and then setting A = a k+1 for all units. The GMF can then be estimated as</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">θeif 2 a =P n I(A = a K+1 ) π0 (a 1 |X) K j=1 πj (a j |X, M j ) πj (a j+1 |X, M j ) Y -μK (X, M K ) + K k=1 I(A = a k ) π0 (a 1 |X) k-1 j=1 πj (a j |X, M j ) πj (a j+1 |X, M j ) μk (X, M k ) -μk-1 (X, M k-1 ) + μ0 (X) . (<label>14</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_49">)</formula><p>The multiple robustness and semiparametric efficiency of θeif 1 a and θeif 2 a are given below.</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">Theorem 3. Let η 1 = {π 0 , f 1 , . . . f K , µ K } denote the K + 2 nuisance functions involved in θeif 1 a ,</formula><p>and η 2 = {π 0 , . . . π K , µ 0 , . . . µ K } denote the 2(K + 1) nuisance functions involved in θeif 2 a . Suppose that Assumption 3* (positivity) and suitable regularity conditions for estimating equations (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Newey and</ref><ref type="bibr">McFadden 1994, p. 2148)</ref> hold. In addition, suppose that µ K (x, m K ) is bounded over the support of (X, M K ). Then, when the elements of η 1 and η 2 are estimated via parametric models, 1. θeif 1 a is consistent and asymptotically normal (CAN) if K +1 of the K +2 nuisance functions in η 1 are correctly specified and their parameter estimates are √ n-consistent; it is semiparametric efficient if all of the K + 2 nuisance functions in η 1 are correctly specified and their parameter weaker condition than that implied by Theorem 3 for θeif 1 010 to be CAN. Specifically, they showed that θeif 1 010 remains CAN even if both f 1 and µ 2 are misspecified. In Section 4, we show that the conditions for θeif 2 a to be CAN can also be relaxed for several particular types of PSEs, including the natural path-specific effect (nPSE), of which ψ 010 -ψ 000 is a special case. For the K = 2 case, Miles et al. also noted that the mediator density ratios in θeif 1 010 can be indirectly estimated through models for π 1 and π 2 . Clearly, this approach will result in θeif 2 010 if the µ k (x, m k ) functions are in the meanwhile estimated through regression-imputation. The K + 2-robustness of θeif 1 a and θeif 2 a , interestingly, resembles the multiple robustness of the <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bang-Robins (2005)</ref> estimator for the mean of a potential outcome with time-varying treatments and time-varying confounders <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Luedtke et al. 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Molina et al. 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Rotnitzky et al. 2017)</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">estimates are √ n-consistent. 2. θeif 2 a is CAN if ∃k ∈ {0, . . . K+1},</formula><p>To gain some intuition as to why θeif 1 a is K + 2-robust, consider cases in which only one nuisance function in η 1 is misspecified. When only π 0 is misspecified, all terms inside P n [•] but μmle 0 (X) will have a zero mean (asymptotically), leaving only P n [μ mle 0 (X)] (i.e., the MLE estimator ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_27">4</ref>)), which is consistent because the corresponding nuisance functions {f 1 , . . . f K , µ K } are all correctly specified.</p><p>When only µ K is misspecified, all terms involving μK (X, M K ) and μmle k (X, M k ) (k = 0, 1, . . . K -1) inside P n [•] will have a zero mean (asymptotically), leaving only a weighted average of Y (i.e., the weighting estimator ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_34">7</ref>)), which is consistent because the corresponding nuisance functions</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">{π 0 , f 1 , . . . f K } are all correctly specified. Finally, when only f k is misspecified (for some k ∈ [K]),</formula><p>it can be shown that all terms involving fk and μmle</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">k (X, M k ) (∀k &lt; k ) inside P n [•]</formula><p>will have a zero mean (asymptotically), leaving only a weighted average of μmle k (X, M k ). The latter constitutes a "hybrid" estimator similar to those mentioned in the previous section, and it is consistent in this case because its nuisance functions {π</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">0 , f 1 , . . . f k -1 , f k +1 , . . . f K , µ K } are all correctly specified. The K + 2-robustness of θeif 2 a</formula><p>is due to a similar logic to that of θeif 1 a . Yet, different from θeif 1 a , θeif 2 a involves estimating 2(K + 1) nuisance functions, K + 1 for the conditional probabilities of treatment and K + 1 for the conditional means of observed/imputed outcomes. Also, unlike θeif 1 a , the treatment models involved in θeif 2 a are not variationally independent; neither are the outcome models. For example, when</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">M K ⊥ ⊥ A|X, M K-1 , π K (A|X, M K ) should be identical to π K-1 (A|X, M K-1 ); similarly, when M K ⊥ ⊥ Y |X, A, M K-1 , µ K (X, M K ) should be identical to µ K-1 (X, M K-1</formula><p>). Thus, in practice, both the treatment and outcome models should be specified in a mutually compatible way, otherwise some of the conditions in Theorem 3 may fail by design.</p><p>The local efficiency of θeif 1 a and θeif 2 a is due to the fact that both of the EIF-based estimating equations ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_44">12</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_48">14</ref>) have a zero derivative with respect to the nuisance functions at the truth. This property, referred to as "Neyman orthogonality" by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Chernozhukov et al. (2018)</ref>, implies that first step estimation of the nuisance functions has no first order effect on the influence functions of θeif 1 a and θeif 2 a . This property suggests that the nuisance functions can be estimated using dataadaptive/machine learning methods or their ensembles. In this case, these estimators will still be consistent as long as the nuisance functions associated with one of the K + 2 conditions in Theorem 3 are consistently estimated. For θeif 2 a , an added advantage of employing data-adaptive methods to estimate the nuisance functions is that, by exploring a larger space within P np , the risk of model incompatibility is reduced.</p><p>When data-adaptive/machine learning methods are used to estimate the nuisance functions, it is advisable to use sample splitting to render the empirical process term asymptotically negligible <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Zheng and van der Laan 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Chernozhukov et al. 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Newey and Robins 2018)</ref>. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Chernozhukov et al. (2018)</ref> suggest the method of "cross-fitting," which involves the following steps:</p><p>(a) randomly partition the sample S into J folds: S 1 , S 2 . . . S J ; (b) for each j, obtain a fold-specific estimate of the target parameter using only data from S j ("main sample"), but with nuisance functions learned from the remainder of the sample (i.e., S\S j ; "auxiliary sample"); (c) average these fold-specific estimates to form a final estimate of the target parameter.</p><p>When cross-fitting is used, θeif 1 a and θeif 2 a will be semiparametric efficient if the corresponding nuisance function estimates are all consistent and converge at sufficiently fast rates. For example, a sufficient (but not necessary) condition for θeif 1 P and its estimates implied by η1 and η2 , and that all other assumptions required for Theorem 3 hold. Then, when the nuisance functions are estimated via data-adaptive methods and cross-fitting,</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">1. θeif 1 a is consistent if K + 1 of the K + 2 elements in η1 are consistent in the L 2 -norm; it is</formula><p>CAN and semiparametric efficient if all elements in η1 are consistent in the L 2 -norm and </p><formula xml:id="formula_57">u,v∈η 1 ;u =v r n (u)r n (v) = o(n -1/2 ); 2. θeif 2 a is consistent if ∃k ∈ {0, . . . K + 1}, π0 , . . . πk</formula><formula xml:id="formula_58">K j=0 r n (π j )r n (μ j ) = o(n -1/2 ).</formula><p>The multiple robustness result for θeif 1 a echoes Theorem 3. Moreover, the first part of Theorem 4 states that θeif 1 a is CAN and semiparametric efficient if all nuisance functions in η 1 are consistently estimated and, for every two nuisance functions in η 1 , the product of their convergence rates is o(n -1/2 ). Thus θeif 1 a is CAN and semiparametric efficient if all of the K + 2 nuisance function estimates are consistent and converge at faster-than-n -1/4 rates, but it will also attain semiparametric efficiency under alternative conditions. For example, when estimates of the treatment and mediator models {π 0 , f1 , . . . fK } all converge to the truth at a rate of n -1/3 and estimates of the outcome model μK converge to the truth at a rate of n -1/5 , the product of the convergence rates of any two elements in η1 is either</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">O(n -1/3 )O(n -1/3 ) = O(n -2/3 ) or O(n -1/3 )O(n -1/5 ) = O(n -8/15 ), both faster than O(n -1/2 ).</formula><p>The second part of Theorem 4 states that θeif 2 a is consistent if there exists a k such that the first k treatment models and the last K + 1 -k outcome models in η 2 are consistently estimated, echoing Theorem 3. As with θeif 1 a , θeif 2 a will be CAN and semiparametric efficient if all of the required nuisance functions are consistently estimated and converge at faster-than-n -1/4 rates.</p><p>The rate condition</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">K j=0 r n (π j )r n (μ j ) = o(n -1/2</formula><p>) appears to be weaker than that for θeif 1 a as it involves the sum of only K + 1, rather than K+2 2 , product terms. Because the outcome models are estimated iteratively, the convergence rate of μk will in general depend on the convergence</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">rates of {μ k+1 , . . . μK }. That is, if r n (μ k+1 ) = O(n δ ), r n (μ k ) is unlikely to be faster than O(n δ ).</formula><p>Nonetheless, θeif 2 a will be CAN and semiparametric efficient under relatively weak conditionsfor example, when estimates of the treatment models all converge to the truth at a rate of n -1/3 and estimates of the outcome models all converge to the truth at a rate of n -1/5 , in which case</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">K j=0 r n (π j )r n (μ j ) = K j=0 O(n -8/15 ) = o(n -1/2 ).</formula><p>For inference on θeif 1 a and θeif 2 a , a simple variance estimator can be constructed from the empirical analog of the EIF, i.e., P n [ φ2 a (O)]/n. However, unlike θeif 1 a and θeif 2 a , this variance estimator is not multiply robust -it will be consistent only if the conditions for semiparametric efficiency in Theorem 3 or Theorem 4 are satisfied. Thus, when the nuisance functions are estimated using parametric models, the variance estimator constructed from the empirical EIF may be inconsistent even when the corresponding estimator for θ a is CAN -for example, when only K + 1 of the K + 2 nuisance functions involved in θeif 1 a are correctly specified. In this case, the nonparametric bootstrap is a convenient approach to more robust inference. When the nuisance functions are estimated using data-adaptive/machine learning methods, however, the nonparametric bootstrap is not theoretically justified, and the EIF-based variance estimator may still be preferred.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Multiply Robust Regression-Imputation Estimators</head><p>Both of the multiply robust estimators described above involve inverse probability weights. When the positivity assumption is nearly violated, the inverse probability weights tend to be highly variable, which may lead to poor finite sample performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Kang and Schafer 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Petersen et al. 2012)</ref>. A variety of methods have been proposed to reduce the influence of highly variable weights on doubly robust and multiply robust estimators in similar settings (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Robins et al. 2007</ref>;</p><p>Tchetgen Tchetgen and Shpitser 2012; Seaman and Vansteelandt 2018). Among them, a common strategy is to tailor the estimating equation of the outcome model(s) such that the terms involving inverse probability weights will equal zero, leaving only a regression-imputation or "substitution"</p><p>estimator that typically resides in the parameter space of the estimand. Below, we briefly describe how this approach can be adapted to θeif 1 a and θeif 2 a .</p><p>Let us start with θeif 2 a , which can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">θeif 2 a =P n ŵK (X, A, M K ) Y -μK (X, M K ) + K k=1 ŵk-1 (X, A, M k-1 ) μk (X, M k ) -μk-1 (X, M k-1 ) + μ0 (X) ,<label>(15)</label></formula><p>where ŵk (A, X, M k ) (0 ≤ k ≤ K) are estimates of the corresponding inverse probability weights as displayed in equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_48">14</ref>). Note that the nuisance functions μk (X, M k ) (0 ≤ k ≤ K) here are all estimated via the regression-imputation approach. When the corresponding outcome models are fitted via generalized linear models (GLM) with canonical links, one can either (a) fit weighted GLMs (with an intercept term) for μk (X, M k ) using ŵk (A, X, M k ) as weights, or (b) add the corresponding inverse probability weight as an additional covariate in these regressions <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Robins et al. 2007)</ref>. Either way, the score equations for GLMs will ensure that all terms inside P n [•] but μ0 (X) have a sample mean of zero, leaving only P n [μ 0 (X)], which will reside in the parameter space of θ a if the latter equals the range of the GLM specified for µ 0 (x).</p><p>Alternatively, one can use the method of targeted maximum likelihood estimation (TMLE; van Der Laan and Rubin 2006; Zheng and van der Laan 2012), which, by fitting each of the outcome models in two steps, will also ensure a zero sample mean for all terms inside P n [•] but μ0 (X). This approach does not require the first-step models to be GLM and thus can be used with a wider range of outcome models. In our case, it involves the following steps:</p><p>1. For k = K, . . . 0 (a) Using μtmle k+1 (X, M k+1 ) (or, in the case k = K, the observed outcome Y ) as the response variable, obtain a first-step regression-imputation estimate of µ k (X, M k );</p><p>(b) Fit a one-parameter GLM for the conditional mean of μtmle k+1 (X, M k+1 ) (or, in the case k = K, the observed outcome Y ), using g(μ k (X, M k )) as an offset term and ŵk (A, X, M k )</p><p>as the only covariate (without an intercept term), and obtain an updated estimate</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">μtmle k (X, M k ) = g -1 g(μ k (X, M k )) + βk ŵk (A, X, M k ) , where g(•)</formula><p>is the link function for the GLM and βk is the estimated coefficient on ŵk (A, X, M k );</p><p>2. Obtain the final estimate θtmle</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">a = P n [μ tmle 0 (X)].</formula><p>In the one-mediator case, the above estimator is similar to the TMLE estimator proposed by Zheng and van der Laan (2012) for the NDE, i.e., ψ 01 -ψ 00 . Since Zheng and van der Laan's estimand is the NDE instead of the mediation functional, their TMLE procedure involves fitting a model for the "mediated mean outcome difference" (p. 6), i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">E[E[Y |X, A = 1, M ]-E[Y |X, A = 0, M ]|X, A = 0],</formula><p>instead of the conditional mean of the imputed outcome itself, i.e., µ 0 (X).</p><p>As with the GLM-based adjustments, the TMLE approach also yields a regression-imputation estimator that resides in the parameter space of θ a if the latter equals the range of the model specified for µ 0 (x). It should be noted that when data-adaptive methods are used to obtain firststep estimates of the nuisance functions, sample splitting should be employed so that steps 1(a)</p><p>and steps 1(b) are implemented on different subsamples. In cross-fitting, for example, steps 1(a) should be implemented in the auxiliary sample (S\S j ) and steps 1(b) implemented in the main sample S j . The method of TMLE can also be used to adjust θeif 1 a , in which case the first step estimates of µ k (X, M k ) (0 ≤ k ≤ K -1) are based on equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_45">13</ref>), and the weights ŵk (A, X, M k ) (0 ≤ k ≤ K) reflect the corresponding terms in equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_44">12</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Special Cases</head><p>We have so far considered θ a for the unconstrained case where a 1 , . . . a K+1 can each take 0 or 1.</p><p>In many applications, the researcher may be interested in particular causal estimands such as the natural direct effect (NDE), the natural/total indirect effect (NIE/TIE), and natural path-specific effects (nPSE; <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Daniel et al. 2015)</ref>. Below, we discuss how the multiply robust semiparametric estimators of θ a apply to these estimands. In addition, we discuss a set of cumulative path-specific effects (cPSEs) that together compose the ATE. In Supplementary Material E, we connect these cPSEs to noncausal decompositions of between-group disparities that are widely used in the social sciences. For illustrative purposes, we focus on estimators based on θeif 2 a , although similar results hold for those based on θeif 1 a . Throughout this section, we maintain Assumptions 1*-3* so that θ a = ψ a .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Natural Direct Effect (NDE)</head><p>The NDE measures the effect of switching treatment status from 0 to 1 in a hypothetical world where the mediators (M 1 , . . . M K ) were all set to values they would have "naturally" taken for each unit under treatment status A = 0. It is thus given by ψ 0 K ,1 -ψ 0 K+1 . The first row of </p><formula xml:id="formula_67">NDE eif 2 = θeif 2 0 K ,1 -θeif 2 0 K+1 . (<label>16</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_68">)</formula><p>If we treat M K = (M 1 , . . . M K ) as a whole, ψ 0 K ,1 -ψ 0 K+1 coincides with the NDE defined in the single mediator setting. In fact, NDE eif 2 is akin to the semiparametric estimator of the NDE given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Zheng and van der Laan (2012)</ref>. By contrast, if we use θeif 1 a instead of θeif 2 a in equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_67">16</ref>), we obtain Tchetgen Tchetgen and Shpitser's (2012) estimator of the NDE.</p><p>Setting a 1 = . . . a K+1 = 0 in equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_48">14</ref>), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">θeif 2 0 K+1 = P n I(A = 0) π0 (0|X) Y -μ0 (X) + μ0 (X) ,<label>(17)</label></formula><p>Baseline where</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">NDE: A M 2 M 1 Y NIE M 1 : A M 2 M 1 Y TIE M 1 : A M 2 M 1 Y nPSE M 2 : A M 2 M 1 Y cPSE M 2 : A M 2 M 1 Y Comparison A M 2 M 1 Y A M 2 M 1 Y A M 2 M 1 Y A M 2 M 1 Y A M 2 M 1 Y</formula><formula xml:id="formula_71">µ 0 (X) = E[Y |X, A = 0]. Not surprisingly, θeif 2 0 K+1</formula><p>is the standard doubly robust estimator for E[Y (0)], which is consistent if either π0 (0|X) or μ0 (X) is consistent. Similarly, by setting a 1 = . . . a K = 0 and a K+1 = 1 in equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_48">14</ref>), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">θeif 2 0 K ,1 = P n I(A = 1) π0 (0|X) πK (0|X, M K ) πK (1|X, M K ) Y -μ K (X, M K ) + I(A = 0) π0 (0|X) μK (X, M K )-μ 0,K (X) +μ 0,K (X) .</formula><p>In contrast to the general case where a K is unconstrained, θeif 2 0 K ,1 involves estimating only four nuisance functions: π 0 (a|x), π K (a|x, m K ), µ 0,K (x), and µ K (x, m K ), where</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">µ K (x, m K ) = E[Y |x, A = 1, m K ] and µ 0,K (x) = E[µ K (X, M K )|x, A = 0]</formula><p>. Hence µ 0,K (x) can be estimated by fitting a model for the conditional mean of μK (X, M K ) given (X, A) and then setting A = 0 for all units. It follows from Theorem 3 that θeif 2 0 K ,1 is triply robust in that it is consistent if one of the following three conditions holds: (a) π0 and πK are consistent; (b) π0 and μK are consistent; and (c) μ0,K and μK are consistent. In the meantime, we know that θeif 2 0 K+1</p><p>is consistent if either π0 or μ0 is consistent. By taking the intersection of the multiple robustness conditions for θeif 2 0 K ,1 and θeif 2 0 K+1</p><p>, we deduce that NDE eif 2 is also triply robust, as detailed in Corollary 1.</p><p>Corollary 1. Suppose all assumptions required for Theorem 4 hold. When the nuisance functions are estimated via parametric models, NDE eif 2 is CAN provided that one of the following three sets of nuisance functions is correctly specified and its parameter estimates are √ n-</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">consistent: {π 0 , π K }, {π 0 , µ K }, {µ 0 , µ 0,K , µ K }. NDE eif 2 is semiparametric efficient if all of</formula><p>the above nuisance functions are correctly specified and their parameter estimates √ n-consistent.</p><p>When the nuisance functions are estimated via data-adaptive methods and cross-fitting, NDE eif 2 is CAN and semiparametric efficient if all of the nuisance functions are consistently estimated and</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">r n (π 0 )r n (μ 0,K ) + r n (π K )r n (μ K ) + r n (π 0 )r n (μ 0 ) = o(n -1/2 ).</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Natural and Total Indirect Effects for M 1</head><p>In Section 2.1, we noted that ψ 100 -ψ 000 and ψ 111 -ψ 011 correspond to the NIE and TIE for the first mediator M 1 (illustrated in the second and third rows of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>). This correspondence extends naturally to the case of K mediators, where the NIE and TIE for M 1 are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">NIE M 1 = ψ 1,0 2 -ψ 0 K+1 , TIE M 1 = ψ 1 K+1 -ψ 0,1 2 ,</formula><p>where 0 2 = (0, . . . 0) and 1 2 = (1, . . . 1) are vectors of length K representing the fact that a 2 = . . . = a K+1 = 0 in NIE M 1 and a 2 = . . . = a K+1 = 1 in TIE M 1 . Since TIE M 1 can be obtained by switching the 0s and 1s in NIE M 1 and then flipping the sign, we focus on NIE M 1 below, noting that analogous results hold for TIE M 1 .</p><p>A semiparametric efficient estimator of NIE M 1 can be constructed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">NIE eif 2 M 1 = θeif 2 1,0 2 -θeif 2 0 K+1 . As shown previously, θeif 2 0 K+1</formula><p>is given by the doubly robust estimator (17). Setting a 1 = 1 and a 2 = . . . a K+1 = 0 in equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_48">14</ref>), we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">θeif 2 1,0 2 =P n I(A = 0) π0 (1|X) π1 (1|X, M 1 ) π1 (0|X, M 1 ) Y -μ1 (X, M 1 ) + I(A = 1) π0 (1|X) μ1 (X, M 1 ) -μ0,1 (X) + μ0,1 (X) .</formula><p>Like θeif 2 0 K ,1 , θeif 2 1,0 2 also involves estimating four nuisance functions: π 0 (a|x), π 1 (a|x, m 1 ), µ 0,1 (x), and </p><formula xml:id="formula_79">µ 1 (x, m 1 ), where µ 1 (x, m 1 ) = E[Y |x, A = 0, m 1 ] and µ 0,1 (x) = E[µ 1 (X, M 1 )|x, A = 1]. It</formula><formula xml:id="formula_80">(π 0 )r n (μ 0,1 ) + r n (π 1 )r n (μ 1 ) + r n (π 0 )r n (μ 0 ) = o(n -1/2 ).</formula><p>4.3 Natural Path-Specific Effects (nPSE) for M k (k ≥ 2)</p><p>In the same spirit of the NIE for M 1 , the natural path-specific effect (nPSE; <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Daniel et al. 2015)</ref> for</p><formula xml:id="formula_81">mediator M k (k ≥ 2) is defined as nPSE M k = ψ 0 k-1 ,1,0 k+1 -ψ 0 K+1 .</formula><p>It can be interpreted as the effect of activating the path A → M k Y while all other causal paths are "switched off," as shown in the fourth row of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>. A semiparametric efficient estimator of nPSE M k can be constructed as nPSE</p><formula xml:id="formula_82">eif 2 M k = θeif 2 0 k-1 ,1,0 k+1 -θeif 2 0 K+1</formula><p>.</p><p>If, instead, we use θeif 1 a in the above equation, the resulting estimator nPSE is given by the doubly robust estimator (17). Setting a 1 = . . . a k-1 = a k+1 = . . . a K+1 = 0 and a k = 1 in equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_48">14</ref>), we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_83">θeif 2 0 k-1 ,1,0 k+1 =P n I(A = 0) π0 (0|X) πk-1 (0|X, M k-1 ) πk-1 (1|X, M k-1 ) πk (1|X, M k ) πk (0|X, M k ) Y -μk (X, M k ) . + I(A = 1) π0 (0|X) πk-1 (0|X, M k-1 ) πk-1 (1|X, M k-1 ) μk (X, M k ) -μk-1,k (X, M k-1 ) + I(A = 0) π0 (0|X) μk-1,k (X, M k-1 ) -μ0,k-1,k (X) + μ0,k-1,k (X) .</formula><p>We can see that θeif 2</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">0 k-1 ,1,0 k+1</formula><p>involves estimating six nuisance functions: π 0 (a|x), π k-1 (a|x, m k-1 ),</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">π k (a|x, m k ), µ 0,k-1,k (x), µ k-1,k (x, m k-1 ), and µ k (x, m k ), where µ k (X, M k ) = E[Y |X, A = 0, M k ], µ k-1,k (X, M k-1 ) = E[µ k (X, M k )|X, A = 1, M k-1 ], and µ 0,k-1,k (X) = E[µ k-1,k (X, M k-1 )|X, A = 0]. Hence µ k-1,k<label>(x</label></formula><p>) can be estimated by fitting a model for the conditional mean of μk (X, M k )</p><p>given (X, A, M k-1 ) and then setting A = 1 for all units, and µ 0,k-1,k (x) can be estimated by fitting a model for the conditional mean of μk-1,k (X, M k-1 ) given (X, A) and then setting A = 0 for all units. It follows from Theorem 3 that θeif 2 M k is CAN provided that one of the following four sets of nuisance functions is correctly specified and its parameter estimates are √ n-consistent: </p><formula xml:id="formula_86">0 k-1 ,1,0 k+1</formula><formula xml:id="formula_87">{π 0 , π k-1 , π k }, {π 0 , π k-1 , µ k }, {π 0 , µ k-1,k , µ k }, {µ 0 , µ 0,k-1,k , µ k-1,k , µ k }. nPSE eif 2 M k is semiparamet- ric efficient if</formula><formula xml:id="formula_88">(π 0 )r n (μ 0,k-1,k ) + r n (π k-1 )r n (μ k-1,k ) + r n (π k )r n (μ k ) + r n (π 0 )r n (μ 0 ) = o(n -1/2 ). 4.4 Cumulative Path-Specific Effects (cPSE) for M k (k ≥ 2)</formula><p>The NDE, NIE, and nPSE are all defined as the effect of activating one causal path while keeping all other causal paths "switched off." By contrast, in equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_23">3</ref>), the ATE is decomposed into K + 1 components, each of which reflects the cumulative contribution of a specific mediator to the ATE. Specifically, the component ψ 0 K ,1 -ψ 0 K+1 equals the NDE, the component ψ 1 1 -ψ 0,1 2 equals TIE M 1 , and the component ψ 0 k-1 ,1 k -ψ 0 k ,1 k+1 gauges the additional contribution of the causal path</p><formula xml:id="formula_89">A → M k Y after the causal paths A → M k+1 Y, . . . A → M K Y, A → Y are "switched</formula><p>on." Such a decomposition will be useful in applications where the investigator aims to partition the ATE into its path-specific components.</p><p>We define the cumulative path-specific effect (cPSE) for mediator M k (k ≥ 2) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_90">cPSE M k = ψ 0 k-1 ,1 k -ψ 0 k ,1 k+1 .</formula><p>The last row of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref> gives the baseline and comparison interventions associated with cPSE M 2 in the case of K = 2. A semiparametric efficient estimator for cPSE M k can be constructed as cPSE</p><formula xml:id="formula_91">eif 2 M k = θeif 2 0 k-1 ,1 k -θeif 2 0 k ,1 k+1</formula><p>.</p><p>Setting a 1 = . . . a k = 0 and a k+1 = . . . = a K+1 = 1 in equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_48">14</ref>), we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_92">θeif 2 0 k ,1 k+1 = P n I(A = 1) π0 (0|X) πk (0|X, M k ) πk (1|X, M k ) Y -μk (X, M k ) + I(A = 0) π0 (0|X) μk (X, M k ) -μ0,k (X) + μ0,k (X) ,<label>(18)</label></formula><p>where M k involves fitting seven working models -for π 0 (a|x), π k-1 (a|x, m k-1 ), </p><formula xml:id="formula_93">µ k (X, M k ) = E[Y |X, A = 1, M k ] and µ 0,k (X) = E[µ k (X, M k )|X, A = 0]. It</formula><formula xml:id="formula_94">π k (a|x, m k ), µ k-1 (x, m k-1 ), µ 0,k-1 (x), µ k (x, m k ),</formula><formula xml:id="formula_95">, π k-1 , π k };{π 0 , π k-1 , µ k };{π 0 , µ k-1 , π k };{π 0 , µ k-1 , µ k };{µ 0,k-1 , µ 0,k , µ k-1 , µ k }. cPSE eif 2</formula><p>M k is semiparametric efficient if all of the above nuisance functions are correctly specified and their parameter estimates √ n-consistent. When the nuisance functions are estimated via data-adaptive methods and cross-fitting, cPSE eif 2</p><p>M k is semiparametric efficient if all of the nuisance functions are consistently estimated and r n (π 0 )r n (μ 0,k-1 ) + r n (π 0 )r n (μ 0,k ) + r n (π k-1 )r n (μ k-1 ) +</p><formula xml:id="formula_96">r n (π k )r n (μ k ) = o(n -1/2 ).</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">A Simulation Study</head><p>In this section, we conduct a simulation study to demonstrate the robustness of various estimators under different forms of model misspecification. Specifically, we consider a binary treatment A, a continuous outcome Y , two causally ordered mediators M 1 and M 2 , and four pretreatment covariates X 1 , X 2 , X 3 , X 4 generated from the following model:</p><formula xml:id="formula_97">(U 1 , U 2 , U 3 , U XY ) ∼ N (0, I 4 ), X j ∼ N ((U 1 , U 2 , U 3 , U XY )β X j , 1), j = 1, 2, 3, 4, A ∼ Bernoulli logit -1 [(1, X 1 , X 2 , X 3 , X 4 )β A ] , M 1 ∼ N (1, X 1 , X 2 , X 3 , X 4 , A)β M 1 , 1 , M 2 ∼ N (1, X 1 , X 2 , X 3 , X 4 , A, M 1 )β M 2 , 1 , Y ∼ N (1, U XY , X 1 , X 2 , X 3 , X 4 , A, M 1 , M 2 )β Y , 1 . The coefficients β X j (1≤ j ≤ 4), β A , β M 1 , β M 2 , β Y are produced from a set of uniform distributions</formula><p>(see Supplementary Material F for more details). Given the coefficients, we generate 1,000 Monte Carlo samples of size 2,000. Note that in the above model, the unobserved variable U XY confounds the X-Y relationship but does not pose an identification threat for ψ a and the associated PSEs (i.e., Assumption 2 still holds).</p><p>Without loss of generality, we focus on the estimand cPSE M 2 , which we estimate by θ011 -θ001 .</p><p>To highlight the general results stated in Theorem 3, we use only estimators for the generic θ a (i.e., those described in Section 3). First, we consider the weighting estimator θw-a a , the regression-imputation estimator θri a , and the hybrid estimators θri-w-w a and θri-ri-w a , where the mediator density ratio involved in θri-w-w a is estimated via the corresponding odds ratio of the treatment variable.</p><p>We in that the outcome models µ 2 (x, m 1 , m 2 ), µ 1 (x, m 1 ), and µ 0 (x) are fitted using a set of weighted GLMs such that in equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_63">15</ref>), all terms inside P n [•] but μ0 (X) have a zero sample mean, yielding a regression-imputation estimator that may perform better in finite samples.</p><p>All of the above estimators are constructed using estimates of six nuisance functions: π 0 (a|x), , we generate a set of "false covariates" Z = X 1 , e X 2 /2 , (X 3 /X 1 ) 1/3 , X 4 /(e X 1 /2 + 1) and use them to fit a misspecified GLM for each of the nuisance functions (with only the main effects of Z 1 , Z 2 , Z 3 , Z 4 ).</p><formula xml:id="formula_98">π 1 (a|x, m 1 ), π 2 (a|x, m 1 , m 2 ), µ 0 (x), µ 1 (x,</formula><p>We evaluate each of the parametric estimators under five different cases: or linear models that depend on X = (Z 1 , 2 log(Z 2 ), Z 1 Z 3 3 , (1+e Z 1 /2 )Z 4 ). We obtain nonparametric estimates of cPSE M 2 using both five-fold cross-fitting and no cross-fitting.</p><p>Results from the simulation study are shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">3</ref>, where each panel corresponds to an estimator, and the y axis is recentered at the true value of cPSE M 2 . The shaded box plots highlight cases under which a given estimator should be consistent, and the box plots with a lighter shade  .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">An Empirical Application</head><p>In this section, we illustrate semiparametric estimation of PSEs by analyzing the causal pathways through which higher education affects political participation. Prior research suggests that college attendance has a substantial positive effect on political participation in the United States (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Dee 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Milligan et al. 2004</ref>). Yet, the mechanisms underlying this causal link remain unclear.</p><p>The effect of college on political participation may operate through the development of civic and political interest (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Hillygus 2005)</ref>, through an increase in economic status (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Kingston et al. 2003)</ref>, or through other pathways such as social and occupational networks (e.g., Rolfe 2012). To examine these direct and indirect effects, we consider a causal structure akin to the top panel of In this model, economic status is allowed to affect civic and political interest but not vice versa, which we consider to be a reasonable approximation to reality. Nonetheless, the conditional independence assumption (Assumption 2) is still strong in this context, as it rules out unobserved confounding for any of the pairwise relationships between college attendance, economic status, civic and political interest, and political participation. Thus, the following analyses should be viewed as an illustration of the proposed methodology rather than a definitive assessment of the PSEs of interest.</p><p>We does not affect M 1 essential for identifying the direct and path-specific effects.</p><p>To minimize potential bias due to unobserved confounding, we include a rich set of pre-college individual and contextual characteristics in the vector of pretreatment covariates X. They include gender, race, ethnicity, age at 1997, parental education, parental income, parental assets, presence of a father figure, co-residence with both biological parents, percentile score on the Armed Services Vocational Aptitude Battery (ASVAB), high school GPA, an index of substance use (ranging from 0 to 3), an index of delinquency (ranging from 0 to 10), whether the respondent had any children by age 18, college expectation among the respondent's peers, and a number of school-level characteristics. Descriptive statistics on these pre-college characteristics as well as the mediators and the outcome are given in Supplementary Material G. Some components of X, M 1 , and M 2 contain a small fraction of missing values. They are imputed via a random-forest-based multiple imputation procedure (with ten imputed data sets). The standard errors of our parameter estimates are adjusted using <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Rubin's (1987)</ref> method.</p><p>Under Assumptions 1-3 given in Section 2.1, a set of PSEs reflecting the causal paths A → Y ,</p><p>A → M 1 Y , and A → M 2 → Y are identified. For illustrative purposes, we focus on the cumulative PSEs (cPSEs) defined in Section 4.4:</p><formula xml:id="formula_99">ATE = ψ 001 -ψ 000 A→Y + ψ 011 -ψ 001 A→M 2 →Y + ψ 111 -ψ 011 A→M 1 Y . (<label>19</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_100">)</formula><p>Here, the first component is the NDE of college attendance, and the second and third components reflect the amounts of treatment effect that are additionally mediated by civic/political interest and economic status, respectively. Since M 2 is multivariate, it would be difficult to model its conditional distributions directly. We thus estimate the PSEs using the estimator θeif 2 a 1 ,a 2 ,a . Each of the nuisance functions is estimated using a super learner composed with Lasso and random forest.</p><p>For computational reasons, the feature matrix supplied to the super learner consists of only firstorder terms of the corresponding variables. As in our simulation study, we implement two versions of this EIF-based estimator, one based on the original estimating equation ( θnp,eif 2 a ), and one based ). Five-fold cross-fitting is used to obtain the final estimates.</p><p>The results are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_11">1</ref>. We can see that the two estimators yield similar estimates of the total and path-specific effects. By θnp,eif 2 a , for example, the estimated total effect of college attendance on voting is 0.152, meaning that, on average, college attendance increases the likelihood of voting in 2010 by about 15 percentage points. The estimated PSE via M 2 is 0.042, suggesting that a small fraction of the college effect operates through the development of civic and political interest.</p><p>By contrast, the estimated PSE via economic status is substantively negligible and statistically insignificant. A large portion of the college effect appears to be "direct," i.e., operating neither through increased economic status nor through increased civic and political interest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Concluding Remarks</head><p>By considering the general case of K(≥ 1) causally ordered mediators, this paper offers several new insights into the identification and estimation of PSEs. First, under the assumptions associated with Pearl's NPSEM with mutually independent errors, we have defined a set of PSEs as contrasts between the expectations of 2 K+1 potential outcomes, which are identified via what we call the generalized mediation functional (GMF). Second, building on its efficient influence function, we have developed two K + 2-robust and semiparametric efficient estimators for the GMF. By virtue of their multiple robustness, these estimators are well suited to the use of data-adaptive methods for estimating their nuisance functions. For such cases, we have established the rate conditions required of the nuisance functions for consistency and semiparametric efficiency.</p><p>As we have seen, our proposed methodology is general in that the GMF encompasses a variety of causal estimands such as the NDE, NIE/TIE, nPSE, cPSE. Nonetheless, it does not accommodate PSEs that are not identified under Pearl's NPSEM, some of which may be scientifically important.</p><p>For example, social and biomedical scientists are often interested in testing hypotheses about "serial mediation," i.e., the degree to which the effect of a treatment operates through multiple mediators sequentially, such as that reflected in the causal path A → M 1 → M 2 → Y (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Jones et al. 2015)</ref>.</p><p>Given that the corresponding PSEs are not nonparametrically identified under Pearl's NPSEM, previous research has proposed strategies that involve either additional assumptions <ref type="bibr">(Albert and Nelson 2011)</ref> or alternative estimands <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Lin and VanderWeele 2017)</ref>. We consider semiparametric estimation and inference for these alternative approaches a promising direction for future research.</p><formula xml:id="formula_101">= x m K E[Y (a K+1 , m K )|X = x, A = a K+1 ] K k=1 dP M k (a k ,m k-1 )|X (m k |x) dP X (x) = x m K E[Y (a K+1 , m K )|x, a K+1 , M K = m K ] K k=1 dP M k (a k ,m k-1 )|X,A,M k-1 (m k |x, a k , m k-1 ) dP X (x) = x m K E[Y |x, a K+1 , m K ] K k=1 dP M k |X,A,M k-1 (m k |x, a k , m k-1 ) dP X (x).</formula><p>B Hybrid Estimators of θ a 1 ,a 2 ,a</p><p>For notational brevity, let us use the following shorthands:</p><formula xml:id="formula_102">λ j 0 (A|X) ∆ = I(A = a j ) p(a j |X) λ j 1 (M 1 |X) ∆ = p(M 1 |X, a 1 ) p(M 1 |X, a j ) λ j 2 (M 2 |X, M 1 ) ∆ = p(M 2 |X, a 2 , M 1 ) p(M 2 |X, a j , M 1 ) , In addition, define λ 0 (A|X) = I(A = a)/p(a|X), λ 1 (M 1 |X) = p(M 1 |X, a 1 )/p(M 1 |X, a) and λ 2 (M 2 |X, M 1 ) = p(M 2 |X, a 2 , M 1 )/p(M 2 |X, a, M 1 ).</formula><p>With the above notation, the iterated conditional means µ 1 (X, M 1 ), µ 0 (X), and θ a 1 ,a 2 ,a can each be written in several different forms:</p><formula xml:id="formula_103">µ 1 (X, M 1 ) =    E[µ 2 (X, M 1 , M 2 )|X, a 2 , M 1 ] E[λ 2 (M 2 |X, M 1 )Y |X, a, M 1 ] µ 0 (X) =                E[µ 1 (X, M 1 )|X, a 1 ] =    E E[µ 2 (X, M 1 , M 2 )|X, a 2 , M 1 ]|X, a 1 E E[λ 2 (M 2 |X, M 1 )Y |X, a, M 1 ]|X, a 1 E[λ 2 1 (M 1 |X)µ 2 (X, M 1 , M 2 )|X, a 2 ] E[λ 1 (M 1 |X)λ 2 (X, M 1 , M 2 )Y |X, a] θ a 1 ,a 2 ,a =                                          E[µ 0 (X)] =                  E E E[µ 2 (X, M 1 , M 2 )|X, a 2 , M 1 ]|X, a 1 (RI-RI-RI) E E E[λ 2 (M 2 |X, M 1 )Y |X, a, M 1 ]|X, a 1 (W-RI-RI) E E[λ 2 1 (M 1 |X)µ 2 (X, M 1 , M 2 )|X, a 2 ] (RI-W-RI) E E[λ 1 (M 1 |X)λ 2 (X, M 1 , M 2 )Y |X, a] (W-W-RI) E[λ 1 0 (A|X)µ 1 (X, M 1 )] =    E λ 1 0 (A|X)E[µ 2 (X, M 1 , M 2 )|X, a 2 , M 1 ] (RI-RI-W) E λ 1 0 (A|X)E[λ 2 (M 2 |X, M 1 )Y |X, a, M 1 ] (W-RI-W) E[λ 2 0 (A|X)λ 2 1 (M 1 |X)µ 2 (X, M 1 , M 2 )] (RI-W-W) E[λ 0 (A|X)λ 1 (M 1 |X)λ 2 (M 2 |X, M 1 )Y ] (W-W-W)</formula><p>The first set of equations suggest two different ways of estimating µ 1 (x, m 1 ): (a) fit a model for the conditional mean of μ2 (X, M 1 , M 2 ) given X, A, M 1 and then set A = a 2 for all units; (b) fit a model for the conditional mean of λ2 (M 2 |X, M 1 )Y given X, A, and M 1 and then set A = a for all units. Similarly, the second set of equations suggest four different ways of estimating µ 0 (x), and the last set of equations point to eight different ways of estimating θ a 1 ,a 2 ,a . Each of these eight estimators corresponds to a unique combination of regression-imputation and weighting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C Proof of Theorem 2</head><p>To show that equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_40">11</ref>) is the EIF of θ a in P np , it suffices to show</p><formula xml:id="formula_104">∂θ a (t) ∂t t=0 = E[ϕ a (O)S 0 (O)],<label>(24)</label></formula><p>where S 0 (O) is the score function for any one-dimensional submodel P t (O) evaluated at t = 0. We first note that S t (O) can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_105">S t (O) = S t (X) + S t (A|X) + K k=1 S t (M k |X, A, M k-1 ) + S t (Y |X, A, M K )</formula><p>, where S t (u|v) = ∂ log p t (u|v)/∂t and p t (u|v) is the conditional probability density/mass function of U given V . Using equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_20">2</ref>) and the product rule, the left-hand side of equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_104">24</ref>) can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_106">∂θ a (t) ∂t t=0 = ∂ ydP t (y|x, a K+1 , m K ) K k=1 dP t (m k |x, a k , m k-1 ) dP t (x) ∂t t=0 = yS 0 (x)dP 0 (y|x, a K+1 , m K ) K k=1 dP 0 (m k |x, a k , m k-1 ) dP 0 (x) =:φ 0 + K k=1 yS 0 (m k |x, a k , m k-1 )dP 0 (y|x, a K+1 , m K ) K k=1 dP 0 (m k |x, a k , m k-1 ) dP 0 (x) =:φ k + yS 0 (y|x, a K+1 , m K )dP 0 (y|x, a K+1 , m K ) K k=1 dP 0 (m k |x, a k , m k-1 ) dP 0 (x) =:φ K+1 = K+1 k=0 φ k</formula><p>where the second equality follows from the fact that ∂dP t (u|v)/∂t = S t (u|v)dP t (u|v). Below, we</p><formula xml:id="formula_107">verify that φ k = E[ϕ k (O)S 0 (O)] for all k ∈ {0, . . . K + 1}, where ϕ k (O) is defined in Theorem 2.</formula><p>First,</p><formula xml:id="formula_108">E[ϕ 0 (O)S 0 (O)] =E[ µ 0 (X) -θ a S 0 (O)] =E[µ 0 (X)S 0 (O)] =E µ 0 (X) S 0 (X) + S 0 (A|X) + K k=1 S 0 (M k |X, A, M k-1 ) + S 0 (Y |X, A, M K ) =E µ 0 (X)S 0 (X) + E µ 0 (X) E S 0 (A|X)|X =0 + K k=1 E µ 0 (X) E S 0 (M k |X, A, M k-1 )|X, A, M k-1 =0 + E µ 0 (X) E S 0 (Y |X, A, M K )|X, A, M K =0 = µ 0 (x)S 0 (x)dP 0 (x) = yS 0 (x)dP 0 (y|x, a K+1 , m K ) K k=1 dP 0 (m k |x, a k , m k-1 ) dP 0 (x) =φ 0 . Second, for k ∈ [K], E[ϕ k (O)S 0 (O)] =E ϕ k (O) S 0 (X) + S 0 (A|X) + K j=1 S 0 (M j |X, A, M j-1 ) + S 0 (Y |X, A, M K ) =E E ϕ k (O) S 0 (X) + S 0 (A|X) + k-1 j=1 S 0 (M j |X, A, M j-1 ) |X, A, M k-1 + E ϕ k (O)S (M k |X, A, M k-1 ) + K j=k+1 E ϕ k (O) E S 0 (M j |X, A, M j-1 )|X, A, M j-1 =0 + E ϕ k (O) E S 0 (Y |X, A, M K )|X, A, M K =0 =E S 0 (X) + S 0 (A|X) + k-1 j=1 S 0 (M j |X, A, M j-1 ) E ϕ k (O)|X, A, M k-1 =0 + E ϕ k (O)S 0 (M k |X, A, M k-1 ) =E ϕ k (O)S 0 (M k |X, A, M k-1 ) =E E I(A = a k ) p(a k |X) k-1 j=1 p(M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) p(M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) µ k (X, M k ) -µ k-1 (X, M k-1 ) S 0 (M k |X, A, M k-1 ) X, A, M k-1 =E I(A = a k ) p(a k |X) k-1 j=1 p(M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) p(M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) µ k (X, M k )S 0 (M k |X, A, M k-1 ) =E X E k-1 j=1 p(M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) p(M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) µ k (X, M k )S 0 (M k |X, A, M k-1 ) |X, A = a k = S 0 (m k |x, a k , m k-1 ) y m K ydP 0 (y|x, a K+1 , m K ) K j=k+1</formula><p>dP 0 (m j |x, a j , m j-1 )</p><formula xml:id="formula_109">•dP 0 (m k |x, a k , m k-1 ) k-1 j=1 p(m j |x, a j , m j-1 ) p(m j |x, a k , m j-1 ) k-1 j=1 dP 0 (m j |x, a k , m j-1 ) dP 0 (x) = yS 0 (m k |x, a k , m k-1 )dP 0 (y|x, a K+1 , m K ) K j=1 dP 0 (m j |x, a j , m j-1 ) dP 0 (x) =φ k ,</formula><p>where the fourth equality is due to the fact that</p><formula xml:id="formula_110">E ϕ k (O)|X, A, M k-1 =E I(A = a k ) p(a k |X) k-1 j=1 p(M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) p(M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) µ k (X, M k ) -µ k-1 (X, M k-1 ) |X, A, M k-1 =E k-1 j=1 p(M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) p(M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) µ k (X, M k ) -µ k-1 (X, M k-1 ) |X, A = a k , M k-1 = k-1 j=1 p(M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) p(M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) E µ k (X, M k ) -µ k-1 (X, M k-1 )|X, A = a k , M k-1 =0 =0.</formula><p>Finally,</p><formula xml:id="formula_111">E[ϕ K+1 (O)S 0 (O)] =E ϕ K+1 (O) S 0 (X) + S 0 (A|X) + K j=1 S 0 (M j |X, A, M j-1 ) + S 0 (Y |X, A, M K ) =E E ϕ K+1 (O) S 0 (X) + S 0 (A|X) + K j=1 S 0 (M j |X, A, M j-1 ) |X, A, M K + E ϕ K+1 (O)S 0 (Y |X, A, M K ) =E S 0 (X) + S 0 (A|X) + K j=1 S 0 (M j |X, A, M j-1 ) E ϕ K+1 (O)|X, A, M K =0 + E ϕ K+1 (O)S 0 (Y |X, A, M K ) =E ϕ K+1 (O)S 0 (Y |X, A, M K ) =E E I(A = a K+1 ) p(a K+1 |X) K j=1 p(M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) p(M j |X, a K+1 , M j-1 ) Y -µ K (X, M K ) S 0 (Y |X, A, M K ) X, A, M K =E E I(A = a K+1 ) p(a K+1 |X) K j=1 p(M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) p(M j |X, a K+1 , M j-1 ) Y S 0 (Y |X, A, M K ) X, A, M K =E E I(A = a K+1 ) p(a K+1 |X) K j=1 p(M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) p(M j |X, a K+1 , M j-1 ) Y S 0 (Y |X, A, M K ) X, A =E X E K j=1 p(M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) p(M j |X, a K+1 , M j-1 ) Y S 0 (Y |X, A, M K ) X, A = a K+1 = yS 0 (y|x, a K+1 , m K )dP 0 (y|x, a K+1 , m K ) K j=1 p(m j |x, a j , m j-1 ) p(m j |x, a K+1 , m j-1 ) K j=1 dP 0 (m j |x, a K+1 , m j-1 ) dP 0 (x) = yS 0 (y|x, a K+1 , m K )dP 0 (y|x, a K+1 , m K ) K j=1 dP 0 (m j |x, a j , m j-1 ) dP 0 (x) =φ K+1 ,</formula><p>where the third equality is due to the fact that Hence it suffices to show E[m 1 (O; η * 1 )] = θ a whenever all but one elements in η * 1 equal the truth. Consistency follows from the law of large numbers. By treating θeif 1 a = P n [m 1 (O; η1 )] as a two-stage M-estimator, asymptotic normality follows from standard regularity conditions for estimating equations (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Newey and</ref><ref type="bibr">McFadden 1994, p. 2148)</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_112">E ϕ K+1 (O)|X, A, M K =E I(A = a K+1 ) p(a K+1 |X) K j=1 p(M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) p(M j |X, a K+1 , M j-1 ) Y -µ K (X, M K ) |X, A, M K = p(a K+1 |X, M K ) p(a K+1 |X) K j=1 p(M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) p(M j |X, a K+1 , M j-1 ) E Y -µ K (X, M K )|X, A = a K+1 , M K =0 =0. Since φ k = E[ϕ k (O)S 0 (O)] for all k ∈ {0, . . . K + 1},</formula><p>First, if η * 1 = (π * 0 , f 1 , . . . f K , µ K ), the MLE of µ k (0 ≤ k ≤ K -1) will also be consistent. Thus,</p><formula xml:id="formula_113">E[m 1 (O; η * 1 )] =E I(A = a K+1 ) π * 0 (a K+1 |X) K j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a K+1 , M j-1 ) Y -µ K (X, M K ) + K k=1 I(A = a k ) π * 0 (a k |X) k-1 j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) µ k (X, M k ) -µ k-1 (X, M k-1 ) + µ 0 (X) =E π 0 (a K+1 |X, M K ) π * 0 (a K+1 |X) K j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a K+1 , M j-1 ) E Y -µ K (X, M K ) X, A = a K+1 , M K =0 + K k=1 π 0 (a k |X, M k-1 ) π * 0 (a k |X) k-1 j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) E µ k (X, M k ) -µ k-1 (X, M k-1 ) X, A = a k , M k-1 =0 + µ 0 (X) =E[µ 0 (X)] =θ a . Second, if η * 1 = (π 0 , f 1 , . . . f k -1 , f * k , f k +1 , . . . f K , µ K )</formula><p>, the MLE of µ k for any k ≥ k will also be consistent. Thus,</p><formula xml:id="formula_114">E[m 1 (O; η * 1 )] =E I(A = a K+1 ) π 0 (a K+1 |X) K j=1 f * j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f * j (M j |X, a K+1 , M j-1 ) Y -µ K (X, M K ) + K k=k +1 I(A = a k ) π 0 (a k |X) k-1 j=1 f * j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f * j (M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) µ k (X, M k ) -µ k-1 (X, M k-1 ) + I(A = a k ) π 0 (a k |X) k -1 j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) µ k (X, M k ) -µ * k -1 (X, M k -1 ) + k -1 k=1 I(A = a k ) π 0 (a k |X) k-1 j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) µ * k (X, M k ) -µ * k-1 (X, M k-1 ) + µ * 0 (X) =E π 0 (a K+1 |X, M K ) π 0 (a K+1 |X) K j=1 f * j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f * j (M j |X, a K+1 , M j-1 ) E Y -µ K (X, M K ) X, A = a K+1 , M K =0 + K k=k +1 π 0 (a k |X, M k-1 ) π 0 (a k |X) k-1 j=1 f * j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f * j (M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) E µ k (X, M k ) -µ k-1 (X, M k-1 ) X, A = a k , M k-1 =0 + I(A = a k ) π 0 (a k |X) k -1 j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) µ k (X, M k ) + k -1 k=1 µ * k (X, M k )E I(A = a k ) π 0 (a k |X) k-1 j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) - I(A = a k+1 ) π 0 (a k+1 |X) k j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a k+1 , M j-1 ) |X, M k + µ * 0 (X) E 1 - I(A = a 1 ) π 0 (a 1 |X) |X =0 =E I(A = a k ) π 0 (a k |X) k -1 j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) µ k (X, M k ) + E k -1 k=1 µ * k (X, M k ) π k (a k |X, M k ) π 0 (a k |X) k-1 j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) - π k (a k+1 |X, M k ) π 0 (a k+1 |X) k j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a k+1 , M j-1 ) = E I(A = a k ) π 0 (a k |X) k -1 j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) µ k (X, M k ) =θ a + E k -1 k=1 µ * k (X, M k ) k j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j-1 (a j |X, M j-1 ) - k j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j-1 (a j |X, M j-1 ) =0 =θ a ,</formula><p>where the penultimate equality is due to the fact that</p><formula xml:id="formula_115">π k (a k |X, M k ) π 0 (a k |X) k-1 j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) = π k (a k |X, M k ) π 0 (a k |X) k-1 j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a k |X, M j ) • π j-1 (a k |X, M j-1 ) π j-1 (a j |X, M j-1 ) = π k (a k |X, M k ) π 0 (a k |X) k-1 j=1 π j-1 (a k |X, M j-1 ) π j (a k |X, M j ) k-1 j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j-1 (a j |X, M j-1 ) = π k (a k |X, M k ) π k-1 (a k |X, M k-1 ) k-1 j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j-1 (a j |X, M j-1 ) = k j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j-1 (a j |X, M j-1 ) and that π k (a k+1 |X, M k ) π 0 (a k+1 |X) k j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a k+1 , M j-1 ) = π k (a k+1 |X, M k ) π 0 (a k+1 |X) k j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a k+1 |X, M j ) • π j-1 (a k+1 |X, M j-1 ) π j-1 (a j |X, M j-1 ) = π k (a k+1 |X, M k ) π 0 (a k+1 |X) k j=1 π j-1 (a k+1 |X, M j-1 ) π j (a k+1 |X, M j ) k j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j-1 (a j |X, M j-1 ) = k j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j-1 (a j |X, M j-1 )</formula><p>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_116">Finally, if η * 1 = (π 0 , f 1 , . . . f K , µ * K ), we have E[m 1 (O; η * 1 )] =E I(A = a K+1 ) π 0 (a K+1 |X) K j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a K+1 , M j-1 ) Y -µ * K (X, M K ) + K k=1 I(A = a k ) π 0 (a k |X) k j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) µ * k (X, M k ) -µ * k-1 (X, M k-1 ) + µ * 0 (X) =E I(A = a K+1 ) π 0 (a K+1 |X) K j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a K+1 , M j-1 ) Y + K k=1 µ * k (X, M k ) E I(A = a k ) π 0 (a k |X) k-1 j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a k , M j-1 ) - I(A = a k+1 ) π 0 (a k+1 |X) k j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a k+1 , M j-1 )</formula><p>|X, M k =0 (same as the previous case) Hence it suffices to show E</p><formula xml:id="formula_117">+ µ * 0 (X) E 1 - I(A = a 1 ) π 0 (a 1 |X) ||X =0 =E I(A = a K+1 ) π 0 (a K+1 |X) K j=1 f j (M j |X, a j , M j-1 ) f j (M j |X, a K+1 , M j-1 ) Y =θ a .</formula><formula xml:id="formula_118">[m 2 (O; η * 2 )] = θ a if η * 2 = (π 0 , . . . π k -1 , π * k , . . . π * K , µ * 0 , . . . µ * k -1 , µ k , . . . µ K )</formula><p>for every k ∈ {0, . . . K + 1}.</p><p>First, if k = 0, then all the outcome models are correctly specified, which implies </p><formula xml:id="formula_119">E[m 2 (O; η * 2 )] =E I(A = a K+1 ) π * 0 (a 1 |X) K j=1 π * j (a j |X, M j ) π * j (a j+1 |X, M j ) Y -µ K (X, M K ) + K k=1 I(A = a k ) π * 0 (a 1 |X) k-1 j=1 π * j (a j |X, M j ) π * j (a j+1 |X, M j ) µ k (X, M k ) -µ k-1 (X, M k-1 ) + µ 0 (X) =E I(A = a K+1 ) π * 0 (a 1 |X) K j=1 π * j (a j |X, M j ) π * j (a j+1 |X, M j ) E Y -µ K (X, M K ) X, A = a K+1 , M K =0 + K k=1 I(A = a k ) π * 0 (a 1 |X) k-1 j=1 π * j (a j |X, M j ) π * j (a j+1 |X, M j ) E µ k (X, M k ) -µ k-1 (X, M k-1 ) X, A = a k , M k-1 =0 + µ 0 (X) =E[µ 0 (X)] =θ a . Second, if k ∈ {1, . . . K -1}, we have E[m 2 (O; η * 2 )] =E I(A = a K+1 ) π * 0 (a 1 |X) K j=1 π * j (a j |X, M j ) π * j (a j+1 |X, M j ) Y -µ K (X, M K ) + K k=k +1 I(A = a k ) π * 0 (a 1 |X) k-1 j=1 π * j (a j |X, M j ) π * j (a j+1 |X, M j ) µ k (X, M k ) -µ k-1 (X, M k-1 ) + I(A = a k ) π 0 (a 1 |X) k -1 j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a j+1 |X, M j ) µ k (X, M k ) -µ * k -1 (X, M k -1 ) + k -1 k=1 I(A = a k ) π 0 (a 1 |X) k-1 j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a j+1 |X, M j ) µ * k (X, M k ) -µ * k-1 (X, M k-1 ) + µ * 0 (X) =E I(A = a K+1 ) π * 0 (a 1 |X) K j=1 π * j (a j |X, M j ) π * j (a j+1 |X, M j ) E Y -µ K (X, M K ) X, A = a K+1 , M K =0 + K k=k +1 I(A = a k ) π * 0 (a 1 |X) k-1 j=1 π * j (a j |X, M j ) π * j (a j+1 |X, M j ) E µ k (X, M k ) -µ k-1 (X, M k-1 ) X, A = a k , M k-1 =0 + I(A = a k ) π 0 (a 1 |X) k -1 j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a j+1 |X, M j ) µ k (X, M k ) + k -1 k=1 µ * k (X, M k )E I(A = a k ) π 0 (a 1 |X) k-1 j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a j+1 |X, M j ) - I(A = a k+1 ) π 0 (a 1 |X) k j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a j+1 |X, M j ) |X, M k + µ * 0 (X) E 1 - I(A = a 1 ) π 0 (a 1 |X) |X =0 =E I(A = a k ) π 0 (a 1 |X) k -1 j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a j+1 |X, M j ) µ k (X, M k ) + E k -1 k=1 µ * k (X, M k ) π k (a k |X, M k ) π 0 (a 1 |X) k-1 j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a j+1 |X, M j ) - π k (a k+1 |X, M k ) π 0 (a 1 |X) k j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a j+1 |X, M j ) = E I(A = a k ) π 0 (a 1 |X) k -1 j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a j+1 |X, M j ) µ k (X, M k ) =θ a + E k -1 k=1 µ * k (X, M k ) k j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j-1 (a j |X, M j-1 ) - k j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j-1 (a j |X, M j-1 ) =0 =θ a . Finally, if k = K, we have E[m 2 (O; η * 2 )] =E I(A = a K+1 ) π 0 (a 1 |X) K j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a j+1 |X, M j ) Y -µ * K (X, M K ) + K k=1 I(A = a k ) π 0 (a 1 |X) k-1 j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a j+1 |X, M j ) µ * k (X, M k ) -µ * k-1 (X, M k-1 ) + µ * 0 (X) =E I(A = a K+1 ) π 0 (a 1 |X) K j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a j+1 |X, M j ) Y + K k=1 µ * k (X, M k ) E I(A = a k ) π 0 (a 1 |X) k-1 j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a j+1 |X, M j ) - I(A = a k+1 ) π 0 (a 1 |X) k+1 j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a j+1 |X, M j ) |X, M k =0 (same as the previous case) + µ * 0 (X) E 1 - I(A = a 1 ) π 0 (a 1 |X) ||X =0 =E I(A = a K+1 ) π 0 (a 1 |X) K j=1 π j (a j |X, M j ) π j (a j+1 |X, M j ) Y =θ a . D.2</formula><formula xml:id="formula_120">a -θ a =P n [m 2 (O; η2 )] -P [m 2 (O; η 2 )] =(P n -P )m 2 (O; η * 2 ) + P [m 2 (O; η2 ) -m 2 (O; η 2 )] + (P n -P )[m 2 (O; η2 ) -m 2 (O; η * 2 )] (25) =(P n -P ) [m 2 (O; η * 2 ) -θ a ] ∆ =ϕ a (O;η * 2 ) +P [m 2 (O; η2 ) -m 2 (O; η 2 )] + (P n -P )[m 2 (O; η2 ) -m 2 (O; η * 2 )] (26) =P n ϕ a (O; η * 2 ) -P ϕ a (O; η * 2 ) + P [m 2 (O; η2 ) -m 2 (O; η 2 )] ∆ =R 2 (η 2 ) +(P n -P )[m 2 (O; η2 ) -m 2 (O; η * 2 )]<label>(27)</label></formula><p>In equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_120">27</ref>), the last term is an empirical process term that will be o p (n -1/2 ) either when parametric models are used to estimate the nuisance functions or when cross-fitting is used to induce independence between η2 and O <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Chernozhukov et al. 2018)</ref>. Thus it remains to analyze the first three terms:</p><formula xml:id="formula_121">P n ϕ a (O; η * 2 ), P ϕ a (O; η * 2 ), and R 2 (η 2 ) = P [m 2 (O; η2 ) -m 2 (O; η 2 )]. First, from our proofs in Section D.1, we know that when η * 2 = (π 0 , . . . π k -1 , π * k , . . . π * K , µ * 0 , . . . µ * k -1 , µ k , . . . µ K )</formula><p>for some k , i.e., when the first k treatment models and the last K -k + 1 outcome models are consistently estimated, P ϕ a (O; η * 2 ) = 0. Because in this case, P n ϕ a (O; η * 2 )</p><p>p → P ϕ a (O; η * 2 ) = 0 by the law of large numbers, it suffices to show R 2 (η 2 ) = o p (1) to establish the consistency of θeif 2 a . Second, in the case where η * 2 = η 2 , i.e., when all of the 2(K + 1) nuisance functions are consistently estimated, the first two terms in equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_120">27</ref>) reduces to P n ϕ a (O; η 2 ), i.e., the sample average of the efficient influence function, which has an asymptotic variance of E[ ϕ a (O) 2 ]. Thus, in this case, θeif 2 a will be asymptotically normal and semiparametric efficient as long as R 2 (η 2 ) = o p (n -1/2 ).</p><p>To analyze R 2 (η 2 ), we first observe that</p><formula xml:id="formula_122">P [m 2 (O; η2 )] = P I(A = a K+1 ) π0 (a 1 |X) K j=1 πj (a j |X, M j ) πj (a j+1 |X, M j ) Y -µ K (X, M K ) + K k=1 I(A = a k ) π0 (a 1 |X) k-1 j=1 πj (a j |X, M j ) πj (a j+1 |X, M j ) µ k (X, M k ) -µ k-1 (X, M k-1 ) + µ 0 (X) = P π 0 (a K+1 |X, M K ) π0 (a 1 |X) K j=1 πj (a j |X, M j ) πj (a j+1 |X, M j ) E Y -µ K (X, M K ) X, A = a K+1 , M K =0 + K k=1 π 0 (a k |X, M k-1 ) π0 (a 1 |X) k-1 j=1 πj (a j |X, M j ) πj (a j+1 |X, M j ) E µ k (X, M k ) -µ k-1 (X, M k-1 ) X, A = a k , M k-1 =0 + µ 0 (X) = P [µ 0 (X)] = P [m 2 (O; η 2 )].</formula><p>Then, by substituting m 2 (O; η2 ) for m 2 (O; η 2 ) in R 2 (η 2 ), rearranging terms, and applying the Cauchy-Schwartz inequality, we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_123">R 2 (η 2 ) = P [m 2 (O; η2 ) -m 2 (O; η2 )] = P π0 (a 1 |X) -π 0 (a 1 |X) μ0 (X) -µ 0 (X) π0 (a 1 |X) + K k=1 P k j=1 πj (a j |X, M j ) πj (a j+1 |X, M j ) πk (a k+1 |X, M k ) -π k (a k+1 |X, M k ) μk (X, M k ) -µ k (X, M k ) π0 (a 1 |X) - K k=1 P k-1 j=1 πj (a j |X, M j ) πj (a j+1 |X, M j ) πk (a k |X, M k ) -π k (a k |X, M k ) μk (X, M k ) -µ k (X, M k ) π0 (a 1 |X) = K k=0 O p πk (a k+1 |X, M k ) -π k (a k+1 |X, M k ) • μk (X, M k ) -µ k (X, M k ) + K k=1 O p πk (a k |X, M k ) -π k (a k |X, M k ) • μk (X, M k ) -µ k (X, M k ) (<label>28</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_124">)</formula><p>where g = ( g T gdP ) 1/2 . The last equality uses the positivity assumption that πk (a|X, M k ) is bounded away from zero for all k and a. Thus, assuming that the empirical process term is on the order of o p (n -1/2 ) (e.g., via cross-fitting), we can write equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_120">27</ref>) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_125">θeif 2 a -θ a = P n ϕ a (O; η * 2 ) -P ϕ a (O; η * 2 ) + K k=0 O p ( πk -π k ) • O p ( μk -µ k ) + o p (n -1/2 ), where π k = (π k (0|X, M k ), π k (1|X, M k )) T .</formula><p>Clearly, when there exists a k such that the first k treatment models and the last K -k +1 outcome models are consistently estimated, </p><formula xml:id="formula_126">K k=0 O p ( πk - π k ) • O p ( μk -µ k ) = o p (1). In this case, since P n ϕ a (O; η * 2 ) -P ϕ a (O; η * 2 ) = P n ϕ a (O; η * 2 ) = o p (1), θeif 2 a is consistent. When η * 2 = η 2 and K k=0 O p ( πk -π k ) • O p ( μk -µ k ) = o p (n -1/2 ), we have θeif 2 a -θ a = P n ϕ a (O; η 2 ) + o p (n -1/2 ), implying</formula><formula xml:id="formula_127">√ n-consistent, K k=0 O p ( πk -π k ) • O p ( μk -µ k ) = K k=0 O p (n -1/2 ) • O p (n -1/2 ) = o p (n -1/2</formula><p>), hence the second part of Theorem 3. Now let us consider θeif 1 a . In a similar vein, we can write θeif 1 a -θ a as</p><formula xml:id="formula_128">θeif 1 a -θ a = P n ϕ a (O; η * 1 ) -P ϕ a (O; η * 1 ) + K k=0 O p ( πk -π k ) • O p ( μk -µ k ) ∆ =R 2 (η 1 ) +o p (n -1/2 ),</formula><p>where πk and μk are estimates of π k and µ k constructed from η1 = {π 0 , f1 , . . . fK , μK }. First, from our proofs in Section D.1, we know that when K + 1 of the K + 2 nuisance functions in η 1 are consistently estimated, P ϕ a (O; η * 1 ) = 0. Since in this case P n ϕ a (O; η * 1 )</p><p>p → P ϕ a (O; η * 1 ) = 0, it suffices to show R 2 (η 1 ) = o p (1) to establish the consistency of θeif 1 a . Second, in the case where η * 1 = η 1 , i.e., when all of the K + 2 nuisance functions are consistently estimated, the first two terms in equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_120">27</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E Multiply Robust Decomposition of Between-group Disparities</head><p>The multiply robust semiparametric estimators can also be used to estimate noncausal decompositions of between-group disparities <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Fortin et al. 2011)</ref>. For example, social scientists in the United</p><p>States have a long-standing interest in decomposing the black-white income gap into components that are attributable to racial differences in various ascriptive and achieved characteristics. Using linear structural equation models, ? decomposed the total black-white income gap into components that reflect black-white differences in family background, academic performance (net of family background), educational attainment (net of family background and academic performance), occupational attainment (net of family background, academic performance, and educational attainment), and a "residual" component that cannot be explained by the above characteristics.</p><p>Although proposed prior to ? and ?, Duncan's decomposition can be viewed as a generalization of the Blinder-Oaxaca decomposition widely used in labor economics.</p><p>Duncan's decomposition is similar in form to equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_23">3</ref>), but it is defined in terms of the statistical parameters θ a rather than the causal parameters ψ a . Moreover, the left-hand side is now the black-white income gap rather than the average causal effect of a manipulable intervention, and, therefore, there are no pretreatment confounders. It should be noted that this decomposition is different from causal mediation analysis for a randomized trial, in which case pretreatment covariates may still be needed to adjust for potential confounding of the mediator-mediator and mediator-outcome relationships. The components associated with Duncan's decomposition, by contrast, are purely statistical parameters and should not be interpreted causally.</p><p>Consequently, in the context of decomposing between-group disparities, the functional θ 0 k ,1 k+1 can be estimated as To implement the full decomposition, we need to estimate θ 0 k ,1 k+1 for each k ∈ 0, 1, . . . K + 1, i.e., estimate the vector-valued parameter θ decomp = (θ 1 1 , θ 0,1 2 , . . . θ 0 K ,1 , θ 0 K+1 ). Since θ 1 1 and θ 0 K+1 is doubly robust with respect to πk and μk , the semiparametric estimator θeif 2 decomp = ( θeif 2 1 1 , θeif 2 0,1 2 , . . . θeif 2 0 K ,1 , θeif 2 0 K+1</p><p>) is 2 K -robust: it is consistent if for each k ∈ [K], either πk or μk is consistent. Note that in this case, the functions µ k (M k ) = E[Y |A = 1, M k ] are not estimated iteratively, but separately for each k.</p><p>Corollary 5. Define θeif 2 decomp = ( θeif 2 1 1 , θeif 2 0,1 2 , . . . θeif 2 0 K ,1 , θeif 2 0 K+1</p><p>). Suppose X = ∅, and that all assump-tions required for Theorem 4 hold. When the nuisance functions (π 1 , . . . πK , μ1 , . . . μK ) are estimated via parametric models, θeif 2 decomp is CAN if for each k ∈ [K], either πk or μk is correctly specified and its estimates are √ n-consistent. θeif 2 decomp is semiparametric efficient if all of the nuisance functions are correctly specified and their parameter estimates √ n-consistent. When the nuisance functions are estimated via data-adaptive methods and cross-fitting, θeif 2 decomp is semiparametric efficient if all of the nuisance functions are consistently estimated and K k=1 r n (π k )r n (μ k ) = o(n -1/2 ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F Additional Details of the Simulation Study</head><p>The variables X 1 , X 2 , X 3 , X 4 , A, M 1 , M 2 , Y in the simulation study are generated via the following model:</p><p>(U 1 , U 2 , U 3 , U XY ) ∼ N (0, I 4 ), X j ∼ N ((U 1 , U 2 , U 3 , U XY )β X j , 1), j = 1, 2, 3, 4, It can be shown that under the above model, the six nuisance functions π 0 (a|x), π 1 (a|x, m 1 ), π 2 (a|x, m 1 , m 2 ), µ 0 (x), µ 1 (x, m 1 ), and µ 2 (x, m 1 , m 2 ) for any θ a 1 ,a 2 ,a can be consistently estimated via the following GLMs:</p><formula xml:id="formula_129">A ∼ Bernoulli logit -1 [(1, X 1 , X 2 , X 3 , X 4 )β A ] , M 1 ∼ N (1, X 1 , X 2 , X 3 , X 4 , A)β M 1 , 1 , M 2 ∼ N (1, X 1 , X 2 , X 3 , X 4 , A, M 1 )β M 2 , 1 , Y ∼ N (1, U XY , X 1 , X 2 , X 3 , X 4 , A, M 1 , M 2 )β Y , 1 .</formula><formula xml:id="formula_130">π 0 (1|X) = logit -1 [(1, X 1 , X 2 , X 3 , X 4 )γ 0 ],</formula><p>π 1 (1|X, M 1 ) = logit -1 [(1, X 1 , X 2 , X 3 , X 4 , M 1 )γ 1 ], </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the parameters for p(a|x, m k ) are not variationally independent across different values of k. As in the case of the regression-imputation estimator, care should be taken to ensure the compatibility of the models specified for p(a|x, m k ) (see<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Miles et al. 2020</ref> for some practical recommendations).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the first k treatment models π 0 , . . . π k-1 and the last K+1-k outcome models µ k , . . . µ K in η 2 are correctly specified and their parameter estimates are √ nconsistent; it is semiparametric efficient if all of the treatment and outcome models in η 2 are correctly specified and their parameter estimates are √ n-consistent. robust in the sense that they are CAN provided that one of K + 2 sets of nuisance functions is correctly specified and the corresponding parameter estimates are √ n-consistent. Several special cases are worth noting. First, in the degenerate case where K = 0, it is clear that both θeif 1 a and θeif 2 a reduce to the standard doubly robust estimator for E[Y (a)] (Scharfstein et al. 1999). Second, when K = 1, θeif 1 01 coincides with Tchetgen Tchetgen and Shpitser's (2012) triply robust estimator for E[Y 1, M (0) ]. Finally, when K = 2, θeif 1 010 is identical to Miles et al.'s (2020) estimator for θ 010 . For this case, however, Miles et al. provide a slightly</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>a and θeif 2 a</head><label>2</label><figDesc>to attain the semiparametric efficiency bound is when all of the nuisance function estimates converge at faster-than-n -1/4 rates. More precise conditions are given in Theorem 4. Theorem 4. Let η1 = {π 0 , f1 , . . . fK , μK } and η2 = {π 0 , . . . πK , μ0 , . . . μK } denote estimates of the nuisance functions involved in θeif 1 a and θeif 2 a , respectively. Let r n (•) denote a mapping from a nuisance function estimator to its L 2 (P ) convergence rate where P represents the true distribution of O = (X, A, M K , Y ). Suppose that Assumption 3* (positivity) holds for both the true distribution</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2 illustrates the baseline and comparison interventions associated with the NDE for the case of K = 2, where the black solid and dashed arrows for A → M 1 , A → M 2 , and A → Y denote activated (A = 1) and unactivated (A = 0) paths, respectively. A semiparametric efficient estimator for the NDE can be constructed as</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Illustrations of NDE, NIE, TIE, nPSE, and cPSE in the case of two mediators. Note: A denotes the treatment, Y denotes the outcome of interest, and M 1 and M 2 denote two causally ordered mediators. Solid and dashed arrows for A → M 1 , A → M 2 , and A → Y denote activated (A = 1) and unactivated (A = 0) paths, respectively. Gray arrows M 1 → M 2 , M 1 → Y , and M 2 → Y signify that the mediators M 1 and M 2 are not under direct intervention.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>eif 1 M</head><label>1</label><figDesc>k can be seen as Mileset al.'s (2020) estimator of θ 010 -θ 000 applied to M 1 = (M 1 , M 2 , . . . M k-1 ) and M 2 = M k . Again, θeif 2 0 K+1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>M</head><label></label><figDesc>is quadruply robust in that it is consistent if one of the following four conditions holds: (a) π0 , πk-1 , and πk are consistent; (b) π0 , πk-1 , and μk are consistent; (c) π0 , μk-1,k , and μk are consistent; and (d) μ0,k-1,k , μk-1,k , and μk are consistent. By taking the intersection of the multiple robustness conditions for θeif 2 1k is also quadruply robust, as detailed in Corollary 3.Corollary 3. Suppose all assumptions required for Theorem 4 hold. When the nuisance functions are estimated via parametric models, nPSE eif 2</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>in that it is consistent if one of the following three conditions holds: (a) π0 and πk are consistent; (b) π0 and μk are consistent; and (c) μ0,k and μk are consistent. By replacing k with k -1 in equation (18), we obtain a similar expression for θeif 2 0 k-1 ,1 k , which is also triply robust in that it is consistent if one of the following three conditions holds: (a) π0 and πk-1 are consistent; (b) π0 and μk-1 are consistent; and (c) μ0,k-1 and μk-1 are consistent. As a result, cPSE eif 2</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a) only π 0 , π 1 , π 2 are correctly specified; (b) only π 0 , π 1 , µ 2 are correctly specified; (c) only π 0 , µ 1 , µ 2 are correctly specified; (d) only µ 0 , µ 1 , µ 2 are correctly specified; and (e) all of the six nuisance functions are misspecified. In theory, θw-a a is consistent in case (a), θri-w-w a is consistent in case (b), θri-ri-w -(d). The corresponding estimators of cPSE M 2 should follow the same properties. For the two nonparametric estimators, θnp,eif 2 a is based on estimating equation (14), and θtmle,eif 2 a is based on the method of TMLE. Like θpar 2 ,eif 2 via a super learner (van der Laan et al. 2007) composed of Lasso and random forest, where the feature matrix consists of first-order, second-order, and interaction terms of the false covariates Z. The super learner is more flexible than a misspecified GLM consisting of only the main effects of Z, but it remains agnostic about the true nuisance functions, which are either logit</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Sampling distributions of eight different estimators for n = 2, 000. Cases (a)-(e) are described in the main text. The symbols y and n denote whether cross-fitting is used to implement the nonparametric estimators (y = yes, n = no).</figDesc><graphic coords="30,72.00,72.00,468.01,280.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 1 ,</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1, where A denotes college attendance, Y denotes political participation, and M 1 and M 2 denote two causally ordered mediators that reflect (a) economic status, and (b) civic and political interest, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>=</head><label></label><figDesc>O) S 0 (O) = E ϕ a (O)S 0 (O) . D Proof of Theorems 3 and 4 D.1 Parametric Estimation of Nuisance Parameters In this subsection, we prove the multiple robustness of θeif 1 a and θeif 2 a for the case where parametric models are used to estimate the corresponding nuisance functions. The local efficiency of these estimators is implied by our proof in Section D.2, which considers the case where data-adaptive methods and cross-fitting are used to estimate the nuisance functions. Let us start with θeif 1 a = P n [m 1 (O; η1 )], where m 1 (O; η1 ) denotes the quantity inside P n [•] in equation (12), and η1 = (π 0 , f1 , . . . fK , μK ). In the meantime, let η 1 = (π 0 , f 1 , . . . f K , µ K ) denote the truth and η * 1 = (π * 0 , f * 1 , . . . f * K , µ * K ) the probability limit of η1 . A first-order Taylor expansion of P n m 1 (O; η * 1 ) + o p (1).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Now consider θeif 2 a=</head><label>2</label><figDesc>P n [m 2 (O; η2 )], where m 2 (O; η2 ) denotes the quantity inside P n [•] in equation (14), and η2 = (π 0 , . . . πK , μ0 , . . . μK ). In the meantime, let η 2 = (π 0 , . . . π K , µ 0 , . . . µ K ) denote the truth and η * 2 = (π * 0 , . . . π * K , µ * 0 , . . . µ * K ) denote the probability limit of η2 . A first-order Taylor expansion of θeif 2 a yields θeif 2 a = P n m 2 (O; η * 2 ) + o p (1).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>that θeif 2 a is CAN and semiparametric efficient. If the nuisance functions are estimated via parametric models and their parameter estimates are all</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>.</head><label></label><figDesc>) reduces to P n ϕ a (O; η 1 ), i.e., the sample average of the efficient influence function, which has an asymptotic variance of E[ ϕ a(O)   2 ]. Thus, in this case, θeif 1 a will be asymptotically normal and semiparametric efficient as long as R 2 (η 1 ) = o p (n -1/2 ).We first note that for any a, πk (a|X, M k ) -π k (a|X, M k ) can be decomposed asπk (a|X, M k ) -π k (a|X, M k ) = p(M k |X, a)π 0 (a|X) a p(M k |X, a )π 0 (a |X) -p(M k |X, a)π 0 (a|X) a p(M k |X, a )π 0 (a |X) = p(M k |X, a) π0 (a|X) -π 0 (a|X) a p(M k |X, a )π 0 (a |X) k |X, a) -p(M k |X, a) π 0 (a|X) a p(M k |X, a )π 0 (a |X) k |X, a)π 0 (a|X) a p(M k |X, a )π 0 (a |X) -p(M k |X, a )π 0 (a |X) a p(M k |X, a )π 0 (a |X) a p(M k |X, a )π 0 (a |X)By the positivity assumption, we have ∆ 1 π = O p ( π0 -π 0 ). Using the factorization p(M k |X, a) = k j=1 p(M j |X, a, M j-1 ), ∆ 2 π can be expressed as ∆ 2 π = π 0 (a|X) k j=1 fj (M j |X, a, M j-1 ) -k j=1 f j (M j |X, a, M j-1 ) a p(M k |X, a )π 0 (a |X)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>k ) πk (1|M k ) Y -μk (M k ) + I(A = 0) π0 (0) μk (M k ) -μ0,k + μ0,k ,(32)whereπ 0 (0) = Pr[A = 0], µ k (M k ) = E[Y |A = 1, M k ], and µ 0,k = E[µ k (M k )|A = 0]. Since π0 (0)can be estimated by the sample average of 1 -A and µ 0,k the sample average of μk (M k ) among units with A = 0, equation (32) involves estimating only two nuisance functions: πk (a|m k ) and μk (m k ). It follows from Theorem 3 that θeif 2 0 k ,1 k+1 is now doubly robust -it is consistent if either πk (a|m k ) or μk (m k ) is consistent.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>can be estimated by the sample analogs of E[Y |A = 1] and E[Y |A = 0] and θeif 2 0 k ,1 k+1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The coefficients β X j (1≤ j ≤ 4) and β Y are drawn from Uniform[-1, 1], the coefficients β A are drawn from Uniform[-0.5, 0.5], and the coefficients β M 1 and β M 2 are drawn from Uniform[0, 0.5].Specifically,β X 1 = (0.77, -0.86, 0.35, 0.88), β X 2 = (-0.99, -0.72, -0.1, 0.54), β X 3 = (-0.74, 0.1, 0.91, 0.46), β X 4 = (-0.21, -0.43, -0.21, -0.7), β A = (-0.36, -0.08, -0.06, 0.4, -0.14), β M 1 = (0, 0.3, 0.42, 0.48, 0.28, 0.41), β M 2 = (0.04, 0.2, 0.09, 0.12, 0.39, 0.34, 0.24), β Y = (-0.27, -0.1, 0.25, 0.2, -0.08, 0.78, 0.76, -0.4, 0.96).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the natural indirect effect (NIE;<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Pearl 2001)</ref> or the pure indirect effect (PIE;<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Robins and Greenland 1992)</ref> for M 1 , whereas τ A→M 1 Y (1, 1) is sometimes called the total indirect effect (TIE; Robins and Greenland 1992) for M 1 . Note, however, that the term NIE has also been used to denote τ A→M 1 Y (1, 1) (e.g., Tchetgen Tchetgen and Shpitser 2012). To avoid ambiguity, we use NIE and TIE to denote τ A→M 1 Y (0, 0) and τ A→M 1 Y (1, 1), respectively. By definition, these PSEs are identified if the corresponding expected potential outcomes, i.e., E[Y a, M 1</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>follows from Theorem 3 that θeif 2 1,0 2 is triply robust in that it is consistent if one of the following three</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="4">conditions holds: (a) π0 and π1 are consistent; (b) π0 and μ1 are consistent; and (c) μ0,1 and μ1</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">are consistent. By taking the intersection of the multiple robustness conditions for θeif 2 1,0 2 and θeif 2 0 K+1</cell><cell>,</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">we deduce that NIE eif 2 M 1 is also triply robust, as detailed in Corollary 2.</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Corollary 2. Suppose all assumptions required for Theorem 4 hold. When the nuisance functions</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">are estimated via parametric models, NIE eif 2 M 1 is CAN provided that one of the following three sets</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">of nuisance functions is correctly specified and its parameter estimates are</cell><cell>√</cell><cell>n-consistent: {π 0 , π 1 },</cell></row><row><cell>{π 0 , µ 1 }, {µ 0 , µ 0,1 , µ 1 }. NIE</cell><cell cols="3">eif 2 M 1 is semiparametric efficient if all of the above nuisance functions are</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">correctly specified and their parameter estimates</cell><cell>√</cell><cell>n-consistent. When the nuisance functions are</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">estimated via data-adaptive methods and cross-fitting, NIE</cell><cell>eif 2</cell></row></table><note><p>M 1 is semiparametric efficient if all of the nuisance functions are consistently estimated and r n</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>all of the above nuisance functions are correctly specified and their parameter esti-</figDesc><table><row><cell>mates</cell><cell>√</cell><cell>n-consistent. When the nuisance functions are estimated via data-adaptive methods and</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">cross-fitting, nPSE eif 2 M k is semiparametric efficient if all of the nuisance functions are consistently</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">estimated and r n</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>m 1 ), and µ 2 (x, m 1 , m 2 ). To demonstrate the conse-</figDesc><table><row><cell>quences of model misspecification and the multiple robustness of</cell><cell>θpar,eif 2 a</cell><cell>and</cell><cell>θpar 2 ,eif 2 a</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>interest in government and public affairs and involvement in volunteering, donation, community group activities between 2007 and 2010. The overlap of the periods in which M 1 and M 2 were measured is a limitation of this analysis, and it makes our earlier assumption that M 2</figDesc><table><row><cell>use data from n = 2, 969 individuals in the National Longitudinal Survey of Youth 1997</cell></row><row><cell>(NLSY97) who were age 15-17 in 1997 and had completed high school by age 20. The treatment</cell></row><row><cell>A is a binary indicator for whether the individual had attended a two-year or four-year college by</cell></row></table><note><p>age 20. The outcome Y is a binary indicator for whether the individual voted in the 2010 general election. We measure economic status (M 1 ) using the respondent's average annual earnings from 2006 to 2009. To gauge civic and political interest (M 2 ), we use a set of variables that reflect the respondent's</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Estimates of total and path-specific effects of college attendance on voting.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Estimating equation (</cell><cell>θnp,eif 2 a</cell><cell>) TMLE (</cell><cell>θtmle,eif 2 a</cell><cell>)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Data-Adaptive Estimation of Nuisance Parameters</figDesc><table><row><cell>Let us start with θeif 2</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>by η  *  2 the probability limit of η2 . θeif 2 a</cell><cell>can now be written as</cell></row><row><cell>θeif 2</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>a = P n [m 2 (O; η2 )]. Let η2 = (π 0 , . . . πK , µ 0 , . . . µ K ) denote a combination of estimated treatment models πj and true outcome models µ j (0 ≤ j ≤ K + 1), and let P g = gdP denote the expectation of a function g of observed data O at the true model P . As before, denote</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>Table G1 :</head><label>G1</label><figDesc>Overall and group-specific means in pretreatment covariates, mediators, and outcome.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Overall Non-College-Goers College Goers</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Age at 1997</cell><cell>15.98</cell><cell>16.02</cell><cell>15.96</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Female</cell><cell>0.5</cell><cell>0.42</cell><cell>0.55</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Black</cell><cell>0.16</cell><cell>0.22</cell><cell>0.13</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Hispanic</cell><cell>0.12</cell><cell>0.15</cell><cell>0.1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Parental Education</cell><cell>13.08</cell><cell>12.05</cell><cell>13.71</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Parental Income</cell><cell>86,520</cell><cell>60,706</cell><cell>102,568</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Parental Assets</cell><cell>119,242</cell><cell>62,573</cell><cell>154,550</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Lived with Both Biological Parents</cell><cell>0.53</cell><cell>0.39</cell><cell>0.62</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Presence of a Father Figure</cell><cell>0.76</cell><cell>0.68</cell><cell>0.8</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Lived in Rural Area</cell><cell>0.27</cell><cell>0.29</cell><cell>0.26</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Lived in the South</cell><cell>0.37</cell><cell>0.39</cell><cell>0.35</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ASVAB Percentile Score</cell><cell>53.4</cell><cell>37.26</cell><cell>62.72</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>High School GPA</cell><cell>2.9</cell><cell>2.5</cell><cell>3.16</cell></row><row><cell>Pretreatment</cell><cell>Substance Use Index</cell><cell>1.36</cell><cell>1.56</cell><cell>1.23</cell></row><row><cell>Covariates</cell><cell>Delinquency Index</cell><cell>1.54</cell><cell>2.06</cell><cell>1.22</cell></row><row><cell>(X)</cell><cell>Had Children by Age 18</cell><cell>0.06</cell><cell>0.11</cell><cell>0.02</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>75%+ of Peers Expected College</cell><cell>0.56</cell><cell>0.41</cell><cell>0.66</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>90%+ of Peers Expected College</cell><cell>0.19</cell><cell>0.12</cell><cell>0.24</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Property Ever Stolen at School</cell><cell>0.24</cell><cell>0.27</cell><cell>0.22</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Ever Threatened at School</cell><cell>0.19</cell><cell>0.27</cell><cell>0.14</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Ever in a Fight at School</cell><cell>0.12</cell><cell>0.18</cell><cell>0.08</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Mediator M 1 Average Earnings in 2006-2009</cell><cell>33,600</cell><cell>25,082</cell><cell>38,899</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Volunteerism</cell><cell>1.57</cell><cell>1.46</cell><cell>1.64</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Community Participation</cell><cell>1.26</cell><cell>1.17</cell><cell>1.32</cell></row><row><cell>Mediator M 2</cell><cell>Donation Activity</cell><cell>0.3</cell><cell>0.22</cell><cell>0.35</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Political Interest</cell><cell>2.63</cell><cell>2.34</cell><cell>2.81</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Outcome (Y ) Voted in the 2010 General Election</cell><cell>0.45</cell><cell>0.3</cell><cell>0.54</cell></row><row><cell>Sample Size</cell><cell></cell><cell>2,976</cell><cell>1,240</cell><cell>1,736</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Note: All statistics are calculated using NLSY97 sampling weights.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head>Table G2 :</head><label>G2</label><figDesc>Regression models for the mediators and the outcome. Regression coefficients for the pretreatment covariates are omitted. Numbers in parentheses are heteroskedasticity-robust standard errors, which are adjusted for multiple imputation via<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Rubin's (1987)</ref> method.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>M 1</cell><cell></cell><cell>M 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Log Earnings</cell><cell>Volunteerism</cell><cell>Community Participation</cell><cell>Donation Activity</cell><cell>Political Interest</cell><cell>Voting</cell></row><row><cell>College</cell><cell>0.367</cell><cell>0.038</cell><cell>0.039</cell><cell>0.036</cell><cell>0.259</cell><cell>0.117</cell></row><row><cell>Attendance</cell><cell>(0.055)</cell><cell>(0.046)</cell><cell>(0.028)</cell><cell>(0.023)</cell><cell>(0.046)</cell><cell>(0.023)</cell></row><row><cell>Log</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.001</cell><cell>0.008</cell><cell>0.036</cell><cell>0.050</cell><cell>0.016</cell></row><row><cell>Earnings</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.017)</cell><cell>(0.011)</cell><cell>(0.009)</cell><cell>(0.016)</cell><cell>(0.009)</cell></row><row><cell>Volunteerism</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.028 (0.013)</cell></row><row><cell>Community Participa-tion</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.041 (0.019)</cell></row><row><cell>Donation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.007</cell></row><row><cell>Activity</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.024)</cell></row><row><cell>Political</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.148</cell></row><row><cell>Interest</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.010)</cell></row><row><cell>Note:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary Materials</head><p>A Proof of Theorem 1 Assumption 2* implies that for any k ∈ {2, . . . K} and any j ∈ {1, . . . k -1},</p><p>Setting</p><p>Now suppose that for some j ∈ {1, . . . k -1},</p><p>By the contraction rule of conditional independence, the relationships ( <ref type="formula">20</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>) imply</p><p>Hence, by the initial relationship (21) and mathematical induction, we have</p><p>In the meantime, because M k+1 (a k+1 , m k ), . . . M K (a K , m K-1 ), Y (a K+1 , m K ) ⊥ ⊥ A|X, we have (by the contraction rule)</p><p>Thus the components in A, M 1 (a 1 ), . . . M K (a K , m K-1 ), Y (a K+1 , m K ) are mutually independent given X. Therefore,</p><p>where</p><p>. By a similar logic, ∆ 3 π can be written as</p><p>In sum, we have</p><p>Now consider μk -µ k . Using the fact that</p><p>Using the notation dP 2 = K j=k+1 f j (m j |x, m j-1 )dm j and dP 1 = dP X (x)• k j=1 f j (m j |x, m j-1 )dm j , we have</p><p>The last equality uses the assumption that µ K (X, M K ) (and hence h 2 l dP 2 ) is bounded. From equations ( <ref type="formula">29</ref>)-(30), we have</p><p>Clearly, when K +1 of the K +2 nuisance functions in η 1 are consistently estimated, R 2 (η 1 ) = o p (1).</p><p>In this case, since</p><p>). If the nuisance functions are estimated via parametric models and their parameter estimates are all are relatively small and not statistically significant. The estimated direct effect of college attendance on political interest, by contrast, is much larger and statistically significant. The last column shows statistically significant effects of volunteerism, community participation, and political interest on voting (at the p &lt; 0.05 level). The estimated effect of political interest is particularly strong: a one unit increase in the four-point scale of political interest is associated with a 14.8 percentage point increase in the estimated probability of voting. The coefficient of college attendance in the last model can be interpreted as the direct effect of college on voting (i.e., A → Y ), i.e., the effect that operates neither through economic status nor through civic and political interest. The estimate, 11.7 percentage points, is comparable to our semiparametric estimates reported in the main text.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mediation analysis for nonlinear models with confounding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Albert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Albert</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1028" to="1038" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2012. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Biometrics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The decomposition of effects in path analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Alwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Sociological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifiability of path-specific effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Avin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Shpitser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 19th International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the 19th International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann Publishers Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="357" to="363" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Doubly robust estimation in missing data and causal inference models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="962" to="973" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The moderator-mediator variable distinction in social psychological research: Conceptual, strategic, and statistical considerations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Baron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kenny</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1173</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Double/debiased machine learning for treatment and structural parameters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Chernozhukov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chetverikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Demirer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Duflo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Newey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Econometrics Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="C68" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causal mediation analysis with multiple mediators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Daniel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>De Stavola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cousens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Are there civic returns to education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Dee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Public Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1697" to="1720" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decomposition methods in economics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Fortin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lemieux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Firpo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Labor Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="102" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation of controlled direct effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Goetgeluk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Goetghebeur</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B (Statistical Methodology)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1049" to="1066" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alternative assumptions for the identification of direct and indirect effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hafeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vanderweele</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="753" to="764" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiply robust estimation in regression analysis with missing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1159" to="1173" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation with missing data: Beyond double robustness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="430" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The missing link: Exploring the relationship between higher education and political engagement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hillygus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification, inference and sensitivity analysis for causal mediation effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Imai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Keele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistical Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The health belief model as an explanatory framework in communication research: Exploring parallel, serial, and moderated mediation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Scherr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Christy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weaver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="566" to="576" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Demystifying double robustness: A comparison of alternative strategies for estimating a population mean from incomplete data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Schafer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistical Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="523" to="539" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why education matters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kingston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hubbard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lapp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociology of Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interventional approach for path-specific effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-H</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Vanderweele</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Causal Inference</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Luedtke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Sofrygin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Carone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1705.02459</idno>
		<title level="m">Sequential double robustness in right-censored longitudinal models</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantifying an adherence path-specific effect of antiretroviral therapy in the nigeria pepfar program</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Miles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Shpitser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kanki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Meloni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tchetgen Tchetgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1443" to="1452" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On semiparametric estimation of a path-specific effect in the presence of mediator-outcome confounding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Miles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Shpitser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kanki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Meloni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tchetgen Tchetgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="172" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does education improve citizenship? evidence from the united states and the united kingdom</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Milligan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Moretti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Oreopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Public Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1667" to="1695" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple robustness in factorized likelihood models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Molina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rotnitzky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sued</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="561" to="581" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Large sample estimation and hypothesis. Handbook of Econometrics, IV</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Newey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mcfadden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>RF Engle and DL McFadden</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2112" to="2245" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cross-fitting and fast remainder rates for semiparametric estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Newey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1801.09138</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the application of probability theory to agricultural experiments. essay on principles. section 9</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Neyman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Agricultural Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="1923">1923</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct and indirect effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Seventeenth Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the Seventeenth Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann Publishers Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="420" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Causality: Models, Reasoning, and Inference</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diagnosing and responding to violations in the positivity assumption</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Porter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gruber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistical Methods in Medical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="54" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation of direct causal effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Sinisi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="276" to="284" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comment: Performance of doublerobust estimators when &quot;inverse probability&quot; weights are highly variable</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sued</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Lei-Gomez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rotnitzky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistical Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="544" to="559" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Semantics of causal dag models and the identification of direct and indirect effects. Highly Structured Stochastic Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="81" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifiability and exchangeability for direct and indirect effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Greenland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Alternative graphical causal models and the identification of direct effects. Causality and psychopathology: Finding the determinants of disorders and their cures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="158" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Voter Turnout: A Social Theory of Political Participation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rolfe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On the multiply robust estimation of the mean of the g-functional</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rotnitzky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Babino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1705.08582</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating Causal Effects of Treatments in Randomized and Nonrandomized Studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Rubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="688" to="701" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Multiple Imputation for Nonresponse in Surveys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Rubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<publisher>Wiley and Sons</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adjusting for nonignorable drop-out using semiparametric nonresponse models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Scharfstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rotnitzky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1096" to="1120" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduction to double robust methods for incomplete data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Seaman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistical Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">184</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Counterfactual graphical models for longitudinal mediation analysis with unobserved confounding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Shpitser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cognitive Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1011" to="1035" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flexible mediation analysis with multiple mediators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Steen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Loeys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Moerkerke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">186</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inverse odds ratio-weighted estimation for causal mediation analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tchetgen Tchetgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistics in Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4567" to="4580" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semiparametric theory for causal mediation analysis: Efficiency bounds, multiple robustness, and sensitivity analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tchetgen Tchetgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Shpitser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1816</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Polley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hubbard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Super learner. Statistical Applications in Genetics and Molecular Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Targeted maximum likelihood learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Journal of Biostatistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Explanation in Causal Inference: Methods for Mediation and Interaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Vanderweele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mediation analysis with multiple mediators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Vanderweele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiologic Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="115" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Concerning the consistency assumption in causal inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vanderweele</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="880" to="883" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect decomposition in the presence of an exposure-induced mediator-outcome confounder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vanderweele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="300" to="306" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Imputation strategies for the estimation of natural direct and indirect effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bekaert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lange</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiologic Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="158" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interventional effects for mediation analysis with multiple mediators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vansteelandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Daniel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">258</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect decomposition in the presence of treatment-induced confounding: A regression-with-residuals approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wodtke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="375" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cross-validated targeted minimum-loss-based estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Targeted Learning</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="459" to="474" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Targeted maximum likelihood estimation of natural direct effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Journal of Biostatistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Tracing causal paths from experimental and observational data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.31235/osf.io/2rx6p</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">SocArXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E[y</forename><surname>|x</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>2 , µ 2 (X, M 1 , M 2 ) = E[Y |X</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>1, X 1 , X 2 , X 3 , X 4 , A, M 1</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>µ 1 (X, M 1 ) = E[µ 2 (X, M 1 , M 2 )|X, A = a 2 , M 1 ], E[µ 1 (X, M 1 )|X, A] = (1, X 1 , X 2 , X 3 , X 4 , A)α 0 , µ 0 (X) = E[µ 1 (X, M 1 )|X, A = a 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">/X 1 ) 1/3 , X 4 /(e X 1 /2 + 1) to fit a misspecified model for each of the nuisance functions: π 0 (1|Z) = logit -1 [(1, Z 1 , Z 2 , Z 3 , Z 4 )γ 0 ], π 1 (1|Z, M 1 ) = logit -1</title>
		<idno>logit -1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Z 1 , Z 2 , Z</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2 /2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Z = X. 1, Z 1 , Z 2 , Z 3 , Z 4 , M 1 , M 2 )γ 2</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E[y</forename><surname>|z</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Z 1 , Z 2 , Z 3 , Z 4 , A, M 1 ) α1 , µ 1 (Z, M 1 ) = E</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">) = E[y</forename><surname>|z</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Z 1 , Z 2 , Z. µ 2 (Z, M 1 , M 2 )|Z, A = a 2 , M 1 ], E[µ 1 (Z, M 1 )|Z, A] = (1, Z 1 , Z 2 , Z 3 , Z 4 , A)α 0 , µ 0 (Z) = E[µ 1 (Z, M 1 )|Z, A = a 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Each of the five cases described in Section 5 reflects a combination of estimated nuisance functions from these correctly and incorrectly specified models. For example, in case (a), all parametric estimators of cPSE M 2 use correctly specified models for π 0 (1|x), π 1 (1|x, m 1 ), π 2 (1|x, m 1 , m 2 ) and incorrectly specified models for µ 0 (x), µ 1 (x, m 1 )</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>and µ 2 (x, m 1 , m 2</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Parental education is measured using mother&apos;s years of schooling; when mother&apos;s years of schooling is unavailable, it is measured using father&apos;s years of schooling. Parental income is measured as the average annual parental income from 1997 to 2001. The mediator M 2 , which gauges civic and political interest, includes four components: volunteerism, community participation, donation activity, and political interest. Volunteerism represents the respondent&apos;s self-reported frequency of volunteering work over the past 12 months</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>times; 4: 12 times or more). Community participation represents the respondent&apos;s self-reported frequency of attending a meeting or event for a political, environmental. or community group (1: None; 2: 1 -4 times; 3: 5 -11 times; 4: 12 times or more. Donation activity is a dichotomous variable indicating whether</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
