<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">AC 2009-1022: UNDERSTANDING FACTORS CONTRIBUTING TO RETENTION IN ENGINEERING: A STRUCTURAL EQUATION MODELING (SEM) APPROACH</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">DUE</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_XZH6Uud">
					<orgName type="full">National Science Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">NSF/ CISE</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">MSU</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mark</forename><surname>Urban-Lurain</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Science and Mathematics Education at</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit6">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit7">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit8">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit9">Michigan State University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michigan</forename><surname>State</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Science and Mathematics Education at</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit6">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit7">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit8">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit9">Michigan State University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jon</forename><surname>Sticklen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Science and Mathematics Education at</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit6">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit7">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit8">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit9">Michigan State University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Daina</forename><surname>Briedis</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Science and Mathematics Education at</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit6">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit7">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit8">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit9">Michigan State University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Science and Mathematics Education at</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit6">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit7">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit8">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit9">Michigan State University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Neeraj</forename><surname>Buch</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Science and Mathematics Education at</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit6">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit7">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit8">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit9">Michigan State University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Science and Mathematics Education at</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit6">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit7">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit8">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit9">Michigan State University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Wolff</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Science and Mathematics Education at</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit6">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit7">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit8">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit9">Michigan State University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Science and Mathematics Education at</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit6">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit7">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit8">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit9">Michigan State University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">AC 2009-1022: UNDERSTANDING FACTORS CONTRIBUTING TO RETENTION IN ENGINEERING: A STRUCTURAL EQUATION MODELING (SEM) APPROACH</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T17:42+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Dr. Briedis has been involved in several areas of education research including student retention, curriculum redesign, and the use of technology in the classroom. She is a co-PI on two NSF grants in the areas of integration of computation in engineering curricula and in developing comprehensive strategies to retain early engineering students. She is active nationally and internationally in engineering accreditation and is a Fellow of ABET.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Retention of early engineering students is a nation-wide concern that will affect the strength of the future engineering workforce and, hence, the role of the United States as a dominant world player in engineering and technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> . Michigan State University (MSU) and Lansing Community College (LCC) were recently awarded a five-year NSF STEP grant (STEM Talent Expansion Program) to increase retention by 10% over current levels at our large, researchintensive institution. The project is titled Engaging Early Engineering Students to Expand Numbers of Degree Recipients (EEES).</p><p>The major research challenge in this project is to understand the interactions among the various components of the project. Our engineering curricula are not lock-step, so students may elect to participate in various programs and the interactions among the interventions may vary by student and the choices they make. These challenges make traditional statistical techniques difficult to use.</p><p>Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) is a multivariate procedure that supports hypothesis-testing of causal models in observational studies without the need for random assignment of participants to treatment and control groups. This paper outlines our project, introduces SEM and the models we are evaluating and discusses the data collection, management and analysis we are implementing to track the various components of the project. The methods are appropriate for other in situ studies of educational interventions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Overview of EEES</head><p>EEES targets two groups of students who are at-risk for leaving engineering: 1) students who are academically capable of completing an engineering degree but perceive the education environment of early engineering as being unsupportive and not engaging <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> ; and 2) students who struggle with core prerequisite courses, mainly calculus and physics. Analysis of our past student retention patterns show that grades in these core courses are the best predictors of future admission to Engineering in the junior year. The goal of the EEES project will be achieved through the synergistic deployment of four components designed to involve engineering faculty in rethinking the structure of the introductory courses.</p><p>EEES has four components as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. They are: 1) Connector faculty; 2) Peer Assisted Learning (PAL); 3) Course cross linkages; and (4) Diagnostic (DX) Driven Early Intervention. Details of these components of the EEES project are available in other papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> .</p><p>EEES targets students in four key technical courses taken by early engineering students to prepare them for upper level disciplinary courses: pre-calculus algebra and trigonometry (MTH 116), calculus 1 (MTH 132), physics 1 (PHY 183) and computation-based problem solving (EGR 102). The four EEES components are shown in the bubbles in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. The dark boxes show groups of faculty or students who are part of the implementation of EEES. The dark bubble shows the target group: early engineering students.</p><p>Page 14.1295.2</p><p>Since the mathematics and physics courses are outside of the College of Engineering, the EGR 102 course is the primary locale for engaging engineering faculty in 1) changing the curriculum;</p><p>2) incorporating more active-learning, team-based projects, and integrating mathematics and physics into the curriculum; and 3) fostering a sense of engineering community among faculty and students. To support students who are struggling with the crucial calculus courses, we implemented two interventions. The first is a series of online diagnostic (DX) tests that provide formative feedback to students about the areas in which they need to focus their studying. By providing early and frequent opportunities for students to check their progress, the DX program allows students to seek additional help with these courses. To provide that assistance, we implemented a program of Supplemental Instruction <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> , which we have called Peer Assisted Learning. The goal of this program is to provide undergraduate peer-led study sessions that target difficult courses, not at-risk students.</p><p>In addition to addressing academic issues, some of the interventions we designed for EEES are based on literature that shows that many students leave STEM disciplines not because they are academically incapable, but because they find the academic environment in these disciplines unsupportive and have serious reservations about future careers in STEM disciplines <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> . To address these needs, we created a Connector Faculty program that pairs incoming first year engineering students with engineering faculty <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> . The goal of this program is to create a welcoming atmosphere for students where they can feel connected to the community of faculty and upper division students in the college.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Questions</head><p>Our research questions include: That is, does participating in multiple components have an additive, multiplicative, or negative interaction? Does this differ by types of students?</p><p>Answers to these questions will be crucial to the formative evaluation of EEES, for continuous quality improvement on the program, and to provide a basis for helping students decide what components of EEES to draw upon.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Challenges</head><p>The major research challenge in this project is to understand the interactions among the different types of at-risk students, different interventions, and final outcomes over the course of the project. Since the project is being implemented college-wide, it is not feasible to compare contemporaneous students who are and are not participating in the interventions. Furthermore, students may elect to participate in various parts of the program (or not) and the interactions among the interventions may vary by student and the choices they make. These challenges make traditional statistical techniques difficult to use.</p><p>In traditional statistical analysis, when we want to predict future successful admission to engineering based on the grades in calculus and physics, we could create a regression equation.</p><p>For example, we would define Y as a binary dependent variable (admit/no admit), and X i as the independent variables of grades in the i-th calculus and physics courses of interest. Each of the independent variables has a weight, β i , that is calculated to reduce the overall error, ε, of the equation. The resulting regression equation would be:</p><p>In regression, the assumption is that the individual measurement errors are randomly distributed and that all of the variance which is unaccounted for is subsumed in a single error term, ε. However, while this equation captures the observed variables (X i ), we have little information that allows us to understand what factors influenced these variables. Furthermore, regression and other multivariate techniques assume that the independent variables are in fact, independent. That is, the values of X 1 and X 2 should not be correlated. Yet, we know from previous studies that students who do well in one course tend to do well in other courses. At our university, overall GPA correlates with grades in individual courses at about r = .6 or more, depending on the course.</p><p>As noted above, when we analyzed the grades of students who were previously accepted or declined admission to engineering, we found that grades in calculus courses (followed closely by physics) had the strongest correlation with admission to engineering and final GPA at graduation. The grades in these courses are the observed variables, which we infer are measuring some latent variable such as mathematical knowledge. It is the underlying latent variable that is of interest but we have only the proxy variable of a grade in a course that has been measured. As we plan an intervention, we must be careful not to focus only on the observed variable (course grade) but to intervene in a manner that will affect the latent variable (mathematical knowledge) which, in turn, should result in a higher course grade. If we simply focus on improving the course grade, then it is possible that we will help students improve their grades in the target courses, only to face a subsequent hurdle in later courses because they do not have the necessary mathematical knowledge.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Structural Equation Modeling</head><p>Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) is a multivariate procedure that supports hypothesis-testing of causal models in observational studies without the need for random assignment of participants to treatment and control groups <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> . By focusing on covariance structures and including explicit error terms in the models, rather than trying to minimize residuals as in traditional multivariate techniques <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> , it is possible to estimate latent variables (e.g., engagement, persistence, academic ability) that are theorized to be the "causes" of observed variables (e.g., grades, retention). Generally SEM is used for hypothesis testing to see how well a hypothesized model fits the data, rather than for exploratory model building. However, it is possible to compare different models as a data exploration technique. SEM is a relatively recent technique (Bollen 10 provides historical background) that gained wider acceptance with the creation of the LISREL software to support the calculations needed. SEM does not appear to have been used very much in Engineering Education research. A search of ASEE conference proceedings for the terms "structural equation modeling" and "SEM" did not turn up any papers since 1996. Vogt <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> recently used SEM to model the impact of faculty interactions with students on retention in engineering.</p><p>SEM includes other techniques such as path analysis and factor analysis and usually represents the models by a path diagram rather than in the form of equations. SEM path diagrams show the relationships among the variables and can be used to represent standard regression models.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> shows the path representation of the previous regression equation that we created using AMOS <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> , software that supports SEM analysis. Page 14.1295.5</p><p>In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>, each of the observed independent variables -grades in the various courses -is shown by a box on the left side of the figure. The dependent variable, admit, is show by the box in the middle of the diagram. The proportional variances (r-square) for each of the independent variables are shown by the straight arrows labeled r2. The error term is shown by the circle because it is a latent variable. In other words, we presume that there is error, but we do not explicitly identify or measure it -it is simply everything not measured by the observed variables plus any measurement error. The straight arrows represent that the independent variables plus the error term account for the variance of the dependent variable. The curved arrows represent the interactions, or covariance, among the independent variables. To analyze data with AMOS, the user specifies a model graphically as shown above, then attaches variables from a dataset to the boxes. The software then solves the model and calculates the beta weights for the independent variables in a traditional least-squares manner.</p><p>So far, using SEM in this manner does not provide any particular advantage over traditional statistical techniques. However, the advantage of SEM emerges when we want to analyze more complex situations that are not easily modeled as a single linear equation among observed variables. Building on the previous example, when we use regression to model the admission decision, all of the error is collapsed into a single error term. Often, the predictor variables (i.e., the grades in the courses) can account for the majority of the variance, but the parts of the unaccounted-for variance are all collapsed into the single error term. In practice, there are likely differing amounts of error associated with the different variables. In addition, the grades in the individual courses are inter-related (r ≈ .6), which can cause some prediction instabilities in the model. One reason for this inter-relationship among the course grades is that the observed variables (grades) are a manifestation of latent (unobservable) variables such as academic ability or motivation. Using SEM, we can re-specify a hypothetical model as shown in Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>.</p><p>The model shown in Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> is a modification of previous model shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>. Here, the interaction terms among the observed variables have been removed and two latent variables are</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A SEM Model for EEES</head><p>We are in the first year of the EEES project and are beginning to implement the various components of the project: Connector Faculty, Peer Assisted Learning, DX Intervention, and Cross-Course Linkages. These changes are occurring within the larger setting of ongoing programs throughout the college of engineering. However, all new incoming students are participating in these programs. Therefore, we cannot compare students (or cohorts of students) who are participating in the various components of EEES to understand how the individual components work. Furthermore, EEES was designed to be a series of interconnected components, so it is unreasonable to try to examine any individual component alone. Yet, we will want to understand the components individually to see what works and to make improvements to the individual components. We believe that SEM has the potential to help us understand the contributions of each component plus the interactions among the components.</p><p>To address these research needs, we have begun to collect a large amount of data on students and faculty in the College of Engineering. These data include student demographic data (class standing, gender, ethnicity, ACT scores); assignment, exam and course grades in the core preengineering courses; course grades in other courses; math diagnostic exam scores; number of PAL sessions attended; number of meetings with Connector Faculty, surveys/interviews on student perceptions of the various components of the EEES program; surveys/interviews on student engagement and desire to persist in engineering. We are tracking students from their first year in the program through one of three outcomes: 1) students who graduate with an engineering degree; 2) students who are academically qualified for engineering but elect to leave for other majors; and 3) students who apply but are not admitted to engineering due to insufficient GPA. Our goal is to understand what, if any, affect the EEES program has on these three types of students and how different students respond to the various components.</p><p>Our hypothesized model is shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4</ref>. Recall that the observed variables are shown in boxes. These are the variables we can measure and include our outcome variables (degree completion/leaving/no admit), other observable variables (demographics, grades, test results, number of PAL sessions and CF meetings attended) and indirect measures of engagement and persistence (surveys and interviews.) Each observed variable has measurement error shown by the black circle with an arrow pointing to it.</p><p>Persistence is necessary if a student is going to succeed in any academic discipline, but particularly in one as demanding as engineering <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> . The ability to learn from mistakes and change tactics is crucial but requires ongoing support. We anticipate that the support of the peer mentors in the PAL program and interactions with the Connector Faculty will help motivate students to persist in the face of these challenges and help them acquire the skills needed to become successful engineers.</p><p>Engagement is crucial to support students' intrinsic motivation, which, in turn, is crucial to learning <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> . While the challenge of problem-solving can be engaging for engineers, supporting new students and helping engage them requires more than the far-off goal of engineering work after graduation. It is important to help new students feel welcomed as part of the community of engineers and scaffold their engagement as part of that community <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref>   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Anticipated Outcomes</head><p>SEM can test hypothesized causal models to determine how well the observed data fit the proposed model. However, the large number of nodes in this model requires substantial datasets. At Michigan State University, we have about 1000 incoming first-year students who express interest in engineering and take the pre-engineering curriculum, but they are not formally admitted to engineering until their junior year. These numbers are sufficient for the complexity of the hypothesized model. However, we will have to track these students throughout their programs before we will have outcome data and can completely test the model. Since we are just completing the first year of the project, we have begun collecting data for this cohort. By the end of next year, we will begin to have seen some attrition and will accept or decline students to engineering so we will be able to begin evaluating the model fit at that time.</p><p>When SEM models are fit with data, the software tests the fit of the resulting model using chisquare tests. The goal is to have a good fit, that is, not to reject the proposed model, so we look for p &gt; .05 (usually substantially higher) to show that the model fits. If the model fits, then the resulting parameter estimates associated with each path in the model indicate how much of the variance of that part of the model is accounted for by each of the subcomponents. For example, in the proposed model, there are three factors that directly influence degree completion: GPA, persistence and engagement. Of these, only GPA is an observed variable. However, GPA is a function of all of the other grades in the courses, which, in turn, are a function of academic ability and PAL support. However, academic ability is influenced by persistence and engagement which are influenced by PAL support and CF support. Each of these paths will have weights that will tell us the proportional contribution of each of the subcomponents, when considered in the context of the whole system. In that way, we will be able to understand the relative contributions of the components of EEES and use that data to improve and refine the various components.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>Improving student retention in engineering programs requires a multi-faceted approach that addresses academic, social and personal issues that vary across an increasingly heterogeneous student population. The EEES project is taking a four-prong approach to this problem: 1) Connector faculty; 2) Peer Assisted Learning (PAL); 3) Course Cross Linkages; and (4) Diagnostic (DX) Driven Early Intervention. These components are inter-related and cannot be evaluated in isolation from each other, presenting a challenge for traditional statistical techniques. In this paper we have presented an introduction to Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) which can be used to analyze complex, inter-related systems consisting of a mixture of observed and latent variables. SEM makes it possible to propose and test causal models using observational data that educational researchers routinely encounter and can be used in a variety of settings to gain deeper insight into the factors affecting educational outcomes.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: EEES Schematic Diagram.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,72.00,178.68,467.52,359.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Path representation of regression equation</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Hypothesized Model for EEES</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Which groups of students are impacted by which components of EEES? Do different EEES components have different impact on students who are not struggling academically but might leave due to the climate in the College of Engineering compared with students who are struggling academically? Do different components have different impact on women and underrepresented groups? 4. What are the interactions among the EEES components for different groups of students?</figDesc><table><row><cell>1. What are the changes in retention as a result of EEES?</cell></row><row><cell>2. What are the impacts of each of the components of EEES on retention? That is, what</cell></row><row><cell>proportion of the variance is accounted for by each component?</cell></row><row><cell>3.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. Both the Connector Faculty and PAL components of EEES are designed to do that. Page 14.1295.8</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell># CF</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Meetings</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>CF</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Support</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>CF</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Survey</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Surveys /</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Interviews</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Engagement</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Surveys / Interviews</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Degree Completion</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Persistence</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Leavers</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Academic</cell><cell>GPA</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ability</cell><cell></cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Admit</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Math DX</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Results</cell></row><row><cell>ACT</cell><cell>Other Grades</cell><cell>EGR Grades</cell><cell>Physics Grades</cell><cell>Math Grades</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell># PAL</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Sessions</cell><cell>PAL</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Support</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>PAL</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Survey</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgement</head><p>This material is based upon work supported by the <rs type="funder">National Science Foundation</rs> under award <rs type="grantNumber">0757020</rs> (DUE). Any opinions, findings and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the <rs type="funder">National Science Foundation (NSF)</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><p><rs type="person">Jon Sticklen</rs> is the Director of the Applied Engineering Sciences major, <rs type="affiliation">College of Engineering, Michigan State University</rs>. <rs type="person">Dr. Sticklen also</rs> serves as the College Coordinator for engineering education research, and is an Associate Professor in the Computer Science and Engineering Department, <rs type="funder">MSU</rs>. <rs type="person">Dr. Sticklen</rs> has lead a laboratory in knowledge-based systems focused on task specific approaches to problem solving. More recently, <rs type="person">Dr. Sticklen</rs> has pursued engineering education research focused on early engineering; his current research is supported by <rs type="funder">NSF</rs>/<rs type="funder">DUE</rs> and <rs type="funder">NSF/ CISE</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_XZH6Uud">
					<idno type="grant-number">0757020</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>added: academic ability and motivation. We cannot directly measure these variables, but they are hypothesized to be the causal variables behind the observed variables of grades in each of the courses. These latent traits are assumed to be characteristics of each individual student that affect student outcomes in the course. Academic ability and motivation are shown as co-varying by the double-headed arrow because they are hypothesized to influence each other. That is, students who are motivated, tend to work harder and perform better. But students who perform better receive positive feedback which in turns motivates them. Academic ability and motivation are both shown as affecting course grades, but each one has separate arrow because the weights of these are computed independently. It may be that motivation has differing influence on performance in different courses, so these are allowed to vary independently. By acknowledging that measurement is error-prone and including measurement errors for each of the observed variables, SEM makes it possible to provide unbiased estimates for the latent variables (academic ability and motivation.) In addition to including the latent variables, SEM also allows the specification of error terms on each observed variable, rather than a single error term for the entire model. This facilitates modeling the affect of the latent variables by partitioning the error across the different independent variables by minimizing each error term in order to calculate the optimal weights for each of the paths in the model.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno>NSB-02-1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">National Science Board Science and Engineering Indicators</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-04">2002. April, 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>National Science Foundation: Arlington, VA</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding our students: A longitudinal study of success and failure in engineering with implications for increased retention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bernold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Spurlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Anson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Engineering Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracking the processes of change in US undergraduate education in science, mathematics, engineering, and technology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Seymour</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="105" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Talking about leaving: why undergraduates leave the sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Seymour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hewitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<publisher>Westview Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">429</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Boulder; Colo</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Briedis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Buch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Collins-Eaglin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Erlich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fleming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hinds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sticklen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Urban-Lurain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Wolff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Connector faculty: A friendly face for early engineering students, ASEE Conference and Exposition</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Austin, TX; Austin, TX</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">June 14-17. 2009. 2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">IEEE</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Engaging early engineering students (EEES): Background and goals of an NSF STEP project to increase retention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sticklen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wolff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Bauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Briedis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Buch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Courtney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ehrlich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fleming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Heckman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mickelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Paquette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Urban-Lurain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Weil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">June 14-17. 2009. 2009</date>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Austin, TX; Austin, TX</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Breaking the attrition cycle: The effects of supplemental instruction on undergraduate performance and attrition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Blanc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Debuhr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Higher Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="80" to="90" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Research studies on the effectiveness of supplemental instruction in mathematics. New Directions for Teaching and Learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kenney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kallison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="82" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural equation modeling with AMOS: Basic concepts, applications, and programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Byrne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N.J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">338</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<publisher>Mahwah</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>p xiv</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Structural equations with latent variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bollen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<publisher>Wiley: New York</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">514</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>p xiv</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Faculty as a critical juncture in student retention and performance in engineering programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Vogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Engineering Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Arbuckle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">Amos 17.0. 2008</date>
			<publisher>SPSS, Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Crawfordville, FL</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Academic perseverance, class attendance, and performance in the college classroom</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Van Blerkom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ERIC</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">407618</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factors influencing the self-efficacy beliefs of first-year engineering students</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hutchison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Follman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sumpter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bodner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Engineering Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An examination of indicators of engineering students&apos; success and persistence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>French</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Immekus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Oakes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Engineering Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="419" to="425" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of college major persistence based on vocational interests, academic preparation, and first-year academic performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Robbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research in Higher Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="62" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motivation and instruction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Stipek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of educational psychology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Berliner</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Calfee</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Eds</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Library</forename><surname>Macmillan</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Usa</forename><surname>Reference</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Schuster</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Macmillan</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice Hall International</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="113" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">How people learn: Brain, mind, experience and school</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bransford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cocking</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<publisher>National Academy Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">319</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Situated learning: Legitimate peripheral participation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lave</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Wenger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
