<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Examining The Relationship Between Empathy, Helpfulness, Respect and Fairness: A Path Analysis Işıner SEVER a* (ORCID ID -0000-0001-5381-6976) Ömür GÜRDOĞAN BAYIR b (ORCID ID -0000-0002-7455-7237)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Article</forename><surname>Info</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Education</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hakkari University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hakkari</settlement>
									<country>Turkiye</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Makale</forename><surname>Bilgisi Öz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Education</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Anadolu University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Eskişehir</settlement>
									<country>Turkiye</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Examining The Relationship Between Empathy, Helpfulness, Respect and Fairness: A Path Analysis Işıner SEVER a* (ORCID ID -0000-0001-5381-6976) Ömür GÜRDOĞAN BAYIR b (ORCID ID -0000-0002-7455-7237)</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.14812/cufej.605274</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received Revised Accepted 14.08.2019 07.01.2020 13.03.2020</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T19:21+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Social studies</term>
					<term>value education</term>
					<term>empathy</term>
					<term>helpfulness</term>
					<term>respect</term>
					<term>fairness</term>
					<term>path analysis Sosyal bilgiler</term>
					<term>değer eğitimi</term>
					<term>Empati</term>
					<term>yardımseverlik</term>
					<term>saygı</term>
					<term>adil olma</term>
					<term>yol analizi</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In this study, it was aimed to examine the presence and power of prediction of the relationships among the behaviors of empathy, respect, helpfulness and fairness. In the proposed hypothetical model, three powers of prediction were examined: the power of empathy to predict helpfulness and respect, the power of helpfulness and respect to predict fairness, and finally the power of empathy to predict fairness through respect and helpfulness. A total of 332 fourth-grade elementary school students participated in the study. Structural equation modeling was employed to analyze the data. The findings of the study show that the ability to empathize had a large effect on the emergence of the behaviors of helpfulness and respect. However, the effect of the behaviors of helpfulness and respect on fairness was found to be moderate in size. Finally, the indirect effect of empathy on fairness mediated by the behaviors of respect and helpfulness was found to be significant and moderate.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>The act of an individual to understand the emotions and thoughts of a person before him by putting himself in the place of that person is defined as empathy. In other words, empathy is to be able to look at events from someone else's window and to be aware of feelings, emotions and experiences. Empathy, which involves understanding what others experience and feel, is to exhibit compassion. In this context, empathy consists of three fundamental elements: someone's (1) addressing the events and situations from the perspective of a person before him by putting himself in the place of that person, (2) accurately understanding the feelings and thoughts of that person before him, and (3) conveying the created empathic understanding to the recipient side <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Dökmen, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Yılmaz, 2016)</ref>. Empathy can be addressed under cognitive and sensory dimensions because it involves understanding personal problems, thoughts of others, and empathic anxiety <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Decety &amp; Cowell, 2015)</ref>. Individuals with empathy skills can be healthier and happier by establishing healthier relationships with their environment <ref type="bibr">(Şimşek &amp; Öztürk, 2014)</ref>.</p><p>Empathy is closely related to sensitivity, solidarity and helping each other <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Kabapınar, 2004)</ref>. Empathy is important in terms of adhering to social rules, helping without expecting nothing in return, and serving public interest. This is because individuals who have high social sensitivity and are more congruent with the society are more likely to help others <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Dökmen, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">McDonald and Messinger, 2011</ref> as cited in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Cartabuke et al., 2017)</ref>. Helping others ensures to strengthen the connectedness among individuals in the community, eliminate shortcomings and fill gaps. In order for societies to maintain their existence, it is necessary that individuals demonstrate solidarity and helpfulness behaviors. Helpfulness is a value that every individual should have, including traits such as to use their own opportunities for the good of others, doing a work voluntarily, and the work done by people who are sensitive <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Aktepe, 2010)</ref>.</p><p>Helpfulness is a value that has emerged as a necessity of social life. Individuals who make up the society differ from each other in terms of variables such as intelligence, physical appearance, and social status. These differences can make individuals disadvantaged in certain subjects. In minimizing the aforementioned disadvantages, helpfulness plays an important role. Helpfulness contributes to individuals' living together. Respect is another value that contributes to the ability of individuals with different characteristics who constitute the society to live together. Respect includes many subjects such as self-esteem, respect for others, respect for characteristics and possessions of others, respect for laws, and respect for cultural differences and religion <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Kılınç, 2015)</ref>. Respect for diversity is also closely related to tolerance, being open-minded and having empathy <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Kabapınar, 2004)</ref>. Empathy with the other side will help an individual to respect differences <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Kabapınar, 2012)</ref>.</p><p>Respect that constitutes a person's original identity must be defined during childhood. Respect that is regarded as a sense of value is important because of the rights that individuals have such as the right to live, have education, be healthy, think, and believe. Individuals must respect these rights <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Yılmaz, 2016)</ref>. A person who does not adhere to respect cannot appreciate other values. Respect for claims of individuals represents the essence of the concept of justice. Therefore, justice is closely related to respecting the rights of others. In other words, the values of justice and respect are intertwined. Justice, which is of great importance to social life, can be defined as a framework that makes it possible for people to live together. The idea of equality constitutes the basis of justice <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Aral, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Çengelci Köse, 2017)</ref>.</p><p>The sense and desire of equality generally get formed in childhood. Children are aware of what may be fair or what may be wrong. Therefore, children pay attention to observe justice <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Aral, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">KEDV, 2006</ref><ref type="bibr">as cited in Eren, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Moore, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">)</ref>. Justice is one of the cornerstones of social behaviors. It is closely related to a whole range of social behaviors and skills, such as seeing and understanding another person's perspective and interpreting social situations <ref type="bibr">(Rosenthal et al., 2008</ref><ref type="bibr">as cited in Hod-Shemer et al., 2018)</ref>. For example, empathy and justice are closely associated with emotions and play a key role in social interaction. The sense of injustice is also a sign that something must be done to change the status quo <ref type="bibr">(Frith, 2006)</ref>. To this respect, empathy can be thought of something important in promoting fair behaviors. But the relations among empathy, morality and justice are complex <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Decety and Cowell, 2015)</ref>. Therefore, when explaining some of the skills and values that individuals have, it is also important to explain other skills and values that are closely related to them. It is also important that students grasp these values as a whole because the values are closely related to each other.</p><p>Research reveals the relationships among the values of empathy, helpfulness, respect and fairness. It is stated in the literature that empathy predicts values such as respect, tolerance, responsibility and friendship <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Dereli &amp; Aypay, 2012)</ref>, and that there is a positive correlation between empathy and helpfulness behaviors in the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Duru, 2004)</ref>. Based on his research, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Erken (2009)</ref> has reached the conclusion that students with high empathy skills are fairer, more tolerant, helpful, respectful and patient. In the study conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hod-Shemer et al. (2018)</ref> on preschool children, it has been concluded that having empathy skills, explaining problems and finding solutions to problems are the basis for the development of the value of justice in children. However, there are studies in the literature referring to the relationship between social empathy and social justice <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Cartabuke et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Gerdes et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Segal 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Segal and Wagaman, 2017)</ref>.</p><p>As mentioned in the above paragraphs, it is stated in the literature that there are significant relationships among the behaviors of empathy, helpfulness, respect and fairness. However, there is no study where a model for possible relationships between these behaviors is proposed. In this context, it was aimed in this study to examine the presence and power of prediction of the relationships among the values of empathy, respect, helpfulness and fairness. Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> presents the hypothetical model tested in the study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1. Proposed Hypothetical Model</head><p>In the proposed hypothetical model, three powers of prediction were aimed to be examined: the power of empathy to predict helpfulness and respect, the power of helpfulness and respect to predict fairness, and finally the power of empathy to predict fairness through respect and helpfulness. The findings obtained from this research study are expected to contribute to the subject of values education.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method</head><p>This research study is a descriptive study as it reveals an existing situation. Structural equation modeling was employed to analyze the data of the study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participants</head><p>The data of the study was collected in the 2017-2018 spring semester from 400 fourth-year elementary school students determined using random sampling method in Tepebaşı district of Eskişehir. From the data, 40 cases were excluded due to incomplete forms. To ensure normality, 28 cases were excluded from the analyses as their calculated z scores were outside the range of -3 to +3. In this context, analyses were carried out using the data of 332 students. Of the students included in the study, 189 were females and 143 were males. Of these students, 65 were the only child, 187 had two siblings, 80 had three or more siblings. Mothers of 21 of the students who participated in the study were not literate, and of 74 were elementary school graduates, of 66 were middle school graduates, of 99 were high school graduates, and of 72 were university graduates. Fathers of five students were not literate, of 46 were elementary school graduates, of 66 were middle school graduates, of 114 were high school graduates, and of 101 were university graduates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Empathy</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Helpfulness</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Respect</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Fairness</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Instrument</head><p>In this study, the "Personal Information Form", the "Fairness Tendency Scale", the "Respect Tendency Scale", the "Helpfulness Scale" and the "Empathetic Tendency Scale" were used to collect data.</p><p>Personal Information Form: The personal information of the participants in the study were collected by using the Personal Information Form. The information form included information on gender, how many siblings the participants had in the family, and the parental education status.</p><p>Fairness Tendency Scale: The scale was developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Sarmusak (2011)</ref>. The scale consisted of 9 items in a single dimension. The variance explained by the scale was 34.01%. Factor loadings of the items forming the scale ranged between .758 and .336. The Cronbach Alpha internal consistency coefficient of the scale was .73. A higher score on the scale suggested that the tendency to be fair was high. The minimum score on the scale was 9, and the maximum score was 36.</p><p>Respect Tendency Scale: The scale developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Sarmusak (2011)</ref> consisted of 20 items and a single dimension. Factor loadings of the items that made up the scale varied between .697 and .341, and the total variance it explained was 30.26%. The Cronbach Alpha internal consistency coefficient of the scale was .77. The minimum score on the scale was 14, and the maximum score was 56. A higher score suggested that the tendency to be respectful was high.</p><p>Helpfulness Scale: The scale, developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Demirci (2017)</ref>, consisted of 7 items in one dimension. The variance that the scale explained was 42.62%. Factor loadings of the items forming the scale ranged between .74 and .50. The Cronbach Alpha internal consistency coefficient of the scale was .76. Fit index values of the Helpfulness Scale as a result of a confirmatory factor analysis were stated to be X 2 = 41.74, p &lt; .001, CFI = .98, NFI = .96, NNFI = .96, SRMR = .037, and RMSEA = .066.</p><p>Empathetic Tendency Scale: The scale, developed by <ref type="bibr">Kaya and Siez (2010)</ref>, consisted of a total of 13 items in 2 dimensions, and the total variance it explained was 44.308%. Factor loadings of the items forming the scale ranged between .73 and .54. The Cronbach Alpha internal consistency coefficient of the scale was .92. Fit index values of the scale as a result of a confirmatory factor analysis were stated to be X 2 = 76.97, p &lt; .001, CFI = .99, GFI = .97, AGFI = .95, RMSA = .02, and SRMR = .04.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Collection and Analysis</head><p>The data of the study were collected using the data collection instruments consisting of the Personal Information Form, Fairness Tendency Scale, Respect Tendency Scale, Empathetic Tendency Scale and Helpfulness Scale. Research data were collected by researchers. The data collection tool was applied after the relevant explanations were made to the students. The data collection process of each class, including explanations, took approximately one lesson hour. SPSS and LISREL package programs were used in the analysis of the research data. In the study, the Personal Information Form was analyzed through frequencies. The measurement models of fairness tendency, respect tendency, empathic tendency and helpfulness variables were tested using confirmatory factor analysis, and the relationships among the variables were determined through path analysis. The statistical significance level was set to be .05 in this study. The covariance matrix and the maximum likelihood method were employed. In the study, the fit indices Chi Square, RMSEA, RMR, SRMR, NFI, NNFI and CFI were used to determine whether the measurement models and the hypothetical model were confirmed in this study. Due to the fact that AGFI and GFI are sensitive to sampling, they were not taken into consideration.</p><p>The preliminary condition of the structural equation model was examined before the hypothetical model was tested in the study. In this context, first, the multicollinearity relationships between the variables were checked. Therefore, the correlational relationships between the variables and the VIF and tolerance values of the independent variables were discussed. Accordingly, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> presents the correlation values.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, the magnitudes of correlations between the variables were smaller than .80 <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Field, 2009)</ref>. Therefore, it was found that there was no multicollinearity relationship between the variables. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> shows the VIF and tolerance values of the independent variables. As shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>, the VIF values of empathetic tendency, fairness, respect, and helpfulness were 1.90, 1.38, 1.39, and 1.95, respectively. Because these values were smaller than 10, it can be said that there was no multicollinearity problem <ref type="bibr">(Myers, 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr">O'Connel, 1990</ref><ref type="bibr">as cited in Field, 2009)</ref>. Tolerance values of empathetic tendency, fairness, respect, and helpfulness were .53, .72, .72, and .51, respectively. Accordingly, the tolerance values of the variables were greater than .20, which indicates that there was no collinearity problem <ref type="bibr">(Menard, 1995</ref><ref type="bibr">as cited in Field, 2009)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Findings</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Findings on the Testing of the Measurement Models</head><p>In this study, it was investigated whether the hypothetical model for relations among fairness tendency, respect tendency, helpfulness and empathic tendency was confirmed. Within this scope, the measurement models of the variables in the model were tested first.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The measurement model of the Fairness Tendency Scale</head><p>The one-dimensional Fairness Tendency Scale was examined by using first-level confirmatory factor analysis. Based on the results obtained, t values varied between 1.96 and 12.01, and indicated significant relationships at the p level of .05. The fit indices for this model were X 2 (27, N = 332) = 65.75, p &lt; .05, x 2 /df = 2.43, RMSEA = .066, SRMR = .056, CFI = .95, and NNFI = .93. These findings show that the measurement model of the Fairness Tendency Scale was confirmed at the first level <ref type="bibr">(Brown,2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kline, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Steiger, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tabachnick &amp; Fidell, 2001)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The measurement model of the Respect Tendency Scale</head><p>The one-dimensional Respect Tendency Scale was examined by using first-level confirmatory factor analysis. Based on the results obtained, t values varied between 5.11 and 14.70, and indicated significant relationships at the p level of .01. The fit indices for this model were X 2 (77, N = 332) = 335.22, p &lt; .01, x 2 /df = 4.35, RMSEA = .10, SRMR = .075, CFI = .92, and NNFI = .90. These findings show that the measurement model of the Respect Tendency Scale was confirmed at the first level <ref type="bibr">(Brown,2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kline, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Sümer, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tabachnick &amp; Fidell, 2001)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The measurement model of the Empathic Tendency Scale</head><p>The two-dimensional Empathic Tendency Scale was examined by using second-level confirmatory factor analysis. Based on the results obtained, t values varied between 10.48 and 14.84, and indicated significant relationships at the p level of .01. The fit indices for this model were X 2 (64, N = 332) = 119.74, p &lt; .01, x 2 /df = 1.87, RMSEA = .051, SRMR = .038, CFI = .98, and NNFI = .98. These findings show that the measurement model of the empathic tendency scale was confirmed at the second level <ref type="bibr">(Brown,2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Hu &amp; Bentler, 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kline, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Sümer, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tabachnick &amp; Fidell, 2001)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The measurement model of the Helpfulness Scale</head><p>The one-dimensional Helpfulness Scale was examined by using first-level confirmatory factor analysis. Based on the results obtained, t values varied between 3.09 and 15.46, and indicated significant relationships at the p level of .01. The fit indices for this model were X 2 (14, N = 332) = 39.46, p &lt; .01, x 2 /df = 2.81, RMSEA = .074, SRMR = .039, CFI = .97, and NNFI = .96. These findings show that the measurement model of the Helpfulness Scale was confirmed at the first level <ref type="bibr">(Brown,2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kline, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Sümer, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tabachnick &amp; Fidell, 2001)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Findings on the Testing of the Hypothetical Model</head><p>In this study, the model proposed for the relationships among fairness tendency, respect tendency, helpfulness and empathic tendency was tested through path analysis and given in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 2. Structural Equation Model for The Proposed Model</head><p>When the t values in the model were examined, the path coefficients between empathetic tendency, respect, helpfulness and fairness were found to be significant at the p level of 01. The goodness fit indices of the established model were X 2 (460, N = 332) = 1100.50, x 2 /df = 2.39, RMSEA = .065, SRMR = .076, CFI = .94, and NNFI = .94. It can be said that the proposed model was confirmed when the fit indices are taken into consideration <ref type="bibr">(Brown,2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kline, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Steiger, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Sümer, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tabachnick &amp; Fidell, 2001)</ref>. When the total variance values explained by the model were examined, the variance that empathy explained in the helpfulness variable was .70, and the variance it explained in the respect variable was .31. The variance that the helpfulness and respect variables explained in the fairness variable was .38. The variance explained in the fairness variable by the empathy variable through the helpfulness and respect variables was .21.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Findings on Direct Effects</head><p>In the structural model, the indirect effect of empathy on fairness through respect and helpfulness was significant. Accordingly, as the empathy tendency increased, the respect and helpfulness tendencies increased, and the fairness tendency increased as these two tendencies increased. The standardized path coefficient for the indirect effect in this relationship was 0.46 (p &lt; .01). This value indicates that the effect size was moderate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion &amp; Conclusion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion on Direct Effects</head><p>It was found in this study that the empathy variable significantly and directly predicted the helpfulness and respect variables among the elementary school students. Moreover, the helpfulness and respect variables significantly and directly predicted the fairness variable.</p><p>In the study, empathy was found to be a variable that highly predicted helpfulness (β = .84). It can be said that the finding in question corresponded to those found in the previous research in the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Batson, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Batson, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Davis, 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Deutsch, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Erken, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Hoffman, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kühnlenz, Sosnowski, Buß et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Toi &amp; Batson, 1982)</ref>. Similarly, Van der Mark, Van Ijzendoorn and Bakermans-Kranenburg ( <ref type="formula">2002</ref>) have indicated that children with high levels of empathy are less aggressive and more helpful. It can be argued that it is necessary to be aware of the emotional state of a person who is in need of help in order for the helpfulness behavior to emerge. It can be asserted that empathy assumes a key role in the emergence of this awareness and motivates the behavior of helping.</p><p>Through the findings of the study, empathy was found to be a variable that highly predicted respect (β = .55). It can be argued that this finding is consistent with the research in the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Dereli &amp; Aypay, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Erken, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Jeffers, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr">Uğur, 2007)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Breyer and Gigliotti (1980)</ref> have expressed that empathetic preferences are the series of preferences that do not interfere with the rights of others in the current social decision literature. Breyer and Gigliotti have stated that empathetic individuals have a great tolerance for respecting others' use of their rights, and that tolerance may be manifested by means of empathy. In a manner similar to helpfulness, it can be said that it is an important factor for someone to understand the emotional state of the individual before him in the emergence of the behavior of being respectful.</p><p>According to the findings, helpfulness was found to be a variable that moderately predicted fairness (β = .24). In their study, Schwartz and Bilsky have expressed that the sense of justice feeds on the support of other people's welfare <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Schwartz, 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Schwartz &amp; Bilsky, 1990</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">, 1987)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Karremans and Van Lange (2005)</ref> have also stated that justice is in a deep relationship with values that observe the welfare of others. It can be argued that the power of helpfulness to predict fairness is also theoretically significant when it is taken into account that the dynamics underlying the helpfulness behavior are the welfare of others.</p><p>As a results of the study, respect was found to be a variable that moderately predicted fairness (β = .47). It can be argued that this finding is consistent with the research in the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Heuer et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Hill, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Sashkin &amp; Williams, 1990)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Sashkin and Williams (1990)</ref> have stated that being fair is predicted by the emotions of attaching importance to people and respecting them. Referring to Kant's perspective, <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Hill (2000)</ref> has stated that respect as a moral ideal reveals the demand for justice, which is a deeper necessity than the tangible necessities of human beings. From this viewpoint, individuals who are respectful can be argued to have internalized being fair in parallel to the aforementioned necessity. However, it may be thought that respecting the rights of others would require fairness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion on Indirect Effects</head><p>According to the findings of this study, the variables of helpfulness and respect mediate the relationship between the empathy and fairness variables (β = .46, p &lt; .01). Accordingly, as empathy increases, helpfulness and respect increase, and as these two variables increase, fairness increases. In other words, the empathy behavior can be said to improve the fairness behavior by supporting helpfulness and respect. It can be argued that this finding is consistent with the research in the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Batson, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Lasa Aristu et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Nam, Jost &amp; Feldman, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Segal, 2011)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Batson (1991), and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Miller and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Eisenberg (1988)</ref> have stated that empathy is a prerequisite for helping others and asking for justice on their behalf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Segal (2011)</ref> has expressed that empathy creates social empathy within the social context, and social empathy triggers the demand for social justice. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Segal (2011)</ref> has indicated that social empathy is a combination of personal empathy and the awareness of social inequality. This means that social empathy emerges when an empathetic individual has a grasp of social inequalities/injustices. It can be thought that the idea of respecting the rights of others underlies a perception of social inequality/injustice. An individual may exhibit the behavior of helpfulness at the next stage to solve the inequality/injustice that was mentioned. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Hoffman (2000)</ref> has indicated that there is a relationship between empathy and prosocial behaviors, and that empathy encourages a person to comply with certain moral principles. As proposed in the model of the study, it is thought that empathy predicts respect and helpfulness, which are some of the prosocial behaviors, and that empathy is also considered to predict fairness, which is another prosocial behavior, through respect and helpfulness.</p><p>The findings of the study show that empathy skills have a large effect on the emergence of helpfulness behavior. In addition, empathy was found to have a large effect on the emergence of respect. Empathy appears to be decisive in the emergence of respect behavior although not as much decisive as in the emergence of helpfulness behavior. When the fairness behavior was examined, helpfulness was found to have a moderate effect on fairness. The size of the effect of respect behavior on fairness was greater when compared to that of helpfulness. The inference that can be made from this is that the effect of respect behavior on fairness was more decisive than that of helpfulness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recommendations for Educators</head><p>In light of the findings obtained within the scope of this study, it can be argued that empathy has significant effects on the behaviors of helpfulness, respect and fairness. It is important to focus on the importance of empathy in order to have students gain the values of helpfulness, respect and fairness, and to cover empathy skills in "values education" programs. However, variables that mediate the indirect effect of empathy on the behavior of fairness are the variables of helpfulness and respect. It can be said that it is important to take into consideration the two behaviors that were mentioned in having students become fair and to include these behaviors in the education program to be prepared.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recommendations for Researchers</head><p>While designing this study, it was also aimed to examine the behavior of tolerance in addition to the behaviors of empathy, helpfulness, respect and fairness. However, the measurement instrument used to measure the behavior of tolerance was excluded from the scope because it did not show a good fit in the confirmatory factor analysis. The inability to include tolerance, which is considered to be closely related to the values examined, can be considered as a limitation of the study. A more comprehensive outcome can be achieved in future research by examining the value mentioned and other values that are considered to be related.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Türkçe Sürümü</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Giriş</head><p>Toplumsal yapının bir parçası olan bireyler kendilerinden farklı fiziksel özelliklere, duygu ve düşüncelere, dini inanışlara, ekonomik düzeye, kültürel ve eğitsel geçmişe sahip diğer bireylerle bir arada yaşarlar. Bu farklılıklardan kaynaklanan durumlarla baş etmek için bireylerin bazı bilgi, beceri ve değerlerle donanmış olması gerekir. Bu bilgi, beceri ve değerler birbiriyle yakından ilişkili olduğu gibi, aynı zamanda karmaşık ve çok boyutludur. Birbiriyle yakından ilişkili olan bu değer ve beceriler bireylerin birbirini anlamasını ve buna göre davranmasını sağlar.</p><p>Bireyin kendisini karşısındaki insanın yerine koyarak onun duygu ve düşüncelerini doğru anlaması empati olarak tanımlanmaktadır. Başka bir deyişle empati; olaylara başkasının penceresinden bakabilmek, hislerin, duyguların ve deneyimlerin farkında olmaktır. Başkalarının ne yaşadığını ve hissettiğini anlayabilmeyi içeren empati, eşduyum sergilemektir. Bu kapsamda empati, kendisini karşısındaki kişi yerine koyarak olayları ve durumları onun bakış açısıyla ele alma, karşıdaki kişinin duygu ve düşüncelerini doğru olarak anlama ve oluşturulan empatik anlayışı karşı tarafa iletme olmak üzere üç temel ögeden oluşmaktadır <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Dökmen, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Yılmaz, 2016)</ref>. Empati; bireysel sorunları, başkalarının düşüncelerini anlamayı ve empatik kaygıyı barındırması nedeniyle bilişsel ve duyuşsal boyutlar altında ele alınabilir <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Decety &amp; Cowell, 2015)</ref>. Empati becerisine sahip bireyler daha sağlıklı ilişkiler kurarak çevresiyle barışık ve mutlu olabilirler <ref type="bibr">(Şimşek &amp; Öztürk, 2014)</ref>.</p><p>Empati; duyarlılık, dayanışma ve yardımlaşma ile yakından ilişkilidir <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Kabapınar, 2004)</ref>. Empati; sosyal kurallara uyma, karşılık beklemeden yardım etme ve toplum yararına davranışlar sergileme bakımından önemlidir. Çünkü sosyal duyarlılığı yüksek ve topluma daha uyumlu olan empatik bireylerin yardım etme davranışları daha yüksektir <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Dökmen, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">McDonald &amp; Messinger, 2011</ref><ref type="bibr">'den akt. Cartabuke ve diğerleri, 2017)</ref>. Yardım etme toplumdaki bireyler arasındaki bağlılığı güçlendirmeyi, eksiklikleri gidermeyi ve boşlukları doldurmayı sağlar. Toplumların varlıklarını sürdürmeleri, dayanışmaya ve bireylerin yardımseverlik davranışlarını sergilemelerine bağlıdır. Yardımseverlik, kendi olanaklarını başkalarının iyiliği için kullanma, bir işi gönüllü olarak yapma, duyarlı olan insanların yaptığı iş gibi özellikleri içinde barındıran, her bireyin sahip olması gereken bir değerdir <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Aktepe, 2010)</ref>.</p><p>Yardımlaşma, toplumsal yaşamın bir gereği olarak ortaya çıkmış bir değerdir. Toplumu oluşturan bireyler; zekâ, fiziksel görünüm, sosyal statü gibi değişkenler açısından birbirlerinden farklıdır. Bu farklılıklar bireyleri bazı konularda dezavantajlı duruma getirebilir. Sözü edilen dezavantajın en aza indirgenmesinde yardımlaşma önemli rol oynar. Yardımlaşma bireylerin bir arada yaşamasına katkıda bulunur. Toplumu oluşturan farklı özellikteki bireylerin bir arada yaşayabilmesinde önemli katkısı olan diğer bir değer ise saygıdır. Saygı; özsaygı, başkalarına saygı, başkalarının özelliklerine ve mülkiyete saygı, kanunlara saygı, kültürel farklılıklar ve dine saygı gibi birçok konuyu içermektedir <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Kılınç, 2015)</ref>. Farklılıklara saygı; hoşgörü, açık fikirli olma ve empati ile de yakından ilişkilidir <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Kabapınar, 2004)</ref>. Karşı tarafla kurulan empati, bireye farklılıklara saygı gösterme konusunda yardımcı olacaktır <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Kabapınar, 2012)</ref>.</p><p>İnsanın özgün kimliğini oluşturan saygı çocuk yaşta tanımlanmalıdır. Değer görme duygusu olarak ele alınan saygı, bireylerin sahip olduğu yaşama, eğitim, sağlık, düşünme, inanış vb. haklardan dolayı önemlidir. Bireyler bu haklara saygılı olmak durumundadır <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Yılmaz, 2016)</ref>. Saygıyı tanımayan bir insan diğer değerleri yaşayamaz. Bireylerin hak taleplerine duyulan saygı adalet kavramının özünü oluşturmaktadır. Bu nedenle adalet, başkalarının haklarına saygı duymakla yakından ilişkilidir. Başka bir ifadeyle; adalet ve saygı değerleri iç içe değerlerdir. Toplumsal yaşam için büyük bir önem taşıyan adalet, insanların bir arada yaşamalarını olanaklı kılan bir çerçeve olarak tanımlanabilir. Eşitlik düşüncesi, adaletin temelini oluşturmaktadır <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Aral, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Çengelci Köse, 2017)</ref>.</p><p>Eşitlik duygusu ve istemi daha çocukluk çağında oluşmaktadır. Çocuklar neyin adil olduğunun ya da neyin yanlış olabileceğinin farkındadırlar. Bu nedenle çocuklar adaleti göz önünde bulundurarak davranmaya özen gösterirler <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Aral, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">KEDV, 2006</ref><ref type="bibr">'dan akt. Eren, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Moore, 2009)</ref>. Adalet sosyal davranışların temel taşlarından biridir. Adalet, bir başkasının bakış açısını görüp anlamak, sosyal durumları yorumlamak gibi bir dizi sosyal davranış ve beceri ile yakından ilişkilidir (Rosenthal ve diğerleri, 2008'den akt. Hod-Shemer ve diğerleri, 2018). Örneğin, empati ve adalet, duygularla yakından ilişkilidir ve sosyal etkileşimde kilit rol oynar. Adaletsizlik duygusu da mevcut durumu değiştirmek için bir şeyler yapılması gerektiğinin bir işaretidir <ref type="bibr">(Frith, 2006)</ref>. Buna dayanarak adil davranışları teşvik etmede empatinin önemli olduğu düşünülebilir. Ancak empati, ahlak ve adalet arasındaki ilişkiler karmaşıktır <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Decety &amp; Cowell, 2015)</ref>. Bu nedenle bireylerin sahip olduğu bazı beceri ve değerleri açıklamada onlarla yakından ilişkili olan diğer beceri ve değerleri de açıklamak önemlidir. Aynı zamanda, değerlerin birbiri ile yakından ilişkili olması nedeniyle öğrencilerin bu değerleri bir bütün halinde kavraması da önem taşımaktadır.</p><p>Alanyazındaki araştırmalar empati, yardımseverlik, saygı ve adil olma değerleri arasındaki ilişkileri ortaya koymaktadır. Alanyazında empatinin; saygı, hoşgörü, sorumluluk ve dostluk gibi değerleri yordadığı <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Dereli &amp; Aypay, 2012)</ref>, empati ile yardım etme davranışı arasında pozitif yönlü bir ilişki olduğu <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Duru, 2004)</ref> ifade edilmektedir. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Erken (2009)</ref>, yaptığı araştırmada empati becerisi yüksek öğrencilerin daha adaletli, hoşgörülü, yardımsever, saygılı ve sabırlı davrandıkları sonucuna ulaşmıştır. Hod-Shemer vd. ( <ref type="formula">2018</ref>) tarafından okulöncesi dönem çocuklarıyla yapılan araştırmada ise çocuklarda adalet değerinin gelişmesinde; empati becerisine sahip olma, sorunları açıklama ve bunlara çözüm bulmanın temel oluşturduğu sonucuna ulaşılmıştır. Bununla birlikte alanyazında sosyal empati ve sosyal adalet arasındaki ilişkiye değinen araştırmalar bulunmaktadır <ref type="bibr">(Cartabuke vd., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Gerdes vd., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Segal 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Segal &amp; Wagaman, 2017)</ref>.</p><p>Alanyazında -yukarıdaki paragraflarda da sözü edildiği üzere-; empati, yardımseverlik, saygı ve adil olma davranışları arasında anlamlı ilişkilerin olduğu ifade edilmektedir. Ancak bu davranışlar arasındaki olası ilişkilere yönelik bir modelin önerildiği çalışmaya rastlanmamıştır. Bu bağlamda, bu araştırmada empati, saygı, yardımseverlik ve adil olma değerleri arasındaki ilişkiler ve yordama güçleri incelemek amaçlanmıştır. Araştırmada test edilen hipotetik model Şekil 1'de sunulmuştur.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Şekil 1. Önerilen Hipotetik Model</head><p>Önerilen hipotetik modelde; empatinin yardımseverlik ve saygılı olmayı, yardımseverlik ve saygılı olmanın adil olmayı ve son olarak empatinin saygı ve yardımseverlik değerleri aracılığıyla adil olmayı yordama gücü incelenmek istenmiştir. Bu araştırmadan elde edilen bulguların, değer eğitimi konusuna katkıda bulunması beklenmektedir.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Yöntem Katılımcılar</head><p>Araştırmanın verileri 2017-2018 Bahar Dönemi'nde Eskişehir ili Tepebaşı İlçesi'ndeki ilkokullara devam eden 400 dördüncü sınıf öğrencilerinden seçkisiz örnekleme yöntemiyle toplanmıştır. Verilerden 40 tanesi, formlar eksik doldurulduğundan elenmiştir. Normalliğin sağlanması için hesaplanan z puanları sonrasında -3, +3 aralığının dışında kalan 28 veri analize dahil edilmemiştir. Bu kapsamda 332 öğrencinin verisiyle analizler yapılmıştır. Çalışmaya dahil edilen öğrencilerin 189'u kız, 143'ü erkektir. Bu öğrencilerden 65'i tek çocuk, 187'si iki kardeş, 80'i üç ve üzeri kardeşe sahiptir. Çalışmaya katılan öğrencilerden 21'inin annesi okuma-yazma bilmezken, 74'ü ilkokul, 66'sı ortaokul, 99'u lise ve 72'si Empati Yardımseverlik Saygılı olma Adil olma üniversite mezunudur. Öğrencilerin beşinin babası okuma yazma bilmezken, 46'sı ilkokul, 66'sı ortaokul, 114'ü lise, 101'i üniversite mezunudur.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Kullanılan Veri Toplama Araçları</head><p>Bu araştırmada "Kişisel Bilgi Formu", "Adil Olma Eğilimi Ölçeği", "Saygılı Olma Eğilimi Ölçeği", "Yardımseverlik Ölçeği" ve "Empatik Eğilim Ölçeği" kullanılmıştır.</p><p>Kişisel Bilgi Formu: Araştırmadaki katılımcıların kişisel bilgileri kişisel bilgi formu ile toplanmıştır. Bilgi formunda cinsiyet, ailede kaç kardeş oldukları ve anne baba eğitim durumu yer almaktadır.</p><p>Adil Olma Eğilimi Ölçeği: Sarmusak (2011) tarafından geliştirilen tek boyutta 9 maddeden oluşan ölçeğin açıkladığı varyans Ölçeği oluşturan maddelerin faktör yükleri ,758 ile ,336 değerleri arasında değişmektedir. Ölçeğin Cronbach Alpha iç tutarlık katsayısı ,73'tür. Ölçekten alınan puanın yüksek olması adil olma eğiliminin yüksek olduğunu göstermektedir. Ölçekten alınabilecek minimum puan 9, maksimum puan 36'dır.</p><p>Saygılı Olma Eğilimi Ölçeği: <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Sarmusak (2011)</ref> tarafından geliştirilen ölçek 20 madde ve tek boyuttan oluşmaktadır. Ölçeği oluşturan maddelerin faktör yükleri ,697 ile ,341 değerleri arasından değişmekte olup açıkladığı toplam varyans %30,26'dır. Ölçeğin Cronbach Alpha iç tutarlık katsayısı ,77'dir. Ölçekten alınabilecek minimum puan 14, maksimum puan 56'dır. Puanın yüksek olması saygılı olma eğiliminin yüksek olduğunu göstermektedir.</p><p>Yardımseverlik Ölçeği: Demirci (2017) tarafından geliştirilen ölçek tek boyutta 7 maddeden oluşmaktadır. Ölçeğin açıkladığı varyans %42,62'dir. Ölçeği oluşturan maddelerin faktör yükleri ,74 ile ,50 değerleri arasında değişmektedir. Ölçeğin Cronbach Alpha iç tutarlık katsayısı ,76'dır. Yardımseverlik Ölçeği'nin doğrulayıcı faktör analizi sonucunda uyum indeks değerleri; X 2 = 41,74, p &lt; .001; CFI = .98; NFI = .96; NNFI = .96; SRMR = .037; RMSEA = .066 olduğu ifade edilmiştir.</p><p>Empatik Eğilim Ölçeği: Kaya ve Siez (2010) tarafından geliştirilen ölçek 2 boyutta toplam 13 maddeden oluşmakta olup açıkladığı toplam varyans % 44,308'dir. Ölçeği oluşturan maddelerin faktör yükleri ,73 ile ,54 değerleri arasında değişmektedir. Ölçeğin Cronbach Alpha iç tutarlık katsayısı ,92'dır. Ölçeğin doğrulayıcı faktör analizi sonucunda uyum indeks değerleri; X 2 = 76,97, p &lt; .001; CFI = .99; GFI = .97; AGFI = ,95, RMSEA = ,02; SRMR= ,04 olduğu ifade edilmiştir.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Verilerin Toplanması ve Analizi</head><p>Araştırmanın verileri kişisel bilgi formu, adil olma eğilimi ölçeği, saygılı olma eğilimi ölçeği, empatik eğilim ölçeği ve yardımseverlik ölçeklerinden oluşan veri toplama aracıyla elde edilmiştir. Araştırma verileri araştırmacılar tarafından toplanmıştır. Veri toplama aracı öğrencilere gerekli açıklamalar yapıldıktan sonra uygulanmıştır. Her bir sınıfın veri toplama süreci, açıklamalar dâhil olmak üzere, yaklaşık olarak bir ders saati sürmüştür. Araştırma verilerinin analizinde SPSS ve LISREL paket programları kullanılmıştır. Araştırmada kişisel bilgiler formunun analizinde frekanstan yararlanılmıştır. Adil olma eğilimi, saygılı olma eğilimi, empati eğilimi ve yardımseverlik değişkenlerinin ölçme modelleri doğrulayıcı faktör analizi ile değişkenler arasındaki durum ise yol analizi testi ile test edilmiştir. İstatistiksel anlamlılık düzeyi ,05 alınan bu araştırmada kovaryans matrisi ve en çok olabilirlik yöntemi kullanılmıştır. Araştırmada ölçme modellerinin ve hipotetik modelin doğrulanıp doğrulanmadığının belirlenmesinde uyum indekslerinden ki kare, RMSEA, RMR, SRMR, NFI, NNFI ve CFI ele alınmıştır. AGFI ve GFI'nın örnekleme duyarlı olması nedeniyle <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Kline, 2005)</ref>  Tablo 2'de görüldüğü gibi VIF değerlerinin empatik eğilim için 1.90, adil olma için 1.38, saygılı olma 1.39 ve yardımseverlik için 1.95'tir. Bu değerler 10'un altında olduğu için çoklu doğrusallık probleminin olmadığı söylenebilir <ref type="bibr">(Myers, 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr">O'Connel, 1990</ref><ref type="bibr">akt. Field, 2009)</ref>. Tolerans değerleri ise empatik olma için .53, adil olma için .72, saygılı olma için .72 ve yardımseverlik için .51 olduğu görülmektedir. Buna göre değişkenlerin tolerans değerlerinin .20'nin üzerinde olması doğrusallık sorununun olmadığını göstermektedir <ref type="bibr">(Menard, 1995</ref><ref type="bibr">akt. Field, 2009)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bulgular Ölçme Modellerinin Test Edilmesine İlişkin Bulgular</head><p>Bu araştırmada adil olma eğilimi, saygılı olma eğilimi, yardımseverlik ve empatik eğilim arasındaki ilişkilere yönelik hipotetik modelin doğrulanıp doğrulanmadığı incelenmiştir. Bu kapsamda, öncelikle modelde yer alan değişkenlerin ölçme modelleri test edilmiştir.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adil olma eğilimi ölçeğinin ölçme modeli</head><p>Tek boyutlu olan adil olma eğilimi ölçeği birinci düzey doğrulayıcı faktör analizi ile incelenmiştir. Elde edilen sonuçlar doğrultusunda t değerleri 1.96 ile 12.01 arasında değişmekte ve .05 düzeyinde anlamlı ilişkiler göstermektedir. Bu modele ait uyum indeksleri X 2 (27, N=332) =65,75, p&lt;.05; x 2 /sd = 2,43; RMSEA = .066; SRMR = .056; CFI = .95; NNFI = .93'dür. Bu bulgular adil olma eğilimi ölçeği ölçme modelinin birinci düzeyde doğrulandığını göstermektedir <ref type="bibr">(Brown,2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kline, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Steiger, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tabachnick &amp; Fidell, 2001)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Saygılı olma eğilimi ölçeğinin ölçme modeli</head><p>Tek boyutlu olan saygılı olma eğilimi ölçeği birinci düzey doğrulayıcı faktör analizi ile incelenmiştir. Elde edilen sonuçlar doğrultusunda t değerleri 5.11 ile 14.70 arasında değişmekte ve .01 düzeyinde anlamlı ilişkiler göstermektedir. Bu modele ait uyum indeksleri X 2 (77, N=332) =335.22, p&lt;.01; x 2 /sd = 4,35; RMSEA = .10; SRMR = .075; CFI = .92; NNFI = .90'dır. Bu bulgular saygılı olma eğilimi ölçeği ölçme modelinin birinci düzeyde doğrulandığını göstermektedir <ref type="bibr">(Brown,2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kline, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Sümer, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tabachnick &amp; Fidell, 2001)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Empatik eğilim ölçeğinin ölçme modeli</head><p>İki boyutlu olan empatik eğilim ölçeği ikinci düzey doğrulayıcı faktör analizi ile incelenmiştir. Elde edilen sonuçlar doğrultusunda t değerleri 10.48 ile 14.84 arasında değişmekte ve .01 düzeyinde anlamlı ilişkiler göstermektedir. Bu modele ait uyum indeksleri X 2 (64, N=332) =119.74, p&lt;.01; x 2 /sd = 1,87; RMSEA = .051; SRMR = .038; CFI = .98; NNFI = .98'dir. Bu bulgular empatik eğilimi ölçeği ölçme modelinin ikinci düzeyde doğrulandığını göstermektedir <ref type="bibr">(Brown,2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Hu &amp; Bentler, 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kline, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Sümer, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tabachnick &amp; Fidell, 2001)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Yardımseverlik ölçeğinin ölçme modeli</head><p>Tek boyutlu olan yardımseverlik ölçeği birinci düzey doğrulayıcı faktör analizi ile incelenmiştir. Elde edilen sonuçlar doğrultusunda t değerleri 3.09 ile 15.46 arasında değişmekte ve .01 düzeyinde anlamlı ilişkiler göstermektedir. Bu modele ait uyum indeksleri X 2 (14, N=332) =39.46, p&lt;.01; x 2 /sd = 2,81; RMSEA = .074; SRMR = .039; CFI = .97; NNFI = .96'dır. Bu bulgular yardımseverlik ölçeği, ölçme modelinin birinci düzeyde doğrulandığını göstermektedir <ref type="bibr">(Brown,2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kline, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Sümer, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tabachnick &amp; Fidell, 2001)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hipotetik Modelin Test Edilmesine İlişkin Bulgular</head><p>Bu çalışmada adil olma eğilimi, saygılı olma eğilimi, yardımseverlik ve empatik eğilim arasındaki ilişkilere yönelik önerilen model yol analizi ile test edilmiş ve Şekil 2'de verilmiştir.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Şekil 2. Önerilen Modele İlişkin Yapısal Eşitlik Modeli</head><p>Modeldeki t değerleri incelendiğinde empatik eğilim, saygılı olma, yardımseverlik ve adil olma arasındaki yol katsayılarının .01 düzeyinde anlamlı olduğu bulunmuştur. Kurulan modelin uyum iyiliği indeksleri X 2 (460, N=332) =1100,50; x 2 /sd = 2,39; RMSEA = .065; SRMR = .076; CFI = .94; NNFI = .94'dür. Uyum indeksleri göz önünde bulundurulduğunda önerilen modelin doğrulandığı söylenebilir <ref type="bibr">(Brown,2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kline, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Steiger, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Sümer, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tabachnick &amp; Fidell, 2001)</ref>. Modelde açıklanan toplam varyans değerleri incelendiğinde empatik olmanın; yardımseverlik değişkeninde açıkladığı varyans .70, saygılı olma değişkeninde açıkladığı varyans .31'dir. Yardımseverlik ve saygılı olma değişkenlerinin adil olma değişkeninde açıkladığı varyans .38'dir. Empatik olma değişkeninin yardımseverlik ve saygılı olma değişkenleri yoluyla adil olma değişkeninde açıkladığı varyans ise .21'dir.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Doğrudan Etkilere İlişkin Bulgular</head><p>Modeldeki doğrudan etkilere ait bulgular incelendiğinde empatinin yardımseverliği yordadığı görülmektedir (Standardize yol katsayısı=0.84). Buna göre empati eğilimi arttıkça yardımseverlik eğilimi de artmaktadır. İki değişken arasındaki standardize edilmiş yol katsayısı, empatinin yardımseverlik üzerindeki etki büyüklüğünün yüksek düzeyde <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Suhr, 2008)</ref> olduğunu göstermektedir. Modeldeki doğrudan etkilere ait bulgular incelendiğinde empatinin saygılı olmayı da yordadığı görülmektedir (Standardize yol katsayısı= 0.55). Buna göre empati eğilimi arttıkça saygılı olma eğilimi de artmaktadır. İki değişken arasındaki standardize edilmiş yol katsayısı, empatinin saygılı olma üzerindeki etki büyüklüğünün yüksek düzeyde olduğunu göstermektedir. Modeldeki doğrudan etkilere ait bulgular incelendiğinde yardımseverliğin adil olmayı yordadığı görülmektedir (Standardize yol katsayısı=0.24). Buna göre yardımseverlik arttıkça adil olma da artmaktadır. İki değişken arasındaki standardize edilmiş yol katsayısı, yardımseverliğin adil olma üzerindeki etki büyüklüğünün orta düzeyde <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Suhr, 2008)</ref> olduğu görülmektedir. Benzer şekilde saygılı olmanın da adil olmayı yordadığı görülmektedir (Standardize yol katsayısı=0.47). İki değişken arasındaki standardize edilmiş yol katsayısı saygılı olmanın adil olma üzerindeki etki büyüklüğünün yine orta düzeyde olduğunu göstermektedir.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dolaylı Etkilere İlişkin Bulgular</head><p>Yapısal modelde empatinin saygılı olma ve yardımsever olma aracılığıyla adil olma üzerindeki dolaylı etkisi anlamlıdır. Buna göre empati eğilimi arttıkça saygılı olma ve yardımseverlik eğilimi artmakta, bu iki eğilim arttıkça da adil olma eğilimi artmaktadır. Bu ilişkide dolaylı etkiye ait standardize edilmiş yol katsayısı 0.46'dır (p&lt;.01). Bu değer, etki büyüklüğünün orta düzeyde olduğunu göstermektedir.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tartışma ve Öneriler</head><p>Bu araştırmada; empati değişkeninin adil olma değişkenini, yardımseverlik ve saygılı olma değişkenleri aracılığıyla yordama gücünü test etmek için geliştirilen hipotetik model doğrulanmıştır. Modele ilişkin bulgular doğrudan etkiler ve dolaylı etkiler başlıkları altında tartışılmıştır.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Doğrudan Etkilere İlişkin Tartışma</head><p>Bu araştırmada ilkokul öğrencilerinde empati değişkeninin yardımseverlik ve saygılı olma değişkenlerini, yardımseverlik ve saygılı olma değişkenlerinin de adil olma değişkenini doğrudan ve anlamlı düzeyde yordadığı bulunmuştur.</p><p>Araştırmada empatinin yardımseverliği yüksek düzeyde yordayan bir değişken olduğu belirlenmiştir (β=.84). Sözü edilen bulgu alanyazındaki önceki araştırmalar ile örtüşmektedir <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Batson, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Batson, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Davis, 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Deutsch, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Erken, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Hoffman, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kühnlenz, Sosnowski, Buß vd., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Toi &amp; Batson, 1982)</ref>. Benzer biçimde <ref type="bibr">Van der Mark, Van Ijzendoorn ve Bakermans-Kranenburg (2002)</ref> empati düzeyi yüksek olan çocukların daha az saldırgan ve daha çok yardımsever olduğunu belirtmektedir. Yardım etme davranışının ortaya çıkabilmesi için öncelikli olarak yardıma muhtaç kişinin içinde bulunduğu duygu durumunun farkında olunmasının gerekli olduğu söylenebilir. Bu farkındalığın ortaya çıkışında empatinin anahtar rol üstlendiği ve yardım etme davranışına motivasyon oluşturduğu öne sürülebilir.</p><p>Araştırmada empatinin saygılı olmayı yüksek düzeyde yordayan bir değişken olduğu belirlenmiştir (β=.55). Bu bulgu alanyazındaki araştırmalarla örtüşmektedir <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Dereli &amp; Aypay, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Erken, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Jeffers, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr">Uğur, 2007)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Breyer ve Gigliotti (1980)</ref> mevcut sosyal karar alanyazınında; empatik tercihlerin, başkalarının haklarına müdahale etmeyen tercih dizileri olduğunu ifade etmektedir. Breyer ve Gigliotti, empatik bireylerin başkalarının haklarını kullanmalarına saygı konusunda yüce bir hoşgörüye sahip olduklarını ve bu hoşgörünün de empati ile ortaya çıkıyor olabileceğini ifade etmektedirler. Yardımseverliğe benzer biçimde saygılı olma davranışının da ortaya çıkışında, karşıdaki bireyin duygu durumunun anlaşılabiliyor olmasının önemli bir etken olduğu söylenebilir.</p><p>Araştırmada yardımseverliğin adil olmayı orta düzeyde yordayan bir değişken olduğu belirlenmiştir (β=.24). Schwartz ve Bilsky yaptıkları araştırmalarda adalet duygusunun, başka insanların refahının desteklenmesinden beslendiğini ifade etmektedir <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Schwartz, 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Schwartz &amp; Bilsky, 1990</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">, 1987)</ref>. Karremans ve Van Lange (2005) de adaletin, başkalarının refahını gözeten değerlerle derin bir ilişki içerisinde olduğunu ifade etmektedir. Yardımseverlik davranışının temelinde yatan dinamiğin başkalarının refahı olduğu göz önünde bulundurulduğunda yardımseverliğin adil olma üzerindeki yordayıcılığının kuramsal olarak da anlamlı olduğu söylenebilir.</p><p>Araştırmada saygılı olmanın adil olmayı orta düzeyde yordayan bir değişken olduğu belirlenmiştir. (β=.47). Bu bulgu alanyazındaki araştırmalarla örtüşmektedir <ref type="bibr">(Heuer vd., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Hill, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Sashkin &amp; Williams, 1990)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Sashkin ve Williams (1990)</ref> adil olmanın, insanlara önem verme ve onlara saygı duyma duyguları tarafından yordandığını ifade etmektedir. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Hill (2000)</ref> Kant'ın perspektifine göre; ahlaki bir ideal olarak saygının, insanın somut gereksinimlerinden daha derin bir gereksinim olan adalet talebini ortaya çıkardığını ifade etmektedir. Bu bakış açısıyla saygılı bireylerin sözü edilen gereksinime paralel olarak adil olmayı içselleştirdikleri öne sürülebilir. Bununla birlikte başkalarının haklarına saygılı olmanın, adil olmayı gerektireceği düşünülebilir.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dolaylı Etkilere İlişkin Tartışma</head><p>Bu araştırmanın bulgularına göre yardımseverlik ve saygılı olma değişkenleri empati ile adil olma değişkenleri arasındaki ilişkiye aracılık etmektedir (β=.46 p&lt;.01). Buna göre empati yükseldikçe; yardımseverlik ve saygılı olma yükselmekte, bu iki değişken yükseldikçe de adil olma yükselmektedir. Bir başka ifadeyle empati davranışının, yardımseverliği ve saygılı olmayı destekleyerek adil olma davranışını artırdığı söylenebilir. Sözü edilen bulgu alanyazındaki araştırmalarla örtüşmektedir <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Batson, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lasa Aristu vd., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Nam, Jost &amp; Feldman, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Segal, 2011)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Batson (1991</ref><ref type="bibr">), Miller ve Eisenberg (1988)</ref> empatinin başkalarına yardım etme ve onlar adına adalet istemede bir önkoşul olduğu ifade edilmektedir. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Segal (2011)</ref> ise empatinin toplumsal bağlam içerisinde sosyal empatiyi yarattığını, sosyal empatinin de sosyal adalet talebini tetiklediğini ifade etmektedir. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Segal (2011)</ref> sosyal empatinin; bireysel empati ile toplumsal eşitsizliğe ilişkin bir farkındalığın birleşimi olduğunu belirtmektedir. Yani empatik birey, sosyal eşitsizlik/adaletsizliklerle ile ilgili bir kavrayışa sahip olduğunda sosyal empati ortaya çıkmaktadır. Sosyal eşitsizlik/adaletsizlikle ilgili bir kavrayışın temelinde, başkalarının haklarına saygı konusunun yer aldığı düşünülebilir. Bundan sonraki aşamada birey sözü edilen eşitsizlik/adaletsizliğe çözüm amacıyla yardımda bulunma davranışı sergileyebilir. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Hoffman (2000)</ref> empati ile prososyal davranışlar arasında bir ilişkinin olduğunu; empatinin kişiyi bazı ahlaki ilkelere uymaya teşvik ettiğini ifade etmektedir. Araştırmanın modelinde de önerildiği üzere; empatinin prososyal davranışlardan olan saygı ve yardımseverliği yordadığı, empatinin aynı zamanda saygı ve yardımseverlik üzerinden diğer bir prososyal davranış olan adil olmayı yordadığı düşünülmektedir.</p><p>Yapılan araştırmanın bulguları yardımseverlik davranışının ortaya çıkışında empati becerisinin yüksek etki büyüklüğüne sahip olduğunu göstermektedir. Ayrıca saygı davranışının ortaya çıkışında da empatinin etki büyüklüğünün yüksek olduğu belirlenmiştir. Saygı davranışının ortaya çıkışında empati; yardımseverlik davranışındaki kadar olmasa da, yine de önemli düzeyde belirleyici görünmektedir. Adil olma davranışı incelendiğinde; yardımseverliğin adil olma üzerindeki etki büyüklüğünün orta düzeyde olduğu belirlenmiştir. Saygı davranışının adil olma üzerindeki etki büyüklüğü ise yardımseverliğe göre daha yüksektir. Buradan çıkarılacak yorum saygı davranışının adil olma üzerindeki etkisinin, yardımseverliğe kıyasla daha belirleyici olduğudur.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Eğitimcilere Öneriler</head><p>Çalışma kapsamında elde edilen bulgular ışığında, empatinin yardımseverlik, saygı ve adil olma davranışları üzerinde önemli etkilerinin olduğu söylenebilir. Yardımseverlik, saygı ve adil olma değerlerinin öğrencilere kazandırılmasında empati becerisinin önemle üzerinde durulmasının, değer eğitimi programlarında empati becerisine yer verilmesinin önemli olduğunu ifade edilebilir. Bununla birlikte empatinin adil olma davranışı üzerindeki dolaylı etkisine aracılık eden değişkenler, yardımseverlik ve saygılı olma değişkenleridir. Adil olma davranışının öğrencilere kazandırılmasında sözü edilen iki davranışın dikkate alınmasının ve hazırlanan eğitim programında bu davranışlara yer verilmesinin önemli olduğu söylenebilir.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Araştırmacılara Öneriler</head><p>Bu çalışma tasarlanırken; empati, yardımseverlik, saygılı olma ve adil olma davranışlarının yanı sıra hoşgörülü olma davranışı da incelenmek istenmiştir. Ancak hoşgörülü olma davranışını ölçmek için kullanılan ölçme aracı yapılan doğrulayıcı faktör analizinde iyi uyum göstermediği için kapsam dışında bırakılmıştır. İncelenen değerlerle yakından ilişkili olabileceği düşünülen hoşgörü değerinin çalışmaya dâhil edilememesi araştırmanın bir sınırlılığı olarak düşünülebilir. Yapılacak olan araştırmalarda; sözü edilen değerin ve ilişkili olduğu düşünülen başka değerlerin de incelenmesi ile konuyla ilgili daha kapsamlı bir sonuca ulaşılabilir.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Correlation</figDesc><table><row><cell>Values Between Variables</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Empathetic</cell><cell>Helpfulness</cell><cell>Respect</cell><cell>Fairness</cell></row><row><cell>Tendency</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Empathetic Tendency</cell><cell>.67*</cell><cell>.40*</cell><cell>.38*</cell></row><row><cell>Helpfulness</cell><cell></cell><cell>.41*</cell><cell>.41*</cell></row><row><cell>Respect</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.46*</cell></row><row><cell>As shown in the Table</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>The</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">VIF and Tolerance Values of the Variables</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>VIF</cell><cell>Tolerance</cell></row><row><cell>Empathetic Tendency</cell><cell>1.90</cell><cell>.53</cell></row><row><cell>Fairness</cell><cell>1.38</cell><cell>.72</cell></row><row><cell>Respect</cell><cell>1.39</cell><cell>.72</cell></row><row><cell>Helpfulness</cell><cell>1.95</cell><cell>.51</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>dikkate alınmamıştır.Araştırmada hipotetik model test edilmeden önce yapısal eşitlik modelinin ön koşulu incelenmiştir. Bu kapsamda öncelikle değişkenler arasındaki çoklu doğrusallık ilişkisine bakılmıştır. Bu nedenle, değişkenler arasındaki korelasyon ilişkisi ve bağımsız değişkenlerin VIF ve tolerans değerleri ele alınmıştır. Buna göre korelasyon değerleri Tablo 1'de sunulmuştur.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Tablo 1.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Değişkenler Arasındaki Korelasyon Değerleri</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Empatik Eğilim</cell><cell>Yardımseverlik</cell><cell>Saygılı Olma</cell><cell>Adil Olma</cell></row><row><cell>Empatik Eğilim</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.67*</cell><cell>.40*</cell><cell>.38*</cell></row><row><cell>Yardımseverlik</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.41*</cell><cell>.41*</cell></row><row><cell>Saygılı Olma</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.46*</cell></row><row><cell>*p&lt; .01</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Tabloda görüldüğü gibi, değişkenler arasındaki korelasyon ,80 altındadır (Field, 2009). Bu nedenle,</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">değişkenler arasında çoklu doğrusallık ilişkisinin olmadığı görülmüştür. Bağımsız değişkenlerin VIF ve</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">tolerans değerleri Tablo 2'de gösterilmiştir.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Tablo 2.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Değişkenlerin VIF ve Tolerans değerleri</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>VIF</cell><cell>Tolerans</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Empatik Eğilim</cell><cell>1.90</cell><cell>.53</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Adil Olma</cell><cell>1.38</cell><cell>.72</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Saygılı Olma</cell><cell>1.39</cell><cell>.72</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Yardımseverlik</cell><cell>1.95</cell><cell>.51</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>SEVER &amp; GÜRDOĞANBAYIR -Çukurova Üniversitesi Eğitim Fakültesi Dergisi, 49(1), 2020, 257-277   </p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">İlköğretim 4. sınıf sosyal bilgiler dersinde yardımseverlik değerinin etkinlik temelli öğretimi ve öğrencilerin tutumlarına etkisi [Primary 4th grade in social studies course teaching &apos;philantropy&apos; value with activity based and effect on students&apos; attitudes] Unpublished doctoral dissertation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Aktepe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<pubPlace>Ankara</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Gazi University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Hukuk felsefesinin temel sorunları.*Basic problems of philosophy of law+ İstanbul: On İki Levha Yayıncılık</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Aral</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prosocial motivation: Is it ever truly altruistic?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Batson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Advances in Experimental Social Psychology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Berkowitz</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="122" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The altruism question: toward a social-psychological answer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Batson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>Erlbaum</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Hillsdale, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Empathy and respect for the rights of others</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Breyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gigliotti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Confirmatory factor analysis for applied research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>Guilford Publications, Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>First Edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Empathy as an antecedent of social justice attitudes and perceptions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cartabuke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Westerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Bergman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Whitaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Westerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Beekun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Ethics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hukuk ve adalet dersi öğretim programı ve öğretim materyalinde değerler</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Çengelci Köse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Uluslararası Sosyal Araştırmalar Dergisi</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="656" to="664" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Values in law and justice course curriculum and teaching material</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Empathy: A social psychological approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<publisher>Westview Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Empathy, justice, and moral behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Decety</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cowell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJOB neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Huzurlu ve mutlu yaşamın değerler ve karakter güçleri bağlamında karma bir araştırmayla incelenmesi [The investigation of peaceful and happy life in the context of values and character strengths by using the mixed method] Unpublished Doctoral Dissertation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">İ</forename><surname>Demirci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<pubPlace>Istanbul</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Marmara University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The prediction of empathetic tendency and characteristic trait of collaboration on humane values in secondary education students and the examining to those characteristics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Dereli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aypay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Educational Sciences. Theory &amp; Practise</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1262" to="1270" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Justice and conflict</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Deutsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Conflict, Interdependence, and Justice</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Coleman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Sanatta ve günlük yaşamda iletişim çatışmaları ve empatik [Communication conflicts in art and everyday life, and empathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ü</forename><surname>Dökmen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Remzi Kitabevi</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Ankara</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ögretmen adaylarında empati-yardım etme eğilimi ilişkisi ve yardım etme eğiliminin bazı psikososyal değişkenler açısından incelenmesi *Investigation of the relationship between empathy and helping tendency in terms of some psychosocial variables]</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Duru</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pamukkale University Journal of Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="41" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Öyküleştirme yöntemine dayalı eğitimin beş yaş çocuklarında farklılıklara saygı kazanımına etkisinin incelenmesi [Studying the effect of story-based education on the respect of differences in five-year-old children+</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Eren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<pubPlace>Ankara</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Hacettepe University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Unpublished master&apos;s thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Empati becerisinin ahlaki davranışlar üzerindeki etkisi [The effect of empathy on moral behaviors+</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Erken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<pubPlace>Sakarya</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Sakarya University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Unpublished master&apos;s thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Field</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Discovering statistics using SPSS</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage Publication</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Chair&apos;s introduction in empathy and fairness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Frith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/9780470030585.ch1</idno>
		<editor>Novartis Foundation, G. Bock and J. Goode</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A deservingness approach to respect as a relationally based fairness judgment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Heuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Blumenthal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Douglas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Weinblatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0146167299258009</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0146167299258009" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1279" to="1292" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Respect, pluralism and justice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preschool children&apos;s perceptions of fairness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Hod-Shemer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zimerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hassunah-Arafat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wertheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Early Childhood Education Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="186" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Empathy and moral development: implications for caring and justice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London, England</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cutoff criteria for fit indexes in covariance structure analysis: conventional criteria versus new alternatives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bentler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Structural Equation Modelling</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">İlköğretimdeki hayat bilgisi ve sosyal bilgiler derslerinde kullanılacak bir öğretim etkinliği olarak resim çizimi yoluyla empati *Emapthy as a teaching activity to be used in life science and social studies courses in primary education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kabapınar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Atatürk Eğitim Fakültesi Eğitim Bilimleri Dergisi</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="100" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kuramdan uygulamaya hayat bilgisi ve sosyal bilgiler öğretimi [From theory to practice: Life sciences and social studies instructions]</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kabapınar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genişletilmiş 3. Baskı. Ankara: Pegem Akademi</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">KA-Sİ Çocuk ve ergenler için empatik eğilim ölçeği: geliştirilmesi geçerlik ve güvenirlik çalışması. *Child and adolescent KA-Sİ empathic tendecy scale: development, validity and reliability study] Eğitim ve Bilim</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Siyez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="110" to="125" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Okulöncesi dönemde değerlerin kapsamı. *The scope of value in early childhood education+</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kılınç</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Okulöncesi ve İlkokul Döneminde Değerler Eğitimi</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Yağan</forename><surname>Güder</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ankara</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Eğiten Kitap</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="35" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principles and practice of structural equation modelling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Guilford Publications, Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Second Ediciton</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increasing helpfulness towards a robot by emotional adaption to the user</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kühnlenz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sosnowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Buß</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wollherr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kühnlenz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Buss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s12369-013-0182-2</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s12369-013-0182-2" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Robotics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="476" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The structure of bryant&apos;s empathy index for children: A cross-validation study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lasa Aristu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Holgado Tello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Carrasco Ortiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Del Barrio Gándara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18988452" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Spanish Journal of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="670" to="677" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development of empathy in girls during the second year of life: Associations with parenting, attachment, and temperament</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ijzendoorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bakermans-Kranenburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1467-9507.00210</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="451" to="468" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relation of empathy to aggressive and externalizing/antisocial behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Eisenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="324" to="344" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fairness in children&apos;s resource allocation depends on the recipient</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="944" to="948" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The neurobiology of fairness and social justice: an introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Nam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Jost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Feldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11211-017-0296-z</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11211-017-0296-z" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Justice Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="299" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">İlköğretim öğrencilerinin empatik eğilimleri ve algıladıkları öğretmen tutumlarının öğrencilerin ahlakî değer yargılarına etkisi [The effect of primary school students? empathic inclinations and perceptions of teacher attitudes on their value judgements] Unpublished master thesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sarmusak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<pubPlace>Ankara</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Gazi University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does fairness make a difference?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sashkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0090-2616(90)90071-V</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/0090-2616(90)90071-V" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organizational Dynamics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Universals in the content and structure of human values: theoretical advances and empirical tests in 20 countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in experimental social psychology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Zanna</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Diego</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="65" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward a universal psychological structure of human values</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Bilsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="550" to="562" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward a theory of the universal content and structure of values: extensions and cross-cultural replications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Bilsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="878" to="891" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social empathy: A model built on empathy, contextual understanding, and social responsibility that promotes social justice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Segal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/01488376.2011.564040</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01488376.2011.564040" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Social Service Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="266" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social empathy as a framework for teaching social justice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Segal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wagaman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Social Work Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="211" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sosyal bilgiler eğitiminde beceriler *Skills in social studies education+</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Şimşek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Öztürk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sosyal Bilgiler Eğitimine Giriş</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>İnan</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ankara</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Anı Yayıncılık</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="97" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding the limitations of global fit assessment in structural equation modelling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Steiger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Individual Differences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="893" to="898" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Step your way through path analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Suhr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.lexjansen.com/wuss/2008/pos/pos04.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Western Users of SAS Software Conference Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Yapısal eşitlik modelleri</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sümer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Türk Psikoloji Yazıları</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Using multivariate statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tabachnick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Fidel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<publisher>MA: Allyn &amp;Bacon, Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Fourth Edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">More evidence that empathy is a source of altruistic motivation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Toi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Batson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0022-3514.43.2.281</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.43.2.281" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="281" to="292" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Milenyum çağının unutulan gerçeği şahsiyet ve değerler eğitimi [Forgotten truth of the millennium era: Personality and values education]</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yılmaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Vize Yayıncılık</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Ankara</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
