<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Dimensionality of morphological knowledge 1 Running head: DIMENSIONALITY OF MORPHOLOGICAL KNOWLEDGE Exploring the Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge for Adolescent Readers</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Institute of Child Health and Human Development</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Vanderbilt University&apos;s Peabody College</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_PeBKRVu #_QwDUdPH #_S874xsH #_2NA28Mc">
					<orgName type="full">Institute of Education Sciences</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Amanda</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Goodwin</surname></persName>
							<email>amanda.goodwin@vanderbilt.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Vanderbilt University&apos;s Peabody College</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nashville</settlement>
									<region>TN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Vanderbilt University&apos;s Peabody College</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Florida State University&apos;s Florida Center for Reading Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">University of Michigan</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Florida State University&apos;s Florida Center for Reading Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">Vanderbilt University&apos;s Peabody College</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nashville</settlement>
									<region>TN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Vanderbilt University&apos;s Peabody College</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nashville</settlement>
									<region>TN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Vanderbilt University&apos;s Peabody College</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Florida State University&apos;s Florida Center for Reading Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">University of Michigan</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Florida State University&apos;s Florida Center for Reading Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">Vanderbilt University&apos;s Peabody College</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nashville</settlement>
									<region>TN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Yaacov</forename><surname>Petscher</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Florida Center for Reading Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Florida State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tallahassee</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Florida Center for Reading Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Florida State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tallahassee</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Florida Center for Reading Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Florida State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tallahassee</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Florida Center for Reading Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Florida State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tallahassee</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Joanne</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Carlisle</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Michigan</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ann Arbor</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Michigan</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ann Arbor</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Michigan</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ann Arbor</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Michigan</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ann Arbor</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Alison</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Florida Center for Reading Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Florida State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tallahassee</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Florida Center for Reading Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Florida State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tallahassee</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Florida Center for Reading Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Florida State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tallahassee</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Florida Center for Reading Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Florida State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tallahassee</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Vanderbilt University&apos;s Peabody College</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Florida State University&apos;s Florida Center for Reading Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">University of Michigan</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Florida State University&apos;s Florida Center for Reading Research</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Dimensionality of morphological knowledge 1 Running head: DIMENSIONALITY OF MORPHOLOGICAL KNOWLEDGE Exploring the Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge for Adolescent Readers</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1467-9817.12064</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T20:12+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>morphological knowledge</term>
					<term>morphological knowledge</term>
					<term>dimensionality</term>
					<term>measurement</term>
					<term>adolescent readers</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This study examined the dimensionality of morphological knowledge. The performance of 371 seventh-and eighth-graders on seven morphological knowledge tasks was investigated using confirmatory factor analysis. Results suggested morphological knowledge was best fit by a bifactor model with a general factor of morphological knowledge and seven specific factors, representing tasks that tap different facets of morphological knowledge. Next, structural equation modeling was used to explore links to literacy outcomes. Results indicated the general factor and the specific factor of morphological meaning processing showed significant positive associations with reading comprehension and vocabulary. Also, the specific factor of generating morphologically related words showed significant positive associations with vocabulary, while specific factors of morphological word reading and spelling processing showed small negative relationships to reading comprehension and vocabulary. Findings highlight the complexity of morphological knowledge and suggest the importance of being cognizant of the nature of morphology when designing and interpreting studies.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exploring the Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge for Adolescent Readers</head><p>Morphemes are the smallest units of meaning in a language. In English, root words (whether bound or free) and affixes (whether prefixes or suffixes) are combined to form words that express particular meanings and serve various syntactic roles (e.g., enforce, forceful, reinforce, forcing). Combining root words and affixes may involve shifts in sound and spelling of the root word (e.g., decide, decision), making morphology a complex component of language that is integrally linked to other language components (i.e., phonology, syntax, and semantics).</p><p>Students' knowledge of morphology is significantly related to literacy achievement in the elementary years (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Carlisle &amp; Goodwin, 2013)</ref>. In the middle school years, morphological knowledge becomes especially important because the textbooks and content-area instruction during this time place heavier burdens on students' academic language. Academic language is more complex and cognitively challenging than language used in everyday social interactions. It includes content-area words, many of which are morphologically complex (e.g., hydroelectric, photosynthesis) or which have morphological relatives (e.g., analyze, interpret). For example, <ref type="bibr">Coxhead's Academic Word List (2000)</ref> shows that analyze is the base form used in 11 additional words (e.g., re-analyze) and interpret is used in 19 additional words (e.g., misinterpret, interpretive). Morphological knowledge has been found to contribute to adolescents' word reading (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Carlisle &amp; Stone, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Gilbert, Goodwin, Compton, &amp; Kearns, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Goodwin, Gilbert, &amp; Cho, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Singson, Mahony, &amp; Mann, 2000)</ref>, spelling (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Deacon &amp; Bryant, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Nunes, Bryant, &amp; Bindman, 2006)</ref>, and vocabulary (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Carlisle &amp; Fleming, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Nagy, Berninger, &amp; Abbott, 2006)</ref>. Studies have also shown that morphological knowledge may have a direct effect on reading comprehension <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(McCutchen, Logan, &amp; Biangardi-Orpe, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Nagy et</ref> This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved. <ref type="bibr">Knowledge 4 al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Siegel, 2008)</ref> or an effect that is mediated by relations to other variables such as vocabulary knowledge (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Goodwin, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Kieffer &amp; Lesaux, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Nagy et al., 2006)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dimensionality of Morphological</head><p>Although significant associations have been found between morphology and different areas of literacy, these associations and their interpretations depend in part on how researchers are framing the construct, which relates to the different tasks and content of the measure(s) of morphological knowledge used in particular studies (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Carlisle &amp; Goodwin, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Kuo &amp; Anderson, 2006)</ref>. A related (and unanswered) question is whether morphological knowledge is unidimensional or multidimensional. Unidimensionality would mean that tasks assessing different elements of morphological knowledge would draw on the same general sensitivity to morphological structures and be significantly related to each other. In contrast, multidimensionality would mean that performance on tasks assessing different morphological knowledge and processing would relate but assess different aspects of morphological knowledge.</p><p>While in theory aspects of morphological knowledge differ in important ways and relate differently to various literacy measures, we currently lack evidence to support any theoretical explanation of the dimensionality of morphological knowledge. The updated Standards for <ref type="bibr">Educational and Psychological Testing (AERA, APA, &amp; NCME, 2014)</ref> emphasize that the validity of empirical studies depends in part on the claim that measurements preserve the key characteristics of the phenomena they represent. Thus, researchers' assumptions about the nature of morphological knowledge may affect how results are interpreted to build understanding of adolescents' academic language acquisition and use. Thus, the goal of this study is to explore the dimensionality of morphological knowledge and the relation of possible dimensions to reading comprehension and vocabulary knowledge for adolescents.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tacit Morphological Processing and Strategic Morphological Analysis</head><p>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>Given different views of morphological knowledge (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Nagy, Carlisle, &amp; Goodwin, 2014)</ref>, one approach to examining dimensionality is to explore the distinction between tacit morphological processing and strategic morphological analysis. Such an approach fits within <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Bialystok and Ryan's (1985)</ref> framework for examining metalinguistic abilities, building on distinctions between knowledge ("knowing that is intuitive", p. 233, acquired implicitly from language learning) and analysis of knowledge ("knowing that is explicit…more analyzed forms <ref type="bibr">[developed]</ref> through the increasing ability to structure and classify knowledge", p. 233). As <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bialystok and Mitterer (1987)</ref> write, Some language uses, such as conversation, are adequately supported by unanalyzed representations of language structure, but other uses, such as reading, writing, solving metalinguistic problems, and lecturing, require a more explicit conceptualization of the units of language and their rules of combination. <ref type="bibr">(p. 148)</ref> In English, as in other languages, morphology conveys semantic, grammatical, and syntactic information <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Frost, 2012)</ref>. Applying the above framework, linguistic information conveyed by morphology is acquired first via tacit processing of words and sentences. Young children implicitly learn from the statistical properties of the language they are exposed to. For example, preschool children extract from experiences with -er, used as an agentive or instrumental suffix (winder) and also as a comparative form of adjectives (tireder), to correctly use -er to create novel words that play different semantic and grammatical roles like referring to a teacher as a lessoner <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Clark, 1978)</ref>. The more encounters with words and morphemes in different contexts, the stronger the lexical representations become in memory <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Perfetti, 2007)</ref>.</p><p>Strategic morphological analysis builds on what was initially learned tacitly, and it also involves a metalinguistic regard for words. Adolescents move from functional use of linguistic units to This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved. deliberate analysis and manipulation of linguistic units <ref type="bibr">(Valtin, 1984)</ref>. Adolescents therefore use representations of morphemes in their mental lexicon to read or figure out the meaning of unknown words (e.g., treelet) if they realize that words can be decomposed into units of meaning <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Anglin, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Carlisle &amp; Fleming, 2003)</ref>. While tacit morphological processing builds and speeds access to lexical representations, strategic morphological analysis promotes an analytic approach to understanding and using words, especially through figuring out the many derived and compounded words adolescents encounter in their reading.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tacit Morphological Processing</head><p>A closer look at tacit morphological processing shows that root words (i.e., free morphemes) and affixes that are represented in a student's mental lexicon contribute to the processing and spelling of printed words by spreading activation; the surface level (e.g., lovable), the root word (e.g., love), and affix(es) (e.g., -able) contribute to the speed and/or accuracy of responses by students and adults <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Feldman, Rueckl, DiLiberto, Pastizzo, &amp; Vellutino, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Frost, Grainger, &amp; Carreiras, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Goodwin et al., 2014)</ref>. Evidence for this tacit morphological processing emerges from studies showing that students read aloud (presented and recorded by a computer) derived words like hilly faster and more accurately than pseudo-derived words like silly which had been matched for word length, frequency, and spelling (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Carlisle &amp; Stone, 2005)</ref>. They also read aloud (to a researcher) words with suffixes (e.g., locked) more accurately than words with pseudo-suffixes (e.g., ladder; <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Laxon, Rickard, &amp; Coltheart, 1992)</ref> and chose the correct spelling of derivational suffixes for two-morpheme words (lucky) more often than for one-morpheme words (candy; <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Sangster &amp; Deacon, 2011)</ref>. The influence of morphological processing cannot be explained by overlap with phonological, orthographic, or semantic features.</p><p>For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">McCutchen et al. (2009)</ref> found that fifth and eighth graders responded more This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge 7 quickly to target words like assume when words were primed by a morphologically related word like assumption versus when the prime was a semantically (e.g., expect) or orthographically (e.g., assignment) related word. This tacit morphological processing depends largely on the quality of the lexical representations that have developed from exposure to words and morphemes <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Perfetti, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Reichle &amp; Perfetti, 2003)</ref>. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Carlisle and Stone (2005)</ref> found high school students recognized derived words with stable (e.g., depend-dependence) and shifting pronunciation (e.g., nature-natural) faster than middle schoolers and were similarly fast and accurate on the stable and shift words whereas the middle school students performed less well on the shift words. Low literate adults, who have difficulties with reading, seem to have even more difficulty with morphological processing: they read single morpheme words more accurately than morphologically complex words matched for frequency and length <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Tighe &amp; Binder, 2015)</ref>. It seems that higher quality lexical representations and well-specified associations between morphemes and related morphologically complex words contribute to fluent word identification such that mental processes can largely be devoted to higher level comprehension. These high quality lexical representations likely support vocabulary breadth and depth as well as fluent reading and comprehension of texts.</p><p>Tasks that assess tacit morphological processing might assess accuracy or speed of word reading, spelling, or meaning knowledge of morphologically complex words. Ideally, such tasks include examining the relationship between performance on morphemes (i.e., root words like isolate or affixes like ion) and their application to performance on a related morphologically complex word (i.e., isolation), which adds confidence that morphological knowledge has contributed to performance on the morphologically complex word when there is evidence that This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>the student read the morpheme correctly. A main characteristic is that these tasks focus students on a morphologically complex word without explicitly drawing attention to the internal structure of that word.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Strategic Morphological Analysis</head><p>Literacy experiences and discussions of words and their meanings also help students become more cognizant of the ways that the sound, spelling, and meaning of morphemes contribute to expressions of meaning. This can lead to more strategic, deliberate use of morphological knowledge in reading and writing. Improvements in morphological analysis are based in part on growth of students' vocabulary, but are also related to adolescents' ability to reflect on the content and form of language simultaneously <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Anglin, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr">Van Kleeck, 1982)</ref>.</p><p>Conscious morphological analysis likely occurs in settings that encourage analysis of the internal structure of the word, the meanings and grammatical roles of the affixes, and the context in which the word is used. For example, middle school students were better able than elementary students to judge whether corner comes from corn and also choose the appropriate pseudoword with a real suffix to complete a sentence, probably because they were consciously considering the overlap between form and content <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Berninger et al., 2010)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Anglin (1993)</ref> shows this conscious analysis through a fifth grader's efforts to identify the meaning of priesthood by first identifying the morphemic constituents (the student was familiar with the word priest and remarked that hood was in the word childhood); the student then faced the problem of trying to determine what the whole word might mean. Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Pacheco and Goodwin (2013)</ref> describe a middle schooler's use of morphological analysis to deepen understanding of the word cavity from a bad thing in a tooth to the more accurate meaning of a hole in a tooth.</p><p>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge 9</head><p>Strategic morphological analysis may contribute to vocabulary and comprehension differently. For vocabulary, conscious morphological analysis would support vocabulary breadth and depth by deepening the meanings of known words or inferring the meanings of unfamiliar words from familiar morphemic elements <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Nagy et al., 2014)</ref>. Additional supports for comprehension would be expected, as students need to be able to consider the semantic and syntactic roles of the component morphemes that make up unfamiliar words, phrases, and sentences they are reading <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Tyler &amp; Nagy, 1990)</ref>. For example, students reading about "militant groups" might consider the suffix -ant (a person who) and the root word military to establish that the text is referring to a group who are armed like the military <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Goodwin &amp; Perkins, 2015)</ref>. Some tasks used to assess morphological knowledge require strategic analysis by encouraging students to analyze the morphological structure of a word. The problem solving aspect may be presented in the directions, examples, or the items themselves. For example, a morphological judgment task draws students' attention to morphological structure via directions (determine if a second word is derived or comes from another) and examples (corn and corner versus heal and health). Similarly, sentence completion tasks ask students to select a word or pseudoword that ends with an appropriate suffix to complete a sentence (e.g., suffix tests, Tyler <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">&amp; Nagy, 1989)</ref>; this draws their attention to the internal structure of words by focusing on the only element that changes within the answer choices-the suffixes. In analyzing the internal structure of words (i.e., analysis of root words and affixes), students are encouraged to focus on how the orthography conveys meaning.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Perspectives on Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge</head><p>While researchers may use tasks that require tacit processing or strategic analysis, they may be assuming that morphological knowledge is a unidimensional construct. The assumption may be that any task of morphological knowledge will provide an understanding of a student's morphological knowledge as it is related to literacy (see Model 1 in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>). Identifying the base word in derived words could serve as a measure of students' morphological knowledge (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Carlisle, 1988)</ref>, but so too could their reading of morphologically complex words made of familiar morphemes (e.g., shady, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Carlisle &amp; Stone, 2005)</ref>.</p><p>There is some evidence for unidimensionality of morphological knowledge. <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Muse (2005;</ref><ref type="bibr"></ref> also reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Wagner, Muse, &amp; Tannenbaum, 2007)</ref> administered nine morphological analysis measures to fourth graders, with fit indices suggesting the data fit best as a single latent variable (i.e., a general factor). Muse explored multiple conceptualizations including possible dimensions related to implicit morphological processing and conscious awareness of morphemes; she also used different tasks, such as written versus oral measures and multiple-choice versus production response formats. Her results consistently suggest unidimensionality. <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Tighe and Schatschneider (2015)</ref> similarly explored dimensionality of morphological knowledge, although with low literate adult learners. A single latent variable fit best for most explorations, suggesting unidimensionality related to many task characteristics like derived versus inflected words and context clues versus isolated word presentation. <ref type="bibr">Nagy, Berninger, Abbott, Vaughan, and Vermeulen (2003)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Nagy et al. (2006)</ref> provide further evidence as they used multiple morphological analysis measures to create a latent variable representing elementary and middle school students' morphological knowledge.</p><p>In contrast, some evidence from studies with multiple morphological measures indicate that morphological knowledge may be multidimensional (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Berninger et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Carlisle, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Elbro &amp; Arnbak, 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Goodwin et al., 2013</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Goodwin et al., , 2014))</ref>. Model 2 in Table <ref type="table">1</ref> shows such relationships. For example, Danish adolescents with dyslexia had greater difficulty on analogy, This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved. compound formation, and root word extraction measures (i.e., strategic morphological analysis measures) versus measures of more tacit morphological processing involving reading and spelling morphologically complex words <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Elbro &amp; Arnbak, 1996)</ref>. Studies also suggest different assessments of morphological knowledge contributed differently to literacy outcomes. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Goodwin et al. (2013</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Goodwin et al. ( , 2014) )</ref> found tacit morphological processing (applying knowledge of root-word reading, spelling, and meaning) and morphological analysis (analyzing the internal structure of words) contributed uniquely to derived-word reading and lexical representations. In another study, tacit morphological processing (i.e., a derived word reading test), but not strategic morphological analysis (i.e., where credit for successful defining was given if the fifth graders explained the meaning of the root word and used it correctly in a sentence), made a unique contribution to standardized vocabulary knowledge <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Carlisle, 2000)</ref>. In contrast, the morphological analysis task but not the morphological processing task made a unique significant contribution to reading comprehension. It may be that in addition to types of processing, differences in tasks are important. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Tighe and Schatschneider's (2015)</ref> work with low literate adults showed that real word and pseudoword tasks made up two dimensions of morphological knowledge, yet this was only found after differences in response types (i.e., freeresponse vs production) were taken into account.</p><p>An alternative way of conceptualizing the multidimensionality of morphological knowledge is a bi-factor model, wherein morphological knowledge involves students' general sensitivity to the morphological structure of words and a separate set of dimensions that represent unique supports of morphological processing and strategic analysis for various language and literacy tasks (see Model 3 in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>). From this perspective, there is a general dimension of morphological knowledge representing what is similar about all the tasks, but there This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>are also specific dimensions representing differences in processing and analysis stemming from the demands of morphological tasks.</p><p>If a bifactor model is confirmed, general morphological sensitivity may support vocabulary on the one hand by building automatic recognition of the meaning of many morphologically complex words and, on the other hand, by deepening understandings of the semantic and syntactic aspects of morphologically complex words. Performance related to strategic morphological analysis, though, may contribute to vocabulary uniquely beyond the general factor because a student's analysis of the internal structure of words often is key to inferring the meaning of an unknown word (see priesthood example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Anglin, 1993)</ref>. Similarly, performance on reading comprehension may involve both the general dimension and the specific dimensions of morphological analysis, which would help an adolescent infer the meaning of unknown words necessary for comprehension.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Purpose and Design</head><p>Our study examines the dimensionality of morphological knowledge framed within the context of possible differences between tacit processing and strategic analysis. We examine (a) the dimensionality of adolescents' performances on categories of morphological knowledge tasks and (b) the extent to which various dimensions within morphological knowledge uniquely contribute to vocabulary and reading comprehension skills for adolescent readers. relatively affluent populations (e.g., School A: 11% minority, 5% economically disadvantaged; School B 19% minority; Tennessee Department of Education Report Card, 2011). School A included more morphological instruction, using a Greek and Latin morphemes curriculum <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Harris, 2009)</ref> whereas School B approached vocabulary instruction through directly teaching words from texts students were reading. Students of 12 teachers participated (7 School A, 5 School B). Students ranged between the second and 99 th percentile on standardized reading comprehension and reading vocabulary tests, averaging the 72 nd percentile on each.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Procedure</head><p>This study involves analysis of students' performance on morphological knowledge and literacy measures from an earlier study <ref type="bibr">(Author et al., 2013)</ref> and on a larger battery of morphological knowledge assessments administered for this study and another <ref type="bibr">(Author et al., 2014)</ref>. Unlike the prior study, which focused on development of lexical representations, this study makes an important unique contribution by exploring the dimensionality of the morphological knowledge tasks. Consent procedures were similar at each school. Snow days (i.e., days where the amount of snow cancelled school) made it impossible to administer the full battery to all students, so a subsample of students took as many assessments as possible during shortened class periods. To minimize priming of visual forms, derived-word aspects of each measure were administered before root-word measures. Also, the morphological spelling, meaning, and analysis measures were administered before the morphological word reading measures. Assessments were administered by teams of study personnel trained in two practice sessions and then required to observe implementation of the assessments prior to independent administration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures</head><p>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge 14</head><p>A battery of seven written morphological measures and two standardized tests of reading vocabulary and reading comprehension were administered. All were group administered except the morphological word reading measure. Four of the measures were based on tasks used by other researchers, but we held the content constant by using the same 40 root words and their derived counterparts (see Appendix A and Author et al., 2013 for more information). This list was developed after consulting studies of the types of words found in adolescent academic texts, which include morphologically complex words of Latin and Greek origin <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Bar-Ilan &amp; Berman, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Nagy &amp; Anderson, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr">Nagy &amp; Townsend, 2012)</ref>. The list was purposefully varied, considering what <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Nagy and Anderson (1984)</ref> termed the "great variety of types and degrees of relatedness among words" (p. 306). We primarily included derivations that differed in the closeness of the relationship between the root word and affixes (i.e., tranquil and tranquility vs. quest and unquestionably) and in the frequency and amount of meaning conveyed by affixes.</p><p>Words in this list ranged from 2 to 5 morphemes; the mean frequencies of the derived and root words were 37.80 and 45.51<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">foot_1</ref> respectively <ref type="bibr">(Zeno, Ivens, Millard, &amp; Duvvuri, 1995)</ref>. About 46% of the words were phonologically opaque, 26% were both orthographically and phonologically opaque, and 31% were semantically opaque. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref> reports measure information, including example items, reliabilities, means, and number of items.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Strategic morphological analysis.</head><p>To assess strategic use of morphological knowledge, tasks were used that encouraged students to consider the internal structure of words. Rather than presenting just a derived word or root word, each task focused students' attention on the morphological makeup of words by drawing attention to root-words or affixes as they related to larger morphologically complex words. All tasks were read aloud, although participants were allowed to proceed at their own pace.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Suffix choice (Pseudoword &amp; real word tasks).</head><p>The two suffix choice subtests focused on students' ability to choose from a set of options either the suffixed word or pseudoword that most accurately completed each sentence. Students' attention was drawn to suffixes as that was what changed within the answer choices. Pilot testing suggested the need to use pseudoword items from <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Singson et al. (2000)</ref> and harder real word items from <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Mahony (1994)</ref>. Suffixes turned root words into nouns (e.g., -ist, -ion/-ation, -ity, and -ness), verbs (e.g., -ate, -ize and -ify), or adjectives (e.g., -ous/-ious, -al and -ive).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Morphological judgment task (Comes from task).</head><p>Using the 24 highest frequency of 42 original items from <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Mahony (1994)</ref>, we asked participants to analyze the internal structure of words and determine whether pairs of words were morphologically related (e.g., add and additive) or not (e.g., alto and altogether). Students could also respond, 'I don't know' to minimize guessing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Generate morphologically-related words. Adapted from the Academic Vocabulary and</head><p>Spelling Inventory (AVSI; <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Flanigan et al., 2011)</ref>, participants analyzed a morphological family's overlap by writing down as many morphologically related words (i.e., words that shared the same root word) as possible. The example of forget was provided; related words were forgetful, forgetting, forgettable. Students were cautioned that words which conveyed the definition (e.g., not remember) were not morphologically related because they did not share the root forget.</p><p>Responses were scored based on quantity and accuracy (no correct responses, value of 0; 1 or more correct responses, value of 1). Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Reichle and Perfetti (2003)</ref>, correct responses This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge 16 included derivations, inflections, and compounds; students received credit for any phonologically plausible responses.</p><p>Tacit morphological processing. To confirm the likelihood that morphological knowledge was used when processing a given derived word, we used processing measures that related performance on root words to performance on a derived form of the word. Root word and derived word content were presented separately (at different times) so students' attention was focused on whole words rather than the morphemes within the words. Evidence suggests by middle school readers have "encapsulated word representations in which a word's orthographic form contains the word's phonological and semantic information… [and therefore] do not consciously rely on morphological information" <ref type="bibr">(Gilbert, Goodwin, Compton, &amp; Kearns, 2014, p. 40)</ref> when processing whole words.</p><p>Morphological word reading processing. Students read a list of derived words followed by a list of related root words; responses were recorded. Research team members analyzed the audiofiles, scoring responses as correct (value of 1) if the student correctly pronounced both the root word and the related derived word or incorrect (value of 0) if the related root word or derived word was pronounced incorrectly based on legal dictionary pronunciations or allowable differences due to dialect variation. Morphological spelling processing. This measure assessed students' ability to spell derived words and their related root words when presented in isolation. A research team member read aloud a list of derived words followed by a list of root words; words were scored as correct (value of 1) if the student correctly spelled both the root-word and the related derived-word or incorrect (value of 0) if the related root-word or derived-word was spelled incorrectly.</p><p>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge 17</head><p>Morphological meaning processing (self-perceived). Participants rated their knowledge of a list of derived words followed by a list of related root words, choosing whether they had no knowledge, some knowledge, or full knowledge of the meaning of each member of the 40 word pairs. Previous research provided evidence of the validity of this group-administered measure <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Tyler &amp; Nagy, 1989)</ref>. Participants were given the example of forget and were shown how knowledge of this word might be classified. Each word was read aloud by the test administrator.</p><p>Responses were scored as correct (value of 1) if the participant reported some or full knowledge of both the root word and the related derived word or incorrect (value of 0) if no knowledge of the root or the derived word was reported. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Standardized literacy measures.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reading comprehension. The Gates-MacGinitie</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Analysis</head><p>Given the large pool of items from the pilot testing (n = 229), we first conducted an item analysis to evaluate poorly functioning or redundant items. The goal was to reduce each subscale to relatively few items such that a reduced battery would maintain or improve upon the base This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge 18 level reliability of each subscale. Two primary pieces of data were used to render decisions concerning item culling: the alpha-if-deleted index and item-total correlations. Items were deleted if they presented with one or more of the following criteria: 1) an equivalent or higher alpha-if-deleted index compared to the base reliability coefficient, 2) a negative item-total correlation, or 3) an item-total correlation &lt; .15.</p><p>Once we culled our pool of items, we explored the dimensionality of morphological knowledge via confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) as shown in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. The bi-factor model is conceptually similar to a second-order measurement model because an additional factor is modeled above that of the primary theoretical latent constructs.</p><p>What differentiates the bi-factor model is where the general factor appears. The second-order construct is indicated by the first-order specific factors and thus models the common variance among first-order latent factors. Conversely, a bi-factor model views the primary latent factors as specific factors related to the skills being measured, and the additional factor (the general factor) is fit to the observed measures; thus, the specific factors represent sources of variance among the indicators above that captured by the general factor <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Reise, Morizot, &amp; Hays, 2007)</ref>. An additional distinction between the second-order and bi-factor models is that the bi-factor model allows testing of whether variance across the observed measures is due to a general factor, such as morphological knowledge, or due to specific factors of morphological knowledge like strategic morphological analysis and tacit morphological processing. The second-order This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved. specification does not allow for such estimation because the higher order construct is capturing the common variance in the first-order factors and not the observed measures. Model fit for the measurement comparisons was conducted using Akaike Information Criteria (AIC) and the sample-size adjusted Bayes Information Criteria (ABIC). Although several hypothesized models were nested, the literature is mixed as to whether bi-factor models are nested versions of multidimensional models. As such, we opted to use AIC and the ABIC for relative fit comparisons with smaller values for AIC and ABIC desired <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Raftery, 1995)</ref>. Models were also evaluated with the comparative fit index (CFI, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bentler, 1990)</ref>, Tucker-Lewis index (TLI; <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bentler &amp; Bonnett, 1980)</ref>, and the root mean square error of approximation (RMSEA, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Browne &amp; Cudeck, 1992)</ref>. CFI and TLI values ≥ 0.95 are minimally sufficient criteria for acceptable model fit, and RMSEA and SRMR estimates &lt; 0.05 are desirable, with up to .10 considered acceptable. All models were run with the culled item set and then confirmed with the entire set of items. Our final modeling decisions took into account the fit statistics of the best fitting models (both with the culled and full item set) and also relationship to theory. Once our measurement model was established, we then explored the relationship between the suggested This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved. dimensions of morphological knowledge and standardized literacy outcomes (i.e., vocabulary and reading comprehension) using Structural Equation Modeling. All analyses were run in Mplus 7.2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Muthén &amp; Muthén, 2013)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Preliminary Data Analysis</head><p>Descriptive results for experimental measures are presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref>. The mean score for reading comprehension and vocabulary was 561.01 (N=358; SD=35.42) and 558.50 (N=358; SD=32.54) respectively. As described, there were different amounts of missing data due to inclement weather, ranging from 20% for the suffix choice and morphological judgment tasks to 58% for the generating morphologically related words task. While the data were not missing completely at random (i.e., MCAR, Little's test of data missing completely at random; χ²(92) = 194.86, p &lt; .001), a review of the data suggested missingness patterns were not due to the variables themselves. In other words, the data were missing at random because the reason for missingness was weather (i.e., snow) NOT item or participant characteristics. We were guided by the psychometric literature in our approach to missingness: we leveraged full information maximum likelihood estimation (FIML) in the latent variable analyses because studies suggest that less bias is present when analyses involve data from the full sample of participants versus only including data from the sub-sample with full data on all measures <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Enders, 2010)</ref>. Since our data were missing at random, FIML and multiple imputation (MI) give the same result (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Collins, Schafer, &amp; Karn, 2001)</ref>. Correlations of performance on the experimental and standardized measures are presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">3</ref> with correlations provided for the full item set below the diagonal and correlations for the culled item set provided above the diagonal. The This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge 22 strongest associations were observed between measures that shared the same format but differed in content (i.e., the real word and pseudoword suffix choice tasks, r =.75, .67).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Item Reduction</head><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref> reports the results of the reliability analysis of the response matrix for the full item set and the culled item set. All full item set estimates of Cronbach's α for internal consistency were above .85 except for the MJT task, which had a reliability of .57. By evaluating the alpha-if-deleted index and the item total correlations, 10 items were dropped from MJT increasing the reliability to α = .68. Also, 16 items were dropped from SCR resulting in α = .90; 9 items were dropped from SCP for α = .82; 24 items were dropped from GMRW resulting in α = .90; 20 items were dropped from MSPELL resulting in α = .88; 21 items were dropped from MMEAN resulting in α = .87; and 23 items were dropped from MREAD for a α = .83. In total, item culling removed 124 items without significantly altering the internal consistency of the item responses. By reducing the overall item total bank from 230 to 106, a better item-to-person ratio was maintained which increased the precision of the standard errors for the latent variable modeling and improved the run-time for the model algorithms. Correlations among the total scores from the reduced subscales are reported on the upper diagonal of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measurement Model</head><p>Summary results for the measurement specifications are reported in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">4</ref>. The These similar, yet different results led us to embrace theory to guide us in further unraveling the statistics to determine our final measurement model. As discussed in the literature review, theory and research suggest a common set of core elements are tapped by different morphological tasks. Therefore, we looked more closely at results related to overlap or shared variance in each model. A main difference between the two models is where the overlap amongst tasks is modeled (i.e., in the 7-factor TASK model, the overlap is modeled as correlations amongst the specific factors whereas in the 7-factor-bifactor model or bi-factor TASK model, the overlap is modeled in the general factor and then the specific factors are modeled as unique). In the 7-factor (TASK) model, the specific factors were strongly correlated with 19 out of the 21 correlations being greater than .45 and seven of the correlations being greater than .70 (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">5</ref>). This suggests, in reality, the specific factors were not as unique as the 7-factor (TASK) model suggested. In fact, the strength of the correlations amongst the specific factors may have masked the ability to evaluate the relative exogeneity of each factor. We then examined the standardized factor loadings (presented in Appendix B) of each item on the generalized morphological knowledge factor within the 7-factor-bifactor (bi-factor TASK) model. These highlight that the relation between the strength of the item loadings relative to the morphological knowledge versus the strength of the item loadings relative to the specific factor itself. Loadings greater than 0.4 between the item and the general factor would suggest overlap with the general factor. Over This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge 24 90% of loadings met that criterion, again suggesting important overlap amongst the items across tasks. Based on these considerations, we settled upon the 7-factor bi-factor (bi-factor TASK) model as the best fitting model since it showed excellent fit to the data and most clearly communicated the overlap present amongst all the morphological items from the seven morphological tasks.</p><p>It is important to note that note that the 7-factor-bifactor (bi-factor TASK) model allowed different tasks to vary in its relationship to the general morphological knowledge factor (i.e., there was some general overlap, but also specific factors reflecting unique differences). For example, Appendix B shows that items on the MMEAN task (i.e., morphological meaning processing task) were less related to the general factor, yet more closely related to the specific factor than the other tasks. Similarly, the GMRW task (i.e., generating morphologically related words) items maintained strong associations with the specific factor of GMRW controlling for the strong relationship between the GMRW items and the general factor. Conversely, items on the MJT (i.e., morphological judgment task) were more weakly associated with that specific factor compared to the general morphological knowledge factor. Across the seven tasks, only the GMRW and MMEAN items generally maintained stronger associations with the specific factor compared to the morphological knowledge factor. Such evidence points to task-specific items sharing greater variance with other items across multiple tasks compared to within-task items, again providing evidence for the 7-factor-bifactor (bi-factor TASK) model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Structural Analysis</head><p>From the bi-factor model, the seven specific factors along with the general factor of </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>The dimensionality of morphological knowledge is important to understand when interpreting current theory, research, and practice. Results of our study indicated that morphological knowledge is best considered a multidimensional construct represented by a general construct (i.e., a general morphological knowledge factor) and seven dimensions (i.e., specific factors) that signify different morphological skills or knowledge assessed by different tasks. Although we had hypothesized our seven tasks would represent two morphological knowledge dimensions related to tacit processing and strategic analysis, results did not confirm this. Instead, the seven tasks could not be reduced to a smaller number of dimensions, suggesting that the different tasks used to assess morphological knowledge involve common morphological processing mechanisms, but also tap important differences in performance beyond tacit processing and strategic analysis. Differences were indicated related to different morphological subskills like root word processing within morphological reading, morphological spelling, This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge 26 morphological meaning, as well as consideration of morphological relationships, analysis of the role of suffixes in real words and in pseudowords, and generation of morphologically related words. These results raise questions about the tendency to view morphological knowledge as either unidimensional (all tasks similarly represent morphological knowledge; <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Muse, 2005)</ref> or multidimensional (different tasks represent independent categories of morphological knowledge tasks; <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Tighe &amp; Schatschneider, 2015)</ref>. Instead, an alternative view is suggested.</p><p>The first main component of morphological knowledge suggested by our study involves a core set of knowledge that highlights the presence of meaningful units within words; these understandings can be applied to various literacy areas and are involved in any assessment of morphological knowledge. For example, a student would likely use the morphological structure of a word like detective when attempting to spell, read, or ascertain its meaning. The student would use morphological understandings to consider the root word, detect, the suffix ive, or related words detection, detecting, detects, detection, detector, detected, etc. He may think about the overlap in meaning, spelling, or pronunciation or other word-formation rules. The general factor found in our study is similar to the single dimension found in others <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Muse, 2005</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">, Kieffer &amp; Lesaux, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Tighe &amp; Schatschneider, 2015)</ref> where no additional dimensions were noted for different types of tasks like oral versus written tasks or multiple-choice versus production <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Muse, 2005)</ref> or context versus isolated word or tasks with derived versus inflected words <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(Tighe &amp; Schatschneider, 2015)</ref>. This general factor seems to represent sensitivity to a word's morphological structure.</p><p>The second component involves specific dimensions (i.e., specific factors) that represent different aspects of morphological knowledge that can be applied in different ways to support performance in different areas of literacy. These specific understandings go beyond This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>understanding morphological structure and instead include specific skills that can develop separately. For example, a student reading detective may engage knowledge of morphological rules like how the suffix ive is pronounced differently in detective than within single morpheme words like hive. This is different from the skills used to figure out the meaning of detective, where the same student may focus more on the meaning and syntactical role of the suffix ive rather than its pronunciation. The student may further apply skills like considering the meaning of detect or linking to the larger morphological family to determine the meaning of detective.</p><p>This multidimensionality related to different tasks is suggested in the literature as <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Tighe and Schatschneider (2015)</ref> noted differences between peudoword and real word tasks and also possible differences between multiple-choice and free-response tasks. Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Kieffer and Lesaux (2012)</ref> indicated distinctions related to task features within four morphological knowledge tasks. Neither of these studies examined a bifactor model that allowed for possible overlap and also distinctive dimensions, highlighting the contribution of our study. Our results suggest that although the skills assessed by the tasks in our study share an understanding of morphological structure, they also involve unique understandings that can develop and be applied in different ways.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Contributions to Reading Comprehension and Vocabulary</head><p>Predictive validity related to vocabulary and reading comprehension was also explored.</p><p>Attending to dimensionality had important consequences as the combination of the seven morphological tasks (i.e., the combination of the general factor and the seven specific factors) explained a large amount of variance in each literacy outcome. These results confirm findings from prior research that suggest that morphological knowledge is closely related to vocabulary and reading comprehension <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Carlisle &amp; Goodwin, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Nagy et al., 2006)</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>. Most of this variance</head><p>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>was associated with the general factor, which represented core elements of morphological knowledge tapped by all seven morphological tasks. The general factor made a large and meaningful contribution to standardized vocabulary and reading comprehension. Considering morphological overlap in meaning, spelling, or pronunciation helped adolescents build more high quality lexical representations that then aided reading comprehension efforts.</p><p>Of interest is that solely considering overlap in tasks would likely miss unique contributions of dimensions (i.e., specific factors) of morphological knowledge, beyond the contribution of the general factor. This means that including tasks that tap these different aspects of morphology help to unravel the relationship between morphological knowledge and different literacy outcomes. Our results suggest that knowing the meaning of more derived words (given knowing that word's root word) and being able to generate morphologically related words for a target word supports vocabulary knowledge beyond general morphological sensitivity (i.e., the general factor). Students with these skills either build more high quality lexical representations across time or are better able to problem-solve the meanings of unfamiliar words using knowledge of a root word or additional morphological relatives. As such, considering words within morphological families seems to support general vocabulary knowledge.</p><p>In contrast, morphological spelling processing had a negative relationship with vocabulary controlling for the other variables in the model. This signifies that beyond the general factor (i.e., sensitivity to the morphological structure of words), overly focusing on spelling may hinder vocabulary knowledge. Here, the bifactor model results should be interpreted carefully as morphological spelling processing is part of the general factor, which did support vocabulary knowledge in a large way. What our results suggest is that the general factor may be assessing consideration of overlap between form and meaning, which would include recognizing This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge 29 transparent overlap in spelling like between know and knowledge. It may be that the specific factor is isolating an overreliance on morphological spelling processing while not considering overlap in meaning. Because morphological relationships are often conveyed opaquely in English, overly focusing on spelling may get in the way of vocabulary knowledge. For example, when determining the meaning of provision, the change in spelling between provide and provision may hide the morphological overlap, instead suggesting overlap with units like pro or vision. Our results highlight the different application of morphological skills to different literacy tasks. Also, neither the suffix tasks, the morphological judgment task, nor the morphological reading task supported vocabulary skills beyond the general factor, which indicates that the primary support for vocabulary in those tasks was in applying general morphological sensitivity or knowledge of the presence of meaningful units within words to vocabulary knowledge.</p><p>In terms of reading comprehension, beyond the general factor, only morphological meaning processing provided support. Here it seems that general sensitivity to morphological structures was most important in supporting reading comprehension, with additional morphological meaning knowledge providing further supports likely because this extra derived word knowledge could be applied to support reading comprehension endeavors beyond general morphological sensitivity. Beyond considering morphological overlap, applying meaning knowledge of a root word or suffix seems to help reading comprehension. On the other hand, both morphological spelling and morphological reading tasks had a negative relationship with reading comprehension, but this may be related to the age of our participants. As <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Gilbert et al. (2014)</ref> points out, it may be that by 7 th and 8 th grade, lexical representations have become modular such that a word's orthographic form activates information about the word instantaneously. Therefore, perhaps overly focusing on morphemes pronunciation This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge 30 (morphological word reading processing) or orthographic form (morphological spelling processing) when it is not needed may make it hard to focus on meaning or comprehension.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations and Future Research</head><p>Our study is the first attempt to fit this model and more research perhaps including other item level data should be done to replicate our findings. Also, our study involves theoretically identified dimensions; therefore, it would be beneficial for other studies to investigate the relations of tasks and dimensions using other theoretical frameworks and exploratory factor analyses. For example, future research should examine other possible dimensions of morphological awareness not included within our study such as morpho-syntactic knowledge (i.e., knowledge of the grammatical role of morphemes, <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Tong, Deacon, &amp; Cain, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Tyler &amp; Nagy, 1989)</ref> and cognate awareness (i.e., awareness that words in multiple languages share orthographic and semantic characteristics like rapid and rápido; <ref type="bibr">Jiménez, Garcia, &amp; Pearson, 1996)</ref>, as well as other possibilities. This exploration might take age, reading level, and/or language background of students into account as the relationships between tasks may differ for different readers. For example, whereas our study found that morphological meaning processing was uniquely positively associated with reading comprehension beyond the relation of the general factor for adolescent readers, a study with younger students or struggling word readers may find morphological word reading processing may play a significant role in reading comprehension beyond the role of the general factor due to the importance of word reading at that developmental point and for struggling readers. Such relationships have yet to be explored in this manner.</p><p>Another important area to consider in future research is the relation between content and task. Four of our seven morphological measures involved the same set of words, suggesting the This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved. need to replicate with different content. Also, our tasks included various morphological forms (i.e., inflections, derivations, compounds, or a combination of those), different morphological word parts (i.e., free or bound roots, prefixes, suffixes), and variation in lexicality (i.e., complex words, simple words, or pseudowords). The morphological content also differed in transparency of how the units were combined (i.e., phonological, orthographic, and semantic transparency), frequency of the units involved (i.e., frequency of the base, the complex word, and the morphological family), and length (i.e., number of morphemes). Studies such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Goodwin et al. (2013)</ref> have shown that transparency can affect how students apply morphological knowledge to word reading, and therefore, it is important to unravel the relationship between content and task.</p><p>For instance, if the content is inflections or compounds, do the tasks fall into the same categories? And are they likely to be related to outcomes such as reading comprehension?</p><p>A challenge in our study involved missing data. We were fortunate that the psychometric literature included guidelines for dealing with missing data and therefore, we were able to leverage full information maximum likelihood estimation to estimate this missing data within our analyses and gain trustworthy results <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Enders, 2010)</ref>. We also encountered challenges related to priming since we had to administer multiple assessments to determine what students knew about morphological knowledge at a single point in time. We hope future studies will replicate our findings with less missing data and different priming choices.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary</head><p>Overall, our study takes an important first step of identifying the dimensionality of morphological knowledge based on performance on tasks designed to tap application of morphological knowledge to different literacy areas. Our results suggest that morphological knowledge can best be understood as a general construct and specific dimensions that represent This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge 32 distinctive morphological skills that have unique relationships to different literacy skills. For adolescent readers, it seems that the general factor that represents a student's general ability to use, identify, and manipulate morphemes within words is particularly important for facilitating vocabulary knowledge and reading comprehension. Applying morphological knowledge to derived word meanings is also helpful in supporting reading comprehension and vocabulary, while generating morphologically complex words, or thinking about words within morphological families, is helpful in building vocabulary knowledge. For adolescents, it seems that lexical entries are becoming modular, and therefore having to use morphological information to support word reading and spelling of derived words was negatively related to reading comprehension and vocabulary, suggesting overuse of mental resources on code-type work versus more comprehension and meaning-related work. Our study suggests considering dimensionality is likely to lead to more accurate assessment of morphological knowledge and deeper understandings of the mechanisms underlying the contributions of morphological knowledge to literacy achievement.</p><p>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved. This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.  This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved. This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>Dimensionality of morphological knowledge 47  This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Participants</head><label></label><figDesc>There were 371 participants (234 seventh graders and 137 eighth graders; 181 males and 190 females) who attended two suburban schools in the southeastern United States (309 School A and 62 School B). Both schools reported grades of A on state standardized tests and served This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Standardized Test of Reading Comprehension (MacGinitie, MacGinitie, Maria, &amp; Dreyer, 2000) was used to assess reading comprehension via Form S of Level 7 through 9. The measure consisted of 11 passages with 48 multiple choice comprehension questions. Extended scale scores were used. Vocabulary knowledge. The Gates-MacGinitie Standardized Test of Reading Vocabulary (MacGinitie, MacGinitie, Maria, &amp; Dreyer, 2000) was used to assess reading vocabulary knowledge. Participants read an underlined word within a phrase and then selected the word or phrase that means most nearly the same. The 45 items on form S of Level 7 through 9 were administered. Extended scale scores were used.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Each model consisted of a combination of a general factor, a term we use to refer to the latent variable representing the general construct of morphological knowledge stemming from overlap of the seven morphological measures, and/or specific factors, a term we use to refer to each of the hypothesized dimensions representing elements of morphological knowledge unique from the general factor. Based on the literature, we created two hypothesized combinations of specific factors. Models we labeled as TACIT&amp;STRATEGIC had two specific factors representing morphological tacit processing (indicated by morphological spelling, word reading, and meaning processing tasks combined) and morphological strategic analysis (indicated by tasks involving analysis of the internal structure of words). Alternatively, models we labeled as TASK consisted of seven specific factors representing the unique demands of each morphological task (representing different aspects of morphological knowledge such as morphological reading, morphological spelling, morphological meaning, consideration of morphological overlap, analysis of the role of suffixes in real words and in pseudowords, and generation of morphologically related words).In all, six measurement models were evaluated: 1) a 1-factor (i.e., UNIDIMENSIONAL) model of morphological knowledge where the general factor represented overlap of the items This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge 19 from the 7 observed measures (i.e., a general morphological knowledge factor), 2) a two-factor (TACIT&amp;STRATEGIC) model with specific factors of strategic morphological analysis and tacit morphological processing, 3) a seven-factor (TASK) model with specific factors for each of the tasks, 4) a 2 nd order, seven-factor (2 nd order, TASK) model with specific factors for each task and a 2 nd -order factor (representing overlap of the latent composites or general morphological knowledge), 5) a 2-factor bi-factor (bi-factor TACIT&amp;STRATEGIC) model with specific factors representing strategic morphological analysis and tacit processing and an additional general factor of morphological knowledge, which was measured by the 7 manifest variables, and 6) a 7factor bi-factor (bi-factor TASK) model with specific factors representing each task and an additional general factor of morphological knowledge.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Finally</head><label></label><figDesc>, the bi-factor model allows for testing the extent to which the general and specific factors uniquely predict proximal or distal outcomes. The specification of the bi-factor model requires that the specific factors of morphological knowledge are uncorrelated. This achieves several purposes; by specifying the orthogonality of the specific and general factors, the specific factors represent what is uniquely measured by the respective constructs after controlling for what is shared by the general factor. Therefore, in a subsequent structural analysis, it is possible to determine whether the specific components uniquely relate to the vocabulary and reading comprehension tests, after controlling for what is shared between them.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>UNIDIMENSIONAL model [χ²(5,459) = 6,270.66, CFI = .89, TLI = .89, RMSEA = .02 (95% CI = .017, .022), AIC = 22696.51, ABIC = 22854.14] indicated that a general factor of morphological knowledge did not fit well. When comparing the criterion and relative fit indices across models, the two best fitting specifications were the 7-factor model (TASK) [χ²(5,438) = 5,593.38, CFI = .98, TLI = .98, RMSEA = .009 (95% CI = .000, .013), AIC =21598.22, ABIC This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved. Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge 23 =21771.46] and the 7-factor-bifactor (bi-factor TASK) model [χ²(5,353) = 5,575.02, CFI = .97, TLI = .97, RMSEA = .011 (95% CI = .005, .014), AIC = 21748.85, ABIC = 21985.29]. Results with the full sample echoed these findings of excellent fit, although suggesting the 7-factorbifactor (bi-factor TASK) model might be superior based on AIC and ABIC values [7-factor model AIC= 46525, BIC=48409; 7-factor-bifactor model AIC= 46508, ABIC=47021].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>morphological knowledge were used to test the predictive validity of the factors in understanding individual differences in reading comprehension and reading vocabulary. The standardized This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved. Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge 25 coefficients from this model are displayed in Figure 2. The SEM model provided excellent fit to the data [χ²(5550) = 5784.14, CFI = .97, TLI = .97, RMSEA = .011 (95% CI = .005, .014)]. The estimates suggest that the general morphological knowledge factor most strongly predicted reading comprehension (.70), with small, unique effects observed for morphological reading (-.20), morphological spelling (-.17), and morphological meaning (.19); sixty-one percent of the variance in reading comprehension was explained by the factors. For the vocabulary outcome, the general morphological knowledge factor maintained the strongest association (.76) with small, unique effects of morphological generation of root words (.13), morphological spelling (-.16), and morphological meaning (.20); sixty-nine percent of the variance in vocabulary was explained by the latent factors.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Structural model results showing standardized coefficients of the general factor (i.e., morphological knowledge) and the seven specific morphological factors predicting reading comprehension and vocabulary.</figDesc><graphic coords="48,93.60,150.53,50.99,490.94" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Experimental MeasuresNote: Morph=Morphological; Morph-related=Morphologically-related; ' =Information for culled item set.</figDesc><table><row><cell>#</cell><cell>Task Type</cell><cell>Subtest</cell><cell>Adapted from</cell><cell>Skill Assessed</cell><cell>Example item</cell><cell>#</cell><cell>Reli-</cell><cell>N</cell><cell>Mean'</cell><cell>Min',</cell><cell>Scale</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(Morph. _)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>items</cell><cell>ability</cell><cell></cell><cell>(SD)'</cell><cell>Max'</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(')</cell><cell>α (')</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>Analysis</cell><cell>Suffix Choice</cell><cell>Mahony</cell><cell>Complete sentence with best of</cell><cell>Did you hear (directs,</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>.90</cell><cell>366</cell><cell>8.41</cell><cell>0,9</cell><cell>0,1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Real Word</cell><cell>(1994)</cell><cell>four answers that are derivations</cell><cell>directions, directed)?</cell><cell>(9)</cell><cell>(.90)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(1.64)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(SCR)</cell><cell></cell><cell>with same stem</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>Analysis</cell><cell>Suffix Choice</cell><cell>Singson et al.</cell><cell>Choose the most appropriate</cell><cell>Our teacher taught us</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>.85</cell><cell>366</cell><cell>9.20</cell><cell>1,11</cell><cell>0,1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Pseudoword</cell><cell>(2000)</cell><cell>pseudoword to complete the</cell><cell>how to (jittling, jittles,</cell><cell>(11)</cell><cell>(.82)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(2.38)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(SCP)</cell><cell></cell><cell>given sentence</cell><cell>jittle).</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell cols="2">Analysis Morph. Judgment</cell><cell>Mahony</cell><cell>Determine whether pairs of</cell><cell>Does personal come from</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>.57</cell><cell cols="2">366 12.19</cell><cell>3,14</cell><cell>0,1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Task</cell><cell>(1994)</cell><cell>words were morphologically</cell><cell>person? [poet-poetic,</cell><cell>(14)</cell><cell>(.68)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(1.99)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(MJT)</cell><cell></cell><cell>related</cell><cell>add-addition, ill-illegal]?</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell cols="2">Analysis Generate Morph-</cell><cell>Townsend,</cell><cell>Produce morphologically related</cell><cell>Given forget, produce</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>.93</cell><cell cols="2">192 12.28</cell><cell>0,16</cell><cell>0,1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>related Words</cell><cell>Bear, &amp;</cell><cell>words given a root word</cell><cell>related words [forgetful,</cell><cell>(16)</cell><cell>(.90)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(4.06)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(GMRW)</cell><cell>Templeton</cell><cell></cell><cell>forgets, forgetting].</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(2009)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell cols="2">Processing Morph. Spelling</cell><cell>Carlisle</cell><cell>Spell a dictated derived word</cell><cell>Spell finance; Spell</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>.90</cell><cell>191</cell><cell>9.64</cell><cell>0,20</cell><cell>0,1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(MSPELL)</cell><cell>(1988)</cell><cell>correctly when the related root</cell><cell>financial.</cell><cell>(20)</cell><cell>(.88)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(5.07)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>was spelled correctly</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell cols="2">Processing Morph. Meaning</cell><cell>Tyler &amp; Nagy</cell><cell>Judge level of knowledge of a</cell><cell>Do you have no, some, or</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>.88</cell><cell>190</cell><cell>9.95</cell><cell>0,19</cell><cell>0,1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(MMEAN)</cell><cell>(1989)</cell><cell cols="2">derived word's meaning based on full knowledge of</cell><cell>(19)</cell><cell>(.87)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(4.61)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>level of knowledge of a related</cell><cell>finance's definition? Of</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>root word</cell><cell>financial' s definition ?</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>Processing</cell><cell>Morph. Word</cell><cell>Carlisle &amp;</cell><cell>Orally pronounce the written</cell><cell>Read aloud finance; Read</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>.89</cell><cell cols="2">311 10.32</cell><cell>0,17</cell><cell>0,1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Reading</cell><cell>Stone (2005)</cell><cell>derived word correctly when the</cell><cell>aloud financial.</cell><cell>(17)</cell><cell>(.83)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(3.88)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(MREAD)</cell><cell></cell><cell>related root word is pronounced</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>correctly</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Pearson Product-Moment Correlations Between Experimental Morphology and Standardized Outcome Measures Note. SCR=suffix choice for real words; SCP=suffix choice for pseudowords; MJT=morphological judgment task; GMRW=Generate morphologically-related words; MSPELL=morphological spelling processing; MMEAN=morphological meaning processing; MREAD= morphological word reading processing; RComp=reading comprehension; ESS=extended scale scores; RVocab=reading vocabulary; *p&gt;.05. Upper diagonal are correlations for the reduced subscales, lower diagonal are correlations for original subscales.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>1. SCR</cell><cell cols="2">1.00 .67</cell><cell>.38</cell><cell>.26</cell><cell>.29</cell><cell>.18</cell><cell>.33</cell><cell>.38</cell><cell>.34</cell></row><row><cell>2. SCP</cell><cell>.75</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>.51</cell><cell>.41</cell><cell>.55</cell><cell>.25</cell><cell>.50</cell><cell>.50</cell><cell>.48</cell></row><row><cell>3. MJT</cell><cell>.46</cell><cell>.48</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>.41</cell><cell>.51</cell><cell>.35</cell><cell>.44</cell><cell>.51</cell><cell>.56</cell></row><row><cell>4. GMRW</cell><cell>.44</cell><cell>.43</cell><cell>.41</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>.54</cell><cell>.39</cell><cell>.51</cell><cell>.42</cell><cell>.46</cell></row><row><cell>5. MSPELL</cell><cell>.47</cell><cell>.56</cell><cell>.49</cell><cell>.62</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>.55</cell><cell>.59</cell><cell>.55</cell><cell>.54</cell></row><row><cell>6. MMEAN</cell><cell>.24</cell><cell>.26</cell><cell>.36</cell><cell>.48</cell><cell>.57</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>.45</cell><cell>.51</cell><cell>.53</cell></row><row><cell>7. MREAD</cell><cell>.52</cell><cell>.58</cell><cell>.44</cell><cell>.56</cell><cell>.71</cell><cell>.43</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>.44</cell><cell>.52</cell></row><row><cell>8. Gates RComp ESS</cell><cell>.51</cell><cell></cell><cell>.52</cell><cell>.49</cell><cell>.58</cell><cell>.49</cell><cell>.47</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>.70</cell></row><row><cell>9. Gates RVocab ESS</cell><cell>.48</cell><cell>.48</cell><cell>.56</cell><cell>.53</cell><cell>.55</cell><cell>.51</cell><cell>.55</cell><cell>.70</cell><cell>1.00</cell></row></table><note><p>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Measurement Model Fit Indices CFI = Comparative Fit Index; TLI = Tucker-Lewis Index,; RMSEA = Root Mean Square Error of Approximation, LB = RMSEA 95% Confidence Interval Lower Bound; UB = RMSEA 95% Confidence Interval Upper Bound; AIC = Akiake's Information Criteria, ABIC = Sample Size Adjusted Bayes Information Criteria; the two best fitting models are italicized.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Model Description</cell><cell>χ²</cell><cell>df</cell><cell>CFI</cell><cell cols="2">TLI RMSEA LB</cell><cell>UB</cell><cell>AIC</cell><cell>ABIC</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>1-factor</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(UNIDIMENSIONAL)</cell><cell cols="2">6270.66 5459</cell><cell cols="2">0.89 0.89</cell><cell>0.020 0.017</cell><cell cols="2">0.022 22696.51 22854.14</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>2-factor</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(TACIT&amp;STRATEGIC)</cell><cell cols="2">6024.06 5458</cell><cell cols="2">0.93 0.92</cell><cell>0.017 0.014</cell><cell cols="2">0.019 22326.61 22484.98</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>7-factor</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(TASK)</cell><cell cols="2">5593.38 5438</cell><cell cols="2">0.98 0.98</cell><cell>0.009 0.000</cell><cell cols="2">0.013 21598.22 21771.46</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>2 nd order 7-factor</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(2 nd order, TASK)</cell><cell cols="2">5707.48 5452</cell><cell cols="2">0.97 0.97</cell><cell>0.011 0.006</cell><cell cols="2">0.015 22845.12 22953.24</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>2-factor bi-factor</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(bi-factor TACIT&amp;STRATEGIC)</cell><cell cols="2">5572.83 5353</cell><cell cols="2">0.97 0.97</cell><cell>0.011 0.005</cell><cell cols="2">0.014 21856.28 22312.29</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>7-factor bi-factor</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(bi-factor TASK)</cell><cell cols="2">5575.02 5353</cell><cell cols="2">0.97 0.97</cell><cell>0.011 0.005</cell><cell cols="2">0.014 21748.85 21985.29</cell></row><row><cell>Note.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Factor Correlation Matrix -7-factor Model Measurement model results showing multidimensionality of morphological knowledge.Note. Labels of observed variables are: SCR=suffix choice for real words; SCP=suffix choice for pseudowords; MJT=morphological judgment task; GMRW=Generate morphologically-related words; MSPELL=Morphological spelling processing; MMEAN= Morphological meaning processing; MREAD=Morphological word reading processing. See Appendix B for factor loadings for each item.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">Construct GMRW MJT</cell><cell>SCP</cell><cell>SCR</cell><cell cols="2">MREAD MSPELL</cell></row><row><cell>GMRW</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>MJT</cell><cell>0.55</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>SCP</cell><cell>0.48</cell><cell>0.82</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>SCR</cell><cell>0.27</cell><cell>0.71</cell><cell>0.93</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>MREAD</cell><cell>0.65</cell><cell>0.65</cell><cell>0.64</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>MSPELL</cell><cell>0.71</cell><cell>0.73</cell><cell>0.73</cell><cell>0.47</cell><cell>0.84</cell><cell>1.00</cell></row><row><cell>MMEAN</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.61</cell><cell>0.45</cell><cell>0.24</cell><cell>0.62</cell><cell>0.61</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p>Dimensionality of morphological knowledge 46</p>Figure 1.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Dimensionality of morphological knowledge 48</figDesc><table><row><cell>Appendix A:</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">List of Overlapping Content Contained within Processing Measures</cell></row><row><cell>Root Words</cell><cell>Derived Words</cell></row><row><cell>out</cell><cell>outsource</cell></row><row><cell>economy</cell><cell>economical</cell></row><row><cell>expedite</cell><cell>expeditious</cell></row><row><cell>strict</cell><cell>restriction</cell></row><row><cell>convene</cell><cell>convention</cell></row><row><cell>sphere</cell><cell>thermosphere</cell></row><row><cell>perceive</cell><cell>perception</cell></row><row><cell>covet</cell><cell>covetousness</cell></row><row><cell>diagnose</cell><cell>diagnostician</cell></row><row><cell>scribe</cell><cell>circumscribe</cell></row><row><cell>phone</cell><cell>phonetic</cell></row><row><cell>quest</cell><cell>unquestionably</cell></row><row><cell>migrate</cell><cell>migratory</cell></row><row><cell>state</cell><cell>reinstate</cell></row><row><cell>meter</cell><cell>biometric</cell></row><row><cell>dorm</cell><cell>dormant</cell></row><row><cell>discrete</cell><cell>discretionary</cell></row><row><cell>enchant</cell><cell>disenchantment</cell></row><row><cell>graph</cell><cell>telegraph</cell></row><row><cell>tranquil</cell><cell>tranquility</cell></row><row><cell>strategy</cell><cell>stratagem</cell></row><row><cell>dictate</cell><cell>dictator</cell></row><row><cell>distinct</cell><cell>distinguish</cell></row><row><cell>reside</cell><cell>residence</cell></row><row><cell>sign</cell><cell>significance</cell></row><row><cell>finance</cell><cell>financially</cell></row><row><cell>relative</cell><cell>irrelevant</cell></row><row><cell>benefit</cell><cell>benefactor</cell></row><row><cell>aqua</cell><cell>aquascape</cell></row><row><cell>verify</cell><cell>veritable</cell></row><row><cell>sense</cell><cell>hypersensitivity</cell></row><row><cell>genuine</cell><cell>disingenuous</cell></row><row><cell>usurp</cell><cell>usurpatory</cell></row><row><cell>irate</cell><cell>irascible</cell></row><row><cell>nation</cell><cell>nationalistic</cell></row><row><cell>compose</cell><cell>composite</cell></row><row><cell>extreme</cell><cell>extremity</cell></row><row><cell>sage</cell><cell>sagacity</cell></row><row><cell>precede</cell><cell>precedent</cell></row><row><cell>malign</cell><cell>malignant</cell></row></table><note><p>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_1"><p>We used the Standard Frequency Index (SFI) where about half of 6 th grade texts have an average SFI value of 32.This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div><p>This research was made possible through startup funding from <rs type="funder">Vanderbilt University's Peabody College</rs>. We thank the students and teachers who participated in the study. <rs type="person">Dr. Petscher</rs>'s time was supported by the <rs type="funder">Institute of Education Sciences</rs> <rs type="grantNumber">R305F100005</rs> and <rs type="grantNumber">P50HD052120</rs> from the <rs type="funder">National Institute of Child Health and Human Development</rs>. This research was made possible through startup funding from <rs type="funder">Vanderbilt University's Peabody College</rs>. We thank the students and teachers who participated in the study. <rs type="person">Dr. Petscher</rs>'s time was supported by the <rs type="funder">Institute of Education Sciences</rs> <rs type="grantNumber">R305F100005</rs> and <rs type="grantNumber">P50HD052120</rs> from the <rs type="funder">National Institute of Child Health and Human Development</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_PeBKRVu">
					<idno type="grant-number">R305F100005</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_QwDUdPH">
					<idno type="grant-number">P50HD052120</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_S874xsH">
					<idno type="grant-number">R305F100005</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_2NA28Mc">
					<idno type="grant-number">P50HD052120</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Zeno, S. M., <ref type="bibr">Ivens, S. H., Millard, R. T., &amp; Duvvuri, R. (1995)</ref>. The educator's word frequency guide. Touchstone Applied Science Associates, INC.</p><p>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge 41</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Standards for educational and psychological testing</title>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">&amp; National Council on Measurement in Education.</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>American Educational Research Association</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Vocabulary development: A morphological analysis. Monographs of the society for research in child development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Anglin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="186" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developing register differentiation: The Latinate-Germanic divide in English</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bar-Ilan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Berman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Linguistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative fit indexes in structural models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bentler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="238" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Significance tests and goodness of fit in the analysis of covariance structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bentler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Bonnett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="588" to="606" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Growth in phonological, orthographic, and morphological knowledge in grades 1 to 6</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Berninger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Abbott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Nagy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Carlisle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10936-009-9130-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Psycholinguistic Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="163" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metalinguistic differences among three kinds of readers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bialystok</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mitterer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="153" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a definition of meta-linguistic skill</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bialystok</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Merrill-Palmer Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="251" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alternative ways of assessing model fit</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Browne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cudeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Methods Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="230" to="258" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge of derivational morphology and spelling ability in fourth, sixth, and eighth graders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Carlisle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Psycholinguistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="247" to="266" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Awareness of the structure and meaning of morphologically complex words: Impact on reading</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Carlisle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reading and Writing: An Interdisciplinary Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="190" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lexical processing of morphologically complex words in the elementary years</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Carlisle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fleming</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific Studies of Reading</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="239" to="253" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morphemes matter: How morphological knowledge contributes to reading and writing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Carlisle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Goodwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of language and literacy: Development and disorders</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Silliman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ehren</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wallach</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Guilford Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="282" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the role of morphemes in word reading</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Carlisle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reading Research Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="428" to="449" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Explanatory multidimensional multilevel random item response model: An application to simultaneous investigation of word and person contributions to multidimensional lexical quality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gilbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Goodwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11336-013-9333-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="830" to="855" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Awareness of language: Some evidence from what children say and do</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>A. Sinclair, R. Jarvella, &amp; W.J.M. Levelt</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
			<publisher>Springerverlag</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="43" />
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The child&apos;s conception of language</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison of inclusive and restrictive strategies in modern missing data procedures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Schafer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="330" to="351" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Coxhead</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A New Academic Word List</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="238" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">This turnip&apos;s not for turning: children&apos;s morphological knowledge and their use of root morphemes in spelling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Deacon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bryant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British Journal of Developmental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="567" to="575" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of morpheme recognition and morphological knowledge in dyslexia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Elbro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Arnbak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Dyslexia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="240" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Enders</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Applied missing data</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>NY, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Guilford Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morphological analysis by child readers as revealed by the fragment completion task</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Feldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rueckl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Diliberto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pastizzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Vellutino</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychonomic Bulletin and Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="535" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Flanigan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Templeton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Bear</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Invernizzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Johnston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Words their way with struggling readers</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Pearson/Allyn &amp; Bacon</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a universal model of reading</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Frost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/S0140525X11001841</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behavioral and Brain Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="329" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Advances in morphological processing: An introduction, Language and Cognitive Processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Frost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Grainger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Carreiras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/01690960802321925</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="933" to="941" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multisyllabic word reading as a moderator of morphological awareness and reading comprehension</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gilbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Goodwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Compton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kearns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0022219413509966</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Learning Disabilities</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Does meaning matter for reading achievement? Untangling the role of phonological recoding and MA in predicting reading and vocabulary achievement for Spanish-speaking English language learners</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goodwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="94" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>60 th Yearbook of the Literacy Research Association</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morphological contributions to adolescent word reading: An item response approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Goodwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gilbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/rrq.037</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reading Research Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probing lexical representations: Simultaneous modeling of word and person contributions to multidimensional lexical representations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Goodwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gilbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kearns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0034754</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="448" to="468" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Word detectives: Morphological instruction that supports academic language</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Goodwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Perkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/trtr.1342</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Reading Teacher</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="504" to="517" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Greek morphemes lessons (It&apos;s not greek to me!), 2 nd Edition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>GOTAGS</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The reading strategies of bilingual Latina/o students who are successful English readers: Opportunities and obstacles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Jiménez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>García</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Pearson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reading Research Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge of words, knowledge about words: Dimensions of vocabulary in first and second language learners in sixth grade</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kieffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Lesaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11145-010-9272-9</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reading and Writing: An Interdisciplinary Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="347" to="373" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morphological awareness and learning to read: A crosslanguage perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1207/s15326985ep4103_3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Educational Psychologist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="180" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Children read affixed words and non-words</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Laxon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rickard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Coltheart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British Journal of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="407" to="423" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Macginitie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Macginitie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Maria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Dreyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Gates-MacGinitie reading test</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Itasca, IL</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Riverside Publishing Company</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>th ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using sensitivity to word structure to explain variance in high school and college level reading ability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mahony</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reading and Writing: An Interdisciplinary Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Making meaning: children&apos;s sensitivity to morphological information during word reading</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mccutchen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Logan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Biangardi-Orpe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1598/RRQ.44.4.4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reading Research Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="360" to="376" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The nature of morphological knowledge (Doctoral dissertation)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Muse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Retrieved from Proquest (No. 3198241</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Muthén</forename><surname>Muthén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Mplus (Version</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Computer software</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The number of words in printed school English</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Nagy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reading Research Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="304" to="330" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Contributions of morphology beyond phonology to literacy outcomes of upper elementary and middle school students</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Nagy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Berninger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Abbott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0022-0663.98.1.134</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="134" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship of morphology and other language skills to literacy skills in at-risk second-grade readers and at-risk fourth-grade writers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Nagy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Berninger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Abbot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Vaughan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>&amp;vermeulen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0022-0663.95.4.730</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="730" to="742" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved. Dimensionality of Morphological Knowledge</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morphological knowledge and literacy acquisition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Nagy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Carlisle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Goodwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0022219413509967</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Learning Disabilities</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effects of learning to spell on children&apos;s awareness of morphology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nunes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bryant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bindman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11145-006-9025-y</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reading and Writing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="767" to="787" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Putting two and two together: Middle school students&apos; morphological problem solving strategies for unknown words</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Pacheco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Goodwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/JAAL.181</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Adolescent and Adult Literacy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="541" to="553" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reading ability: Lexical quality to comprehension</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Perfetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10888430701530730</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific Studies of Reading</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="357" to="383" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian model selection in social research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Raftery</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Methodology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="163" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Reise</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Morizot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hays</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11136-007-9183-7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The role of the bifactor model in resolving dimensionality issues in health outcomes measures</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="31" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morphology in word identification: A word experience model that accounts for morpheme frequency effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Reichle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Perfetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific Studies of Reading</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="237" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development in children&apos;s sensitivity to the role of derivations in spelling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sangster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Deacon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0018569</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Canadian Journal of Experimental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="139" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morphological awareness skills of English language learners and children with dyslexia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Siegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Topics in Language Disorders</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relation between reading ability and morphological skills: Evidence from derivational suffixes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Singson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mahony</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Mann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reading and Writing: An Interdisciplinary Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3-4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="252" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Tennessee Department of Education Report Card</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Report</forename><surname>Tdoe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Card</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://edu.reportcard.state.tn.us/pls/apex/f?p=200:1" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4463180647001600" to="8" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An investigation of morphological awareness and processing in adults with low literacy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Tighe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Binder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/S0142716413000222</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied psycholinguistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">02</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="273" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the dimensionality of morphological awareness and its relations to vocabulary knowledge in adult basic education students</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Tighe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Schatschneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/rrq.102</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reading Research Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morphological and syntactic awareness in poor comprehenders: Another piece of the puzzle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Tong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Deacon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Cain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0022219413509971</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Learning Disabilities</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The acquisition of English derivational morphology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tyler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Nagy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Memory and Language</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="649" to="667" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use of derivational morphology during reading</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tyler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Nagy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cognition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Vocabulary acquisition: Implications for reading comprehension</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Muse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tannenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>The Guilford Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
