<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The temporal conceptual data modelling language Trend</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2024-08-20">August 20, 2024</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sonia</forename><surname>Berman</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cape Town</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ZA">South Africa</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Maria</forename><surname>Keet</surname></persName>
							<email>mkeet@cs.uct.ac.za</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cape Town</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ZA">South Africa</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tamindran</forename><surname>Shunmugam</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cape Town</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ZA">South Africa</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The temporal conceptual data modelling language Trend</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2024-08-20">August 20, 2024</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2408.09427v1[cs.DB]</idno>
					<note type="submission">Preprint submitted to An international Journal</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T18:34+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Entity-Relationship Diagrams</term>
					<term>Temporal Conceptual Data Modeling</term>
					<term>User Studies</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Temporal conceptual data modelling, as an extension to regular conceptual data modelling languages such as EER and UML class diagrams, has received intermittent attention across the decades. It is receiving renewed interest in the context of, among others, business process modelling that needs robust expressive data models to complement them. None of the proposed temporal conceptual data modelling languages have been tested on understandability and usability by modellers, however, nor is it clear which temporal constraints would be used by modellers or whether the ones included are the relevant temporal constraints. We therefore sought to investigate temporal representations in temporal conceptual data modelling languages, design a, to date, most expressive language, Trend, through small-scale qualitative experiments, and finalise the graphical notation and modelling and understanding in large scale experiments. This involved a series of 11 experiments with over a thousand participants in total, having created 246 temporal conceptual data models. Key outcomes are that choice of label for transition constraints had limited impact, as did extending explanations of the modelling language, but expressing what needs to be modelled in controlled natural language did improve model quality. The experiments also indicate that more training may be needed, in particular guidance for domain experts, to achieve adoption of temporal conceptual data modelling by the community.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Temporal constraints in conceptual data models are important for many application domains, ranging from temporal conceptual data modelling, to business process modelling, data analytics, and designing append-only databases for blockchains, among others. Such a variety of application scenarios would ideally be served by a very expressive temporal conceptual data modelling language (TCDML) that would then be used throughout the various application scenarios for once-off effort of learning as well as easy reuse. Most extant TCDMLs, however, either lack transition constraints for object migration, temporal attributes, or relation migration (among others, <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>), and none of them has been evaluated by users on preferences for diagram notation with, importantly, temporal constraints, nor for understanding of a temporal model or ability to create a temporal conceptual data model. Here we include modellers in industry as well as undergraduate and postgraduate students in academia who have been taught conceptual modelling. Thus, there is, as a minimum, a need for an evaluation on fitness for purpose.</p><p>In this paper, we aim to address this through the development of a TCDML that is grounded in the description logic language DLR US and for which we designed and evaluated a graphical notation through a series of experiments. The resulting TCDML we called Trend, Temporal information Representation in ENtity-relationship Diagrams. In so doing, we sought to answer the following questions: RQ1: What diagram notation is preferred for temporal elements and constraints? RQ2: How well is the resulting temporal conceptual model understood by modellers? RQ3: How well are modellers able to design such models?</p><p>To answer these questions, we conducted three sets of experiments. The first was a series of progressive experiments to determine the 'best', or most preferred, notation of temporal information among the plethora of notations, using a qualitative reflective learning approach with participants mainly from industry and a moderately-sized evaluation with postgraduate students. The second set of experiments focussed on model understanding and feedback on a few minor variants in notation for the transition constraint, among postgraduate students and a large cohort of undergraduate students. The third set of experiments zoomed in on the ability to design temporal conceptual models with a temporal conceptual data modelling language we designed, through varying the amount of explanation and the task to carry out, in three large-scale experiments with 200-450 participating students that are comparative novices in modelling, for increased statistical validity of the conclusions.</p><p>The qualitative evaluations led to a 'tentative' notation for our TCDML, Trend, and also indicated a need for some training on modelling temporal information. The quantitative experiments finalised and solidified the Trend notation. The experiments revealed that the labels for the transition constraints have little impact on correctness, but a graphical notation is clearly preferred over controlled natural language text. Temporal entity types, attributes, and dynamic extension are best used. More extensive introductory notes did not assist substantially in modelling and understanding overall, although a marked increase in modelling in temporal attributes and relationships was observed. Better demarcation of the domain, in the form of a set of controlled natural language statements, did improve modelling quality of the temporal constraints.</p><p>This paper extends our previously published work <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref> in a number of ways. While Trend was tested with a small number of participants in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, here we summarise also the experiments leading up to that version and conduct large scale evaluations that also finalised the graphical notation. In addition, the preliminary Trend was only sketched in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, whereas here we present the full language-graphically, textually, and with its formal logic-based underpinning for precision and reference. We also provide an overview of the related work more comprehensively.</p><p>The remainder of the paper is structured as follows. Section 2 summarises related work. Section 3 describes the first set of experiments and results to determine the preferred representation in extended ER diagrams. Section 4 and Appendix 7 introduce Trend and its formal foundation. Section 5 reports on the experiments on model understanding and ability to design. Section 6 discusses the work and Section 7 concludes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Related work</head><p>The related work is divided into three sections. We begin with laying out a few theoretical principles relevant to the context. The two successive sections describe the extant temporal conceptual modelling languages that have a graphical and/or textual representation, and some further notions on how to represent temporal information based on related visualisation work. The latter has been added to broaden the view, because the former did not demonstrate much creativity in representation options.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Theoretical principles on graphical language design</head><p>We first lay out four theoretical principles that will be adopted and extrapolated into the experiments so as to get a better understanding of possible preferred temporal information representation.</p><p>The first principle is that of of usability. This principle, as per definition in the ISO 9241-11 standard, is "the extent to which a product can be used by specified users to achieve specified goals with effectiveness, efficiency and satisfaction" <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> in a specified context of use. This principle will be experimented with in terms of the ability to use the proposed notation when communicating the conceptual model during the Software Development Lifecycle (SDLC).</p><p>The second principle is that of notation, or "visual notation", as defined by Moody <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. He describes that the visual notation can also be represented as visual, graphical, or diagramming notation consisting of a set of: 1) graphical symbols (the visual vocabulary), 2) compositional rules (the visual grammar), and 3) definitions of the meaning of each symbol (the visual semantics). This research will highlight visual conceptual models and visual semantic components that are used to represent the temporal aspects of conceptual models and their perceived meanings they represent.</p><p>The third principle is that of communication theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Communication is a key concept for the interpretation of conceptual models to aid understandability. Most humans seemingly understand concepts better when they see how it works. The aim in this principle is to show that preferred visual metaphors help with, principally: communicating complex ideas effectively, that humans retain information longer when they understand what they are looking at, communicating to a wide range of people with different backgrounds, condensing information onto a limited canvas, and attract and hold the attention of observers as a learning tool.</p><p>Lastly, we take note of principles of the SDLC. That is, accepting that visual conceptual models play an important role viz. in the communication, planning, and data analysis/modelling phases of software development <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Visual Representations in temporal conceptual data models</head><p>Many different TCDMLs have been introduced for the visualisation of temporal information for database development. In this short review, we will include also 'older' TCDMLs, because they typically have more graphical adornments for temporal information than the more recent ones. It is of note that the vast majority of proposals have their origins in (Extended) Entity Relationship Diagram (ERD) rather than UML. Because of this and that the two approaches for extension proposed for UML Class Diagrams are not transferrable to ERD <ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">2</ref> , we focus on ERDbased modelling languages. They are summarised in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> at the end of this section. The temporal aspects included may be valid time (true in the real world), transaction time (when the fact was stored in the database), or both, and more or less constraints on temporal classes, relationships, and attributes.</p><p>For the older models proposed before 1999, we largely base the overview on Gregersen and Jensen's review <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, because not all of the original papers were available. TERM <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> was the first temporally extended ER with valid and transaction time and multiple granularities (as described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>). TERM is entirely text-based, as is TEER <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, and has no adornments at all in the diagrams, unlike the 15 others. Gregersen and Jensen's 'TempEER' (unnamed by the authors) is TEER extended to the relational model according to the proposers <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, and thus obviously has no relevant adornments.</p><p>The other seven 'old' TCDMLs all have one or more adornments to the ERD, of which only the most recent in that set had a clock icon, being TERC+ from 1997 <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. TERC+ is a predecessor to the spatiotemporal MADS <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> that was developed by the same group over the period of 1997-2006, which in its final version has seven different clock types and one hourglass to indicate different aspects of time, such as time, instant, interval, and timespan (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">1-A</ref>). The only other TCDML with an icon, also a clock, is LTRM <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, as depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">1-B</ref>.</p><p>RAKE <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> extends the ER model with timestamps to supports modelling the type DATE, which still persist in current DBMSs, and has further attributes such as a 'BEGIN' and time periods as a class attached to a relationship. Other graphical extensions include signalling temporal elements by creating a double-lined element, as in MOTAR (Narasimhalu in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>), shading temporal elements like in STEER <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, and adding two parallel diagonal lines as in 'TempRT' (Kraft in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>). The characteristic graphics are included in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">1-C</ref>.</p><p>TER by Tauzovich, as described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, differentiates itself by including lifetime and snapshot time varying cardinality constraints. The lifetime aspects are denoted by an "L" with minL and maxL and snapshot by "S" with minS and maxS and they are represented on the model using the following format: L [minL,maxL] and S[minS,maxS]. A similar adornment is used in TimeERplus <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. This brings us to the more recent proposals which, as can be seen also from Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, have predominantly textual adornments rather than graphical modifications or icons, with the exception of LTRM and MADS. A selection of the typical notations in context are included in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>. LTRM is based on mathematical expressions <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> where data is represented with past as well as present values and activation start and activation end on a temporal entity that is indicated with a clock symbol. That is, it has a combination of ways to communicate temporal information.</p><p>Three of the eight 'recent' (post-1999) models follow the same approach of adornments as ERT <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, which adds a mini-rectangle to the rectangle of the entity type or relationship, where a T is written. This "T-stamping" approach is also used in TimeER <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, TimeERplus <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, ER VT <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, and EER ++ VT <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Each of these adds further 'letter stamps', depending on what the TCDML supports, such as VT, TT, BT, and LS.</p><p>Further adornments largely depend on the type of temporal features the TCDML supports. For instance, TimeERplus <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> extends EER with both valid time and transaction time, lifespan, and time granularities, similar to TimeER <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. Khatri et al.'s telic/atelic extension to USM, here dubbed 'TA USM' as it was nameless in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, add the notion of accomplishments denoted with Acc() in the model, among others, which are formally specified in an annotation grammar. These are all temporal features of the elements. ER VT has the notion of transitions, were objects can extend or migrate from one entity type to another, called dynamic extension (Dex) and dynamic evolution (Dev), respectively. This is indicated with labelled arrows in the diagrams. EER ++ VT [5] extends ER VT with attribute and relation migration <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>, also indicated with similar arrows and corresponding abbreviations (ADex and RDex etc.).</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> lists the modelling languages examined with the way how it represents temporal features. Observe that every model differs in terms of the temporal constructs using components of HCI such as different shapes, shading, and pictures, and only TERM and TEER are entirely text based. Except for ST USM, none of these theoretical models have been tested on users. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Techniques for Temporal Data Visual Representations</head><p>Because of the limited creativity on representing termporal notions, we describe other techniques of temporal data using graphical representations namely, Pointwise Object Browsing, Concentric Circles, Agenda, Time Line Browser, Lifelines, Knave, and AsbruView. The reason for broadening the scope is twofold: the adornments described in the previous section assume a lot of in-depth knowledge of temporal information that may not be familiar to the non-expert temporal modeller, and those proposals may perhaps have been limited to stay within the ER notation of ideas and ideas of related extensions, such as the clocks and the 'letter stamping'. Several notations have been discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, such as the visualisation as Lifelines <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, Time Line Browser <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> and "time slider" <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, Knave <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>, Concentric Circles <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34]</ref>, and Agenda <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>, which are summarised in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>, and we highlight three here for their distinct approaches.</p><p>The Pointwise Object Browsing representation <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref> is used to display snapshots of temporal data at a given instant in a drill-down fashion. There are two ways for users to interact with the temporal data: by traversing through traditional object browsers or by altering the reference instant; a diagram is included in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">13</ref>. The features of this technique are that it is not sequential, it supports value alteration, and provides interaction devices for navigating to the previous or next instant where a modification arises in a given conception track expression. This may perhaps be useful for instance-motivated temporal modelling, like is possible for (atemporal) Object-Role Modeling <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> and the FCO-IM method <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref> (cf. the natural language text-oriented temporal data <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref> or constraints <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref> in ORM that emphasise verbalisation of the information in pseudonatural language sentences).</p><p>AsbruView <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> deviates from any TCDML notation by representing 'plans' in a 3-dimensional view, as to what is allowed to happen concurrently, what sequentially, and crucial change points. A sample diagram is included in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">14</ref>.</p><p>Third, to be able to grasp the more complex notions of temporal information in temporal conceptual models, one needs to understand the simplified time period visualisation of intervals. Chittaro and Combi <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> looked into that with three different representations, using metaphors like springs and elastic bands. For instance, the end of strips must be connected and fixed by screws: an interval ends in this case, have fixed and set positions in relation with other intervals. The principal reason motivating this choice is that "the fixed ends cannot move so the strip's ends are fixed." <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>. An example of the notation is included in the Appendix below (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">16</ref>), for it was used in one of the questionnaires.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> summarises the surveyed techniques for the representation of temporal data and history. Some techniques are purely visual whilst others combine text and visual indicators. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Preferences for notations of temporal constraint in diagrams</head><p>To determine the preferred notation of temporal constraints that led up to Trend and to evaluate modelling and understanding of them, a suite of experiments were conducted, which are enumerated and summarised in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>. Those 11 experiments can be grouped into 3 stages: Experiment 1 (E1) to Experiment 6 (E6) that led up to a first assumed stable version of Trend; then a second stage with mainly E7 and part of E8 that had a dual function of finalising some notation and increasing the scale to result in a possibly final Trend; and a third stage consisting mainly of (very) large scale experiments for increased statistical validity and robustness of conclusions to be drawn from them, consisting mainly of experiments E9 and E11 (with the small scale E10 as motivator for E11 to eliminate a lingering doubt emerging from the results of E9). From a research process perspective, experiments E1-E6 and part of E7 and E8 concern the design of the language, whereas the second set of experiments, being the other part of E7 and E8, E9, and E11, concern the evaluation of Trend. This section focuses on the experiments that influenced the design of Trend, whereas the large-scale evaluations are deferred to Section 5.</p><p>Based on the results of the first experiment, the methodology adopted was that of "reflective teachings" <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, for most conceptual modellers are not experts in temporal modelling. Reflective teachings amounts to: 1) a set of tasks is presented to a group of users; 2) the results are critically analysed by the facilitator to ascertain the knowledge level of the population; 3) If the level is too low, the facilitator conducts a knowledge transfer to the group to increase their knowledge level. This process may be repeated as often as needed. The main goals are to dispel all anxiety and ensure that the population knowledge level is increased to an extent whereby results can be used for effective analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">E1-E5: reflective teachings experiments</head><p>The set-up, results, and discussion about small-scale experiments E1-E5 are summarised in this section, with the details described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>. The aim here is to provide an impression and insight in the process that led up to the draft notation of Trend, i.e., mainly serving to narrow down the plethora of possible graphical and textual adornments, rather than a detailed account for reproducibility. The successive experiments are outlined in their approach and key outcomes are discussed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.1.">Experiment 1: Textual and graphical notations</head><p>The aim of the initial experiment was to evaluate the representations of temporal information in conceptual models by means of an online questionnaire.</p><p>This consisted of seventeen exercises and a section for feedback and comments. The URL was sent to an open audience of computer science students, developers, database lecturers, and business users, assumed to have some knowledge of databases and ER diagrams. Some models used were taken from existing work mentioned in Section 2 and others had different colour schemes, visual icons, text and graphics. A selection of the diagrams is included in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">15</ref> in the Appendix. Subjects were asked their model preferences, and they were given one open question requiring a description of what a small temporal conceptual model meant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2.">Experiment 2: Interval notations</head><p>Results of Experiment 1 (E1) showed that few respondents understood the subject matter and temporal aspects in general. The aim of this, and the following, experiment was to close this knowledge gap. To gauge if the knowledge gap was indeed getting smaller, the audience had to be narrowed down to a smaller closed group subset of 12 business users with varied knowledge levels of information technology and database concepts.</p><p>Training was provided before Experiment 2 (E2) in the form of an online video explaining temporal aspects in Microsoft SQL Server 2016 <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>. This was the first step to raise their knowledge level. Participants were then given 12 multiple choice questions to evaluate three temporal representations, viz. springs, elastic bands and paint strips, as proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>. This was followed by a classroom discussion, where it was found that there was still confusion among the group about temporal data. Temporal concepts were further explained using the visual techniques of concentric circles, Agenda, time line browser, and AsbruView. They learnt about time intervals, transaction and valid time, history and why it is important, and differences between atemporal and temporal databases. When questioned about other difficulties in E1, we found they also did not understand the proposed models. Hence, Experiment 3 was setup to introduce modelling to the group.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.3.">Experiment 3: Modelling change</head><p>Three tasks were posed to the same participants as in E2, so as to gauge their understanding of modelling and to show that without a visual language for understanding conceptual models, interpretation of diagrams could be very diverse. The diagrams in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">17</ref> (in the Appendix) were self-generated so as to be ambiguous, and the same 12 participants were asked to give their understanding of each. There was no constraint on the time taken. Qualitative data was also recorded when subjects were asked to describe their interpretations verbally.</p><p>This showed that some members did not grasp concepts such as constraints, if-then, loops, dependencies, and flows. The follow-up training explained entities, attributes, migrations, both evolution and extension, constraints, inheritance and relationships, and that a symbol on a diagram has different meanings depending on the context it is used in.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.4.">Experiment 4: The effects of training</head><p>This was principally a repeat of E1, carried out on the same, but now "knowledgeable", subjects. There was one minor change: an ER VT , EER ++ VT , and a MADS model were added to the "Which conceptual model do you prefer?" question. In analysing the data, some discrepancies were observed, so a follow-up discussion was held with the group to shed light on it.</p><p>Analysis of data from E4 revealed that the preferred temporal conceptual model was RAKE. From interviews it was ascertained that this was chosen because of its simplified notation. Some inconsistencies were noted however. There was a perceived preference for pictorial over textual representation, yet RAKE temporal indicators are text only. Secondly, the preferred picture for temporal representation was the clock, which is not used in RAKE. On discussing this with the group, it emerged that their preference was the ERD diagram and this outweighed the preference for the clock graphic. The Dex/Dev textual representation was preferred by business users due to being easier to draw accurately on flipcharts and whiteboards, and easier to interpret.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.5.">Experiment 5: Model preferences</head><p>In this experiment, the group was asked to rate temporal conceptual models on a linear scale from 1 to 10. All models were drawn with equivalent information. Based on E4 discussions and earlier stated preferences for ERD models, for textual representation of migration constraints, and for less complexity, five questions were used in the survey.</p><p>Each model was derived from the ERD representation, namely: STEER, TER, LTRM, MO-TAR, RAKE, ER VT and TEMPPR models. The first survey question had them unmodified (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">18</ref> in the appendix), whereas the second had them modified using the clock icon (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">19</ref>). All models (except for ER VT ) had a textual representation for constraint migration of Dex in question 3, and then also with the clock icon in question 4. A selection of the models is included in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_19">20</ref>. Comments about the survey were also elicited.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Zooming in on dynamic constraint details with more subjects</head><p>Finally, we wondered about the representation of dynamic (transition) constraints, not covered in the previous experiments. Questions were tagged onto two related experiments that are reported on in detail in Section 5. These involved three different, and larger, sets of university students, so as to canvas a broader group of potential users and potentially obtain results with more statistical validity and confidence. Two kinds of transitions were described to participants: dynamic extension (abbreviated Dex), being one where an entity remains an instance of its type but also becomes an instance of another type, and dynamic evolution (abbreviated Dev), being one where an entity changes from being of one type to being of another type.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1.">Experiment 6: Arrows and labels for dynamic constraints</head><p>Among a set of questions that will be described in detail in Sect. 5, we evaluated preference for a labelled arrow to depict dynamic constraints, as opposed to one with a triangle as in UML's subsumption notation. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> shows the options that participants of E6 could choose from; Dev and Dex having been introduced as the labels representing the two types of dynamic transition. Additionally, we introduced dashed lines for optional transitions and solid lines for mandatory transitions, which was not asked about in the evaluation. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2.">Experiments 7 and 8 (part 1): transition labels</head><p>In the other two experiments, E7 and E8, subjects were asked to propose alternative terms to Dev and Dex, if they wished, as part of a set of questions (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.3.">Experiment 9 (part 1): validating labels</head><p>Results obtained from E7 and E8, which were held in the same year, led to another round of the experiment in a later cohort, comparing the labels Dev and Dex to labels Chg and Ext, respectively, and, for dynamic constraints in the past, the " -" superscript versus lower/uppercase, like Dex -vs dex. The materials and methods are described in Sect. 5 (and only mentioned here for narrative flow), because they could be combined with the quantitive assessment since the class size had more than doubled in the meantime.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.4.">Results</head><p>Eleven of the 15 postgraduate students (PG1, in E6) answered the questions on the arrow's shape in the related experiment <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. For the question on the arrow shape, 4 preferred the arrow and 7 preferred the triangle as illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3b</ref>. However, when put in the light of the question on how to denote persistent extension or evolution, the picture becomes more complicated. Four participants preferred as is, i.e., an arrow with PDex/PDev (but they are not the same 4 as for the previous question), 3 preferred the pin next to the text, 2 preferred a pin in the triangle, and 2 ties for option b and c. Thus, now a majority does not want the triangle. Because of the ambiguous result, we keep the simpler notation, i.e., a simple arrow tip.</p><p>In the related experiment E8, involving 179 participants (UG1), 100 of them provided 1892 alternative labels for Dex and Dev, with a substantial actual overlap in strings having the same stem. The most popular choices were: Change (13), Extend <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>, Add (9), Becomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>, Also <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>, Transform (8), Mutate <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> and Progress <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>.</p><p>Strings that had at least two proposers (n = 34), were independently categorised by two authors as a possible alternative for Dev, Dex, or neither. Fourteen strings were categorised the same by both authors. Combining this with most-proposed, Extend emerged as best alternative for Dex, and Change or Transform for Dev. These could be abbreviated as Ext, and Chg or Tran.</p><p>As we shall see in Sect. 5, E9 showed that there is no overwhelming preference for one or the other set of labels for the transition constraints, nor does it have a large combined effect in modelling and understanding of Trend. We therefore proceeded to defining Trend (presented next, in Sect. 4) and examine its usability, which will be reported on in Section 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Specification of Trend</head><p>We now describe the visual vocabulary and semantics of Trend. We do this by relying on the formal foundation of ER VT (and thus also the extension to EER ++ VT ) and the mapping presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, and extend it for the addition cf. EER ++ VT , being the distinction between optional and mandatory transitions, which in the logic-based reconstruction is an additional existentially quantified relation. As in <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>, the specification consists of several steps, whose orchestration is depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>. Observe that Trend still fully relies on DLR US <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> and does not go beyond it; we exploit its expressiveness better. We summarise the key features first, roughly in the way it was also introduced to the participants of the experiments. Then the textual syntax and the direct semantics are presented, whereas DLR US and the mapping of Trend into DLR US is relegated to the Appendix.  <ref type="figure">4</ref>: Orchestration of approach to obtain the links between a swappable visual modelling language, the reusable syntax and semantics, and relation to DLR US , and their relation to the ER VT specification in <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> (equally applicable for EER ++ VT ). Observe the bi-directional mapping between text and graphics and the unidirectional mapping into DLR US .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Key features of Trend</head><p>Trend focuses on temporalising classes, relationships and attributes, and specifying temporal transition constraints. The core transition constraints are dynamic extension (Ext) and dynamic evolution (Chg). In an extension, the entity is also an instance of the other entity whereas with evolution, the entity ceases to be an instance of the source entity type. An example of extension is when an Employee becomes a Manager they remain an Employee, and of evolution is when a SeniorLecturer becomes an AssociateProfessor because then they are no longer a SeniorLecturer. A clock icon indicates a temporal element, and arrows labeled with Chg and Ext represent temporal transitions. A dashed arrow shaft denotes an optional transition and a solid shaft denotes a compulsory transition. Labels are chg and ext when the transition constraints refers to the past; e.g., a Graduate must have been a Student before. Both future and past transitions are needed when these transition constraints differ: e.g., Student becoming a Graduate in future is optional, but Graduate having been a Student in the past is compulsory. Any transition constraint can include a time quantity to indicate how much time must elapse before the transition can occur.</p><p>The final notation is shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref> and in Table <ref type="table">5</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Formal specification of Trend</head><p>The logic-based reconstruction follows the usual approach as in earlier work <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>. Like ER VT and EER ++ VT , Trend supports timestamping for classes, attributes, and relationships and has both a textual and a graphical syntax, along with a model-theoretic semantics (as a temporal extension of the EER semantics <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>). The basic ER VT was de facto extended with transition constraints (relation migration) in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> and with temporal attributes in <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref> to result in EER ++ VT . This was extended with more mandatory vs optional transitions, more precise language features of EER in the formalisation thanks to the consolidation of separate extensions, and an evaluated notation for Trend. The formal foundations of ER VT has been proven to have a correct encoding of ER VT schemas as knowledge base in DLR US (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47]</ref> for details). The extensions up to and including the features in Trend avail of that and are still expressible within DLR US , as shall be shown in the definition further below.</p><p>Here, we first introduce formally the textual syntax of Trend and its mapping to the graphical syntax. This is followed by the Trend semantics and, finally, the mapping of Trend into DLR US .  </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Definition 1 (Trend Conceptual Data Model). An Trend conceptual data model is a tuple: Σ = (L, rel, att, card A , card R , isa C , isa R , isa U , disj C , disj R , cover, s, t, id, E),</formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">C i ∈ rel(R) then player(R, U i ) = C i and role(R, C i ) = {U i }.</formula><p>The signature of the relationship is σ R ⟨U, C, player, role⟩, where for all U i ∈ U, C i ∈ C, if ♯U ≥ ♯C, then for each U i , C i , rel(R), we have player(R, U i ) = C i and role(R, C i ) = {U i }, and if ♯U &gt; ♯C, then there must be a more than one role played by the same class, i.e., at least once player(R, We denote with cmin(C, A, F) and cmax(C, A, F) the first and second component of card A . Note that card A (C, A, F) may be defined only if (A, D) in att(C) for some D ∈ D. 5. isa C is a binary relationship isa ⊆ (C × C). 6. isa R is a binary relationship isa ⊆ (R × R), which is restricted to relationships with the same arity and compatible signatures. 7. isa U is a binary relationship isa ⊆ (U ×U). isa between roles of a relationship is restricted to relationships with compatible signatures. 8. disj C , cover C are binary relations over (2 C × C), describing disjointness and covering ('total'), respectively, over a group of isa C that share the same superclass.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">U i ) = C i , player(R, U i+1 ) = C i and role(R, C i ) = {U i , U i+1 }. 3. card R is a function C × R × U → N × (N ∪</formula><p>9. disj R are binary relations over (2 R × R), describing disjointness over a group of isa R that share the same super-relation (if explicitly declared). 10. id is a function, id : C → A, that maps a class symbol in C to its identifier ('key') attribute and A ∈ A is an attribute defined in att(C), i.e., id(C) may be declared only if (A, D) ∈ att(C) for some D ∈ D. 11. E is the set of transition constraints, holding either between classes, between relationships, or between attributes, including chg and ext for classes, relationships and attributes for the past and chg and ext for the future, their mandatory counterparts (mchg, mext, Mchg, Mext), quantitative change or extension in the past and future (qchg, qext, Qchg, Qext), and Frz for frozen attribute. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">3</ref> A particular constraint for a class (resp. relationship, attribute) is then denoted as, e.g., chg C i ,C j (resp. chgR R i ,R j and chgA A i ,A j ) where i j, and listing the elements in the order of source,target , and for a frozen attribute, the attribute that it applies to, as in Frz A . Quantitative constraints are indicated in the superscript, adhering to the pattern qext n C i ,C j (resp. for relationships and attributes) where n is the unit of measure for the time interval.</p><p>Observe that EER typically does not contain relationship disjointness, nor subsumption on relationship components (roles), and only a few variants admit cardinality constraints on attributes that are permitted here as well. In contrast, since DLR US does not have extensive support for identification and functional dependency support as its sibling language DLR ifd has, id over weak entity types can be declared in the syntax but will not have a corresponding model-theoretic semantics. While these features can be added to DLR US since it is undecidable already anyway, we chose not to change the logic as such new machinery would distract from the key contribution.</p><p>The mappings between the textual syntax and the graphical syntax of Trend is included in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref> for the elements and Table <ref type="table">5</ref> for the constraints.</p><p>The Trend syntax is not designed for human usage as a way to create a conceptual data model, because the diagram notation is. The syntax is meant to facilitate the formalisation and as an exchange syntax to any other notation, such as possibly a coding style notation or a controlled natural language as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, which were not preferred but not widely disliked options either <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. To illustrate the textual syntax nonetheless, consider the Trend diagram in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref> and its textual notation. Key interesting aspects are that a bonus scheme for an academic may change into a subvention scheme (to top up their salary) after three years, and the transition constraints, whose arrows point in the direction whereto the entity will/does/did migrate. Specifically, each emeritus professor definitely used to be an academic employee and, optionally, an employee may become an academic. Further C T consists of Emeritus prof and Academic and A T consists of UID, Bonus, and Subvention.</p><p>The set-based and model-theoretic semantics of the basic ER VT has been described in [47, 1, 2], which was updated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> for the EER ++ VT extensions notably temporalising attributes and refinements in syntax and formalisation <ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">4</ref> , and again here with the Trend extensions. The key differences compared to EER ++ VT is the set of transition constraints E, of which a systematic full formalisation has been included here (not present in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>) and as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> except for updates in Trend syntax, minor typos, and only those that were finally included in Trend.</p><p>The Trend conceptual data modelling language adopts the snapshot representation of temporal conceptual data models <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>. Specifically, following the snapshot paradigm, we have that  </p><formula xml:id="formula_3">(t) i ∧ ∀d i .a i ∈ A I(t) i → d i ∈ ∆ I D i ).</formula><p>B is said a legal temporal database state if it satisfies all of the constraints expressed in the schema, i.e. for each t ∈ T :</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">• For each C 1 , C 2 ∈ C, if C 1 isa C C 2 , then, C I(t) 1 ⊆ C I(t) 2 . • For each R 1 , R 2 ∈ R, if R 1 isa R R 2 , then, R I(t) 1 ⊆ R I(t) 2 . • For each U 1 , U 2 ∈ R, if U 1 isa U U 2 , then, U I(t) 1 ⊆ U I(t) 2 . • For each cardinality constraint card R (C, R, U), then: o ∈ C I(t) → cmin(C, R, U) ≤ #{r ∈ R I(t) | player(r, U) = o} ≤ cmax(C, R, U). • For each cardinality constraint card A (C, A, F), then: o ∈ C I(t) → cmin(C, A, F) ≤ #{a ∈ A I(t) | player(a, From) = o} ≤ cmax(C, A, F). • For C, C 1 , . . . , C n ∈ C, if {C 1 , . . . , C n } disj C C, then, ∀i ∈ {1, . . . , n}.C i isa C C ∧ ∀ j ∈ {1, . . . , n}, j i.C I(t) i ∩ C I(t) j = ∅. (Similar for {R 1 , . . . , R n } disj R R) • For C, C 1 , . . . , C n ∈ C, if {C 1 , . . . , C n } cover C, then, ∀i ∈ {1, . . . , n}.C i isa C C ∧ C I(t) = n i=1 C I(t) i . • For each snapshot class C ∈ C S , then, o ∈C I(t) → ∀t ′ ∈ T .o ∈C I(t ′ ) . • For each temporal class C ∈ C T , then, o ∈C I(t) → ∃t ′ t.o C I(t ′ ) . • For each snapshot relationship R ∈ R S , then, r ∈ R I(t) → ∀t ′ ∈ T .r ∈ R I(t ′ ) . • For each temporal relationship R ∈ R T , then, r ∈ R I(t) → ∃t ′ t.r R I(t ′ ) . • For each snapshot attribute A ∈ A S , then, a ∈ A I(t) → ∀t ′ ∈ T .a ∈ A I(t ′ ) . • For each temporal attribute A ∈ A T , then, a ∈ A I(t) → ∃t ′ t.a A I(t ′ ) . • For each class C ∈ C, if att(C) = ⟨A 1 : D 1 , . . . , A h : D h ⟩, and ⟨C, A i ⟩ ∈ s, then, (o ∈ C I(t) ∧ a i ∈ A I(t) i ) → ∀t ′ ∈ T .a i ∈ A I(t ′ ) i . • For each class C ∈ C, if att(C) = ⟨A 1 : D 1 , . . . , A h : D h ⟩, and ⟨C, A i ⟩ ∈ t, then, (o ∈ C I(t) ∧ a i ∈ A I(t) i ) → ∃t ′ t.a i A I(t ′ ) i . • For each C ∈ C, A ∈ A such that id(C) = A, then, A is a snapshot attribute-i.e. A ∈ A S - and ∀d ∈ ∆ I D .#{o ∈ C I(t) | a ∈ A I(t) } ≤ 1. • For the transition constraint in E:</formula><p>ext, extension in the future, optional o ∈ ext </p><formula xml:id="formula_5">I(t) C 1 ,C 2 → (o ∈ C 1 I(t) ∧ o C 2 I(t) ∧ o ∈ C 2 I(t+1) ); -Mext, Mandatory ext, o ∈ Mext I(t) C 1 ,C 2 → (o ∈ C 1 I(t) → ∃t ′ &gt; t.o ∈ ext I(t ′ ) C 1 ,C 2 ); -ext, extension in the past, optional o ∈ ext I(t) C 1 ,C 2 → (o ∈ C 1 I(t) ∧ o ∈ C 2 I(t) ∧ o C 2 I(t-1) ); -mext, Mandatory ext, past o ∈ mext I(t) C 1 ,C 2 → (o ∈ C 1 I(t) → ∃t ′ &lt; t.o ∈ ext I(t ′ ) C 1 ,C 2 ); -chg, change (evolution), future, optional o ∈ chg I(t) C 1 ,C 2 → (o ∈ C 1 I(t) ∧ o C 2 I(t) ∧ o ∈ C 2 I(t+1) ∧ o C 1 I(t+1) ); -Mchg, Mandatory change (evolution), future o ∈ Mchg I(t) C 1 ,C 2 → (o ∈ C 1 I(t) → ∃t ′ &gt; t.o ∈ chg I(t ′ ) C 1 ,C 2 ); -chg, past, optional o ∈ chg I(t) C 1 ,C 2 → (o C 1 I(t) ∧ o ∈ C 2 I(t) ∧ o C 2 I(t-1) ∧ o ∈ C 1 I(t-1) ); -mchg, Mandatory change, past: o ∈ mchg I(t) C 1 ,C 2 → (o ∈ C 1 I(t) → ∃t ′ &lt; t.o ∈ chg I(t ′ ) C 1 ,C</formula><formula xml:id="formula_6">∈ Qext I(t) C 1 ,C 2 → ∃(t + n) &gt; t.(o ∈ C 1 I(t) ∧ o C 2 I(t) ∧ C 2 I(t+n) ); -MQext, Quantitative extension, future, mandatory o ∈ MQext I(t) C 1 ,C 2 → (o ∈ C 1 I(t) → ∃(t + n) &gt; t.o ∈ Qext I(t+n) C 1 ,C 2 ); -qext, Quantitative extension, past, optional o ∈ qext I(t) C 1 ,C 2 → ∃(t -n) &lt; t.(o ∈ C 1 I(t-n) ∧ o ∈ C 2 I(t) ∧ o C 2 I(t-n) ); -mqext, Quantitative extension, past, mandatory o ∈ mqext I(t) C 1 ,C 2 → (o ∈ C I(t) 1 → ∃(t -n) &lt; t.o ∈ Qext I(t-n) C 1 ,C 2 ); -Qchg, Quantitative change, future, optional o ∈ Qchg I(t) C 1 ,C 2 → ∃(t + n) &gt; t.(o ∈ C 1 I(t) ∧ o C 2 I(t) ∧ o ∈ C 2 I(t+n) ∧ o C 1 I(t+n) ); -MQchg, Quantitative change, future, mandatory o ∈ MQchg I(t) C 1 ,C 2 → (o ∈ C I(t) 1 → ∃(t + n) &gt; t.o ∈ Qchg I(t+n) C 1 ,C 2 ); -qchg, Quantitative change, past, optional o ∈ qchg I(t) C 1 ,C 2 → ∃(t -n) &lt; t.(o ∈ C I(t) 1 ∧ o C I(t) 2 ∧ o ∈ C I(t-n) 2 ∧ o C I(t-n) 1 ); -mqchg, Quantitative change, past, mandatory o ∈ mqchg I(t) C 1 ,C 2 → (o ∈ C I(t) 1 → ∃(t -n) &lt; t.o ∈ Qchg I(t-n) C 2 ,C 1 ); -extR, extension for relationships, future, optional ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ extR I(t) R 1 ,R 2 → (⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ R 1 I(t) ∧ ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ R 2 I(t) ∧ ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ R 2 I(t+1) ); -MextR, extension for relationships, mandatory ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ MextR I(t) R 1 ,R 2 → (⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ R 1 I(t) → ∃t ′ &gt; t.⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ extR I(t ′ ) R 1 ,R 2 ); -extR, extension for relationships, past, optional ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ extR I(t) R 1 ,R 2 → (⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ R 1 I(t) ∧ ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ R 2 I(t) ∧ ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ R 2 I(t-1)</formula><p>). -mextR, extension for relationships, past, mandatory ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ mextR</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">I(t) R 1 ,R 2 → (⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ R 1 I(t) → ∃t ′ &lt; t.⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ extR I(t ′ ) R 1 ,R 2 ); -chgR, change for relationships, future, optional ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ chgR I(t) R 1 ,R 2 → (⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ R 1 I(t) ∧ ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ R 2 I(t+1) ∧ ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ R 1 I(t+1) ); -MchgR change for relationships, future, mandatory ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ MchgR I(t) R 1 ,R 2 → (⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ R 1 I(t) → ∃t ′ &gt; t.⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ chgR I(t ′ ) R 1 ,R 2 ); -chgR, change for relationships, past, optional ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ chgR I(t) R 1 ,R 2 → (⟨o, o ′ ⟩ R 1 I(t) ∧ ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ R 2 I(t) ∧ ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ R 1 I(t-1) ∧ ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ R 2 I(t-1) ); -mchgR, change for relationships, past, mandatory ⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ mchgR I(t) R 1 ,R 2 → (⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ R 1 I(t) → ∃t ′ &lt; t.⟨o, o ′ ⟩ ∈ chgR I(t ′ ) R 1 ,R 2 ); -Frz, "frozen" attribute a ∈ Frz I(t) → ∀t ′ &gt; t.a ∈ A I(t ′ )</formula><p>; -chgA, attribute evolution, where a is a binary relation between a class and a data type, a ∈ chgA</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">I(t) A 1 ,A 2 → ∃t ′ &gt; t.(a ∈ A 1 I(t) ∧ a A 2 I(t) ∧ a ∈ A 2 I(t ′ ) ∧ a A 1 I(t ′</formula><p>) ); -QchgA, Quantitative evolution of an attribute (a is a binary relation between a class and a data type), a ∈ chgA</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">I(t) A 1 ,A 2 → ∃(t + n) &gt; t.(a ∈ A 1 I(t) ∧ a A 2 I(t) ∧ a ∈ A 2 I(t+n) ∧ a A 1 I(t+n) ) where n ∈ Z;</formula><p>Note that, while rather wordy and elaborate for formalisation, it is more versatile than a direct mapping into DLR US or any other temporal logic. Both modifying the icons or transition labels in the graphical notation and using only a well-defined fragment is easy to select and communicate. For the former, it would mean updating the table only, and for the latter only a one-liner on what is in Σ. It will also facilitate implementation, because it offers a text-based version of Trend. A straight-forward extension is to re-introduce all the attribute transitions, which follow the same pattern in formalisation and notation as the relationships.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Evaluating modelling and understanding with Trend</head><p>As no other modelling language supports all the temporal semantics incorporated in Trend, the ability to understand and model with Trend was evaluated by having students use this, and then indicate their own perceived comfort level with temporal concepts. The quality of the models they produced was assessed by recording the number of correct and incorrect uses of each temporal construct. Sect. 5.1 describes the design of the experiments and Sect. 5.2 the results and discussion. -</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Experiment design for E6-E11</head><p>Six experiments were conducted with separate sets of participants, three with smaller groups of postgraduate students (groups PG1 to PG3) and three with large and even larger cohorts of undergraduates (groups UG1 to UG3), of which E6 (with PG1), E7 (with PG2), and E8 (with UG1) took place in one year, E9 with UG2 and E10 with PG3 in another year (but such that UG1 participants could not have participated in PG3 later on), and E11 with UG3 after that. There are thus a number of elements and comparisons; while Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> lists the experiments in sequence and summarises them, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">6</ref> lists the abbreviations and their descriptions, to facilitate keeping track of them all.</p><p>Overall, the experiments were designed to gauge whether Trend models could be correctly interpreted and constructed. Our hypotheses were that Trend models were understandable and that modellers would be able to design models effectively using Trend. Among the six experiments, there were slight variations based on results and insights obtained from the first round of experiments, which are described below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.1.">Experiment 6: understanding Trend diagrams</head><p>Understanding was evaluated first with a small group of 15 postgraduate Computer Science students, PG1, as part of a study on modelling preferences <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The single paragraph in Sect. 4.1, supplemented by a small example, introduced them to Trend. They were then given a Trend model with entity and relationship names such as "P" and "Q", and asked to interpret its five temporal components <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Submissions were independently assessed by two of the authors on a scale from 1 (not understanding) to 5 (perfect understanding), compared, discussed, and harmonised.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.2.">Experiment 7 and 8: understand and create Trend diagrams</head><p>The second and third experiment, with PG2 and UG1, expanded understanding to also construction of Trend models. For PG2, E7 was conducted during a lecture on data modelling to postgraduate Data Science students, who ranged from novice to proficient modellers. This lecture illustrated Trend using 3 small examples, along with a summary of the notation showing its temporal constructs and a description of each (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">21</ref> in the Appendix). Fourteen students participated voluntarily, which required describing the temporal aspects of two small models, drawing a Trend model for a Loans Company (described in one paragraph), and answering seven multiple choice questions, which are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6</ref>. They were given 40 minutes to complete this in the presence of one of the authors. Descriptions of the given models were evaluated by recording understanding of each temporal construct as complete and correct, correct but incomplete, missing or wrong. This method of recording was also used in assessing their Trend models; since the brief was explicit, correctness was established by comparing each against the expected model. Finally, answers to the questions in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6</ref> were recorded along with subjects' home language and stated level of comfort with data modelling.</p><p>The aims and set-up of the large-scale E8 for the UG1 group will be described in the subsection below, for readability.</p><p>After analysis of Experiments 6-8, three more were designed. Experiment 9 (E9) with UG2 had as hypothesis that more explanation and different labelling of the transition constraintsbased on suggestions from the UG1 students in E8-would result in better models and better understanding (details in subsection below). Experiment 10 (E10) with PG3 sought to exclude the possible effect that the students would not know enough of the subject domain and use the temporal constraints possibly incorrectly (or correctly for incorrect understanding) because of it and to assess understanding at a deeper level. Its outcomes motivated Experiment 11 (E11), which ran like E9, but with a more constrained modelling task (also described in the next subsection). The main aim to verify that Trend modelling and understanding outcomes are attributable to the language indeed, not the subject domain understanding or the lack thereof.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.3.">Experiment 10: constraining the modelling task</head><p>PG3 had carefully worded individual statements from the controlled natural language for Trend <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> of a universe of discourse that had to be modelled, one for each key construct of Trend. Their understanding was tested not through describing it but asking them how that temporal constraint might then be implemented in a database. All 11 students enrolled in the Masters in IT conversion course on Databases participated, since it was part of an assignment. The answers were evaluated manually by one of the authors. The model snippets were coded with a Yes/Partial/No and aggregates were computed. The answers of the understanding question were analysed and summed up in keywords and coded as 0=no answer, 1=an off-topic generic answer, 2=wrong answer, and 3=something plausible. The latter category is flexible because there are no algorithms and agreed upon transformations from temporal conceptual data models to a database and therefore multiple options to achieve the same are possible.</p><p>5.1.4. Experiments E8, E9, and E11: the large-scale experiments on understanding and modelling The three large-scale experiments were conducted as part of the first data modelling assignment in the Second Year Introduction to Databases module at the University of Cape Town (UCT). E8 involved the first test a large group, UG1, which aimed at determining which temporal aspects were most commonly used, eliciting many opinions on alternative notations and perceived understandability, and testing our initial hypotheses on a larger sample of models constructed by novices. E9 with UG2 provided an even larger sample for testing our two hypotheses that Trend models were understandable and novices able to design models using it effectively. It also explored whether a modified notation for transitions, and an expanded explanation of Trend, would lead to fewer errors and/or greater usage of temporal constructs by novices. Finally, E11 with UG3 ran like E9 except that the domain content to model was more constrained to allow for grading against a gold standard (known correct answer) by availing of its controlled natural language <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> to generate the description of the intended model and therewith also eliminating the possibility that students would not know enough of the domain.</p><p>Run in different years, the UG1 and UG2 cohorts were asked to design a Trend model of UCT showing "as many temporal characteristics and transitions as possible", and to describe in English what their model shows. Students worked in groups of five to encourage debate and reflection. They were also required to individually answer the 7 multiple choice questions shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6</ref>.</p><p>The Trend extensions to ER modelling were introduced to the UG1 group in a 3-page document that combined the same paragraph (see Section 4) used initially, with the summary table from <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> (alike Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">21</ref>) and 3 small examples from the second experiment. For E9 and E11, this outline was extended to include a better explanation of the new concepts, a graphical depiction of temporal concepts, and a sample of controlled natural language sentences generated from one of the examples.</p><p>The set-up of E9 was extended cf. E8 since the class had doubled in size. For E9, the UG2 group was divided in two, with one half given the original Trend, and the other half a new version in which Dev and Dex were replaced by Chg (change) and Ext (extend) respectively, and in which past and future transitions were distinguished using lower-or uppercase, rather than minus, (as indicated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">7</ref>) and 3 small examples from the second experiment, one of which is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">8</ref>. For E8 and E9, there were thus 3 separate sets of students: UG1 generating a set of models M-UG1, who were given the original Trend notation and short Trend outline; UG2-C in the second cohort generating models in a set labelled M-UG2-C, who were given the new Trend notation (Chg etc.) and extended outline; and UG2-D that created the set of models labelled M-UG2-D, who were given the original Trend notation (Dev etc.) but the extended Trend description. There were 43, 41 and 38 models in sets M-UG1, M-UG2-D and M-UG2-C, respectively.</p><p>All 122 models were codified in an Excel spreadsheet. For each temporal construct, the number of times this appeared in each model was recorded, as well as the number of times incorrectly and correctly used. The total number of entities and relationships was kept as a rough indicator of model size against which to compare the number of temporal components. Choice of optional/mandatory, and direction of transitions in the past, were both encoded as Y for always correct, N for never correct, P for partly correct, and blank for never appearing in the model. In  order not to penalise potential misunderstanding of the regulations at UCT, only definite errors were recorded as incorrect throughout. Thus, for example, specifying Name as a frozen attribute of Course was considered a reasonable, albeit false, assumption, and not counted as a modelling error.</p><p>Answers to the 7 multiple choice questions were also entered in Excel. As some students omitted these, there were 170, 195 and 178 responses from sets M-UG1, M-UG2-D and M-UG2-C respectively.</p><p>Last, we considered the possibility that students may understand the temporal conceptual modelling but know too little, or be too inexperienced, to design a model from scratch on some given domain. For instance, they may understand Dev/Dex but not the university's rules on course registrations and exclusion policies and a mistake about that in the model may be difficult to attribute to either the language or the domain understanding. To double-check this, we set up the third and final large-scale experiment, E11, with the 2022 class of Introduction to Databases (UG3 as group) that was of similar size as UG2 of 2021. Two of the authors created a Trend diagram in the tourism domain and then used the controlled natural language of <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> to generate natural language sentences, such as "Each traveller must evolve to a previous-customer ceasing to be a traveller." and "Once the value for arrival time is set, it cannot change anymore.". The text and the model answer are included in Appendix A4.</p><p>We again took advantage of the large group and split them up into two (named This and That for the students), where This was given Chg/Ext (whose set of created models are labelled M-UG3-C henceforth) and That was given the original Dev/Dex (labelled M-UG3-D) to also assess whether the labelling affected the modelling in a more controlled setting. Both groups were given the same set of sentences and provided with the same Trend explanations as in E9. Groups of five students were created beforehand in the same manner as in E9. We did not include the 7 multiple choice questions <ref type="foot" target="#foot_5">6</ref> . The submitted answers were mostly marked by the tutors, following the marking rubric set by two of the authors and the model answer of the diagram that the sentences were created from. There were 12 'buckets' for 1 mark each, whose total was divided by 2 for the overall mark for that subquestion of the assignment. Buckets include, among others, 'Traveller, Previous Customer and VIP Customer have a clock' (yes:1, no:0), 'any one "past" transition: VIPcust to PrevCust/Traveller; Took(flight) to Pays(flight)', and 'all 3 above correct'.</p><p>The marks were tabulated in a spreadsheet for analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">Results and discussion</head><p>We first describe the small-scale experiments E6, E7, and E10 that have a qualitative flavour, and subsequently the large-scale experiments E8, E9, and E11, which have a distinctly quantitative angle to the assessment of Trend.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.1.">Small-scale experiments</head><p>The 14 Data Science students (PG2 in E7) clearly preferred using Trend to English. The only one who preferred specifications given in English instead, was also the only one "not at all" comfortable with modelling and gave this as the reason for their choice. Only one of those "fairly comfortable" with modelling preferred English to Trend for designing, saying it was "easier to describe something in language (natural) than re-interpret visually". Altogether 4 preferred English and 10 preferred Trend for creating models. Reasons for preferring Trend were "compact", "quicker", "easier", "shows context", "get overview", "easier for brainstorming" and "ensures you think critically". Difficulty with transitions were expressed only by 2 (who found this "somewhat confusing"), and only 1 felt transitions in the past should use the reverse direction. Their responses are summarised in Table <ref type="table">7</ref> and Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">8</ref> further below, in the last column for easy comparison with the large scale experiments. Students' indication of familiarity with modelling showed a positive correlation with their choice of Trend or English for interpreting and creating models (0.50 and 0.60 respectively) but no correlation with their responses to questions about transitions.</p><p>The Data Science students were given 2 Trend models and asked to explain in detail their temporal aspects. There was only one case of any misunderstanding, when a temporal attribute was given as "can change". However, 3/4 of their explanations were imprecise, stating e.g. "is a temporal attribute", explaining transitions as "may/must become" without saying 'additionally' or 'instead', etc.</p><p>For the PG3 students in E10, eleven students submitted their assignments and they all attempted the third question on temporal aspects. Of the five modelling questions, five students answered more than half of them correctly, but none had all of them correct. Combining 'yes' and 'partial', 9/11 scored ≥ 3/5 overall. Per question, the frozen attribute (Q3) was answered correctly most often (n=8) and then Q1 (optional DEV/CHG on entity types) and Q4 (optional DEX/EXT on entity types) with n=6. Curiously, Q5, a simple temporal entity type (i.e., with a clock icon), caused the most problems, with only 2 correct answers and 7 incorrect.</p><p>As to the questions that tested deeper understanding of temporal information, and noting that temporal databases is part of the study material, it indicated little understanding of the subsumption and the transition constraint that had to be converted to a plausible implementation in the database. Three did not answer the question at all, 2 were off-topic, 3 were wrong, and only the remaining 3 had a plausible database solution. An example of a a plausible solution proposed was to add a column for Previous title and a column for an attribute with datatype Date that records the Promotion date, and of a wrong answer was to "add NOT NULL query". The majority of the answers suggest that the modelling answer to the first question is an outcome of a novice still at the reproducibility or limited understanding level of temporal modelling.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.2.">Large-scale experiments: E8, E9, and E11</head><p>Of the total of 567 students (i.e., UG1+UG2) participating in experiments E8 and E9, 74% preferred Trend and only 19% preferred English when creating models (7% had no preference), while 61% preferred Trend and 31% preferred English for understanding others' model (8% indicated no preference). The proportion preferring Trend to English for both purposes was higher in the UG1 group (in E8) than in the UG2 group (in E9), despite the extended explanation given to the latter, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">9</ref>. While the clear preference for Trend is encouraging, fewer preferring Trend for interpreting models may mean some lack confidence in understanding it. Since none of these students were given either a Trend model or English description to interpret, however, it is probably more indicative of their failure to grasp the ambiguity and complexity of English specifications. Perceived understanding of Trend is important, but subsequent analysis revealed that this did not correlate well with their dynamic transition usage. Finally, among these 567 students, 22% felt transitions in the past should be given in the opposite direction; 69% agreed that the direction used was correct as is, and 9% failed to answer. Their other responses on label preferences and understanding of transitions are summarised in Table <ref type="table">7</ref>, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">8</ref>, and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">10</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.3.">How well is Trend used by novice modellers?</head><p>The Loans example given to the 14 Data Science students (PG2 in E7) clearly distinguished Current loans and Historical loans. Of the 11 who had these as 2 separate entities, 9 used transitions between these correctly (5 had Dev, 2 had Dev-and 2 had both), but 2 had Dex instead. None drew the arrow in the wrong direction, and choice of optional or mandatory transition was always correct. Exactly half had attributes of Historical loans as frozen. Half used temporal attributes wrongly, clearly under the misapprehension that this meant value changes over time. The Table <ref type="table">7</ref>: Self-reported rating of own ease/difficulty understanding transitions, in percentages (question in E7, E8, and E9). Participant group → Answer option ↓ two uses considered reasonable as evidence of understanding temporal attributes, were customer salary and loan balance. Attributes were never wrongly made frozen, but 8 left CustomerID as snapshot. There was no correlation between student's indicated comfort level with modelling and the quality of their Trend models. The large-scale studies, involving novice modellers, revealed that the same misunderstanding of temporal attributes was common, and that dynamic extension was less well used than dynamic evolution, as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">9</ref>, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">10</ref>, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">11</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">12</ref>. Frozen attributes, distinction between optional and mandatory transition, and the direction of the arrow for transitions in the past, were all correctly used in most models. Temporal entities were far more common than temporal relationships, and many models had temporal entities participating in atemporal relationships. Different labels for transitions did not impact accuracy of usage, and the improved explanation of Trend in the final experiment did not lead to better models. It should be noted, however, that unlike its predecessor, E9 involved students who had spent only one month on campus before having to learn Computer Science wholly online, due to the Covid-19 pandemic; so it is possible that they were less prepared than the students in UG1 of E8. Also, they were taught EER by a different (junior) lecturer unfamiliar with temporal conceptual models, which may have affected Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">10</ref>: Self-reported rating of own ease/difficulty understanding transitions in the past (1 worst to 5 best). modelling with Trend which may have negatively affected modelling with Trend.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participant group →</head><formula xml:id="formula_10">Answer option ↓ UG1 (n=164) UG2-D (n=193) UG2-C (n=178) UG1 + UG2-D (n=357) PG2 (n=14) Dev/Dex</formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">UG1 (n=164) UG2-D (n=193) UG2-C<label>(n=178) PG2 (n=14)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.4.">How well is each aspect used by novices?</head><p>From the model descriptions required of students, it was clear that the concept of a frozen attribute was well understood. However, while attributes were rarely incorrectly marked as frozen, there were several models where only a subset of the frozen attributes were indicated on the diagram. The issue of whether or not primary keys should be shown as frozen or not was discussed on the class online forum, and remains unclear. It soon became evident that the need to indicate frozen attributes would alert modellers to their lack of knowledge about an organisation: e.g., students did not know which attributes would require a new course to be created at UCT were they to change, so NQF (South Africa's National Qualifications Framework) level, NQF credits, course name, etc. were considered frozen by some but not others. As regards the notation, the drawing pin was the only Trend symbol that modellers struggled to depict, albeit in very few cases.</p><p>The majority of modellers misunderstood temporal attributes as being those properties which can change over time, rather than those which, once set, may not always have a value. This was also borne out in their model descriptions, where this misconception was explicitly stated. Interestingly, while many of those models thus had every attribute contain either a pin or a clock, it is unclear what semantics the others associated with the attributes that had neither and were thus technically mixed attributes. On a more positive note from the perspective of the experiment, over 20 valid temporal attributes were depicted altogether, as a result of students adding attributes such as registration-hold (due to unpaid fees) and prerequisite-subminimum, and more typical or expected frozen attributes such as YearCompleted, as well as declaring identifier attributes, such as StudentNumber, frozen.</p><p>Most uses of dynamic evolution involved part (or all!) of the academic pathway from Applicant to Undergraduate ... PhDstudent to Lecturer ... Professor. Dynamic evolution for relationships was far less common; those that used this typically depicted this for student:course relationships, e.g., registers becoming completes, or planned becoming enrols, and from takes a course to completes or teaches a course. Almost as many models included this evolution incorrectly by placing the transition on relationships of different types, such as from Student takes Course to Student achieves Result. Valid dynamic extension usage was less common and limited to entity types; examples typically being Student becomes Tutor or the like, Lecturer becomes Advisor or the like, and registers extends to completes. In addition, some models had transitions connecting items of different kinds (e.g., from relationship to entity); but these were typically found where non-temporal aspects of models were also used incorrectly. An example of an optional quantitative transition constraint was a Dev 1 between a MAM1000WStudent and MAM2(2LA)Student, i.e., students optionally proceeding to second year mathematics in the next year, and an optional Dex 0.5 from Undergraduate to Tutor. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">10</ref>: Percentage of models using each construct (% using correctly at least once in brackets), in Experiments E7-E9.  Since we are interested in the transitions, we checked whether the correct modelling of the transitions depends on how well they get the easier non-transition temporal aspects correct. We aggregated the latter (B-F in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">11</ref>) and the former (G-M in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">11</ref>) and carried out a paired t-test for both sets (after calibrating to the same scale, by dividing by 5, resp. 7): for M-UG3-D, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">11</ref>: Scores in percentages (rounded) over the two sets of models (for B-M) and the average for each set (N), in E11. B: Traveller, PrevCust and VIPCust have a clock; C: Client and Flight do NOT have a clock; D: a clock on any of those 3 relationships; E: Arrival has pin, and nothing else in the entire model has a pin; F: company has clock and delay has no clock; G: any one of those 4 dotted arrows is dotted; H: any 1 "past" transition has a minus; I: all 3 above correct; J: any one Dev has that word (irrespective of minus/not); K: all 3 above correct; L: any one Dex has that word (irrespective of minus/not); M: all 6 above correct (i.e.have that word, irrespective of whether minus is there or not). p=0.00026, and for M-UG3-C, p=0.00382, i.e., the difference is statistically significant. That is, the scores for the temporal constraints on the elements are statistically significantly higher than the same model's transition constraints, where more (fewer) errors with the easier elements also means more (resp. fewer) errors in the transition constraints, and that for M-UG3-D slightly more so (with 0.82 vs 0.66 out of 1, i.e. 0.16 less) than for M-UG3-C (with 0.85 vs 0.72 out of 1, i.e., 0.13 less).</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">B C D E F G H I J K L M N M-UG3</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Discussion</head><p>The results showed slightly better outcomes for Chg/Ext than Dev/Dex, especially in the more structured modelling task in E11 (results in <ref type="bibr">Table 11)</ref>, although not convincingly so in E9 <ref type="foot" target="#foot_6">7</ref> . In both cases, we had used the same algorithm for creating groups, which thus excludes the possibility of groups of varying aptitude. An average score of in the low 70s (out of 100) based off highly structured sentences is not an excellent mark for modelling with Trend. However, t they did not do better in the the atemporal, regular, EER diagram creation task of the assignment. Furthermore, it was the last question of the assignment and for relatively few marks. Also, these pass marks were achieved without any teaching or support on temporal conceptual data modelling. The only aide was the few pages of written explanation as part of the assignment. This also suggests that modellers in industry may be able to commence with temporal conceptual modelling without the preparatory training that was needed to create Trend in the first place. Put differently: the lessons learned from the reflective teachings approach in experiments E1-E5 have made it into Trend to a sufficient extent.</p><p>The amount of explanation (M-UG1 versus M-UG2) did not have the expected effect of better results both in perception of understanding and quality of the models developed. While this may be due to saturation of the explanation, the extended brief does have additional explanation on visualising key concepts of the flow of time, a slightly longer description of the Trend elements, and a short paragraph illustrating the controlled natural language sentences. Possible interfering factors may have been the different lecturer for UG2 that that may have affected general understanding of ERD (1st time junior lecturer to UG2 compared to seasoned professor to UG1 who had taught ERD many times) and E8 was conducted during COVID-19's 'physically distanced learning' in 2021 (i.e., online teaching &amp; learning) and the campus fire around the same time had disturbed the students. No substantive decline in accuracy between the models in M-UG1 versus M-UG2 may thus indicate an improved effect thanks to the extended explanation.</p><p>Threats to validity of the results are negligible for the large-scale experiment thanks to the size of both the number of students in each of E8, E9 and E11 and that varying parameters and circumstances yielded comparable results. A possible threat to validity may be larger for E1-E5, since they were largely qualitative with few participants. On the positive side, however, they were in-depth and gave insight into the level of difficulty of mastering TCDM that one could not have obtained with quantitative studies alone. Such a series of experiments with other business users might result in a different narrowing down of icon preferences. However, the scaling-up of asking feedback about notation in E6-E8 and their preferences do strongly suggest the chosen notation is acceptable.</p><p>The only other experiment carried out with TCDMLs are those we reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, where we compared it to set-based semantics notation, Description Logics notation in DLR US , a codingstyle notation, controlled natural language sentences, and hand-drawn sketches of Trend (with Dev/Dex). The clear preference of the graphical notation there held also for the much larger group of participants in E8 and E9 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">9</ref>).</p><p>Another threat to the validity might be that there was no existing modelling tool for Trend, requiring the participants to add the elements manually themselves rather than through drag-'ndrop features. We observed true syntactic mistakes only rarely, such as an ext from the entity type Course to an attribute requirements of an entity type Major, and ample use of temporal constraints, and therefore it is unlikely to affect the overall conclusions.</p><p>Returning to our research questions from the Introduction section, we can answer them, as follows. For RQ1, on what diagram notation is preferred for temporal elements and constraints, this culminated in the final Trend notation. The evaluations provided evidence for RQ2 and RQ3, on how well the resulting temporal conceptual model is understood by modellers and how well they are able to design such models, respectively. The answers to these are, overall, 'well enough', hovering around 67-98% correctness in the controlled domain (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">11</ref>). The amount of mistakes made are not worse than in atemporal EER diagrams.</p><p>Lastly, now that there is an evidence-based very expressive TCDML that is usable by novice modellers, it may merit the effort to implement it in a modelling tool and from there to devise algorithms to convert the temporal constraints of Trend into constraints in the physical schema of the database. Another possible direction could be to create fragments of Trend to match the DLs of temporal ontology-based data access <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52]</ref>. Such a suitable decidable fragment then could also serve to add a feature to computationally verify the semantic coherence and correctness of the temporal and atemporal constraints and deduce implicit constraints. The demonstrated usability of Trend may provide sufficient demand to pursue that line of research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Conclusions and Future Work</head><p>The paper presented the new, to the best of our knowledge most expressive, temporal conceptual data modelling language Trend. It emerged from a rigorous process of language development through qualitative focus-groups to identify key icons for the temporal constructs and six subsequent quantitative experiments that finalised and solidified the notation and assessed understandability and usability by modellers. The large-scale experiments demonstrated that the labels for the transition constraints do not affect model correctness much, and providing an extended written explanation of Trend also did not improve quality. Better quality models were produced when the domain was more precisely described, which emphasises the need for guidance for domain experts to describe their needs. While extensive training was needed initially, the large scale experiments showed that the resultant Trend does result in models of sufficient quality from novice modellers, albeit leaving room for improvement.</p><p>Many future research directions are possible, from tooling to spin-offs for temporal ontologybased data access to reaching out to easing the development of temporal ontologies.   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix A5 -Syntax and semantics of DLR US</head><p>This appendix provides an overview of DLR US <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>, it being the foundation for both the semantics and DL notation. DLR US is a fragment of first order logic that combines the propositional temporal logic with Since and Until operators with the (atemporal) DL DLR <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref> in such a way that they can be used with relationships, entity types, and attributes; its syntax and semantics are included in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_19">23</ref>. As usual for DLs, there are concepts C (atomic ones denoted with CN), n-ary DL roles R (relationships, with n ≥ 2, RN), attributes A between a class and a datatype, and DL role components (U, of which F denotes a role component in an attribute, F ⊆ U, and F = {From, To}). The selection expression U i /n : C denotes an n-ary relation whose i-th argument (i ≤ n) is of type C and [U j ]R denotes the j-th argument ( j ≤ n)-i.e., a DL role component, alike a projection over the role-in role R (we omit subscripts i and j if it is clear from the context). Until and Since together with ⊥ and ⊤ suffice to define the relevant temporal operators: ♢ + ('some time in the future') as ♢ + C ≡ ⊤ U C, ⊕ ('at the next moment') as ⊕ C ≡ ⊥ U C, and likewise for their past counterparts. Analogously, there are □ + ('always 40    </p><formula xml:id="formula_13">C → ⊤ | ⊥ | CN | ¬C | C 1 ⊓ C 2 | ∃ ≶k [U j ]R | ∃[F]A | ♢ + C | ♢ -C | □ + C | □ -C | ⊕ C | ⊖ C | C 1 U C 2 | C 1 S C 2 R → ⊤ n | RN | ¬R | R 1 ⊓ R 2 | U i /n : C | ♢ + R | ♢ -R | □ + R | □ -R | ⊕ R | ⊖ R | R 1 U R 2 | R 1 S R 2 A → ⊤ A | AN | ¬A | F : C | ♢ + A | ♢ -A | □ + A | □ -A | ⊕ A | ⊖ A | A 1 U A 2 | A 1 S A 2 ⊤ I(t) = ∆ I O ⊥ I(t) = ∅ CN I(t) ⊆ ⊤ I(t) (¬C) I(t) = ⊤ I(t) \ C I(t) (C 1 ⊓ C 2 ) I(t) = C I(t)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">⊆ R I(t)</formula><p>2 ), for all t ∈ T p .</p><p>This language can be used to represent temporal entity types, relationships, and attributes, and, importantly, also transition constraints, i.e., constraints on evolving objects, relations, and attributes. For the former, one may use either the notation of the DLR US semantics directly, or the DL notation of DLR US ; e.g., o ∈ Plant I(t) → ∀t ′ .o ∈ C I(t ′ ) (with t, t ′ ∈ T p ) states that object o is a member of the temporal interpretation (indicated with "I(t)") of the concept Plant at time t, and if true, then (i.e., "→") for all times t ′ in the set of time points T p , o is still a member of Plant; that is, o is an instance of plant at all time points in the past, present, and future. In DLR US notation, this is declared as Plant ⊑ □ * Plant. In contrast, o ∈ Pro f essor I(t) → ∃t ′ t.o Pro f essor I(t ′ ) states that there is a time t ′ (different from time t) where an object is not a professor, though at time t it was, is, or will be. In DLR US notation, this is Student ⊑ ♢ * ¬Professor.</p><p>The two key transition constraints are dynamic extension (Dex, or Chg in our experiments) and dynamic evolution (Dev, or Ext in our experiments). In a dynamic extension, the element (object, relation, attribute) is also an instance of the other entity type whereas with dynamic evolution, the element ceases to be an instance of the source element. For instance, there may be an extension Student ⊓ ¬TeachingAssisant ⊓ ⊕ TeachingAssisant, and an evolution is Tadpole ⊓ ¬Frog ⊓ ⊕ (¬Tadpole ⊓ Frog). It is permissible to use shorthand notation for these constraints, as proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>: Dex Student,TeachingAssisant and Dev Tadpole,Frog , respectively. • For the set of transition constraints E:</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">• If R 1 isa R R 2 ∈ Σ, then, R 1 ⊑ R 2 ∈ K; • If rel(R) =</formula><p>- </p><formula xml:id="formula_16">If</formula><formula xml:id="formula_17">-If Qext n C 1 ,C 2 , then K contains: Qext n C 1 ,C 2 ⊑ C 1 ⊓ ¬C 2 ⊓ ⊕ n C 2</formula><p>, where ⊕ n abbreviates n times ⊕ , and similarly for relationships;</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">-If Qchg n C 1 ,C 2 , then K contains: Qchg n C 1 ,C 2 ⊑ C 1 ⊓ ¬C 2 ⊓ ⊕ n (¬C 1 ⊓ C 2 )</formula><p>where ⊕ n abbreviates n times ⊕ , and similarly for relationships (QchgR etc.) and attributes (chgA); </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: A: all MADS icons for temporal elements; B: the LTRM clock; C: characteristic graphical adornments of the older models reviewed in [3].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: A selection of model elements from six different TCDMLs to illustrate the sort of adornments used for temporal constraints in the 'recent' proposals.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,118.42,294.90,163.77,50.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Options for the basic arrow shape for the generic dynamic (transition) constraints and for persistence of those transitions.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>such that: L is a finite alphabet partitioned into the sets: C (class symbols), A (attribute symbols), R (relationship symbols), U (role symbols), D (domain symbols), and F (attribute role symbols) which symobolises From and To, where the set C of class symbols is partitioned into a set C S of Snapshot classes (marked with an S), a set C M of Mixed classes (unmarked classes), and a set C T of Temporary classes (marked with a T). A similar partition applies to the set R and to A, and 1. att is a function that maps a class symbol in C to an A-labeled tuple over D, att(C) = ⟨A 1 : D 1 , . . . , A h : D h ⟩.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Table 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Trend constraints. The formal syntax is given in Definition 1. Constraint Icon Textual syntax Comment card R or card A cardinality on the relationship or the attribute (only a sample shown) disj C or disj R disjointness among subtypes or relationships cover covering constraint for subtypes chg, chg, ext, ext, chgR, chgR, extR, extR, chgA optional change or extension, respectively, for in the future and in the past, respectively, for either entity types or relationships, and change for attributes Mchg, mchg, Mext, mext, MchgR, mchgR, MextR, mextR mandatory change or extension, respectively, for in the future and in the past, respectively, for either entity types or relationships Qchg, qchg, Qext, qext, QchgR, qchgR, QextR, qextR, QchgA quantitative optional change or extension, respectively, for in the future and in the past, respectively, for either entity types or relationships, and change for attributes MQchg, mqchg, MQext, mqext, MQchgR, mqchgR, MQextR, mqextR quantitative mandatory change or extension, respectively, for in the future and in the past, respectively, for either entity type or relationships Pchg, Pext, PchgR, PextR example of adding persistence to the transition; it is likewise for the rest 2. rel is a function that maps a relationship symbol in R to an U-labeled tuple over C, rel(R) = ⟨U 1 : C 1 , . . . , U k : C k ⟩, and k is the arity of R. To facilitate constraint specification, we introduce the player and role functions, as follows: if U i :</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>{∞}) denoting cardinality constraints. We denote with cmin(C, R, U) and cmax(C, R, U) the first and second component of card R . 4. card A is a function C × A × F → N × (N ∪ {∞}) denoting cardinality for attributes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: A small partial Trend diagram (left) and corresponding textual notation (right); see text for explanation.</figDesc><graphic coords="16,320.72,141.03,168.16,92.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Multiple Choice Questions posed to students in the UG1 group (E8). It is the same for UG2 in E9, except question 4, which was "How clear would it be using Tran (transform) instead of Chg, &amp; Also instead of Ext?" for M-UG2-C and "How clear would it be using Tran (transform) instead of Dev , &amp; Also instead of Dex ?" for M-UG2-D.</figDesc><graphic coords="20,106.36,140.99,382.57,102.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure7: Summary table of the revised temporal notation for the transition constraints (and corresponding wording in the explanation) for Trend, which was provided to the applicable subset of the experiments' participants from E9 onwards.</figDesc><graphic coords="22,135.05,141.00,325.17,99.27" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8: One of the sample diagrams provided in the Trend outline that was provided to the applicable subset of the experiments' participants from E9 onwards.</figDesc><graphic coords="22,154.18,282.85,286.92,93.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9: Preference for English or Trend usage by the participants of E8 and E9.</figDesc><graphic coords="24,106.36,321.49,382.56,142.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 11 :</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11: Accuracy of usage by students new to data modelling, in all 122 models of E8 and E9 combined.</figDesc><graphic coords="28,163.74,330.42,267.78,145.23" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 12 :</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 12: Accuracy of transition usage by students new to data modelling, in the 79 models in M-UG2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure 17 :Figure 18 :</head><label>1718</label><figDesc>Figure 17: Diagrams of Experiment 3 that participants had to interpret.</figDesc><graphic coords="36,153.81,403.54,290.17,126.16" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Figure 19 :</head><label>19</label><figDesc>Figure 19: Representation of the same temporal information in the six languages (only a selection is shown), updated with the clock preference, which participants had to rate.</figDesc><graphic coords="38,112.65,270.42,184.71,92.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Figure 20 :Figure 22 :</head><label>2022</label><figDesc>Figure 20: Representation of the same temporal information in the six languages (only a selection is shown, which participants had to rate. Except for ER VT that already has Dex and Dev, the other models have been extended with these constraints not present in the language.</figDesc><graphic coords="38,132.67,526.45,215.56,112.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>1 ∩ C I(t) 2 ( 2 ∧ 1 S 2 ∧ 1 ∩ 1 S 2 ∧Figure 23 :</head><label>1221211223</label><figDesc>Figure 23: Syntax and semantics of DLR US ; o denote objects, d domain values, v, w, t ∈ T p .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>1 ⊆</head><label>1</label><figDesc>C I(t)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>2 (</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>1</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>•••</head><label></label><figDesc>⟨U 1 :C 1 , . . . , U k :C k ⟩ ∈ Σ, then R ⊑ U 1 :C 1 ⊓ . . . ⊓ U k :C k ∈ K; • If att(C) = ⟨A 1 : D 1 , . . . , A h : D h ⟩ ∈ Σ, then, C ⊑ ∃[From]A 1 ⊓ . . . ⊓ ∃[From]A h ⊓ ∀[From](A 1 → To : D 1 ) ⊓ . . . ⊓ ∀[From](A h → To : D h ) ∈ K; If card R (C, R, U) = (m, n) ∈ Σ, then, C ⊑ ∃ ≥m [U]R ⊓ ∃ ≤n [U]R ∈ K; If card A (C, A, F) = (m, n) ∈ Σ, then, C ⊑ ∃ ≥m [From]A ⊓ ∃ ≤n [From]A ∈ K; • If {C 1 , . . . , C n } disj C C ∈ Σ, then K contains: C 1 ⊑ C ⊓ ¬C 2 ⊓ . . . ⊓ ¬C n ; C 2 ⊑ C ⊓ ¬C 3 ⊓ . . . ⊓ ¬C n ; . . . C n ⊑ C; • If {R 1 , . . . , R n } disj R R ∈ Σ, then K contains: R 1 ⊑ R ⊓ ¬R 2 ⊓ . . . ⊓ ¬R n ; R 2 ⊑ R ⊓ ¬R 3 ⊓ . . . ⊓ ¬R n ; . . . R n ⊑ R; • If {C 1 , . . . , C n } cover C ∈ Σ, then K contains: C 1 ⊑ C; . . . C n ⊑ C; C ⊑ C 1 ⊔ . . . ⊔ C n ; If id(C) = A, then, K contains: C ⊑ ∃ =1 [From]□ * A; ⊤ ⊑ ∃ ≤1 [To](A ⊓ [From] : C); • If C ∈ C S , then, C ⊑ (□ * C) ∈ K (similar for R ∈ R S ); • If C ∈ C T , then, C ⊑ (♢ * ¬C) ∈ K (similar for R ∈ R T ); • If ⟨C, A⟩ ∈ s, then, C ⊑ ∀[From](A → □ * A) ∈ K;• If ⟨C, A⟩ ∈ t, then, C ⊑ ∀[From](A → ♢ * ¬A) ∈ K.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head>-</head><label></label><figDesc>and likewise for the past counterparts of the quantitative constraints;-If Pext C 1 ,C 2 , then K contains: ⊕ ext C 1 ,C 2 ⊑ □ + C 2and similarly for relationships;-If Pchg C 1 ,C 2 , then K contains: ⊕ chg C 1 ,C 2 ⊑ □ + C 2and similarly for relationships;-If Frz A , then K contains: C ⊑ ∃[From]A ⊓ □ + [From](A → To : D) ∈ K</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="34,125.49,140.99,344.30,157.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="35,125.49,426.49,344.31,224.09" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="39,106.36,166.55,382.56,201.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Summary of TCDML's representation of temporal information.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Model (year)</cell><cell>Brief description of the representation of the</cell><cell>Text, Icon, or</cell><cell>HCI</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>main temporal constructs</cell><cell>Graphical</cell><cell>eval.</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Older TCDMLs (included in the survey of [3])</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">TERM (1983)</cell><cell>Text based</cell><cell>N/A</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">RAKE (1985)</cell><cell>Timestamps and periods in text, extra rectangles</cell><cell cols="2">Graphic and text No</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>and circles</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">MOTAR (1988)</cell><cell>Double-lined diamonds and squares</cell><cell>Graphic</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">TEER (1990)</cell><cell>Text-based, separate list</cell><cell>N/A</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell>TER (1991)</cell><cell></cell><cell>Lifetime and Snapshot times added</cell><cell>Text</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell>ERT (1992)</cell><cell></cell><cell>Extended rectangles with T 'time box'</cell><cell cols="2">Graphic and text No</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">STEER (1993)</cell><cell>Shaded circles and ellipses, separate text</cell><cell>Graphic</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">'TempEER' (1994)</cell><cell>None (TT and VT added in relational model)</cell><cell>N/A</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">'TempRT' (1996)</cell><cell>Diagonal lines</cell><cell>Graphic</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">TERC+ (1997)</cell><cell>Clock added to an element</cell><cell>Icon</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">More recent TCDMLs</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">ST USM (2004)</cell><cell>Formal annotation schema</cell><cell>Text</cell><cell>Yes</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">TimeERplus (2005) VT , TT, BT etc, dates, time granularity, lifespan</cell><cell>Text</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell>MADS</cell><cell>(1997-</cell><cell>Different clocks and one hourglass on the temporal</cell><cell>Icons</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell>2006)</cell><cell></cell><cell>feature</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ER VT (2007)</cell><cell></cell><cell>T for Temporal, S snapshot, DEV/DEX-labeled ar-</cell><cell>Text</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>rows for transitions</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">TimeER (2008)</cell><cell>Text, with VT, LS etc.</cell><cell>Text</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">LTRM (2010)</cell><cell>Clock on the temporal element, start/end text</cell><cell>Icon and text</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">'TA USM' (2014)</cell><cell>Formal annotation schema</cell><cell>Text</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">EER ++ VT (2015)</cell><cell>As for ER VT , also for attributes and relationships</cell><cell>Text</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">The TCDML proposed in this paper</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Trend (2017)</cell><cell>Clock, pin, DEV and DEX for transitions</cell><cell>Icons and text</cell><cell>Yes</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Summary of Temporal Data History Representations.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Temporal Constructs</cell><cell>Textual/Visual/Both</cell></row><row><cell>Pointwise</cell><cell>Object</cell><cell>Uses Linear visualisation to show events at</cell><cell>Visual linear with value alter-</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Browsing Technique</cell><cell>different instants of time</cell><cell>ation</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Concentric Circles</cell><cell>Circles with common midpoint and different</cell><cell>Visual indicator size shows</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>radii</cell><cell>values over time</cell></row><row><cell>Agenda</cell><cell></cell><cell>Matrix based with line shows evolution of</cell><cell>Visual via hotspots</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>history over time period</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Time Line Browser</cell><cell>Uses Linear visualisation to show events at</cell><cell>Visual using snapshots</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>different instants of time</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Lifelines</cell><cell></cell><cell>History based on different levels of granular-</cell><cell>Both text and visual indicators</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>ity</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>AsbruView</cell><cell></cell><cell>Running track representation of history</cell><cell>Both text and visual indicators</cell></row><row><cell>Elastic Bands</cell><cell></cell><cell>Uses Linear visualisation to show events at</cell><cell>Visual using bands to display</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>different instants of time</cell><cell>events in time</cell></row><row><cell>Springs</cell><cell></cell><cell>Uses Linear visualisation to show events at</cell><cell>Visual using springs to dis-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>different instants of time</cell><cell>play events in time</cell></row><row><cell>Paint Strips</cell><cell></cell><cell>Uses Linear visualisation to show events at</cell><cell>Visual using paint strips to</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>different instants of time</cell><cell>display events in Time</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Summary</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="4">of the experiments, in chronological order; n: number of participants, m: number of models; q:</cell></row><row><cell>number of Multiple Choice Question</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>answers.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>No. What</cell><cell>Who</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>E1 Online survey (S1) on textual and graphical notations</cell><cell cols="3">compsci students, de-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">velopers, db lecturers,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">business users (n=15)</cell></row><row><cell>E2 Education, survey on interval notations, discuss &amp; educate</cell><cell cols="3">select group of busi-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ness</cell><cell>users</cell><cell>(BU)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(n=12)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>E3 Modelling change (survey), educate</cell><cell cols="2">BU (n=12)</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">E4 Effects of training: S1 again + one question on preference, discussion BU (n=12)</cell></row><row><cell>E5 Model preferences survey</cell><cell cols="2">BU (n=12)</cell></row><row><cell>E6 Arrows &amp; labels; Modelling and understanding; questions on notation</cell><cell cols="2">PG1 (n=m=15)</cell></row><row><cell>and on Trend vs text; no domain; in-class explanation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>E7 Modelling and understanding; questions on notation and on Trend vs</cell><cell cols="2">PG2 (n=m=14)</cell></row><row><cell>text; Loans Company domain, restricted; in-class explanation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>E8 Dynamic constraint depiction (which labels), Trend vs text; Mod-</cell><cell cols="3">UG1 (n=177; m=43;</cell></row><row><cell>elling and understanding; University domain, open; brief written</cell><cell>q=170)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>memo on Trend</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>E9 Dynamic constraint depiction (Dev/Dex vs Chg/Ext), Trend vs text;</cell><cell cols="3">UG2 (n=390; m=79;</cell></row><row><cell>Modelling and understanding; University domain, open; extended</cell><cell>q=373)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>written memo on Trend</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>E10 Modelling and understanding (as translation to database schema);</cell><cell cols="2">PG3 (n=11)</cell></row><row><cell>extended written memo on Trend and textbook basics on temporal</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>databases; CNL statements in closed domain</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>E11 Dynamic constraint depiction (Dev/Dex vs Chg/Ext); Modelling and</cell><cell cols="3">UG3 (n=402; m=83)</cell></row><row><cell>understanding; CNL statements in closed domain (Tourism); extended</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>written memo on Trend</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Trend basic elements. The formal syntax is given in Definition 1.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Element Icon</cell><cell>Textual syntax</cell><cell>Comment</cell></row></table><note><p>c (regular) atemporal entity type (may also be written in full, with c S ) c T temporal entity type att atemporal attribute (may also be written in full, with att S ) att T temporal attribute Frz Frozen attribute id identifier attribute r atemporal relationship (may also be written in full, with r S ) r T temporal relationship isa C , isa R , isa U Subsumption</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Experiment abbreviations, participant groups, models created and Multiple Choice Questions answered, in chronological order, totalling 1009 participants who created 246 models.</figDesc><table><row><cell>No. Group that participated</cell><cell>Set of Models</cell><cell>MCQ</cell></row><row><cell>E6 PG1 (n=15); postgraduates (Masters or PhD) in</cell><cell>M-PG1 (m=15)</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Computer Science</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>E7 PG2 (n=14); postgraduates, Masters in Data</cell><cell>M-PG2 (m=14)</cell><cell>q=14</cell></row><row><cell>Science</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>E8 UG1 (n=177); 2nd year undergraduate students,</cell><cell>M-UG1 (m=43)</cell><cell>q=170</cell></row><row><cell>database module</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>E9 UG2 (n=390); 2nd year undergraduate students,</cell><cell>M-UG2-C (m=38) with Chg etc.</cell><cell>q=373</cell></row><row><cell>database module (different cohort from UG1)</cell><cell>and M-UG2-D (m=41) with Dev etc.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>E10 PG3 (n=11); postgraduates, Masters in IT</cell><cell>M-PG3 (m=11, with some as model</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>fragments)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>E11 UG3 (n=402); 2nd year undergraduate students,</cell><cell>M-UG3-C (m=42) with Chg etc.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>database module (different cohort from UG1</cell><cell>and M-UG3-D (m=41) with Dev etc.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>and UG2)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Transition label preferences (in percent) among those who rated both given and alternate labels (question in E7, E8, and E9).</figDesc><table><row><cell>very confusing</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Dev/Dex somewhat confusing</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>14</cell></row><row><cell>Dev/Dex OK-takes getting used to</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>43</cell></row><row><cell>Dev/Dex fairly clear</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>39</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>29</cell></row><row><cell>Dev/Dex not confusing at all</cell><cell>34</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>14</cell></row><row><cell>Chg/Ext very confusing</cell><cell></cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Chg/Ext somewhat confusing</cell><cell></cell><cell>10</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Chg/Ext OK-takes getting used to</cell><cell></cell><cell>29</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Chg/Ext fairly clear</cell><cell></cell><cell>42</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Chg/Ext not confusing at all</cell><cell></cell><cell>17</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Temporal construct usage accuracy across all models in each set of models in E8 and E9.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Participant group →</cell><cell>M-UG1</cell><cell>M-UG2-</cell><cell>M-UG2-</cell><cell>M-UG2</cell><cell>All</cell></row><row><cell>Transition Correctness ↓</cell><cell>(m=43)</cell><cell>D (m=41)</cell><cell>C (m=38)</cell><cell>(m=79)</cell><cell>(m=122)</cell></row><row><cell>Overall % of temporal constructs cor-</cell><cell>71</cell><cell>70</cell><cell>70</cell><cell>70</cell><cell>70</cell></row><row><cell>rectly used (across all models)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Overall % Dev transitions correct Overall % Chg transitions correct</cell><cell>85</cell><cell>81</cell><cell>75</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>82</cell></row><row><cell>Overall % Dex transitions correct Overall % Ext transitions correct</cell><cell>62</cell><cell>70</cell><cell>51</cell><cell>60</cell><cell>61</cell></row><row><cell>Overall % Dev/Dex transitions correct Overall % Chg/Ext transitions correct</cell><cell>72</cell><cell>76</cell><cell>62</cell><cell>69</cell><cell>71</cell></row><row><cell>Models with correct Dev/Chg uses &gt;</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>34</cell><cell>37</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>37</cell></row><row><cell>correct Dex/Ext (in %)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Models with correct Dex/Ext uses &gt;</cell><cell>47</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>26</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>34</cell></row><row><cell>correct Dev/Chg (in %)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Models with Dev/Chg errors &gt;</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>Dex/Ext errors (in %)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Models with Dex/Ext errors &gt;</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>29</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>25</cell></row><row><cell>Dev/Chg errors (in %)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>ext C 1 ,C 2 , then K contains: ext C 1 ,C 2 ⊑ C 1 ⊓ ¬C 2 ⊓ ⊕ C 2and similarly for relationships;-If chg C 1 ,C 2 , then K contains: chg C 1 ,C 2 ⊑ C 1 ⊓ ¬C 2 ⊓ ⊕ (¬C 1 ⊓ C 2 )and similarly for relationships;-If Mext C 1 ,C 2 , then K contains: C 1 ⊑ ♢ + ext C 1 ,C 2and similarly for relationships;-If Mchg C 1 ,C 2 , then K contains: C 1 ⊑ ♢ + chg C 1 ,C 2and similarly for relationships;-If ext C 1 ,C 2 , then K contains: ext C 1 ,C 2 ⊑ C 1 ⊓ C 2 ⊓ ⊖ ¬C 2and similarly for relationships;-If chg C 1 ,C 2 , then K contains: chg C 1 ,C 2 ⊑ ¬C 1 ⊓ C 2 ⊓ ⊖ (C 1 ⊓ ¬C 2 )and similarly for relationships;-If mext C 1 ,C 2 , then K contains: C 2 ⊑ ♢ -ext C 1 ,C 2 and similarly for relationships; -If mchg C 1 ,C 2 , then K contains: C 2 ⊑ ♢ -chg C 1 ,C 2 and similarly for relationships;</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>This is not to say that conceptual models are not used elsewhere, notably during runtime for graphical querying<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref>, but that scenario is out of the current scope.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>To the best of our knowledge, there are stereotypes<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> and OCL, such as in<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, but no ERD variant has either of them.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_2"><p>This list of transition constraints can be extended with 'strong' or 'persistent' versus reversible transition.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_3"><p>Notably that of the attribute set, more clearly distinguishing between object o, attribute a, and domain d.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_4"><p>And so, standard relational databases can be regarded as the result of mapping a temporal database from time points in T to atemporal constructors, with the same interpretation of constants and the same domain.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_5"><p>A quiz was added on the CMS to gain feedback on groupwork, but for a purpose unrelated to the Trend evaluation.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="7" xml:id="foot_6"><p>Specifically regarding the results of E9: it leans toward better results with Dev/Dex than Chg/Ext in Table9, due to the generally higher accuracy, but with mixed results in self-reported ease/difficulty in Table7, and slightly clearer Dev -/Dex -over lower-case (Fig.10). In contrast, Chg/Ext constraints are used more per model than Dev/Dex (Table9), thus contradicting perception, and those models have a higher usage of other temporal features compared to the models that use Dev/Dex, notably regarding temporal entity types, more use of temporal relationships, and temporal and frozen attributes.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			
			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We would like to thank all participants in the experiments.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participant group →</head><p>E11 specifically had a controlled setting for what needed to be modelled, eliminating the possibility that the participants knew too little of the universe of discourse. This was achieved by creating the specification from the controlled natural language sentences generated from the</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author Contributions</head><p>TS carried out the literature review and Experiments E1-E5, supervised by CMK. SB and CMK designed and executed E6-E11, data analysis of E7, E8, E9, E11 was carried out by SB, E10's analysis by CMK, and E6-E11 was discussed jointly by SB and CMK. The formal definition of Trend was specified by CMK. CMK coordinated the writing of the manuscript.  Appendix A3 -Summary table for E7-E11 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix A1 -Examples of alternative notations for data involving time</head><note type="other">33</note></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix A4 -Story text and model answer for E11</head><p>Draw a TREND data model for the following description:</p><p>Flight is an entity type whose objects will always be a flight.</p><p>Client is an entity type whose objects will always be a client.</p><p>Traveller is a client. Previous-customer is a client. VIP-customer is a client. Each traveller is not a traveller for some time.</p><p>Each previous-customer is not a previous-customer for some time.</p><p>Each VIP-customer is not a VIP-customer for some time.</p><p>A client may also become a traveller. A client may also become a VIP-customer. Each traveller must evolve to a previous-customer ceasing to be a traveller.</p><p>A previous-customer may also become a traveller. A previous-customer may also become a VIP-customer. Each VIP-customer was already a previous-customer. Each VIP-customer was already a traveller. A traveller books a flight A traveller pays for a flight. A previous-customer took a flight. Each traveller books a flight will be followed by traveller pays for flight after exactly 3 days, Appendix A5 -Logic-based reconstruction of Trend into DLR US Given the set-theoretic semantics for Trend (or, for that matter, if it were to have been linked to UML class diagrams or ORM), relevant automated reasoning concepts such as satisfiability, subsumption, and derivation of new constraints by means of logical implication can, and have been, defined rigorously <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Since the formalisation does not strictly extend the logic used, these reasoning services also apply to the logic-based reconstruction of Trend.</p><p>Definition 3 (Reasoning Services). Let Σ be a schema, C ∈ C a class, and R ∈ R a relationship. The following modelling notions can be defined:</p><p>1. C (R) is satisfiable if there exists a legal temporal database state B for Σ such that C I(t) ∅ (R I(t) ∅), for some t ∈ T ;</p><p>2. Σ is satisfiable if there exists a legal temporal database state B for Σ (B is also said a model for Σ);</p><p>A schema Σ ′ is logically implied by a schema Σ over the same signature if every legal temporal database state for Σ is also a legal temporal database state for Σ ′ .</p><p>We briefly summarise how DLR US is able to capture temporal schemas expressed in Trendsee also <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref> for more details. Definition 4 (Mapping Trend into DLR US ). Let Σ = (L, rel, att, card A , card R , isa C , isa R , isa U , disj C , disj R , cover, s, t, id, E) be a Trend conceptual data model. The DLR US knowledge base, K, mapping Σ is as follows.</p><p>• For each A ∈ A, then, A ⊑ From : ⊤ ⊓ To : ⊤ ∈ K;</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolving objects in temporal information systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Artale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Parent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Spaccapietra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Mathematics and Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Essential and mandatory part-whole relations in conceptual data models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Artale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Keet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">21st International Workshop on Description Logics (DL&apos;08)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>dresden, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-05">2008. May 2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">353</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="16" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>CEUR WS</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temporal entity-relationship models -a survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Gregersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Knowl. Data Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="464" to="497" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capturing telic/atelic temporal data semantics: Generalizing conventional conceptual models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Khatri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Snodgrass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Terenziani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="528" to="548" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Formalising temporal attributes in temporal conceptual data models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A N</forename><surname>Ongoma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Computer Science</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Msc thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CREOL: Contextual Representation of Events and Objects in Language</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Keet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Joint Ontology Workshops</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2050</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-09">2017. 2017. September 2017</date>
			<publisher>CEUR-WS</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Bolzano, Italy</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Natural language template selection for temporal constraints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determining the preferred representation of temporal constraints in conceptual models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Keet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Berman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">36th International Conference on Conceptual Modeling (ER&apos;17)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Valencia, Spain</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017-11">2017. Nov 2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="9" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in print</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Baxter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Courage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Understanding Your Users: A Practical Guide to User Requirements Methods, Tools, and Techniques</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier Science</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The physics of notations: Toward a scientific basis for constructing visual notations in software engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Moody</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="756" to="779" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A mathematical theory of communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Shannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Bell System Technical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="423" />
			<date type="published" when="1948">1948</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Query by diagram: a graphical environment for querying databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Catarci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Santucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/191843.191976</idno>
		<ptr target="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/191843.191976" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM SIGMOD Record</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">515</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Web-based graphical querying of databases through an ontology: the WONDER system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Calvanese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Keet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Nutt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rodríguez-Muro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Stefanoni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM Symposium on Applied Computing (ACM SAC&apos;10)</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ossowski</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schumacher</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Palakal</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Hung</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting>ACM Symposium on Applied Computing (ACM SAC&apos;10)<address><addrLine>Sierre, Switzerland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010-03-22">2010. march 22-26 2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1389" to="1396" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ontology-based end-user visual query formulation: Why, what, who, how, and which?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Soylu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Giese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Jimenez-Ruiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kharlamov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zheleznyakov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Horrocks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Universal Access in the Information Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="435" to="467" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cabot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Olivé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Teniente</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Representing temporal information in UML</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E A</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2863</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="59" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>UML 2003</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ziemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gogolla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">OCL Extended with Temporal Logic</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin, Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="357" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Term: An approach to include time dimension in the entity-relationship model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Klopprogge</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Second International Conference on the Entity-Relationship Approach to Information Modeling and Analysis</title>
		<meeting>the Second International Conference on the Entity-Relationship Approach to Information Modeling and Analysis<address><addrLine>Amsterdam, The Netherlands, The Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>North-Holland Publishing Co</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="473" to="508" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A temporal model and query language for er databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Elmasri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T J</forename><surname>Wuu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Sixth International Conference on Data Engineering</title>
		<meeting>the Sixth International Conference on Data Engineering<address><addrLine>Los Angeles, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990-02">1990, 5-9 Feb. 1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Kuilboer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Guynes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/190675.190676</idno>
		<ptr target="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/190675.190676" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Temporal databases: Model design and commercialization prospects</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="18" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TERC+: a temporal conceptual model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Zimányi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Parent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Spaccapietra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pirotte</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the International Symposium on Digital Media Information Base, DMIB&apos;97</title>
		<meeting>the International Symposium on Digital Media Information Base, DMIB&apos;97<address><addrLine>Nara, Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Conceptual modeling for traditional and spatio-temporal applications-the MADS approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Parent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Spaccapietra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Zimányi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>Springer Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin Heidelberg</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A logical temporal relational data model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mahmood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Burney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ahsan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://arxiv.org/abs/1002.1143" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modelling the time dimension in an entity-relationship diagram</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ferg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Fourth International Conference on Entity-Relationship Approach</title>
		<meeting>the Fourth International Conference on Entity-Relationship Approach<address><addrLine>Washington, DC, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="280" to="286" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Gregersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Database: Enterprise, Skills and Innovation, 22nd British National Conference on Databases</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Stirk</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>sunderland, UK</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005-07-05">2005. July 5-7, 2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="59" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>LNCS</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An entity-relationship model extended to describe historical information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mcbrien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Seltveit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wangler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the International Conference on Information Systems and Management of Data (CISMOD&apos;92)</title>
		<meeting>the International Conference on Information Systems and Management of Data (CISMOD&apos;92)<address><addrLine>bangalore, India</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="244" to="260" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capturing temporal constraints in temporal ER models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Combi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Degani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ER</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Spaccapietra</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Olivé</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5231</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="411" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A basic characterization of relation migration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Keet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Artale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">OTM Workshops, 6th International Workshop on Fact-Oriented Modeling (ORM&apos;10)</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Meersman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hersonissou, Crete, Greece</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010-10-27">2010. october 27-29, 2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6428</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="484" to="493" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temporal attributes: their status and subsumption</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Keet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A N</forename><surname>Ongoma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Conferences in Research and Practice in Information Technology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Köhler</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Saeki</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Sydney, Australia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-01-30">2015. 27-30 January, 2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">165</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Asia-Pacific Conference on Conceptual Modelling (APCCM&apos;15). in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Adoption of a visual model for temporal database representation, M. IT thesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Shunmugam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Computer Science, University of Cape Town, South Africa</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Milash</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Widoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, CHI &apos;96</title>
		<meeting>the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, CHI &apos;96<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="227" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Lifelines: Visualizing personal histories</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The visual display of temporal information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Cousins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Artificial Intelligence In Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="357" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geotime information visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kapler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1057/palgrave.ivs.9500097</idno>
		<idno>doi:10.1057/palgrave.ivs.9500097</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1057/palgrave.ivs.9500097" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="136" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model-based visualization of temporal abstractions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shahar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computational Intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="279" to="306" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive visualization of serial periodic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Carlis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Konstan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 11th annual ACM symposium on User interface software and technology (UIST &apos;98)</title>
		<meeting>the 11th annual ACM symposium on User interface software and technology (UIST &apos;98)<address><addrLine>san Francisco, California, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998-11-01">1998. November 01 -04, 1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="38" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Visual exploration of temporal object databases, in: proc of 16es journés bases de données avancées</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Daassi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dumas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fauvet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Nigay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Scholl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-10">2000. octobre 2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="27" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Pointwise Temporal Object Database Browsing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dumas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Daassi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-C</forename><surname>Fauvet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Nigay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="170" to="184" />
			<pubPlace>Berlin Heidelberg, Berlin, Heidelberg</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Information modeling and relational databases, 2nd Edition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Halpin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Morgan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bakema</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Zwart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Van Der Lek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Volledig Communicatiegeoriënteerde Informatiemodellering FCO-IM</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Academic Service</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temporal capabilities in support of conceptual process modeling using object-role modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gianni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bocciarelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>D'ambrogio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Symposium on Theory of Modeling and Simulation-DEVS Integrative</title>
		<meeting>the Symposium on Theory of Modeling and Simulation-DEVS Integrative<address><addrLine>tampa, Florida, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-04">2014. April, 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Halpin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Temporal modeling and ORM</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5333</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="688" to="698" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>OTM 2008 Workshops</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">AsbruView: Capturing Complex, Time-Oriented Plans -Beyond Flow Charts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kosara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Miksch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shahar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="535" to="549" />
			<pubPlace>London, London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Representation of temporal intervals and relations: Information visualization aspects and their evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chittaro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Combi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Eighth International Symposium on Temporal Representation and Reasoning (TIME&apos;01)</title>
		<meeting>the Eighth International Symposium on Temporal Representation and Reasoning (TIME&apos;01)<address><addrLine>Cividale del Friuli, Italy</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001-06-16">2001. 16 June 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Elements of epistemological knowledge for mathematics teachers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Steinbring</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Mathematics Teacher Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="189" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">What&apos;s new in sql server</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Anon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb500435.aspx" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2016 -september update: 2015. 2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2016" to="2020" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Essential, mandatory, and shared parts in conceptual data models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Artale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Keet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Innovations in Information Systems modeling: Methods and Best Practices</title>
		<title level="s">Advances in Database Research Series</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Halpin</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Proper</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Krogstie</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IGI Global</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="52" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A temporal description logic for reasoning about conceptual schemas and queries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Artale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Franconi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wolter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zakharyaschev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 8th Joint European Conference on Logics in Artificial Intelligence (JELIA-02)</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Flesca</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Greco</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Leone</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ianni</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting>the 8th Joint European Conference on Logics in Artificial Intelligence (JELIA-02)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2424</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="98" to="110" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Artale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Franconi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the Int. Conf. on Conceptual Modeling (ER&apos;99)</title>
		<meeting>of the Int. Conf. on Conceptual Modeling (ER&apos;99)<address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Temporal ER modeling with description logics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Artale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Franconi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mandreoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Description Logics for Modelling Dynamic Information</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Logics for Emerging Applications of Databases</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unifying class-based representation formalisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Calvanese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lenzerini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="240" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transition constraints for temporal attributes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A N</forename><surname>Ongoma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Keet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 27th International Workshop on Description Logics (DL&apos;14)</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bienvenu</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ortiz</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rosati</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Simkus</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting>the 27th International Workshop on Description Logics (DL&apos;14)<address><addrLine>Vienna, Austria</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-07">2014. 17-20 July 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1193</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="684" to="695" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>CEUR-WS</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Logics for databases and information systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chomicki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Toman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Temporal logic in information systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kluwer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temporal OBDA with LTL and dl-lite</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Artale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kontchakov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kovtunova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ryzhikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wolter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zakharyaschev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 27th International Workshop on DescriptionLogics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bienvenu</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ortiz</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rosati</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Simkus</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting>the 27th International Workshop on DescriptionLogics<address><addrLine>vienna, Austria</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-07-17">2014. July 17-20, 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1193</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="32" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>CEUR-WS</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ontology-based access to temporal data with ontop: A framework proposal</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kalayci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Calvanese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ryzhikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zakharyaschev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2478/AMCS-2019-0002</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Applied Mathematics and Computer Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The DL Handbook: Theory, Implementation and Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Calvanese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Giacomo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="178" to="218" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Ch. Expressive description logics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reasoning on UML class diagrams</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Berardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Calvanese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Giacomo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">168</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="118" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling the evolution of objects in temporal information systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Artale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Parent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Spaccapietra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">th International Symposium on Foundations of Information and Knowledge Systems (FoIKS&apos;06)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3861</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="42" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
