<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The mediating role of depression in pathways linking positive and negative symptoms in schizophrenia. A Longitudinal Analysis Using Latent Variable Structural Equation Modelling</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">German Federal Ministry of Education and Research</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">NHS Foundation Trust and the Leicestershire Partnership NHS Trust R&amp;D Programme</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Lundbeck A/S</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_rRWJBVj">
					<orgName type="full">Research Association Public Health Saxony</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Giuseppe</forename><surname>Carrà</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>149 Tottenham Court Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>W1T 7NF</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medicine and Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Milano Bicocca</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via Cadore 48</addrLine>
									<postCode>20900</postCode>
									<settlement>Monza</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Cristina</forename><surname>Crocamo</surname></persName>
							<email>cristina.crocamo@unimib.it</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medicine and Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Milano Bicocca</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via Cadore 48</addrLine>
									<postCode>20900</postCode>
									<settlement>Monza</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Francesco</forename><surname>Bartoli</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medicine and Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Milano Bicocca</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via Cadore 48</addrLine>
									<postCode>20900</postCode>
									<settlement>Monza</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Matthias</forename><surname>Angermeyer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Leipzig</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Johannisallee 20</addrLine>
									<postCode>04137</postCode>
									<settlement>Leipzig</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Traolach</forename><surname>Brugha</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">College of Medicine, Biological Sciences and Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Centre for Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Leicester</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Leicester</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>University Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>LE1 7RH</postCode>
									<settlement>Leicester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mondher</forename><surname>Toumi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medicine and Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire de Santé Publique</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université de la Méditerranée</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via Cadore 48</addrLine>
									<postCode>20900</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille Monza</settlement>
									<country>France Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Bebbington</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>149 Tottenham Court Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>W1T 7NF</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The mediating role of depression in pathways linking positive and negative symptoms in schizophrenia. A Longitudinal Analysis Using Latent Variable Structural Equation Modelling</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T17:36+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Schizophrenia</term>
					<term>Positive symptoms</term>
					<term>Negative symptoms</term>
					<term>Depression</term>
					<term>Longitudinal studies</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p>The interaction between positive, negative and depressive symptoms experienced by people with schizophrenia is complex. We used longitudinal data to test the hypothesis that depressive symptoms mediate the links between positive and negative symptoms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p>We analysed data from the European Schizophrenia Cohort, randomly sampled from outpatient services in France, Germany and the UK (N=1208). Initial measures were repeated at 6 and 12 months. Depressive symptoms were identified using the Calgary Depression Scale for Schizophrenia (CDSS), while positive and negative symptoms were assessed with the Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS). Latent variable structural equation modelling was used to investigate the mediating role of depression assessed at 6 months in relation to the longitudinal association between positive symptoms at baseline and negative symptoms at 12 months.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>We found longitudinal associations between positive symptoms at baseline and negative symptoms at 12 months, as well as between both of these and CDSS levels at 6 months. Depression did not mediate the longitudinal association between PANSS scores; all the effect was direct.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>Our findings are incompatible with a mediating function for depression on the pathway from positive to negative symptoms. The role of depression in schizophrenic disorders remains a challenge for categorical and hierarchical diagnostic systems alike. Future research should analyse specific domains of both depressive and negative symptoms (e.g., motivational and hedonic impairments). The clinical management of negative symptoms using antidepressant treatments may need to be reconsidered.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>For the past 40 years, research on schizophrenia has distinguished the concepts of positive and negative symptoms, whether as separate syndromes of the same disease <ref type="bibr">(Crow, 1980)</ref> or as dimensions on which individuals with strong positive symptom profiles differ appreciably from those with the most prominent negative ones <ref type="bibr">(Andreasen and Olsen, 1982)</ref>. However, negative and positive symptoms might not sit in opposition, as they may originate in the same processes <ref type="bibr">(Pogue-Geile and Harrow, 1984)</ref>. They may also influence each other, directly or indirectly. We recently reported that negative symptoms do not predict positive symptoms in people with established schizophrenia, whereas evidence for the opposite causal direction was ambiguous <ref type="bibr">(Carrà et al., 2018)</ref>.</p><p>Depressive symptoms are associated with positive psychotic symptoms <ref type="bibr">(Sax et al., 1996)</ref>, though they do not necessarily predict each other longitudinally <ref type="bibr">(Yung et al., 2007)</ref>. The development of depression may be explained to an extent as a secondary response to the impact of schizophrenia on social status and circumstances <ref type="bibr">(Birchwood et al., 2005)</ref>. However, it may also represent a propensity to affective dysregulation intrinsic to the schizophrenic disorder itself <ref type="bibr">(Marwaha et al., 2014)</ref>. Certainly, depression sometimes precedes the earliest stages of psychosis <ref type="bibr">(Fusar-Poli et al., 2014)</ref>, and specific features like anhedonia may need to be investigated at a symptom level transdiagnostically <ref type="bibr">(Upthegrove et al., 2017)</ref>. In particular, the apparent linkage between positive and negative symptoms may include an important contribution from depressed mood, as both crosssectional and longitudinal studies of schizophrenia confirm that negative and depressive symptoms are associated, albeit to a varying extent (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Millan et al., 2014)</ref>. Moreover, in periods of remission from positive symptoms, depressive and negative symptoms may be similarly associated with impaired functional recovery <ref type="bibr">(Best et al., 2014)</ref>. Assessed cross-sectionally, negative symptoms do emerge as a factor distinguishable from depression and other affective symptoms <ref type="bibr">(Blanchard and Cohen, 2006)</ref>. A recent systematic review has proposed that symptoms of low mood, suicidal ideation and pessimism may be more specifically related to depression, while alogia and blunted affect are specifically characteristic of negative symptoms. Anhedonia, anergia and avolition may be common to both <ref type="bibr">(Krynicki et al., 2018)</ref>. However, some studies have shown that reduction in depressed mood may lead to the alleviation of negative symptoms <ref type="bibr">(Buchanan, 2007)</ref>.</p><p>Thus, if we accept that depression is, at least to some extent, intrinsic to the schizophrenic illness itself <ref type="bibr">(Upthegrove et al., 2017)</ref> , this might imply the existence of common aetiological factors, but also a salient role for depression in the causation of negative symptoms. Some of the overlap between depressed mood and negative symptoms may be conceptual, as apparent from the phenomenological problems of distinguishing them (Bosanac and Castle, 2012). However, work using Research Domain Criteria (RDoC) <ref type="bibr">(Cuthbert and Kozak, 2013)</ref> does suggest significant differences between psychotic and depressive symptoms in terms of the reward-related and hedonic deficits associated with them. Thus, people with psychosis have difficulties in translating reward into action-selection whereas their in-the-moment hedonic processing is relatively intact. In contrast, these processes both seem to be impaired in people with depressive psychopathology <ref type="bibr">(Barch et al., 2016)</ref>. After controlling for depression, impaired well-being in psychosis seems to be associated with the avolition-apathy negative symptom dimension, but not with the diminished expressivity reflected in blunted affect and poverty of speech <ref type="bibr">(Strauss et al., 2012)</ref> . This suggests that, at least in some clinical populations, the reduced well-being seen in individuals with negative symptoms may be independent of the psychological processes underpinning depression.</p><p>A further issue involves the effects of medication in increasing both depression levels and (by definition secondary) negative symptoms <ref type="bibr">(Carpenter et al., 1988)</ref>. Although the impact of both firstand second-generation antipsychotics on negative symptoms remains questionable <ref type="bibr">(Leucht et al., 2009)</ref>, we should take them into account in assessing the pathway between positive and negative symptoms and the role of depression.</p><p>Overall, several lines of evidence suggest that positive, depressive and negative symptoms in psychosis are distinct, but might partake in a common longitudinal pathway. The European Schizophrenia Cohort (EuroSC) provides an opportunity to test this, since it was specifically set up to compare the attributes and correlates of schizophrenia in large and representative cohorts from three European countries, France, Germany and the UK <ref type="bibr">(Bebbington et al., 2005)</ref>.</p><p>We carried out a three-wave prospective analysis to study the potential mediating role of depression on the longitudinal interplay between positive and negative schizophrenic symptoms, based on latent variable (cross-lagged) structural equation modelling. We hypothesized that depressive symptoms would mediate the pathways leading from positive to negative symptoms, while holding antipsychotic medication status as an observed time-varying covariate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participants</head><p>The EuroSC project involved a two-year naturalistic follow-up of a cohort of people aged 18-64, suffering from schizophrenia. They were in contact with community outpatient services in three mental health catchment areas in France, four in Germany, and two in the UK. It was set up to identify and describe treatments and methods of care for people with schizophrenia, and to relate these to clinical outcomes, health conditions, and quality of life. Local ethical approval for the study was obtained in each country. The settings, sampling strategies, inclusion/exclusion criteria and demographic and clinical characteristics are fully described elsewhere <ref type="bibr">(Bebbington et al., 2005)</ref>.</p><p>Eligible patients had a diagnosis of schizophrenia according to DSM-IV criteria, and had given signed informed consent. People were excluded if they had been hospitalized for the past 12 months, or were currently intoxicated, roofless or planning to leave the area (all making follow-up assessment impracticable). Information was also collected on first (FGA) and second (SGAs generation antipsychotic medication. In total, 1208 people with schizophrenia participated in the study, 288 in France, 302 in the UK, and 618 in Germany.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures</head><p>An extensive battery of instruments was used to collect information in face-to-face interviews. Only those relevant to this study are presented here. In the UK and Germany, SCAN (Schedules for Clinical Assessment in Neuropsychiatry-version 1.0) (WHO, 1992) was used to evaluate the 4-week period before interview and the most significant period of earlier psychopathology. Its component algorithm then allowed the establishment of diagnoses of schizophrenia. In the French centres, schizophrenia was identified using the Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV <ref type="bibr">(Spitzer et al., 1992)</ref> . Information on symptom profile at the different time-points was based on the 30-item interviewer-administered Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) <ref type="bibr">(Norman et al., 1996)</ref>.</p><p>Each symptom is rated in relation to the previous 72 hours on a 7-point scale. PANSS has the advantage of codifying the distinction between positive and negative symptoms <ref type="bibr">(Kay, 1990</ref>). In the current analysis, we included the positive and negative sub-scores (based on items P1-P7, and N1-N7, respectively) <ref type="bibr">(Kay et al., 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr">Addington et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Addington et al., 1992)</ref>.</p><p>Depression levels were established from the Calgary Depression Scale for Schizophrenia (CDSS) <ref type="bibr">(Addington et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Addington et al., 1992)</ref>, which comprises nine items, providing scores ranging from zero to 27. It is widely used to assess depression in contradistinction to negative symptoms, as it focuses on subjective reports of hopelessness, guilt, and suicidal ideation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Procedures</head><p>Research assistants consecutively contacted individuals from the list of potential participants, and sought their informed consent after assurance of confidentiality. Interviews took place at home or in the clinical service. The initial assessment took around three hours, the subsequent assessments slightly less. Participants completed standardized measures at baseline (T0) and every 6 months for the following 2 years. The current analysis used assessments at baseline (Time 0: T0), and at 6-and 12-month follow-up (T6 and T12). These intervals were chosen for analysis on the basis that they were clinically appropriate for investigating the mediating role of depression levels in the longitudinal interplay between positive and negative symptoms. At the 6-month follow-up, 1024 respondents took part, while at 12-month follow-up 962 did so. Attrition analyses showed no significant differences in demographic characteristics or any other variables between those participants with data missing at follow-up and those who did not leave the study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis</head><p>The present study evaluated potential mediation through an autoregressive approach based on structural equation modelling in order to allow opposite paths to be estimated simultaneously <ref type="bibr">(Lockhart et al., 2011)</ref> . Positive and negative symptoms were fitted as latent variables, while we used a single-indicator latent variable for depression in order to comply with general recommendations on mediator measurement error <ref type="bibr">(Maxwell and Cole, 2007)</ref>. Our measurement model was based on previous analyses of this cohort that explored whether latent positive symptoms would affect latent later negative symptoms or vice versa <ref type="bibr">(Carrà et al., 2018)</ref>. In sum, Further details are reported elsewhere <ref type="bibr">(Carrà et al., 2018)</ref>.</p><p>Analyses were performed using Mplus 8 <ref type="bibr">(Muthén and Muthén, 2017)</ref>. We used the full information maximum likelihood estimation, as initial analysis of the data showed no evidence of multivariate non-normality and there was little missing data (2% of item responses were missing across T0 to T12). We fitted bivariate structural cross-lagged models in turn, to test the longitudinal associations between latent constructs for positive symptoms at baseline (T0) and negative symptoms at T12 (Figure <ref type="figure">1a</ref>); positive symptoms at baseline (T0) and depression at T6 (Figure <ref type="figure">1b</ref>); and depression at T6 and negative symptoms at T12 (Figure <ref type="figure">1c</ref>). These relationships are a precondition for inferring our hypothesised pathway via depression.</p><p>We allowed correlations between the variables and the errors of individual items over time, in order to account for consistency in item-specific variance <ref type="bibr">(Cole and Maxwell, 2003)</ref>. The cross-lagged paths estimate the effect of one variable on the other, after controlling for the stability of the latent constructs over time. As expected in a clinical population with established schizophrenia assessed six-monthly, there was no indication of measurement variance (results available upon request).</p><p>Nested models with constraints on the structural autoregressive paths over time did not indicate that the paths of interest (positive and negative symptoms across T0, T6 and T12) varied appreciably. This modification was therefore retained. If bivariate models showed any significant paths from either positive or negative to depressive symptoms, we fitted additional structural autoregressive mediation models.</p><p>Based on these models, we assessed total, direct and indirect effects in order to evaluate the impact of the putative mediator on the longitudinal relationship. The product of coefficients method estimated the indirect effect of positive symptoms on negative symptoms through the mediator (i.e., depression). For this, we used the Mplus MODEL INDIRECT command and relevant options.</p><p>Bootstrap confidence intervals were obtained for the effects.</p><p>Following conventional recommendations (Hu and Bentler, 1999), we report three goodness-of-fitindices. The Comparative Fit Index (CFI) represents the extent to which the hypothesized model fits the data better than a null model. The Standardized Root Mean Square Residual (SRMR) signifies the standardized difference between observed and predicted correlations for the hypothesized model. Lastly, the Root Mean Square Error of Approximation (RMSEA) assesses the extent to which the hypothesized model fits the data. Values greater than .90 (CFI), and less than 0.08 (SRMR) and 0.05 (RMSEA) indicate an acceptable fit between models and data <ref type="bibr">(Hu and Bentler, 1999)</ref> . For the final models, we also calculated standardized estimates. We controlled for the potential confounding role of antipsychotic medication status, as an observed time-varying covariate. We included dummy variables to distinguish between monotherapy and the combination of adequate doses of FGAs and SGAs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head><p>The mean scores for the psychotic symptoms and depression measures are shown in table 1.</p><p>Overall, they declined with the passage of time, though not by much.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 1 about here</head><p>We first report the bivariate models. The model estimating the cross-lagged relationships between positive symptoms at baseline (T0) and negative symptoms at T12 showed a significant path (β=0.074, p=0.021), whereas there was no support for pathways in the opposite direction (Fig. <ref type="figure">1a</ref>).</p><p>In addition, the models quantifying the associations of the putative mediator depression at T6, with positive symptoms at baseline (T0) (Fig. <ref type="figure">1b</ref>), and with negative symptoms at T12 (Fig. <ref type="figure">1c</ref>), were both significant (β=0. <ref type="bibr">068, p=0.036; and β=0.046, p=0.043, respectively)</ref>. However, depression at T6 was also significantly associated with positive symptoms at T12 (β=0.058, p=0.037), as were negative symptoms at T6 with depression at T12 (β=0.061, p=0.048). Taken altogether, the bivariate analyses suggested a potential mediating role for depression.</p><p>We consequently fitted a dedicated mediation model. Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> shows the structural equation model testing the longitudinal indirect effect from positive symptoms at T0 to negative symptoms at T12, via depression at T6, holding antipsychotic medication status as observed time-varying covariate.</p><p>The various cross-sectional correlations at T0 between positive, depressive and negative symptoms, were all strong and significant, as would be expected in this clinical population. In addition, the structural model showed strong and significant autoregressive paths over time (all Ps&lt;0.001) for both latent positive and latent negative symptoms. Furthermore, the model supported a significant direct effect of positive symptoms at T0 on negative symptoms at T12 (β=0.05, p=0.032). However, when we assessed mediation via depression, positive symptoms at T0 were not associated with depression at T6 (β=0.06, p=0.090), and this in turn showed no association with negative symptoms at T12. There was consequently no significant indirect effect of positive on negative symptoms. The model showed acceptable fit to the data [(χ 2 (991) = 3085.66, P &lt; 0.001; CFI = 0.913; RMSEA = 0.042 (90% CI: 0.040, 0.044); SRMR = 0.066].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figures 1 and 2 about here</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Main findings</head><p>In a large, representative cohort of people with schizophrenia, we tested the hypothesis that depressive symptoms would mediate the effect of initial positive symptoms on negative symptoms 12 months later. Overall, all types of symptoms declined in frequency over this period, though modestly so, as would be expected in a cohort of people with established schizophrenia. Although we uncovered the required associations between positive symptoms at baseline and negative symptoms at 12 months, and between both of these and CDSS depression levels at 6 months, depression could not be said to mediate the longitudinal association between PANSS scores: virtually all the effect was direct. The results from the modeling therefore did not support our hypothesis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Interpretation of findings</head><p>Depression in people with schizophrenia is a controversial issue in Kraepelinian categorical and hierarchical diagnostic systems <ref type="bibr">(Upthegrove et al., 2017)</ref>. In our study, we established a longitudinal interplay between positive and negative symptoms, but this was not mediated by depressive symptoms assessed with the CDSS. Nevertheless, our results overall are consistent with other evidence that depression is in some sense integral to schizophrenic illness <ref type="bibr">(Upthegrove et al., 2010)</ref>.</p><p>Distinguishing depressive and negative symptoms is particularly challenging <ref type="bibr">(Bosanac and Castle, 2012)</ref> . Empirically, negative symptoms resolve themselves into two factors: the first implies alogia and diminished expression of affect, while the second involves avolition, including anhedonia and asociality <ref type="bibr">(Blanchard and Cohen, 2006)</ref>. However, whereas anhedonia is common to negative symptoms and to depression, subjective reports of hopelessness, guilt and suicidal ideation may be restricted to depressive illness <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Addington et al., 1996)</ref>. Thus depression operates through multiple pathways that are not entirely understood, and which may be in part separate from those linking psychotic symptoms. It may be better conceived through the RDoC approach to negative symptoms, with its "positive valence" system. This proposes differences in the mechanisms of motivational and hedonic impairments across distinct diagnostic categories, including depression and schizophrenia <ref type="bibr">(Cuthbert and Kozak, 2013)</ref>. In particular, there seems to be a critical disparity in the nature of incentive processing impairments. Thus it appears that the pathways leading to impairments in motivated behaviour in psychotic and depressive illness are different <ref type="bibr">(Barch et al., 2016)</ref>. Impaired incentive processing in schizophrenia may be more related to compromised goal representation and utilization mechanisms than to fundamental deficits in hedonic experience <ref type="bibr">(Kring and Barch, 2014)</ref>.</p><p>On the other hand it has been argued that, in the context of depression, altered incentive processing may be more linked to deficits in hedonic experience, which spread to produce impaired motivated behaviour <ref type="bibr">(Liu et al., 2014)</ref>. Thus, whilst anhedonia broadly defined may be found in different diagnostic categories, specific subdomains (e.g., anticipatory, consummatory, and motivational anhedonia) maybe more specific <ref type="bibr">(Upthegrove et al., 2010)</ref>, acting in concert with apathy, social withdrawal, negative self-concept <ref type="bibr">(Barrowclough et al., 2003)</ref>, self-stigma, and poor motivation to build the core features of depression in schizophrenia <ref type="bibr">(Sandhu et al., 2013)</ref>. This is somehow consistent with a recent, elegant, dimensional model, though mainly based on cross-sectional evidence, which has proposed a tripartition for the relationship between depressive and negative features <ref type="bibr">(Krynicki et al., 2018)</ref>. It distinguishes symptoms that span both depressive and negative symptoms (e.g., anergia) and those that represent specific symptoms of depression (e.g., hopelessness) and negative symptoms (such as blunted affect). Future research should provide also longitudinal evidence of this proposed disentanglement among different symptoms in people with schizophrenia.</p><p>While our findings have implications for the conceptualization of schizophrenic processes, they also reflect on the rational choice of treatment. Antidepressants are prescribed to around 30% of people with schizophrenia <ref type="bibr">(Mao and Zhang, 2015)</ref>. The main guidelines are unclear regarding the management of depressive and negative symptoms in schizophrenia with antidepressants <ref type="bibr">(Lehman et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Buchanan et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Barnes, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">NICE, 2014)</ref>. While their addition carries little risk of side effects and relapse in psychosis, they also have scant effect on either depressive or negative symptoms <ref type="bibr">(Helfer et al., 2016)</ref>. Our findings indirectly support this pessimistic view of the likely effect of antidepressant prescription on negative symptoms <ref type="bibr">(Fusar-Poli et al., 2015)</ref>, whose treatment remains generally disappointing <ref type="bibr">(Kirkpatrick et al., 2006)</ref>. Adaptations of cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT) found useful for anxiety and depression are routinely recommended for people with schizophrenia (NICE, 2014). However, CBT research in recent years has primarily focused on effects on positive symptoms, transition from high-risk status and more recently on distress. As yet no studies have used depression as a primary outcome <ref type="bibr">(Mehl et al., 2015)</ref>, and secondary evidence shows no effect on hopelessness <ref type="bibr">(Wykes et al., 2008)</ref>. CBT interventions may therefore need further development to address the specific problems posed by the depressive experience in people with schizophrenia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Strengths and limitations</head><p>Our analyses represent a significant advance over cross-sectional studies, where inferences about the directionality of association must inevitably be very tentative. Our retention of participants in the later time-points was good, though attrition inevitably tends to distort the representativeness of samples. ICD-10 and DSM-IV equivalent research diagnoses for schizophrenia and the assessment of positive and negative symptoms were based on formal interviews, whilst depression was assessed by the CDSS, which focuses specifically on symptoms distinct from those that in their nature might be secondary manifestations of negative symptoms. In addition, by using the PANSS we excluded those negative symptoms with a strong a priori likelihood of being secondary. Finally, our design, which excluded recently hospitalized subjects, would also have the effect of reducing the likelihood of secondary negative symptoms. We controlled for time-varying levels of antipsychotic medication since this might affect symptom levels differentially and hence the corresponding correlations <ref type="bibr">(Sarkar et al., 2015)</ref>. Nonetheless, while our cross-lagged longitudinal models can provide information about causal ordering, the gold standard of causal inference remains targeted intervention <ref type="bibr">(Kenny, 2005)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>Our understanding of the interplay between different symptoms in schizophrenia remains limited, with corresponding limitations on treatment strategies. In particular, the nature of negative symptoms and their relationship with depression is far from fully understood despite ongoing efforts seeking biomarkers and endophenotypes. Pharmacological and other treatment strategies are likely to remain tentative until these gaps are filled. Research should also maintain a focus on nonbiological factors, which have a role regardless of any underlying disease process. Ellipses represent latent variables. Rectangles represent observed (measured) time-varying covariates. Single-headed and double-headed arrows represent the effect of one variable on another and within-time correlations between pairs of latent variables, respectively. Dashed lines represent non-significant paths. T0 = baseline, T6 = 6 months follow-up; T12 = 12 months follow-up. *P &lt;.05, **P &lt;.01, ***P &lt; 0.001</p><note type="other">Figure legends</note></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>two factors measuring positive (P1, P3-P7) and negative (N1-N6) items from PANSS yielded a measurement model with an acceptable fit, allowing us to test its structural equivalent [(χ 2 (543) = 2045.784, P &lt; 0.001; CFI = 0.935; RMSEA = 0.048 (90% CI: 0.046, 0.050); SRMR = 0.062].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 .Figure 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Standardized structural coefficients for the bivariate models of: 1a) PANSS positive at T0 and negative at T12; 1b) PANSS positive at T0 and CDSS at T6; and 1c) CDSS at T6 and PANSS negative at T12</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>Our thanks to all the patients and staff that helped with the study and to the <rs type="institution">Camden and Islington Mental Health</rs> and <rs type="funder">NHS Foundation Trust and the Leicestershire Partnership NHS Trust R&amp;D Programme</rs> and to those who collected the data and otherwise contributed to the main study, including <rs type="person">Gloria Castagna</rs>, <rs type="person">Ilaria Riboldi</rs> and <rs type="person">Giulia Trotta</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><p>The EuroSC study was funded by an unrestricted research grant from <rs type="funder">Lundbeck A/S</rs> and a grant from the <rs type="funder">German Federal Ministry of Education and Research</rs> in the framework of the <rs type="funder">Research Association Public Health Saxony</rs> (grant no. <rs type="grantNumber">01EG9732/7</rs>).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_rRWJBVj">
					<idno type="grant-number">01EG9732/7</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest</head><p>None.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethical standards</head><p>The authors assert that all procedures contributing to this work comply with the ethical standards of the relevant national and institutional committees on human experimentation and with the Helsinki Declaration of 1975, as revised in 2008.</p><p> Addington D, Addington J, Schissel <ref type="bibr">B (1990)</ref>. A depression rating scale for schizophrenics.  Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS); Calgary Depression Scale for Schizophrenia (CDSS). There are missing values for some items that SEM dealt with: the greatest numbers of missing items is for T 3 CDSS</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Schizophrenia</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A psychometric comparison of the Calgary depression scale for schizophrenia and the Hamilton depression rating scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname> Addington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Addington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Atkinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Schizophrenia Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="212" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reliability and validity of a depression rating scale for schizophrenics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname> Addington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Addington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Maticka-Tyndale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Joyce</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Schizophrenia Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="208" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
