<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Managing the Exploration-Exploitation Paradox in Healthcare: Three Complementary Paths to Leverage on the Digital Transformation</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Managing the Exploration-Exploitation Paradox in Healthcare: Three Complementary Paths to Leverage on the Digital Transformation</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1108/BPMJ-04-2017-0092</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T01:10+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Exploration</term>
					<term>Exploitation</term>
					<term>Ambidexterity</term>
					<term>Efficiency Frontier</term>
					<term>Digital technologies</term>
					<term>Healthcare JEL: I10, L31, O33, O30</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Purpose. To understand how digital technologies can help healthcare organisations to improve the exploration-exploitation paradox over time. We explore inputs, processes, and outcomes of implementing digital transformation programs and advance four testable propositions.</p><p>Design/methodology/approach. We conducted multiple case studies with embedded units of analysis: 1) digital transformation processes; 2) hospitals; 3) regional healthcare systems. Primary sources come from 107 semi-structured interviews with key informants within 14 Italian hospitals between 2009 through 2011.</p><p>Findings. Three complementary paths emerge as fundamental to balance exploratory and exploitatory efforts in healthcare: (i) assets digitalisation within hospitals; (ii) digitally-based process integration; (iii) disruptive decision-making through analytics. Intra-and inter-path characteristics are discussed to show how digital transformation can both move hospital within the exploration-exploitation space.</p><p>Research limitations/implications. By its very nature, this study is exploratory. Notwithstanding the number of cases and interviews, its generalisability is limited.</p><p>Practical implications. Digital transformation programs are fundamental to resolve the tensions raised by the exploration-exploitation paradox. Their implementation leads to better performance (cost reductions, quality improvements). A framework is provided for practitioners to make better decisions.</p><p>Originality/value. This study sheds new light on how digital technologies are actually adopted and adapted in healthcare contexts. It does it by entailing a longitudinal perspective.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Healthcare organisations are currently trying to reconfigure and innovate their processes in order to achieve and maintain a continuous balance between quality improvement and cost rationalisation <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Porter and Lee, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">McCullogh and Snir, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Borzekowski, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Djellal and Gallouj, 2007)</ref>.</p><p>Underlying this twofold aim, tensions emerge being produced by exploratory and exploitatory behaviours <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Lavie et al., 2010)</ref>, acting as opposing attractors whose effective balance can only be reached by deploying concrete and persistent efforts. In this vein, latest ambidexterity research <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Birkinshaw and Gupta, 2013)</ref> suggests exploring the processes through which organisations cope with these tensions over time, reconfiguring their activities within an exploration-exploitation space limited by an efficiency frontier, or pushing it out to achieve higher performance.</p><p>The digital transformation characterising the healthcare sector nowadays <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Lin et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Kaushal and Blumenthal, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Andreassen et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">McAlearney et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Arvanitis and Loukis, 2016)</ref> offers important research opportunities from this viewpoint. Furthermore, it is also at the centre of the debate among policymakers and practitioners because of its potential impact in term of both cost reduction and quality improvement <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(OECD, 2016)</ref>. The World Economic Forum <ref type="bibr">(2016)</ref> shows that, although digital healthcare attracted more than $14 billion in funding and investment over the past six years, concrete actions still have to be implemented in order to structurally transform the industry. Indeed, if properly implemented, digital technologies can improve patient empowerment, quality of life, enable the communication among healthcare professionals and patients, and reduce both errors and length of hospitalisation <ref type="bibr">(European Commission, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">European Commission, 2014</ref>). An effective introduction of digital technologies provides occasions to: (i) re-engineer healthcare processes <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Laing, 2002)</ref>; (ii) balance exploratory and exploitatory efforts <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Gastaldi and Corso, 2013)</ref>; (iii) improve the way healthcare services are offered-both in terms of cost and quality <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Agarwal et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Borzekowski, 2009)</ref>. However, literature has produced little evidence on how digital technologies can actually achieve these results.</p><p>By analysing 14 Italian hospitals, and considering their peculiar role in the healthcare innovation process <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Thune and Mina, 2016)</ref>, we want to shed new light on the following research question: How do digital technologies impact on healthcare processes, regarding cost reduction and quality improvement, balancing ambidextrous tensions?</p><p>In the theoretical background, we discuss the exploration-exploitation paradox and introduce an Input-Process-Output framework. Then, we provide methodological details and derive important findings from the cases analysed. The following section characterises the three paths leading healthcare institutions towards a resolution of the paradox via the implementation of digital transformations. Contributions for both theory and practice are discussed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>THEORETICAL BACKGROUND</head><p>Exploration and exploitation represent overarching demands, spurring nested tensions throughout the organisation <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Andriopoulos and Lewis, 2009)</ref>. Paradox thinking assumes these tensions can be beneficial if adequately harnessed <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Andriopoulos and Lewis, 2009)</ref>. This is because the juxtaposition of coexisting opposites intensifies experiences of tension, challenging actors' cognitive limits, demanding creative sense making, seeking more sustainable management strategies <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Benner and Tushman, 2015)</ref>.</p><p>From this viewpoint, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Birkinshaw and Gupta (2013)</ref> propose the concept of 'Efficiency Frontier' (EF). Accordingly, organisations choose first, where to position themselves in the explorationexploitation space delimited by the EF; second, whether organising their processes in such a way that the EF will be reached; third, look for peculiar configurations allowing them to progressively push it out. Moving through the EF entails going through a series of paths that may be more or less complex.</p><p>How to move in this space is the core focus of recent research <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(O'Reilly and Tushman, 2013)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Burgelman and Grove (2007)</ref> suggest that to accommodate these conflicting alignments, organisations need to shift their structures sequentially over time, to align them with firm's strategy. This school of thought looks at exploration and exploitation as two ends of a single continuum, placing inherently conflicting resource and organisational demands on the firm. This approach may allow organisations to innovate beyond-or at least within-the EF.</p><p>Other researchers have begun characterising exploration and exploitation as independent activities, orthogonal to each other: firms can choose to engage in high levels of both at the same time <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Simsek et al., 2009)</ref>. Two ways of carrying them out together have been identified: structural and contextual <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(O'Reilly and Tushman, 2013)</ref>. The former occurs through the simultaneous pursuit of both exploitation and exploration by using separate subunits. The latter suggests leveraging on the individual behavioural capacity to "simultaneously demonstrate alignment and adaptability across an entire business unit" <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Gibson and Birkinshaw, 2004)</ref>; this approach may allow organisations to innovate by pushing the EF out <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Messeni Petruzzelli, 2014)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Raisch et al. (2009)</ref> found a combination of different solutions may be more practical. An effective way to find a solution to these emerging paradoxical tensions in healthcare institutions is through digital transformations <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Gregory et al., 2015)</ref>. They are making increasingly possible deploying new ways of working that were not previously possible. Digital technologies leverage on knowledge assets <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Leidner et al., 2010)</ref>, nurture innovation <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Drnevich and Croson, 2013)</ref>, reconcile the capability to exploit the current knowledge base opening to more exploratory ones <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Laing, 2002)</ref>. An effective digital transformation contributes in shifting the EF up and to the right-allowing not only a higher level of ambidexterity to be reached <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Im and Rai, 2014)</ref>, but also to improve the way healthcare services are offered-both in terms of cost and quality <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Agarwal et al., 2010)</ref>.</p><p>Improvements in healthcare quality include lower mortality rates, improved vaccination rates, increased use of recommended procedures, and patient safety. Lower costs, higher revenues, and higher productivity can contribute to bending the cost curve of healthcare processes.</p><p>In dealing with ambidextrous approaches, we adopt an Input-Process-Output (IPO) framework <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Simsek, 2009)</ref>. Each IPO configuration will represent a specific position concerning the EF. The framework helps to answer our research question because it considers the delivered ambidextrous activities (i.e. Processes) and the resulting consequences (i.e. Outputs). Furthermore, for every process, it takes into account the antecedents (i.e. Inputs) of balanced and ambidextrous processes at different levels of analysis (Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). According to literature, antecedents are a complex function of:</p><p>-Characteristics of the enabling digital solutions: mainly in terms of resources, capabilities, and investments required (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Im and Rai, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Lin et al., 2014)</ref>; -Strategic time frame: considered in terms of short, medium, long term perspectives <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Piao, 2010)</ref>.</p><p>Processes should be meant as components of balanced and ambidextrous use of exploration and exploitation. Such components can be thought of as a complex function of:</p><p>-Approach to balance exploration and exploitation activities: focusing on exploitation-driven, exploration-driven, co-evolving approaches (O'Reilly and Tushman, 2013); -Distance from the efficiency frontier: depending on whether one pursues exploration and exploitation inside, at, or beyond it <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Birkinshaw and Gupta, 2013)</ref>.</p><p>Finally, the output should be thought of as consequences of balanced and ambidextrous use of exploration and exploitation. Such consequences can be described as a complex function of:</p><p>-Degree of innovativeness: incremental, radical, and disruptive outcomes (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Garcia and Calantone, 2002)</ref>; -Performance: mostly in terms of cost rationalisation and quality improvement <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Smith and Lewis, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Borzekowski, 2009)</ref>.</p><p>-Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>. Input-Process-Output framework -</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS</head><p>We implemented an interpretative, inductive perspective, based on multiple case studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Eisenhardt, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Yin, 2003)</ref>. We worked on grounding the main constructs into the healthcare context. On the basis of <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">March's (1991)</ref> seminal work, we defined:</p><p>-Exploratory activities: activities that explore innovative and better alternatives to deliver administrative and clinical services in order to change existing routines;</p><p>-Exploitatory activities: activities that refine and extend the existing competences, simplifying the use of existing routines in both the administrative and clinical domains.</p><p>Both definitions are based not only on literature analysis but also on the suggestions of a group of more than 60 practitioners who contributed in defining a taxonomy of the digital solutions (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>) over which a hospital can base its digital transformation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>-Table 1. Digital solutions adopted by hospitals -</head><p>The first unit of analysis focuses on the unfolding process of digital transformation: it refers to the set of activities and users involved in the adoption, usage and improvement of one of the digital solutions listed in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. To escape abstraction and given the different degrees of innovativeness of the various solutions implemented, we adopted the hospital as a second unit of analysis and the regional healthcare system around the hospital as a third unit of analysis. Furthermore, embedded units of analysis allow us to go beyond the boundaries of the single process regardless the inputs (e.g., external pressures for the integration with EHR) or the outputs (e.g., the implementation of a telemedicine service could bring to privacy concerns due to the presence of an external actor) <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Yin, 2003)</ref>.</p><p>We focused on the digital transformations accomplished within 14 Italian hospitals. The selection of the hospitals was related to the importance they gave to the strategic implementation of digital transformations and the fact that they were all in the same geographical context, which provided the same boundary conditions. The primary data source was 107 semi-structured interviews over three years <ref type="bibr">(Jan. 2009</ref><ref type="bibr">-Dec. 2011)</ref> with Chief Information Officers (CIOs), at least one of the other Clevels (Chief Executive Officers (CEOs), Chief Financial Officers (CFOs), Chief Medical Officers (CMOs)) and-through a snowball technique <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Patton, 2002)</ref>-other knowledgeable informants involved in the digital transformations of the hospitals (e.g., nurses, physicians). Within each hospital, we continued recruiting informants until additional interviews failed to dispute existing categories or relationships (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>-Table 2. Hospitals involved in the case studies and interviews accomplished -</head><p>Each interview lasted at least 2 hours and was designed along a common protocol that evolved during the research. Data were collected in three waves: first, we analysed the different solutions present inside the hospitals, and those that would be developed in the near future (starting before the end of 2012); in the second and third waves, we focused on the digital transformations.</p><p>-Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>. Digital solutions characterising the digital transformation that has been studied -</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Path A: Assets Digitisation Step 1: Efficiency Stimulus</head><p>In all cases, the initial objectives of the digital transformation were related to exploit more effectively the resources of the hospital, and achieve efficiency-mainly regarding time savings, cost reduction, or managerial simplification. From this viewpoint, the CEO of H2 stated that: "Basically we dematerialise to cut costs". For other representative quotes as well as the characterisation of the various cases on the IPO framework, see the attached e-companion.</p><p>A common element emerging from all cases is that it is better focusing on the digitisation of one hospital unit at a time. This allows addressing two objectives: (i) achieving tangible results in short time lags to be shown to the strategic board; (ii) reducing the complexity to be faced in the development of pervasive digital transformations. As the CIO of H5 commented:</p><p>"It is better focusing on a department at a time. Why? Because it is possible to avoid the over-complications associated with the development of pervasive solutions-at least in the initial digitalisation stages and/or in the case of low budgets available".</p><p>Digitisation in the clinical domain is preferred to the one in the administrative domain, as expressed by the chief radiologist at H2: "First you have to focus on clinical assets, and then on administrative ones. The reasons are mainly related to the higher value associated with clinical digitalisation".</p><p>In fact: (i) most of the assets that can be digitised within a hospital are of a clinical nature; (ii) clinical digitisation provides more opportunities both to explore and exploit; (iii) digitisation in the clinical area produces stronger positive impacts on hospital performance-both those directly perceived by physicians (as suggested by the interviews accomplished within H2) and by patients (H7), as well as those not directly perceived by most of the stakeholders (H5). Informants suggested radiology and laboratory as the hospital units from which starting the digital transformation.</p><p>To summarise, a generic hospital aiming to successfully use digital technologies to cope with exploration and exploitation can start following-preferably in the clinical domain-the initial part of the path 1 à 2 in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref>.</p><p>-Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref>. The paths to manage the exploration-exploitation paradox in healthcare -</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Step 2: Assets Integration</head><p>Given that 12 of the 14 cases started this path, it was possible studying how hospitals tended to continue it. After appropriating the main benefits of initial digitisation investments, the solutions introduced in the hospitals allowed the exploration of new, radical ways of providing healthcare services. For instance, H2 started the digitisation of its radiology department mainly to reduce the usage of radiological films, save storage space and rationalise other resources used in this hospital unit. However, the progressive digitalisation of the various radiological devices (especially computed tomographies and magnetic resonance imaging) allowed to easily integrate their reports, opening up many possibilities of combining several layers of information in a comprehensive output, which not only increased the radiologists' capability to make new diagnoses, but also improved their efficiency and effectiveness.</p><p>Similar trends have been discovered in other hospitals that we have analysed, namely (see the ecompanion for further details): (i) the queue management systems in H4; (ii) the software virtualised in H5; (iii) the laboratory devices in H7. Initial investments supporting purely exploitatory activities and efficiency objectives opened up also exploration possibilities that, once seized, allowed not only to better balance the exploratory and the exploitatory efforts in the department (the final part of the path 1 à 2), but also to increase its overall performance. As the CIO of H4 stated: "The benefits are only partially related to less paper-based processes. The real benefits are related to the fact that information circulates quickly, and users are empowered".</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Furthermore:</head><p>"We have always thought of ICT in terms of cost reduction. As a matter of fact, there are tremendous benefits also in terms of quality improvement".</p><p>As suggested by cases of H2, H4, H5 and H7, the more the unit undergoing asset digitisation is detached from the rest of the hospital, the smoother and more successful the digitally-driven balance between exploration and exploitation. Problems encountered during the adoption, usage and improvement of the electronic queue management systems in H4 and the virtualisation realised in H5 traced back to the pervasiveness of these digital solutions and the number of processes affected by digitisation (see the e-companion for further details). Discussions with informants explained this evidence mostly in terms of "protection of the unit" (CIOs of H2, H4 and H5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Path B: Digitally-based Process Integration</head><p>Step 1: Internal Integration Process integration can be realised in both clinical as well as administrative domains (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>). If clinical integration is almost completely accomplished through investments in an Electronic Medical Record (EMR) (IPI3), administrative integration is realised through administrative and HR management systems (IPI1, IPI2). In order to understand the value that hospitals extract through these integrations, the digital transformation ignited by the introduction of four different digital solutions in the internal integration area were compared . Three cases (H1, H9, H14) focused on EMR, while one (H6) studied the introduction of an administrative management system.</p><p>In H1, H9, and H14 the introduction of an EMR allowed to: (i) improve the hospital's overall capabilities to explore and exploit, (ii) better balance exploration and exploitation at different levels (mainly hospital unit and whole hospital), (iii) achieve positive performance in terms of quality improvement and cost rationalisation. Indeed, the CMO of H1 stated that: "Our main focus was cost rationalisation. However, we ended also with a better service". Furthermore, as expressed by a physician at H9: "The final result? Better treatment, quicker diagnoses, and brand new research fields ready on the shelf waiting for us".</p><p>On the other hand, as referred by the CIO of H6: "We need to rethink the workflows, together with the administrative staff, dematerialise more, and, then, review some choices in the system. It is a long, long way".</p><p>H6 faced many issues in producing an impact along these dimensions. These problems cannot be linked to the typology of the processes that H6 decided to integrate. All informants highlighted that an integration realised among administrative processes should tackle fewer problems. Almost all hospitals accomplishing administrative integration (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>), invested in this area to collect what informants called "quick wins" between large waves of clinical integration. According to the cases, the real element able to explain different performance is the level of digitisation previously accomplished by the hospitals. H1, H9 and H14 had good percentages (≥ 40%) of clinical documentation already dematerialised when they started implementing their EMR. Because of this gap, H6 ran into many difficulties and the positive effect of asset integration within hospital units had not yet been explored.</p><p>There are multiple ways that allow switching from 2 to 3 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref>), and multiple combinations of exploration and exploitation-both realised through radical and incremental innovations. Rather than a standalone project, it is more common to proceed with a combination of sequential exploratory and exploitatory investments, as confirmed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Gastaldi et al. (2012)</ref>.</p><p>Step 2: External Integration Among the next steps to be accomplished after the introduction of an EMR, H1, H9 and H14 included extending the underlying integration outside them. The cross-analysis showed two complementary paths of external process integration (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref>). The first (EPI1) is usually driven by the regional council and is based on developing an Electronic Health Record (EHR). The hospital has to answer the region's integration requests proactively-by making its EMR interoperable with other EMRs and/or following the guidelines released by the regional council on EMR development <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Gastaldi and Corso, 2013)</ref>. The second (EPI2) is characterised by the hospital's efforts in directly connecting itself to its patients and general physicians. In order to understand if and how these paths allow hospitals to successfully manage the exploration-exploitation paradox, three digital transformations based on external process integration were compared (Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_11">13</ref><ref type="table" target="#tab_12">14</ref><ref type="table" target="#tab_13">15</ref>, e-companion).</p><p>While introducing an EMR, H3 also decided to better connect it to the regional EHR. The relative process is highly similar to the one accomplished by H1 and ended in improved quality and lower costs <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Adler-Milstein et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Lammers and Mclaughlin, 2016)</ref>. However, these are only a small part of the potential benefits that it can achieve. In fact, CIO of H3 stated that: "The integration with the EHR will bring tons of opportunities not only to further simplify things but also to discover new services to be offered to patients".</p><p>Despite the tremendous potential, in order to be effective, the EHR requires years of exploratory and exploitatory investments by all the hospitals present in a region. Before the start of 2009, both H10 and H12 had already not only digitised and internally integrated most of their processes but also connected their EMR to the regional EHR (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>). This does not mean there are no more opportunities of external process integration. On the one hand, H10 engaged in the development of a telemedicine service for a specific typology of patients suffering from chronic obstructive respiratory disease. As referred by the CIO:</p><p>"Once you have data on the pathology you can better organise home visits, exams, etc., and, thus, you also decrease the overall costs of the treatment." H12, on the other hand, developed a new channel to offer its services to its patients-through an application for latest-generation smartphones, and: "these solutions are tremendously effective in engaging the patients and in getting close to them" (as pronounced by the CMO of H12).</p><p>In both cases, the relative digital transformation followed a similar logic showed before:</p><p>an initial investment was accomplished in one direction (exploration for H10, exploitation for H12) which soon manifested opportunities in the other direction as well (exploitation for H10, exploration for H12);</p><p>by taking advantage of these opportunities, the hospital balanced the two conflicting activities and increased its quality while rationalising its costs.</p><p>As suggested by the cases, external integration also leads to a temporal separation between explorative and exploitative opportunities, hence supporting ambidexterity performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Path C: Disruptive Decision-making through Analytics</head><p>Step 1: Experimentation</p><p>The very first stimulus leading to investments in analytics was related to the informants' desire to explore new ways of extracting value from previously digitised administrative and clinical data. As depicted in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>, H8, H11, and H13, all hospitals that invested in analytics, had high digital maturity in both clinical and administrative domain.</p><p>A cross analysis of the cases showed that the digital transformations pursued to progressively explore the potential of analytics are characterised by four elements. The first is an initial verticalisation in a pilot unit and/or in a functional area in order to: (i) protect development of the solution; (ii) facilitate the definition of the desired achievements and their measurement (as declared by the CEO of H11 "once we have refined the algorithm, everything started to work smoothly, and results arrived"); (iii) develop a solid base to be later extended to the rest of the hospital. Indeed, as stated by the CIO of H8:</p><p>"By focusing on a functional area we could have a niche in which to make things feasible and, at the same time, provide comprehensive benefits to all H8."</p><p>The second is the involvement of clinical (H8 and H11) and administrative (H13) decision makers in the digital transformation-in order to compress the time needed for the overall cycle of collecting, analysing, acting and systematising clinical and/or administrative data. The third element is a progressive refinement of the underlying digital solution. The idea is to make it more effective in supporting decisions by exploiting different data sources, adopting more accurate algorithms, and making the user independent in their usage. The last element is an extension to the rest of the hospital. For instance, as referred by the CIO of H13: "The more you connect, the more digital data you can exploit to support decisions. The more you use digital data to support decisions, the more you need to connect the underlying resources producing these digital data. It is a sort of virtuous cycle that never ends". This extension is performed through a set of exploratory and exploitatory innovations-both of a radical and incremental nature-spanning multiple years. In fact, as stated by the CIO of H11: "Since the very beginning, one has to be aware that the solution is part of a larger system that will be developed in the next years."</p><p>As shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref>, hospitals started exploring the benefits of analytics only after a significant percentage of digitisation was accomplished (point 2). Informants underlined that the potential of analytics is stronger in the clinical domain than in the administrative domain. Solutions are realised in protected niches, in which the support to decision-making is progressively tested, and the disrupted way of performing the activities explored (2 à 4).</p><p>Initially, and consistently with the disruptive innovation framework <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Christensen, Grossman, and Hwang 2009)</ref>, these experimentations tend to negatively affect both the exploitatory capability of the niche and its efficiency. Indeed, as explained by the CEO of H11: "Initially the results were not the ones [the CIO] promised. […] Time and money wasted."</p><p>Informants said that these results are related to the fact that the disadvantages associated with these experimentations are not covered by the benefits generated by analytics <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Davenport and Harris, 2007)</ref>, which initially tend to produce only potential valuable scenarios of disrupted activities that have to be tested and progressively refined before being usable.</p><p>Step 2: Scaling-up Test and refinement phases require a set of exploratory and exploitatory innovations (4 à 5) to be accomplished. The path 4 à 5 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref>) aims simply to emphasise that the introduction of analytics is characterised by multiple combinations of exploratory and exploitatory innovation-both of an incremental and a radical nature. H8, H11 and H13 adopted different combinations to balance exploration and exploitation. The common element to the digital transformations based on analytics that has been studied is the progressive improvement of: (i) capabilities to explore and exploit manifested by the hospital; (ii) performance achieved thanks to digital transformation-both in terms of quality and cost.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CHARACTERISATION OF THE THREE EMERGING PATHS</head><p>In this paragraph, we carry out a full IPO characterization of the three emerging paths (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>-Table 4. IPO characterization of three emerging paths -</head><p>The aim is twofold: first, to explain the intra-path elements on the basis of their IPO characterization; second, to feature comparisons among paths to unveil peculiar inter-path traits. From the process viewpoint, antecedents give rise to a combined use of exploitation and exploration activities, with a prevalence of the former (from here, exploitation-driven balanced approach). This balanced configuration allows hospitals to move inside the efficiency frontier, where the two orthogonal dimensions of exploration and exploitation identify locally optimum trade-offs.</p><p>In terms of output, hospitals get sequential streams of incremental (first part of Path A) and radical (second part of Path A) innovations, accomplishing reasonable rates of quality improvement and cost rationalisation. Hospitals undertaking Path A improve their ability to observe the entire work process in action from "end to end" along with the capability to make decisions about next steps when alternative actions can be accomplished. It is true when the transition between the first part and the second part of Path A takes place, allowing hospitals to set up for appropriating the returns of more radical outcomes. It enables people inside the hospital unit to access and make sense of the requisite information collectively. Moreover, it makes the boundaries of hospital units more permeable yet able to be monitored. Finally, work practices may become more complex as people tend to apply their expertise to actual workflows rather than enact their jobs as separate functions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Path B: Digitally-based Process Integration</head><p>In terms of input, Path B occurs at hospital level as all the units are integrated, involving both clinical and administrative domains. Integrating processes represents a medium-term strategy, requiring a moderate use of digital capabilities for the first part (2 à 3). Instead, for the second part (3 à 5), a combination of operations support systems-aimed at integrating activities and decisions across agents of the healthcare ecosystem-and interpretation support systems-aimed at promoting partners' discovery and learning about inter-organisational relationships and its environment-is necessary. To this purpose, high levels of digital capabilities are necessary.</p><p>From the process viewpoint, these antecedents enable hospitals to pursue a balanced configuration of exploitation and exploration activities, co-evolving towards the EF and, using the modes of external process integration, pushing it further out in the exploration-exploitation space finding globally optimum trade-offs. The digital integration among hospitals' processes and other agents seems to have a positive effect on the capability of a hospital to successfully balance exploration and exploitation <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Gregory et al., 2015)</ref>.</p><p>In terms of output, hospitals tend to initially see sequential streams of incremental and radical innovations, which allow accomplishing good rates of quality improvement and cost rationalisation.</p><p>Next, in the external process integration phase, they concretise the opportunity for structurally incremental and radical innovations as different subunits of different agents may, more or less simultaneously, accomplish the outcomes of explorative and exploitative activities. Cases show that, by following Path B, hospitals improve their overall capabilities to exploit and explore, reaching a better balance at different levels. Given the need to have already implemented Path A, hospitals can improve their ability to collaborate virtually by sharing and integrating each other's knowledge. Such a virtual collaboration highly depends upon intertwining technological and organisational features in ways that encourage open knowledge sharing and acquisition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Path C: Disruptive Decision-making through Analytics</head><p>In terms of input, Path C occurs at the hospital level, mainly in clinical domains. Deploying an active support to decision-making is done by first disrupting the process with the introduction of analytics. This entails increased need for digital capabilities supported by interpretation support systems to make sense of data coming from the surrounding environment and leverage communication and collaboration with external agents. Then, in the second part of Path C (4 à 5), hospitals can scaleup their activities, this time lowering the need for digital resources and investments to a moderate level while maintaining high levels of digital capabilities. This path evolves in the long term, assuming that Path A has been already undertaken.</p><p>From the process viewpoint, these antecedents enable hospitals to pursue an exploration-driven balanced approach (2 à 4) allowing hospitals to reach the efficiency frontier; in 4 à 5, hospitals push the efficiency frontier out while becoming truly ambidextrous and finding globally optimum trade-offs.</p><p>In terms of output, hospitals get sequential streams of incremental and radical innovations (4 à 5), going through punctuated discontinuities (2 à 4) which give Path C its exploratory-driven connotation. The first part (2 à 4) is necessary but not sufficient as this sequence of innovative outcomes would lead hospitals to become singular organic organisations with a high likelihood of failure as they may have many new products but little in the way of competence in realising their full innovative potential. By undertaking the second step, hospitals reach a good balance between exploration and exploitation activities while exploring new ways of extracting value from previously digitised administrative and clinical data. Increasingly better performance in terms of quality and cost trade-offs are realised.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p>In this paper, we focused on how solving the exploration-exploitation paradox in hospitals. Through an in-depth investigation, we disentangled inputs, processes, and outcomes of implementing digital transformation programs, their temporal attainment and configurations. Four contributions to the literature on the exploration-exploitation paradox emerge alongside specific propositions.</p><p>First, the exploration-exploitation paradox can be resolved undertaking digital transformation programs <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Gregory et al., 2015)</ref>. The word paradox, especially in organisational settings, usually takes a negative stance implying contrasting aims, deep process rethinking, as well as mind set changing <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Benner and Tushman, 2015)</ref>. Instead, what is usually overlooked is that the underlying diversity and flexibility in being adopted allows not only to reconfigure exploratory-exploitatory efforts within and across healthcare stakeholders, but also to achieve better organisational performances-both in terms of cost reduction as well as quality improvement <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Watson, 2015)</ref>.</p><p>However, a one-size-fits all solution is neither practicable nor desirable. Indeed, our study highlights three complementary paths which leverage upon a different exploration-exploitation balance, whose activities each of which impacting differently both innovation and efficiency outcomes. Each path, with its peculiarities, allows for different solutions to the exploration-exploitation paradox. Then, the first proposition follows:</p><p>Proposition 1: hospitals can solve the exploration-exploitation paradox through the implementation of different digital transformation programs.</p><p>Furthermore, the exploration-exploitation inputs were identified, being them on one side different digital solutions and, on the other side, strategic time frames (short, medium, long term). What is important, however, is the time-variant perspective <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Piao et al., 2010)</ref>  Regarding processes, we showed how hospitals deploy the exploration-exploitation (re)configurations <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Simsek, 2009)</ref> in a space delimited by an efficiency frontier (EF). In the exploration-exploitation space, depending on where hospitals position themselves and which digital solutions they adopt, the EF can be pushed further out. The reconfigurations can be exploitationoriented as in the case of Path A, exploration-oriented as for Path C, as well as entailing a coevolving balanced approach as for Path B (O'Reilly and Tushman, 2013). Path A paves the way for hospitals to implement Path B and/or Path C, pushing the EF further out <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Birkinshaw and Gupta, 2013)</ref>. The third proposition can be formulated as follows:</p><p>Proposition 3: in case of asset digitisation, the efficiency frontier can be pushed further out by undertaking different exploration-exploitation (re)configurations.</p><p>In terms of outcomes, we highlighted the degree of innovativeness achieved <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Garcia and Calantone, 2002)</ref>, the new ability to manage the exploration-exploitation paradox <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Andriopoulos and Lewis, 2009)</ref>, and the effect on the efficiency metrics namely, costs rationalisation and quality improvement <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Smith and Lewis, 2011)</ref>. Concerning the innovation outcomes, the three identified paths allow To sum up, our research provides theoretical contributions from several standpoints. First, the three paths constitute an example of the existing complementarity between exploitation and exploration, and highlight how alternating exploitative and explorative efforts allows the passage from 1 to 5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Piao, 2010)</ref>. Second, the research is inserted within the academic debate regarding ambidextrous tensions in IT transformation programs. The study provides examples regarding the existing tension between costs and quality in IT portfolio decisions and combines it with the time dimension <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Gregory et al., 2015)</ref>. Third, we investigated ambidexterity considering various levels of analysis spanning from the single department to the relationships between the hospital and the regional council (EPI1) or the citizen and the general practitioner (EPI2). Therefore, it is a step in the direction indicated by O'Reilly and Tushman (2013, p.333) regarding the need of works considering not only the single organisation but also the "firm's larger ecosystem". Fourth, the research describes different paths and the various possible effects in terms of costs or quality, or in terms of the degree of innovativeness <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Garcia and Calantone, 2002)</ref>. Therefore, it is a contribution to the study of the relationships between ambidexterity and outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Simsek et al., 2009)</ref>.</p><p>From the viewpoint of healthcare practitioners, the first contribution is the proof that digital transformation programs are a fundamental resource to resolve the tensions raised by the exploration-exploitation paradox. We have shown how to implement them may produce better performance. One has to consider that many CIOs encounter several issues in justifying to their strategic boards the importance of the expenditures in digital transformations. Also, very often hospital boards tend having confused ideas regarding the impact of digital technologies.</p><p>Another contribution of this research to healthcare organisations is the model depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref> to be used together with the IPO framework. Their combinations may orient managers in supporting those who want to strategically manage digital transformation in order to solve the explorationexploitation paradox. It highlights important elements to consider when undertaking such changes:</p><p>(i) the higher benefits associated with the application within the clinical domain, (ii) the selection of "protected" healthcare units to start the digitisation and/or the implementation of analytics, (iii) the risks associated with comprehensive digitisation attempts, (iv) the minimum level of document digitisation below which the digital integration and analytics are not effective, (v) the need to consider the time lapse present between digital installation and the achievement of a true disruptive potential.</p><p>This research also traces a link between the space in which the exploitatory-exploratory paradox emerges and time. Usually, institutions tend to associate exploitatory investments with the short term, and exploratory investments with the long term. Thus, they tend to over-emphasise exploitation at the expense of exploration because the former provides surer and more immediate results than the latter. The model allows the limitation of this potential problem through a continuous focus on combining exploitatory and exploratory investments-in short as well in the long term.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>LIMITATIONS AND FUTURE RESEARCH</head><p>This paper does not come without limitations. The first one concerns generalisability. The focus on a specific lever (digital) and on a specific industry (healthcare), combined with the extensive use of interpretative studies, risks producing very idiosyncratic phenomena. As a further development, we could combine the interpretative methodology with a more quantitative-oriented set of vertical research that could formally test the effectiveness of proposed contributions in all their details in specific subfields. Furthermore, scholars could mix the findings of this research with a bibliometric or patent analysis, and contrast the sequence of digital technologies described by our model with the dynamics in the domain of digital technologies in healthcare that emerge through the study of publications or patents <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Ardito et al., 2017)</ref>. The second limitation is related to the operationalisation of the constructs. Successful management of the exploration-exploitation paradox requires multidimensional concepts. The empirical analysis showed it is not straightforward to separate these forces completely. Future studies could rely on variables that precisely measure: (i) the level of exploration and exploitation accomplished within and among hospitals; (ii) the performance achieved through their balance; (iii) the impact that digital technologies play in the achievement of the EF.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IPI2</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Human resources management systems</head><p>Digital solutions used for the management of all aspects tied to the hospital's personnel (legal, economic, social, as well as attendances and absences, etc.)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IPI3</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Electronic Medical Record</head><p>Digital solutions providing support to the computerised, uniform, updated and integrated management of personal, clinical data of a patient throughout the entire cycle of medical assistance given within the hospital External process integration</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EPI1</head><p>Digital services to the patients Digital solution to deliver services to the patients through digital channels; included in this category it is possible to find the communication services, those for patient access of clinical information, those supporting the use of healthcare resources, CRM services, and services to support the interaction among patients</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EPI2</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Regional medicine and home assistance</head><p>Digital solutions that respond to the aims of creating integration between the hospital, the district services and family doctors operating within the region EPI3 Integration with the EHR Digital solutions used to create integration with the platforms for Electronic Health Record, defined as the record format for healthcare data coming from various people in charge of treatment in the same territorial area</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analytics</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AN1</head><p>Computerised drug management systems Digital solutions to support drug prescription, preparation and administration</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AN2</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical Governance Tools</head><p>Digital solutions that support clinical decisions with the objective of improving the quality of services offered, and reaching/maintaining elevated healthcare standards (e.g. the systems to define diagnostic paths)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AN3 Governance dashboards</head><p>Digital solutions that support the governance/administrative decisions with the objective of improving the quality of the administrative processes (e.g. the business intelligence tools adopted to balance the peaks of demand)    * Each statement in the table has been rated on a 10 points Likert scale in order to measure its importance (0 = not important; 10 highly important); the number in the squared brackets indicates the average importance provided by the informant in the last round of interviews; the table presents only the statements that have achieved an average importance rate higher than 7.0 ** According the CIO, the problems indicated with "Major" risked to compromise the adoption; the problems indicated with "Minor" do not constituted great threats from this viewpoint *** For each phase, the CIO has indicated its main impact (ER = exploratory; EI = exploitatory) and its grade of innovativeness (RI = radical; II = incremental; DI = disruptive) **** Only the main approaches adopted to ambidextrously balance exploratory and exploitatory activities are reported in the table; refers to §4 for a description of digitally-based asset integration; organisational differentiation means that exploration and exploitation occur simultaneously but are situated within distinct hospital units <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Lavie et al., 2010</ref>) ***** According the CIO, the next steps indicated with "Major" had to be accomplished as soon as possible; the ones indicated with "Minor" were subject to the presence of further budgets for digital transformation * Each statement in the table has been rated on a 10 points Likert scale in order to measure its importance (0 = not important; 10 highly important); the number in the squared brackets indicates the average importance provided by the informant in the last round of interviews; the table presents only the statements that have achieved an average importance rate higher than 7.0 ** According the CIO, the problems indicated with "Major" risked to compromise the adoption; the problems indicated with "Minor" do not constituted great threats from this viewpoint *** For each phase, the CIO has indicated its main impact (ER = exploratory; EI = exploitatory) and its grade of innovativeness (RI = radical; II = incremental; DI = disruptive) **** Only the main approaches adopted to ambidextrously balance exploratory and exploitatory activities are reported in the table; refers to §4 for a description of digitally-based asset integration; administered integration refers to the development of temporal reconfigurations of certain units in order to make possible the collaboration of resources necessary to solve the conflicts present between exploration and exploitation <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Eisenhardt et al., 2010)</ref>; domain differentiation means that each unit specialises in exploratory or exploitatory activities (e.g. standard patient treatment vs. acute patient treatment) while the hospital balance these activities across domains <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Lavie et al., 2010)</ref>. ***** According the CIO, the next steps indicated with "Major" had to be accomplished as soon as possible; the ones indicated with "Minor" were subject to the presence of further budgets for digital transformation * Each statement in the table has been rated on a 10 points Likert scale in order to measure its importance (0 = not important; 10 highly important); the number in the squared brackets indicates the average importance provided by the informant in the last round of interviews; the table presents only the statements that have achieved an average importance rate higher than 7.0 ** According the CIO, the problems indicated with "Major" risked to compromise the adoption; the problems indicated with "Minor" do not constituted great threats from this viewpoint *** For each phase, the CIO has indicated its main impact (ER = exploratory; EI = exploitatory) and its grade of innovativeness (RI = radical; II = incremental; DI = disruptive) **** Only the main approaches adopted to ambidextrously balance exploratory and exploitatory activities are reported in the table; refers to §4 for a description of digitally-based asset integration; temporal differentiation means that the service farm switches between exploration and exploitation over time; organisational differentiation means that exploration and exploitation occur simultaneously but are situated within distinct hospital units <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Lavie et al., 2010)</ref> ***** According the CIO, the next steps indicated with "Major" had to be accomplished as soon as possible; the ones indicated with "Minor" were subject to the presence of further budgets for digital transformation * Each statement in the table has been rated on a 10 points Likert scale in order to measure its importance (0 = not important; 10 highly important); the number in the squared brackets indicates the average importance provided by the informant in the last round of interviews; the table presents only the statements that have achieved an average importance rate higher than 7.0 ** According the CIO, the problems indicated with "Major" risked to compromise the adoption; the problems indicated with "Minor" do not constituted great threats from this viewpoint *** For each phase, the CIO has indicated its main impact (ER = exploratory; EI = exploitatory) and its grade of innovativeness (RI = radical; II = incremental; DI = disruptive) **** Only the main approaches adopted to ambidextrously balance exploratory and exploitatory activities are reported in the table; refers to §4 for a description of IT/IS-based asset integration; organisational differentiation means that exploration and exploitation occur simultaneously but are situated within distinct hospital units <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Lavie et al., 2010)</ref> ***** According the CIO, the next steps indicated with "Major" had to be accomplished as soon as possible; the ones indicated with "Minor" were subject to the presence of further budgets for digital transformation He was right… -Physician F * Each statement in the table has been rated on a 10 points Likert scale in order to measure its importance (0 = not important; 10 highly important); the number in the squared brackets indicates the average importance provided by the informant in the last round of interviews; the table presents only the statements that have achieved an average importance rate higher than 7.0 ** According the CIO, the problems indicated with "Major" risked to compromise EMR adoption; the problems indicated with "Minor" do not constituted great threats from this viewpoint *** For each phase, the CIO has indicated its main impact (ER = exploratory; EI = exploitatory) and its grade of innovativeness (RI = radical; II = incremental; DI = disruptive) **** Only the main approaches adopted to ambidextrously balance exploratory and exploitatory activities are reported in the table; refers to §4 for a description of digitally-based process integration; temporal differentiation means that the hospital switches between exploration and exploitation over time; administered integration refers to the development of temporal reconfigurations of certain units in order to make possible the collaboration of resources necessary to solve the conflicts present between exploration and exploitation <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Eisenhardt et al., 2010)</ref> ***** According the CIO, the next steps indicated with "Major" had to be accomplished as soon as possible; the ones indicated with "Minor" were subject to the presence of further budgets for digital transformation * Each statement in the table has been rated on a 10 points Likert scale in order to measure its importance (0 = not important; 10 highly important); the number in the squared brackets indicates the average importance provided by the informant in the last round of interviews; the table presents only the statements that have achieved an average importance rate higher than 7.0 ** According the CIO, the problems indicated with "Major" risked to compromise EMR adoption; the problems indicated with "Minor" do not constituted great threats from this viewpoint *** For each phase, the CIO has indicated its main impact (ER = exploratory; EI = exploitatory) and its grade of innovativeness (RI = radical; II = incremental; DI = disruptive) **** Since the last reform of the Italian healthcare system, in 1999, all the Italian hospitals are financed by a predefined overall budget composed of two elements: (i) payment for inpatient and outpatient care by means of predetermined rates based on DRG (Diagnosis-Related Group), and (ii) payment based on the average production cost for emergencies, care activities with high waiting costs, prevention schemes, social services, transplant activities and management of chronic illness. Recent evaluations of the impact of DRG system in <ref type="bibr">Italy (e.g., Ferré et al., 2014)</ref> have shown that the introduction of a prospective payment system has led to a greater attention to planning and budgeting within each hospital **** According the CIO, the next steps indicated with "Major" had to be accomplished as soon as possible; the ones indicated with "Minor" were subject to the presence of further budgets for digital transformation • The next piece in this jigsaw is the patient. We need to better integrate out patients to our hospitals -CEO F * Each statement in the table has been rated on a 10 points Likert scale in order to measure its importance (0 = not important; 10 highly important); the number in the squared brackets indicates the average importance provided by the informant in the last round of interviews; the table presents only the statements that have achieved an average importance rate higher than 7.0 ** According the CIO, the problems indicated with "Major" risked to compromise EMR adoption; the problems indicated with "Minor" do not constituted great threats from this viewpoint *** For each phase, the CIO has indicated its main impact (ER = exploratory; EI = exploitatory) and its grade of innovativeness (RI = radical; II = incremental; DI = disruptive) **** Only the main approaches adopted to ambidextrously balance exploratory and exploitatory activities are reported in the table; refers to §4 for a description of digitally-based process integration; temporal differentiation means that the hospital switches between exploration and exploitation over time; emergent integration means that the department spontaneously and often serendipitously activate cross-department collaborations to cope and progressively solve the conflicts present between exploration and exploitation (Martin and Eisenhardt, 2010) ***** According the CIO, the next steps indicated with "Major" had to be accomplished as soon as possible; the ones indicated with "Minor" were subject to the presence of further budgets for digital transformation * Each statement in the table has been rated on a 10 points Likert scale in order to measure its importance (0 = not important; 10 highly important); the number in the squared brackets indicates the average importance provided by the informant in the last round of interviews; the table presents only the statements that have achieved an average importance rate higher than 7.0 ** According the CIO, the problems indicated with "Major" risked to compromise EMR adoption; the problems indicated with "Minor" do not constituted great threats from this viewpoint *** For each phase, the CIO has indicated its main impact (ER = exploratory; EI = exploitatory) and its grade of innovativeness (RI = radical; II = incremental; DI = disruptive) **** Only the main approaches adopted to ambidextrously balance exploratory and exploitatory activities are reported in the table; refers to §4 for a description of digitally-based process integration; domain differentiation means that each unit specialises in exploratory or exploitatory activities in particular domain (e.g. standard patient treatment vs. acute patient treatment) while the hospital balances these activities across domains <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Lavie et al., 2010)</ref>; heuristic integration means that exploration and exploitation are integrated through the usage of a portfolio of deliberately small set of articulated and often informal rules-of-thumb <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Eisenhardt et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Bingham and Eisenhardt, 2011</ref>) ***** According the CIO, the next steps indicated with "Major" had to be accomplished as soon as possible; the ones indicated with "Minor" were subject to the presence of further budgets for digital transformation Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">12</ref>. Main findings of the interviews performed on H14 F * Each statement in the table has been rated on a 10 points Likert scale in order to measure its importance (0 = not important; 10 highly important); the number in the squared brackets indicates the average importance provided by the informant in the last round of interviews; the table presents only the statements that have achieved an average importance rate higher than 7.0 ** According the CIO, the problems indicated with "Major" risked to compromise the adoption; the problems indicated with "Minor" do not constituted great threats from this viewpoint *** For each phase, the CIO has indicated its main impact (ER = exploratory; EI = exploitatory) and its grade of innovativeness (RI = radical; II = incremental; DI = disruptive) **** Only the main approaches adopted to ambidextrously balance exploratory and exploitatory activities are reported in the table; refers to §4 for a description of digitally-based process integration; temporal differentiation means that the hospital switches between exploration and exploitation over time; administered integration refers to the development of temporal reconfigurations of certain units in order to make possible the collaboration of resources necessary to solve the conflicts present between exploration and exploitation <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Eisenhardt et al., 2010)</ref> ***** According the CIO, the next steps indicated with "Major" had to be accomplished as soon as possible; the ones indicated with "Minor" were subject to the presence of further budgets for digital transformation * Each statement in the table has been rated on a 10 points Likert scale in order to measure its importance (0 = not important; 10 highly important); the number in the squared brackets indicates the average importance provided by the informant in the last round of interviews; the table presents only the statements that have achieved an average importance rate higher than 7.0 ** According the CIO, the problems indicated with "Major" risked to compromise the adoption; the problems indicated with "Minor" do not constituted great threats from this viewpoint *** For each phase, the CIO has indicated its main impact (ER = exploratory; EI = exploitatory) and its grade of innovativeness (RI = radical; II = incremental; DI = disruptive) **** Only the main approaches adopted to ambidextrously balance exploratory and exploitatory activities are reported in the table; refers to §4 for a description of digitally-based process integration; organisational differentiation means that exploration and exploitation occur simultaneously but are situated within distinct hospital units <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Lavie et al., 2010)</ref> ***** According the CIO, the next steps indicated with "Major" had to be accomplished as soon as possible; the ones indicated with "Minor" were subject to the presence of further budgets for digital transformation * Each statement in the table has been rated on a 10 points Likert scale in order to measure its importance (0 = not important; 10 highly important); the number in the squared brackets indicates the average importance provided by the informant in the last round of interviews; the table presents only the statements that have achieved an average importance rate higher than 7.0 ** According the CIO, the problems indicated with "Major" risked to compromise the adoption; the problems indicated with "Minor" do not constituted great threats from this viewpoint *** For each phase, the CIO has indicated its main impact (ER = exploratory; EI = exploitatory) and its grade of innovativeness (RI = radical; II = incremental; DI = disruptive) **** Only the main approaches adopted to ambidextrously balance exploratory and exploitatory activities are reported in the table; refers to §4 for a description of digitally-based process integration ***** According the CIO, the next steps indicated with "Major" had to be accomplished as soon as possible; the ones indicated with "Minor" were subject to the presence of further budgets for digital transformation * Each statement in the table has been rated on a 10 points Likert scale in order to measure its importance (0 = not important; 10 highly important); the number in the squared brackets indicates the average importance provided by the informant in the last round of interviews; the table presents only the statements that have achieved an average importance rate higher than 7.0 ** According the CIO, the problems indicated with "Major" risked to compromise the adoption; the problems indicated with "Minor" do not constituted great threats from this viewpoint *** For each phase, the CIO has indicated its main impact (ER = exploratory; EI = exploitatory) and its grade of innovativeness (RI = radical; II = incremental; DI = disruptive) **** Only the main approaches adopted to ambidextrously balance exploratory and exploitatory activities are reported in the table; domain differentiation means that each unit specialises in exploratory or exploitatory activities in particular domain (e.g. pneumonia diagnoses vs. non-pneumonia diagnoses) while the hospital balances these activities across domains; temporal differentiation means that the hospital switches between exploration and exploitation over time <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Lavie et al., 2010)</ref>; organisational differentiation means that exploration and exploitation occur simultaneously but are situated within distinct hospital units <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Lavie et al., 2010)</ref>; heuristic-based integration means that exploration and exploitation are integrated through the usage of a portfolio of deliberately small set of articulated and often informal rules-of-thumb <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Eisenhardt et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Bingham and Eisenhardt, 2011</ref>) ***** According the CIO, the next steps indicated with "Major" had to be accomplished as soon as possible; the ones indicated with "Minor" were subject to the presence of further budgets for digital transformation * Each statement in the table has been rated on a 10 points Likert scale in order to measure its importance (0 = not important; 10 highly important); the number in the squared brackets indicates the average importance provided by the informant in the last round of interviews; the table presents only the statements that have achieved an average importance rate higher than 7.0 ** According the CIO, the problems indicated with "Major" risked to compromise the adoption; the problems indicated with "Minor" do not constituted great threats from this viewpoint *** For each phase, the CIO has indicated its main impact (ER = exploratory; EI = exploitatory) and its grade of innovativeness (RI = radical; II = incremental; DI = disruptive) **** Only the main approaches adopted to ambidextrously balance exploratory and exploitatory activities are reported in the table; temporal differentiation means that the hospital switches between exploration and exploitation over time; domain differentiation means that each unit specialises in exploratory or exploitatory activities in particular domain while the hospital balances these activities across domains; organisational differentiation means that exploration and exploitation occur simultaneously but are situated within distinct hospital units <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Lavie et al., 2010)</ref>; heuristic-based integration means that exploration and exploitation are integrated through the usage of a portfolio of deliberately small set of articulated and often informal rules-of-thumb <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Eisenhardt et al., 2010)</ref> ***** According the CIO, the next steps indicated with "Major" had to be accomplished as soon as possible; the ones indicated with "Minor" were subject to the presence of further budgets for digital transformation </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">DI2 DI3 DI4 DI5 IPI1 IPI2 IPI3 EPI1 EPI2 EPI3 AN1 AN2 AN3 H1 C C C F D [8] F H2 C D D [7] C C C F F F H3 C F C C D C D [9] H4 D [8] D C C C F C F H5 D D [7] C C F F H6 C C C F D [5] C C C H7 D C D [8] F C F H8 C C C C D C D C C F C D [8] F H9 C C C C D [10] F F F H10 C D C C C C C C D [9] C F H11 C C C C C D C C F F C D [6] C H12 D C C C D D C C D [6] C F F H13 C C C D C C C C C F D [7] H14 C D C C C C D [9] F D F * C</formula></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>In terms of input, Path A occurs at the unit level and most often in the clinical domain as clinical digitisation yields better results than administrative digitisation in effectively managing the exploration-exploitation paradox. Digitising assets represents a short-term strategy and requires a low use of digital capabilities. Hospitals undertaking this path are allowed to prioritise resources further to go through both Path B and Path C.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>we unveiled by showing how hospitals move along the identified paths and dynamically deal with the exploration-exploitation paradox. Short-time solutions are more exploitation-oriented (e.g., asset digitisation for Path A), whereas medium or long-term ones embrace more exploration-oriented activities (e.g., EMR and telemedicine services for Path B; analytics for Path C). Two reasons justify this difference: first, both Path B and C presumes the deployment of Path A; second, the digital solutions envisaged for Path B and C are more complex and require longer time frames to be accepted, understood, absorbed, and applied within the organisational context. A second proposition follows: Proposition 2: the implementation of digital transformation programs entails a time variant approach, where different time frames allow for different digital solutions.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>hospitals to intermittently innovate either in an incremental or radical/disruptive way. With the only exception of Path A, which is exploitation-driven because of the important efficiency stimulus to introduce into the organisation, Path B and Path C begin with a radical and disruptive step respectively. Each step brings also about different efficiency outcomes; however, both Path B and Path C are instrumental in reaching the highest cost rationalisation and quality improvements. Thus, we can advance the following proposition: Proposition 4: through different digital transformation programs, hospitals accomplish different innovation and efficiency outcomes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>FIGURESFigureFigure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>FIGURES</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>means present at Jan. 2009; D means under development in the period from Jan. 2009 to Dec. 2011; F means development starting before the end of 2012 (but after the end of 2011); the digital solutions with squared parentheses are the one whose introduction process has been studied as the basis of the digital transformation ongoing into the hospital; the number within the parentheses indicates the number of interviews performed in the three years of the research</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="21,56.55,53.85,481.90,153.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="21,134.75,259.34,361.44,245.10" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLES Table 1 . Digital solutions adopted by hospitals</head><label>TABLES1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Area</cell><cell>Id</cell><cell>Digital Solution</cell><cell>Definition *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Tools supporting service</cell><cell>Digital solutions used in the admissions processes, in directing the user flows</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>DI1</cell><cell>management and</cell><cell>within the hospital, and in the communication that is oriented towards the users</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>delivery</cell><cell>who are waiting for service delivery</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Digital solutions guaranteeing the production of informational data, preventing</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>DI2</cell><cell>IT security</cell><cell>access of unauthorised individuals and guaranteeing their access after</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>catastrophic events</cell></row><row><cell>Digitalisation</cell><cell>DI3</cell><cell>Virtualisation</cell><cell>Digital solutions that create a virtual version of HW, operating systems, storage devices or network resources</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>DI4</cell><cell>Systems for the dematerialisation of clinical documents</cell><cell>Digital solutions that allow to eliminate the paper-based or film-based documents that are used in a department, transforming them into electronic documents</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>DI5</cell><cell>Systems for the dematerialisation of administrative docs.</cell><cell>Digital solutions that allow to eliminate the paper-based documents used in the administrative offices of a HCO, transforming them into electronic documents</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>IPI1</cell><cell>Administrative management systems</cell><cell>Digital solutions for the management of accounting, financial flows, logistics, etc.</cell></row><row><cell>Internal</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>process</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>integration</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 . Hospitals involved in the case studies and interviews accomplished</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Pseudonyms are used to protect the anonymity of the hospitals and their members ** AO (Azienda Ospedaliera): public hospital providing patient treatment by specialised staff and equipment as quasi-independent public agency; ASL (Azienda Sanitaria Locale): geographically-based hospital responsible for assessing needs and providing comprehensive care to the population of a defined territory; IRCCS (Istituto di Ricerca e Cura a Carattere Scientifico): hospital with competences in research and treatment of important diseases</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="4">Hospital * Typology ** Employees Ownership</cell><cell>Interviews to CIO</cell><cell>Interviews to CEO</cell><cell>Interviews to CFO</cell><cell>Interviews to CMO</cell><cell>Interviews to physicians and nurses</cell><cell>Total interviews</cell></row><row><cell>H1</cell><cell>AO</cell><cell>3,608</cell><cell>Public</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>H2</cell><cell>AO</cell><cell>2,320</cell><cell>Public</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>H3</cell><cell>ASL</cell><cell>1,286</cell><cell>Public</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>H4</cell><cell>ASL</cell><cell>3,256</cell><cell>Public</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>H5</cell><cell>IRCCS</cell><cell>304</cell><cell>Private</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>H6</cell><cell>IRCCS</cell><cell>783</cell><cell>Private</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>H7</cell><cell>IRCCS</cell><cell>606</cell><cell>Public</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>H8</cell><cell>AO</cell><cell>4,129</cell><cell>Public</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>H9</cell><cell>AO</cell><cell>3,814</cell><cell>Public</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>H10</cell><cell>ASL</cell><cell>805</cell><cell>Public</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>H11</cell><cell>IRCCS</cell><cell>1,446</cell><cell>Public</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>H12</cell><cell>IRCCS</cell><cell>641</cell><cell>Private</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table><note><p>*</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 . Digital solutions characterising the digital transformation that has been studied</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Hospital *</cell><cell>Digitalisation</cell><cell>Internal Process integration</cell><cell>External Process integration</cell><cell>Analytics</cell></row><row><cell>DI1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4 . IPO characterisation of three emerging paths</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Paths</cell><cell></cell><cell>(A) Asset digitalisation within hospitals</cell><cell cols="2">(B) Digitally-based process integration Internal External</cell><cell>(C) Disruptive decision-making</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Level of analysis</cell><cell>Hospital unit</cell><cell>Hospital</cell><cell>Healthcare systems</cell><cell>Hospital (mostly)</cell></row><row><cell>Input</cell><cell>Key enabling digital solution Strategic time-frame</cell><cell>Asset digitalisation (low digital capabilities) Short-term</cell><cell>EMR (moderate digital capabilities) Medium-term</cell><cell>Telemedicine services (high digital capabilities) Medium-term</cell><cell>Analytics (high digital capabilities) Long-term</cell></row><row><cell>Process</cell><cell>Balancing approach Distance from the efficiency frontier</cell><cell>Exploitation-driven balanced approach Inside the efficiency frontier</cell><cell>Co-evolving balanced approach Reaching the efficiency frontier</cell><cell>Ambidextrous approach Beyond the efficiency frontier</cell><cell>Exploration-driven balanced approach Beyond the efficiency frontier</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Degree of Innovativeness</cell><cell>Incremental and then radical innovation</cell><cell cols="2">Sequence of incremental and radical innovations</cell><cell>Disruptive innovation</cell></row><row><cell>Output</cell><cell>Performance</cell><cell>• Initial: moderate efficiency • Final: moderate efficiency and effectiveness</cell><cell cols="2">• Initial: moderate efficiency and/or effectiveness • Final: high efficiency and effectiveness</cell><cell>• Initial: inefficiency and ineffectiveness • Final: high efficiency and effectiveness</cell></row></table><note><p>F</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 5 . Main findings of the interviews performed on H2</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Input</cell><cell>Process</cell><cell>Output</cell><cell>Representative informants quotes</cell></row><row><cell>Digital solution: electronic queues management system (DI1) Stimuli to the adoption of the digital solution: * • Augmenting the efficiency of the front office employees in the admission processes [9.0] • Monitoring and reducing the queues in front of the admission desks (increasing the service level) [10.0] Problems during the adoption phase: * ** • Major: -• Minor: coordination of the front-office employees scattered in the different facilities of H4 and with different needs [7.6] • Minor: tender writing (to avoid the gathering of pure cost-oriented suppliers [7.4] • Minor: problematic purchasing [7.6]</cell><cell>Development phases and impact on exploration and exploitation: *** • Development of a set of interactive electronic multimedia kiosks to manage and standardise patient flow in the outpatient desk present in the main facility of H4 [EI | II] • Extension of the multimedia kiosks to the outpatient desks of the other facilities of H4 [EI | II] • Development of a solution to digitally integrate the different multimedia kiosks and provide a service coherent with patient behaviour [EX | RI] • Empowerment of front office employees with training on how to use the solution [EI | II] Approaches to manage the exploration-exploitation paradox: **** • Departmental level: digitally-based asset integration • Organisational level: administered integration (among the front-office</cell><cell>Challenges/issues: * • Initial user resistance (digital tools seen only as a means to control their performance) [9.2] • Plurality of different stakeholders with different levels of digital readiness [7.9] Performance impact: * • Initial: flexibility and synchronisation of service delivery [7.7] • Final: initial + increased quality of the healthcare service delivered [7.7] Next steps to be accomplished: * ***** • Major: improving the communication to the patients during the queues [8.0] • Major: extending the solution to the exam booking processes [8.6] • Major: Further reducing the time spent in queues [7.2] • Major: Managing the outliers [7.2]</cell><cell>• The benefits are only partially related to less paper-based processes. The real benefits are related to the fact that information circulates quickly, and users are empowered -CEO • There are users who love PCs and users who simply hate them. I had to move within this "space". Trust me: it's not easy at all -CIO • Initially I thought "Just one more tech devilry", but I have to admit that the solution works, and it is useful -Nurse • Now we have a sort of triage for the different patients -Nurse • All this digitalisation is a prerequisite of EMR development -CIO • We have always thought of ICT in terms of cost reduction. As a matter of fact, there are tremendous benefits also in terms of quality improvement -CEO • Clinical data provides many more opportunities to both revise the existing paths through which the service of our organisation is delivered to our patients, as well as to change and improve these paths. Administrative processes are simply not</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>units) and domain differentiation (according to the kind of patient</cell><cell>• Minor: Developing an Electronic Medical Record [8.0]</cell><cell>such as pervasive as clinical processes in a hospital. It's a matter of impact -CMO</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>served)</cell><cell>•</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>F</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 6 . Main findings of the interviews performed on H4</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Input</cell><cell>Process</cell><cell>Output</cell><cell>Representative informants quotes</cell></row><row><cell>Digital solution: virtualisation of hardware devices and the main clinical software (DI3) Stimuli to the adoption of the digital solution: * • Reducing the incidence of hardware and software obsolescence [7.0] • Improving scalability [7.0] • Centralising complex tasks in software and hardware management [7.0] Problems during the adoption phase: * ** • Major: continuously raising requests from the healthcare departments [8.0] • Major: justification of digital budgets (difficulties in quantifying the benefits associated to digital solutions) [7.2] • Major: introduction of the solutions into existing processes (especially the clinical ones) [8.9]</cell><cell>Development phases and impact on exploration and exploitation: *** • Virtualisation of the main clinical software (standardisation and control over updates) [EI | II] • Hardware virtualisation (PCs as thin clients)-one dept. at a time [EI | II] • Integration of the virtualised software and development of new workflows and services (especially in the diagnostic area) [EX | RI] • Virtualisation of administrative software [EI | II] • Integration of administrative and clinical workflows [EX | RI] Approaches to manage the exploration-exploitation paradox: **** • Departmental level: digitally-based asset integration and temporal differentiation in the server farm hosting the virtualised solutions • Organisational level: organisational differentiation between the server farm and the rest of H5</cell><cell>Challenges/issues: * • Business continuity issues [7.7] • Identity management [7.2] • Problems associated with the introduction of the virtualised solutions into existing processes (especially the clinical ones) [8.0] Performance impact: * • Initial: reduction of HW and SW costs and health desk services [9.1] • Final: initial + better management of hardware and software evolutions/change [8.6] Next steps to be accomplished: * ***** • Major: Developing an Electronic Medical Record and better integrating with the regional EHR [8.3] • Major: Considering cloud-based services for some general software to further decreasing costs and outsource their development [7.8] • Major: investing in digital security to guaranteeing access to server farms</cell><cell>• Now there are no longer 1,000,000 different mail clients toward which to offer a helpdesk service -CIO • Now all the healthcare modules of the different solutions that were scattered in H5 are in a unique place. And we can improve them for all the users -CIO • Now with my old-school PC I can run ultramodern apps! -Physician • These kinds of interventions are almost invisible to the final users. At best they do not notice anything -CIO • We are progressively entering into the digital world. One step a time. Our objective is start to implement an EMR by the end of 2012 -CEO • It's better focusing on a department at a time. Why? Because it's possible to avoid the over-complications associated with the development of pervasive solutions-at least in the initial digitalisation stages and/or in the case of low budgets available -CIO • We have clearly missed an opportunity with digital… But we are aware of it, and we are in the process of changing this situation -CMO • We pay our digital ignorance… -CEO</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>after catastrophic events [7.2]</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>•</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>F</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 7 . Main findings of the interviews performed on H5</head><label>7</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Input</cell><cell>Process</cell><cell>Output</cell><cell>Representative informants quotes</cell></row><row><cell>Digital solution: dematerialisation of laboratory documents (DI4) Stimuli to the adoption of the digital solution: * • Reducing the workload peaks of the laboratory (bottle neck for the other departments) [8.7] • Increasing the efficiency of the laboratory [8.5] • Being compliant to regional rules in terms of clinical dematerialisation [7.1] Problems during the adoption phase: * ** • Major: high dependence of the other processes in the H7 (pressures to</cell><cell>Development phases and impact on exploration and exploitation: *** • Preliminary digitalisation of the main laboratory assets and simplification of laboratory routines [EI | II] • Progressive refinement and improvement of laboratory workflows [EI | II] • Digital integration of the assets present in the laboratory in order to produce new diagnoses [EX | RI] • Development of a full Laboratory Information System (LIS) to efficient laboratory workflows [EI | RI] • Implementation of a set of projects to fully explore the benefits of the</cell><cell>Challenges/issues: * • Physicians' resistance in using the tool to manage the analyses to be performed in the laboratory [8.1] • Progressively switching from the logic of asset dematerialisation to process dematerialisation [7.1] Performance impact: * • Initial: reduction of the time and the cost per laboratory analysis [8.2] • Final: initial + improvement of the quality of the analyses carried out in the laboratory [7.9] Next steps to be accomplished: * ***** • Major: continuing the</cell><cell>• Do you know what slogans are used to convince us in investing in dematerialisation? Basically two: "We'll reduce costs", and "A rule obliges us to do it" -CEO • Radiology and laboratory are document-intensive departments, mostly detached by the core services offered by their hospital, with technology-friendly physicians, and many efficiency needs -CIO • There are three things to make clear: it's part of a bigger process, it's easier if you focus on one department at a time, and it has to start in a document-intensive department, like the laboratory -CIO • XXI century, here we are! -Physician • It's not simply an automated order entry.</cell></row><row><cell>dematerialise as soon as possible)</cell><cell>shared data [EX | II]</cell><cell>dematerialisation in the laboratory</cell><cell>Now new analyses are available "on the</cell></row><row><cell>[7.9] • Major: initial user resistance within the laboratory [7.7] • Minor: tender writing (definition of the specifications for the supplier of the digital solution) [7.1]</cell><cell>Approaches to manage the exploration-exploitation paradox: **** • Departmental level: digitally-based asset integration (especially order entry and specimen processing) • Organisational level: organisational differentiation between the laboratory and the rest of H7</cell><cell>[9.0] • Major: dematerialising the radiology department [9.2] • Minor: Digitalising the services through which the patients and the physicians interact with the laboratory [7.0] administrative processes [7.0] • Minor: dematerialising most of the</cell><cell>shelf"… -CMO • The entire hospital was breathing down my neck, urging me to end the project as soon as possible. And I don't think that things will change for the radiology department -CIO • The time between the request of analyses and the delivery of their results is decreased -CIO</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>•</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>F</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table 8 . Main findings of the interviews performed on H7</head><label>8</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Input</cell><cell>Process</cell><cell>Output</cell><cell>Representative informants quotes</cell></row><row><cell>Digital solution: Electronic Medical Record (IPI3) Stimuli to the adoption of the digital solution: * • Reducing the inefficiencies in clinical data management [7.9] • External pressures (integration with the Electronic Health Record) [7.8] • Improving the effectiveness of the treatments [7.4] Problems during the adoption phase: * ** • Major: -• Minor: initial technological resistance of the physicians (used to work accordingly to own workflows) [8.7] • Minor: tender writing (previsions of the modular extensions; willingness to avoid pure cost-oriented vendors) [7.7]</cell><cell>Development phases and impact on exploration and exploitation: *** • Integration of the inter-departmental processes related to therapy management [EI | RI] • Implementation of a set of project in each department to use the shared data on therapies [EX | II] • Integration of the inter-departmental processes related to clinical dossier management [EI | RI] • Implementation of projects in each dept. to use clinical dossier [EX | II] • Integration of the inter-departmental processes related to out-patient management [EI | RI] • Implementation of a set of project in each department to use the shared out-patient data [EX | II] Approaches to manage the exploration-exploitation paradox: **** • Departmental level: digitally-based process integration • Organisational level: temporal</cell><cell>Challenges/issues: * • Balancing standardisation requirements with practitioners' customisation needs [7.8] • Managing user resistance [8.3] Performance impact: * • Initial: cost rationalisation [9.9] • Final: initial + quality improvement [9.8] Next steps to be accomplished: * ***** • Major: continuing the development of the EMR (focus on diagnostic area and Admission, Discharges and Transfers, ADT) [8.4] • Minor: better integrating with the regional Electronic Health Record (not only the mandatory data) [7.6] • Minor: developing an administrative management system [7.1]</cell><cell>• My ideas are pretty clear. I know exactly what I want from an EMR and where we'll end. However, I have to take into account the annual resources in my hands. This solution is the best compromise I've found… -CIO • … and this "technician" comes to tell you that you have to change a decennial, effective way of working! -Physician • This year [2009] we integrate; the next one [2010] we'll start a verticalisation in each department to see how we can use the shared data. Then we'll restart the process of integration… and so on and so forth -CIO • To be honest, our main focus was cost rationalisation… but we ended also with a better service -CMO • EMR is on the agenda also for the year 2012 -CEO • Not surprisingly, a great emphasis has been put on the management of the resistance of the physicians to the use of the electronic tool. I know my hens, and I expected that reaction -CMO • At the end of the story he [referring to the CIO] was right. Goddam! [laughing]</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>differentiation, administered</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>integration</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>•</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table 9 . Main findings of the interviews performed on H1 Managing</head><label>9</label><figDesc>the Exploration-Exploitation Paradox in Healthcare: Three Complementary Paths to Leverage on Digital Transformation</figDesc><table><row><cell>eCompanion</cell></row></table><note><p>F</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table 10 . Main findings of the interviews performed on H6</head><label>10</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Input</cell><cell>Process</cell><cell>Output</cell><cell>Representative informants quotes</cell></row><row><cell>Digital solution: Electronic Medical Record (IPI3) Stimuli to the adoption of the digital solution: * • Improving the effectiveness of the treatments [8.8] • External pressures (EHR integration) [7.6] • Reducing the inefficiencies in clinical data management [7.1] Problems during the adoption phase: * ** • Minor: decision from which department to start (efficiency vs. potential pervasiveness) [7.2] • Minor: clearly understand the necessities of the physicians [7.8] • Minor: technical problems linked to the customisation of the EMR to the workflows of the pilot department and the interoperability issues [7.6]</cell><cell>Development phases and impact on exploration and exploitation: *** • Integration of the processes of the paediatric intensive care to explore new treatments/diagnoses [EX | RI] • Implementation of a set of projects to share the new treatments/diagnoses to the rest of H9 [EI | II] • Integration of the processes of cardiology to explore new treatments/diagnoses [EX | RI] • Implementation of a set of projects to share the new treatments/diagnoses to the rest of H9 [EI | II] • Integration of the processes of the emergency department to explore new treatments/diagnoses [EX | RI] • Implementation of a set of projects to share the new treatments/diagnoses to the rest of H9 [EI | II] Approaches to manage the exploration-exploitation paradox: **** • Departmental level: digitally-based process integration</cell><cell>Challenges/issues: * • Balancing practitioners' customisation needs with standardisation requirements [7.2] • Homogenising the different sections of the EMR [8.6] Performance impact: * • Initial: quality improvement [8.5] • Final: initial + cost rationalisation [7.9] Next steps to be accomplished: * ***** • Major: better integrating the patients to the healthcare processes-offering digital services through the site of the hospital [8.3] • Major: developing a clinical governance support system (extracting value from the digital data) [8.5] • Major: continuing the development of the EMR (focus on the neurology and oncology departments) [8.0]</cell><cell>• One by one we make all of them happy! Seriously: a focus on each department-combined with a good overall design-allows us to understand and better meet the demands from the business lines -CIO • We are simply doing what we have done within each department. But on a bigger scale. Information has to be available everywhere if you want to truly achieve the relative benefits -CEO • Standardisation? it was a bloodbath, but it was worth it -CIO • The end results? Better treatment, quicker diagnoses, and brand new research fields ready on the shelf waiting for us -Physician • The risk is to create a set of fantastic islands with kilometres of sea separating them -CMO • The unique rejection issues are encountered once you try to extend the "tailored" feature to other departments. In these cases, some revisions are necessary -CIO</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• Organisational level: temporal</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>differentiation and emergent</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>integration</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Table 11 . Main findings of the interviews performed on H9</head><label>11</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Input</cell><cell cols="2">Process</cell><cell>Output</cell><cell>Representative informants quotes</cell></row><row><cell>Digital solution: Electronic Medical Record (IPI3) Stimuli to the adoption of the digital solution: * • Improving the effectiveness of the treatments [9.1] • Reducing the inefficiencies in clinical data management [8.7] • External pressures (EHR integration) [7.3] Problems during the adoption phase: * ** • Major: diffused pressures to realise the EMR as soon as possible (necessities of data-sharing among physicians) [9.1] • Major: engagement by the whole organisation (both the creation as well as the maintenance during the adoption) [8.2] • Major: managing the change management process (especially its initial communication) [10.0]</cell><cell cols="2">Development phases and impact on exploration and exploitation: *** • Process integration in the diagnostic area of emergency department [EI | II] • Focus on the digitalisation of clinical dossier management [EX | RI], starting by the digitally-based integration of the emergency department and radiology [EI | RI] • Integration of the processes of the laboratory and exploration of new treatments/diagnoses [EX | RI] • Macro integration of the inter-departmental processes related to out-patient management [EI | RI] • Implementation of a set of projects to (i) fully explore the benefits of the shared data [EX | II] and (ii) extend the new treatments/diagnoses to the rest of H14 [EI | II] Approaches to manage the exploration-exploitation paradox: **** • Departmental level: digitally-based process integration • Organisational level: domain differentiation, heuristic-based</cell><cell>Challenges/issues: * • Financial exposure (resolution: cost compression with hardware virtualisation) [9.3] • Maintaining engagement during the change management process (resolution: mixture of eLearning and Face-to-Face training) [8.6] Performance impact: * • Initial: -[6.7] • Final: cost rationalisation and quality improvement [8.2] Next steps to be accomplished: * ***** • Major: better integrating the patients to the health care processes-offering digital services through the site [7.8] • Major: developing a set of governance dashboards (extracting value from the digital data) for the management of the HCO [8.2] • Major: continuing the development of the EMR (focus on ADT management, and neurology process integration) [8.6]</cell><cell>• I was tired of hearing from every physician I meet how "it would be great to have an EMR". I knew it! […] But now we have these conditions. I thought: let's shut them up once and for all! -CIO • Engagement is everything in such projects; and everything has to start from the board -CEO • With these kinds of solutions you simply cannot adopt a "big-bang" go-live -CIO • Let me tell you one thing: being an IRCCS doesn't simplify things... -CIO • If you want to train more than 2,000 employees, eLearning is a mandatory road… but we've combined with eLearning a smart, face-to-face "train-the-trainer" approach -CEO • When I looked at the budget and the investment plan I threw my hands up in despair [laugh] -CFO • We had to run like a sprinter, but now we have a full EMR -CEO • The entire hospital was breathing down my neck, urging me to end the project as soon as possible -CIO • We didn't have many more alternatives to improve our service to patients. EMR</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>•</cell><cell>integration</cell><cell></cell><cell>was simply unavoidable…. -CMO</cell></row></table><note><p>F</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table 13 . Main findings of the interviews performed on H3</head><label>13</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Input</cell><cell>Process</cell><cell>Output</cell><cell>Representative informants quotes</cell></row><row><cell>Digital solution: telemedicine service</cell><cell>Development phases and impact on</cell><cell>Challenges/issues: *</cell><cell>• Then we involved the CIO, but everything</cell></row><row><cell>(EPI2) Stimuli to the adoption of the digital solution: * • Improving the effectiveness of the treatments offered to chronic patients [8.6] • Improving the efficiency in providing treatment to chronic patients [8.9] • Decentralising the healthcare service [7.6] • Providing a healthcare service in the territory under the responsibility of H10 (which is an ASL, see Table 1) [8.0] Problems during the adoption phase: * ** • Major: installation of the necessary hardware and software at the homes of the chronic patients [9.0] • Major: managing privacy and security issues [10.0] • Minor: training to the family of the chronic patients [8.3]</cell><cell>exploration and exploitation: *** • Selection of the target chronic patients and installation of the necessary hardware/software to deliver the telemedicine service [EX | RI] • Progressive digitalisation of the processes to fully deliver the telemedicine service [EI | II] • Improvement of the solution based on the evidences collected by the sensors installed in patient's house [EX | II] • Development of new treatments exploiting the integration of the assets installed in patient's house with the one in the facilities of H10 [EI | RI] Approaches to manage the exploration-exploitation paradox: **** • Departmental level: digitally-based process integration • Organisational level: organisational diff. (pilot unit vs. the rest of H10) • Regional level: digitally-based</cell><cell>• Privacy and security concerns (due to the presence of an external actor in the system) [9.8] • Organisation of the home visits [8.9] • Maintenance of the solution [7.6] Performance impact: * • Initial: decentralising the healthcare services and augmenting the quality of the treatment (less mortality rate) [9.6] • Final: initial + decreasing of the cost of the treatment [8.6] Next steps to be accomplished: * ***** • Minor: extending the pilot group of chronic patients treated via telemedicine [9.2] • Major: starting a new telemedicine project on another typology of chronic patients [8.1] • Major: developing a clinical governance support system (extract value from the digital data) [7.8] • Minor: virtualising hardware and software (cost compression) [7.1] •</cell><cell>started here -Physician • Most of the hindrances have a privacy label, it's true. However, the competences of the involved stakeholders are equally critical -Physician • I had a hard row to hoe with this project, but looking back… Wow! What a result -CIO • Once you have data on the pathology you can better organise home visits, exams, etc., and, thus, you also decrease the overall costs of the treatment. And we are talking about a chronic disease! -CMO • Whit this project we have saved 12 beds in intensive care -CMO • Our plan is to double the pilot group by the end of 2012 -CEO • Often these projects remain nice experimentation. We have overcome this step. The solution is here to stay -CIO • The benefits of internal integration soon reach their potential, and the Lombard EHR is not developed enough to further improve our services -CIO • ICT automates significant parts of hospital processes, and brings completely new services that permanently change the way healthcare is provided -CEO</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>process integration</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>F</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>Table 14 . Main findings of the interviews performed on H10</head><label>14</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Input</cell><cell>Process</cell><cell>Output</cell><cell>Representative informants quotes</cell></row><row><cell>Digital solution: mobile health services for patients (EPI1) Stimuli to the adoption of the digital solution: * • Better connecting to the patients [8.2] • Reducing the inefficiencies in clinical data management [7.8] • Improving the effectiveness of the healthcare service (both the core as well as the support activities) [8.8] Problems during the adoption phase: * ** • Major: managing privacy and security issues [9.2] • Major: integration of the mobile solution in the existing workflows (partial workflow redesign) [8.7] • Minor: technical problems in the interaction of the solution with information systems of H12 [7.9]</cell><cell>Development phases and impact on exploration and exploitation: *** • Preliminary digitalisation of the basic processes characterising the interaction with the patients [EI | II] • Development of a mobile app for allowing patients to book exams, and pilot over a niche of technology-friendly patients (less than 35 years old) [EX | RI] • Progressive improvement of the mobile app with other functionalities (e.g. allowing patients to access their data and review reports) [EI | II] • Development of a marketing campaign to extend the solutions to all the patients of H12, and training regarding how to use the solutions effectively [EI | RI] Approaches to manage the exploration-exploitation paradox: **** • Departmental level: digitally-based process integration • Organisational level: digitally -based process integration • Regional level: digitally -based process integration</cell><cell>Challenges/issues: * • Privacy and security concerns (due to the presence of an external actor in the system) [8.8] • Compliance to a set of regional rules that are under development [8.4] • Extension of the solution to all the patients of H12 [9.2] Performance impact: * • Initial: decreasing the cost of the healthcare service [8.9] • Final: initial + decentralising the healthcare services and augmenting the proximity to the patients [8.8] Next steps to be accomplished: * ***** • Major: exploration of further ways to better integrate with the patients and/or general physicians [9.2] • Major: developing a clinical governance support system (extract value from the digital data) [10.0] • Major: developing a set of governance dashboards (extracting value from the digital data) for the management of H12 [9.8] •</cell><cell>• Everything around health care is changing. People use social networks and instant messaging instead of emails. Patients want to access their data on the run, with their mobile phones. We felt the necessity to adapt to this brand new digital world out there. Health IT is not simply a matter of EMR… -CIO • Patients do not care about EMR or EHR. Patients do not know what these acronyms mean. Patients want Apps. Patients are increasingly used to live online, and want-for instance-to visualise a report on their smartphones -CEO • "Customer experience" and "virtual workspace" are the new cornerstones in healthcare -CIO • These solutions are tremendously effective in engaging the patients and in getting close to them. -CMO • The EHR will be an incredible tool once completed. Will… Note the tense. We need to offer better services to our patients now. We simply cannot afford to go at a snail's pace -CEO • The mobile app has contributed not only to cut costs-as [the CFO] can confirm-, but also-and especially-in increasing our proximity to the patients -CMO • For many patients the app is already a "must have" -CEO</cell></row></table><note><p>F</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>Table 15 . Main findings of the interviews performed on H12</head><label>15</label><figDesc>We have tons of unused clinical data. I don't believe that we have digitalised them only to accomplish our EMR. We can make use of them to improve our decisions, and this project simply starts doing it -CEO • We thought that by focusing on a functional area we could have a niche in which to make things feasible and, at the same time, provide comprehensive benefits to all H8 -CIO • In my view this is not analytics. Not yet.For the moment we have "just" performed some statistical analyses, and some knowledge extrapolation. The next step is to bring a true active form of decision-support -CIO • We are thinking to a telemedicine solution for some of our cardio-vascular patients -CMO • Solutions like this one tremendously improve the appropriateness of our treatments. It's not my opinion. Now we have plenty of data supporting my claim -CEO • To be honest it took more than I thought in order to see the first benefits -CIO</figDesc><table><row><cell>Input</cell><cell>Process</cell><cell>Output</cell><cell>Representative informants quotes</cell></row><row><cell>Digital solution: clinical governance tools (AN2) Stimuli to the adoption of the digital solution: * • Extracting value from the digitalised</cell><cell>Development phases and impact on exploration and exploitation: *** • Selection of "pneumonia diagnosis" as a pilot functional area, and data mining on historical data to create 12 different pneumonia cases with the</cell><cell>Challenges/issues: * • Switching from passive to active decision support [7.8] • Formalisation and standardisation of the new knowledge created [8.2]</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>clinical documents [9.6] • Actively supporting clinical decision-making [7.8] • Starting an experimentation in the promising field of analytics [8.0] Problems during the adoption phase: * ** • Major: -• Minor: comparisons between</cell><cell>relative antecedents [EX | DI] • Knowledge systematisation with the progressive integration of data from other departments [EI | II] • Development of an active form of support to decision making using the developed knowledge [EX | RI] • Extension to the new pneumonia diagnosis to the rest of H8 [EI | RI]</cell><cell>Performance impact: * • Initial: -[7.6] • Final: improvement of the appropriateness and waste reduction during the treatment [8.8] Next steps to be accomplished: * ***** • Minor: extensions to another functional area (pulmonary</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>documents with a different nature [7.2] • Minor: initial collaboration between clinicians and digital experts [9.0] • Minor: integration of the solution into the workflows relative to the pneumonia diagnosis [7.7]</cell><cell>Approaches to manage the exploration-exploitation paradox: **** • Departmental level: domain differentiation (pneumonia diagnoses and other diagnoses) and temporal differentiation, both facilitated by digital solutions • Organisational level: initially organisational differentiation; then</cell><cell>embolism) [7.8] • Major: experiment a telemedicine project for chronic cardiovascular patients [7.8] • Major: developing a set of governance dashboards (extracting value from the digital data) for the management of H8 [9.2]</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>heuristic-based integration</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>F</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><p>•</p>•</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head>Table 16 . Main findings of the interviews performed on H8 Managing</head><label>16</label><figDesc>the Exploration-Exploitation Paradox in Healthcare: Three Complementary Paths to Leverage on Digital Transformation Since the very beginning, one has to be aware that the solution is part of a larger system that will be developed in the next years -CIO • The Extract-Transform-Load process is always complex-especially in a IRCCS. I knew it. What I didn't know was that it will cost so much -CIO • The decision-support is far away more effective when data is available from multiple sources -Physician • Obviously you cannot expect a "magic" effect, but only good help. Digital technologies will never replace physicians. Digital will simplify physicians' lives, allowing them to focus on what matters: care -Physician • The time needed for collecting, analysing and acting on the data must be reduced. Not only in drug prescription.</figDesc><table><row><cell>eCompanion</cell></row></table><note><p><p>•</p>•</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head>Table 17 . Main findings of the interviews performed on H11</head><label>17</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Input</head><p>* Each statement in the table has been rated on a 10 points Likert scale in order to measure its importance (0 = not important; 10 highly important); the number in the squared brackets indicates the average importance provided by the informant in the last round of interviews; the table presents only the statements that have achieved an average importance rate higher than 7.0 ** According the CIO, the problems indicated with "Major" risked to compromise the adoption; the problems indicated with "Minor" do not constituted great threats from this viewpoint *** For each phase, the CIO has indicated its main impact (ER = exploratory; EI = exploitatory) and its grade of innovativeness (RI = radical; II = incremental; DI = disruptive) **** Only the main approaches adopted to ambidextrously balance exploratory and exploitatory activities are reported in the table; temporal differentiation means that the hospital switches between exploration and exploitation over time; domain differentiation means that each unit specialises in exploratory or exploitatory activities in particular domain while the hospital balances these activities across domains; organisational differentiation means that exploration and exploitation occur simultaneously but are situated within distinct hospital units <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Lavie et al., 2010)</ref>; heuristic-based integration means that exploration and exploitation are integrated through the usage of a portfolio of deliberately small set of articulated and often informal rules-of-thumb <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Eisenhardt et al., 2010)</ref> ***** According the CIO, the next steps indicated with "Major" had to be accomplished as soon as possible; the ones indicated with "Minor" were subject to the presence of further budgets for digital transformation Table <ref type="table">18</ref>. Main findings of the interviews performed on H13</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Adler-Milstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Everson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-Y</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">EHR adoption and hospital performance: time-related effects</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1751" to="1771" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research Commentary-The Digital Transformation of Health care: Current Status and the Road Ahead</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Agarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Desroches</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Systems Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="796" to="809" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Survival of the project: A case study of ICT innovation in health care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Andreassen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kjekshus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tjora</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Science &amp; Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="62" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploitation-Exploration Tensions and Organizational Ambidexterity: Managing Paradoxes of Innovation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Andriopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organization Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="696" to="717" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping innovation dynamics in the Internet of Things domain: Evidence from patent analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ardito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>D'adda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Messeni Petruzzelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technological Forecasting and Social Change</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigating the effects of ICT on innovation and performance of European hospitals: an exploratory study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Arvanitis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Loukis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The European Journal of Health Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="418" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reflections on the 2013 Decade Award</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Benner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Tushman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Exploitation, Exploration, and Process Management: The Productivity Dilemma Revisited&quot; Ten Years Later</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academy of Management Review</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="497" to="514" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Clarifying the Distinctive Contribution of Ambidexterity to the Field of Organization Studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Birkinshaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Academy of Management Perspectives</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="287" to="298" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring the cost impact of hospital information systems: 1987-1994</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Borzekowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Health Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="938" to="949" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Let Chaos Reign, Then Rein in Chaos-Repeatedly: Managing Strategic Dynamics for Corporate Longevity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Burgelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Grove</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Strategic Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="965" to="979" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Innovator&apos;s Prescription: A Disruptive Solution for Health Care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Christensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Grossman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Davenport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Competing on Analytics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>HBS Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Innovation in hospitals: a survey of the literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Djellal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gallouj</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The European Journal of Health Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information Technology and Business-Level Strategy: Toward an Integrated Theoretical Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Drnevich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Croson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MIS Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="483" to="509" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building Theories from Case Study Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Eisenhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="532" to="550" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microfoundations of Performance: Balancing Efficiency and Flexibility in Dynamic Environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Eisenhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Furr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bingham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organization Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1263" to="1273" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">eHealth Action Plan 2012-2020 -Innovative healthcare for the 21st century</title>
		<ptr target="https://ec.europa.eu/digital-single-market/en/news/ehealth-action-plan-2012-2020-innovative-healthcare-21st-century" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-07">2012. July 2017</date>
			<publisher>European Commission</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://ec.europa.eu/digital-single-market/en/blog/future-healthcare-digital" />
		<title level="m">Health inequalities and eHealth</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>European Commission</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014-07">2014. July 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A critical look at technological innovation typology and innovativeness terminology: a literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Calantone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Product Innovation Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="110" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Academics as Effective Orchestrators of Interorganizational Change and Development: The Experience of Italian Observatories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gastaldi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Corso</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Research in Organizational Change and Development</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Woodman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Pasmore</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Shani</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Emerald</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance Improvement in Hospitals: Leveraging on Knowledge Asset Dynamics through the Introduction of an Electronic Medical Record</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gastaldi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Lettieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Corso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Masella</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Measuring Business Excellence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Antecedents, Consequences, and Mediating Role of Organizational Ambidexterity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Birkinshaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Paradoxes and the Nature of Ambidexterity in IT Transformation Programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Gregory</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Keil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Muntermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mähring</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Systems Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IT-Enabled Coordination for Ambidextrous Interorganizational Relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Im</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Systems Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72" to="92" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduction and commentary for special issue on health information technology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kaushal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Blumenthal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Service Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="319" to="324" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Meeting patient expectations: Healthcare professionals and service reengineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Laing</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Health Service Management Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="172" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Meaningful Use of Electronic Health Records and Medicare Expenditures: Evidence from a Panel Data Analysis of U.S. Health Care Markets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lammers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mclaughlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Service Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2016. 2010-2013</date>
			<publisher>in Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploration and Exploitation Within and Across Organizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lavie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Stettner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Tushman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Annals</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="153" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Examination of the Antecedents and Consequences of Organizational IT Innovation in Hospitals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Leidner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Preston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Strategic Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="170" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Elucidating the Role of IT/IS Assessment and Resource Allocation in IT/IS Performance in Hospitals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C K</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information and Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="104" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploration and Exploitation in Organizational Learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>March</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organization Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The journey through grief: insights from a qualitative study of electronic health record implementation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mcalearney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hefner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sieck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Huerta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Service Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="462" to="488" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Monitoring technology and firm boundaries: physicianhospital integration and technology utilization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mccullogh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Snir</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Health Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="467" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Balancing knowledge exploration and exploitation within and across the technological and geographical domains</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Messeni Petruzzelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Knowledge Management Research &amp; Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Health at a Glance: Europe 2016 -State of Health in the EU Cycle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Oecd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.oecd.org/health/health-systems/health-at-a-glance-europe-23056088.htm" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-07">2016. July 2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">26</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>O'reilly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Iii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Tushman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Organizational Ambidexterity: Past, Present, and Future</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academy of Management Perspectives</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="324" to="338" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Patton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Qualitative Research and Evaluation Methods, 3rd Ed</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Sage, Thousand Oaks</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thriving in the New: Implication of Exploration on Organizational Longevity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Piao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1529" to="1554" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Strategy that Will Fix Health Care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Porter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Harvard Business Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Organizational Ambidexterity: Balancing Exploitation and Exploration for Sustained Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Raisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Birkinshaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Probst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tushman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organization Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="685" to="695" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Typology for Aligning Organizational Ambidexterity&apos;s Conceptualizations, Antecedents, and Outcomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Simsek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Heavey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Veiga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Souder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Management Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="864" to="894" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Organizational Ambidexterity: Towards a Multilevel Understanding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Simsek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Management Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="597" to="624" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward a Theory of Paradox: A Dynamic Equilibrium Model of Organizing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="381" to="403" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hospitals as innovators in the health-care systems: a literature review and research agenda</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Thune</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mina</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1545" to="1557" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Yin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Case Study Research: Design and Methods</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Sage, Thousand Oaks</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of the digital age on transforming healthcare</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Healthcare Information Management Systems: Cases, Strategies, and Solutions</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Weaver</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ball</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kiel</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer International Publishing</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>fourth edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">World Economic Forum White Paper Digital Transformation of Industries: Healthcare Industry</title>
		<ptr target="http://reports.weforum.org/digital-transformation/wp-content/blogs.dir/94/mp/files/pages/files/wef-dti-healthcarewhitepaper-final-january-2016.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Economic Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">31</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016-07">2016. July 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
