<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">International Journal of Social Science And Human Research</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anggraeni</forename><surname>Agustin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master of Education Administration Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70123</postCode>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Metroyadi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master of Education Administration Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70123</postCode>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Karyono</forename><forename type="middle">Ibnu</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master of Education Administration Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lambung Mangkurat University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70123</postCode>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">International Journal of Social Science And Human Research</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">(print): 2644-0679</idno>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v6-i6-30</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T00:42+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>academic supervision</term>
					<term>principal leadership</term>
					<term>teacher pedagogical competence</term>
					<term>teacher teaching performance</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This study aims to analyze the influence of academic supervision, principal leadership and teacher pedagogical competence on teaching performance. This study uses regression research with a quantitative approach which is formulated in the path analysis model. The research population consisted of 415 teachers from 32 schools and 203 respondents were taken as the research sample. Data collection was carried out using instruments consisting of academic supervision (26 items), principal leadership (44 items), teacher pedagogical competence (68 items), teaching performance (28 items) which have been tested for validity and reliability. Then, the research data were analyzed using path analysis. The results showed that academic supervision on performance, principal leadership on teaching performance, teacher pedagogic competence on teaching performance, academic supervision on teacher pedagogic competence, principal leadership on teacher pedagogic competence, academic supervision on teaching performance through teacher pedagogic competence and head leadership schools on teaching performance through teacher pedagogic competence.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>The development of science and technology as well as the mobility of society requires teachers to continue to grow and develop in increasing their potential so that they can carry out their functions professionally. A professional teacher means having the ability as an expert in the field of education and teaching, having a sense of responsibility so that he is aware of his commitment and concern for his duties, and lives up to his duties as a life career that upholds the code of ethics for teacher positions. Education is a conscious effort that is deliberately planned to achieve a predetermined goal. Education aims to improve the quality of human resources. One of the efforts to improve the quality of human resources is through the learning process in schools <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Suriansyah, 2014)</ref>. The development of science and technology as well as the mobility of society cause teachers to continuously grow and develop in increasing their potential in order to perform their functions professionally. Professional teachers mean having the ability as experts in the field of educating and teaching, having a sense of responsibility so as to realize their commitment and concern for their duties, and living their duties as a life career that upholds the code of ethics for the position of teacher <ref type="bibr">(Sahertian, 2010:2)</ref>. To improve the quality of educational resources, teachers are a component of human resources that must be built and developed continuously.</p><p>In carrying out its function to be a professional teacher, there are several things that hinder teachers including; school as a cultural center has a duty to select the influence of factors that affect students. Real work, in the form of ideas, ideas, behavior patterns, habits produced by schools to achieve educational goals. The importance of teacher awareness in achieving educational goals is needed to develop students' creative potential and all other efforts to develop school culture. Then, challenges by the development of the times require teachers to continue to improve their abilities in educating students so that they are in line with the educational principles proclaimed by Ki Hajar Dewantara, namely the nature of nature and the nature of the times. The school atmosphere that supports teacher creativity, safety and comfort needs to be realized by the teacher to create good relationships so that teaching and learning situations can provide encouragement or motivation to learn for students. In addition, the demands of the globalization era are marked by free competition, changes in people's mindsets due to the influence of technology and communication, so teachers must be able to adapt to these changes by the norms and values that apply so that they can run well. achieve educational success <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Kuntoro, 2010)</ref>. The success of education requires the optimal role and performance of teachers, to be able to produce human resources that can to compete in the global era. Teacher performance in learning is a major factor in the success of educational goals. The quality of education obtained from quality learning is a reflection of school achievements in preparing human resources to face global challenges in education. The level of the quality of education is much influenced by the quality of the learning process carried out by the teacher, because the teacher directly provides guidance and assistance to students to achieve educational goals. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Habibi et al. (2018)</ref> found that the influence of academic supervision on teacher work motivation is positive and significant. Then <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kusrini et al. (2018)</ref> reporting that there is an influence of supervisor academic supervision on teacher work motivation. The importance of the quality of teacher performance is required to always develop and improve their performance in carrying out their duties as educators which will have a direct or indirect impact the progress of Indonesian education (Fitroliana, Ahmad Suriansyah, 2022; Solekah, Solekah, Sulaiman, 2022; Suratman, Wahyu, 2022; Wais Alkarni, Sulaiman, 2022). Teachers are the forefront in realizing quality education. Teachers deal directly with students in the classroom through the teaching and learning process. It is in the hands of the teacher that quality students will be produced, both academically, skilled, emotionally and morally and emotionally mature. teaching components used in the teaching and learning process which are the responsibility of qualified students if the teacher shows good performance (Martini, Karyono Ibnu Ahmad, 2022).</p><p>The principal has responsibility for his or her leadership and has the authority to carry out a coaching and supervision activity. (Fitroliana, Ahmad Suriansyah, 2022; Haji Munirah, Aslamiah, 2022; Silfiati, Aslamiah, 2022). The quality of education and graduates is often seen as depending on the role of the teacher in managing the teaching used in the teaching and learning process for which he is responsible. Learning is a process of interaction between students and teachers and learning resources in a learning environment, learning must be student-centered because the learning subjects are students <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Rusman, 2010)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. METHODOLOGY</head><p>This study uses a quantitative approach. This study aims to describe and analyze the direct and direct relationship between variables: academic supervision on performance, principal leadership on teaching performance, teacher pedagogic competence on teaching performance, academic supervision on teacher pedagogic competence, school principal leadership on teacher pedagogic competence, academic supervision on teaching performance. through teacher pedagogic competence and principal leadership on teaching performance through teacher pedagogic competence. The research population consisted of 415 teachers from 32 schools and 203 respondents were taken as the research sample by proportional random sampling. Data was collected using a questionnaire consisting of academic supervision (assessing learning outcomes, finding learning problems that impede student achievement, improving learning situations), school principal leadership (personality, knowledge, understanding of vision and mission, ability to make decisions, ability to communicate). , teacher pedagogical competence (mastering student characteristics, mastering learning theory and educational learning principles, curriculum development, educational learning activities, developing student potential, communication with students, assessment and evaluation) and teaching performance (quality of work, quantity, timeliness, influenceiveness, independence)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head><p>Based on the results of data analysis and using path analysis, direct and indirect relationship coefficients were found. as described below:  There is an indirect positive influence of academic supervision on teacher teaching performance through teacher pedagogical competence 0.517 0.277</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">H 7</formula><p>There is an indirect positive influence of the principal's leadership on teacher teaching performance through teacher pedagogical competence 0.146 0.082</p><p>The results of the path analysis as in table 1 are a summary of the decisions H₁, H₂, H₃, H₄, H₅ and H₆ with a significance value criterion of less than 0.05; thus, the hypothesis is accepted. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref> results of the hypothesis H₆ and H₇ with the provision that if the direct correlation coefficient is smaller than the indirect correlation coefficient, then the hypothesis is accepted. Based on the results of the analysis in table 2 and table 3 above, this study found an influence between variables which can be explained as follows.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. The Direct Influence of Academic Supervision on Teacher Teaching Performance</head><p>Based on the results of path analysis between academic supervision and teacher teaching performance, a path coefficient of 0.517 is obtained with a t-count of 9.616 and a significance of 0.000 so that the significance value is less than 0.05. This shows the results that academic supervision has a direct positive and significant influence on the teaching performance of public elementary school teachers in Martapura District, Banjar Regency. assess teacher teaching performance in managing the teaching and learning process. Academic supervision has a good impact on teacher teaching performance.</p><p>This research is also in line with the theory of Mukhtar &amp; Iskandar (2013) that academic supervision is supervision that can improve the quality of learning and aims to foster teachers in carrying out their duties professionally. The research results of Wieyanthi, Wahyu &amp; Suhaimi (2022). This research supports previous research conducted by Hidayah, M. Saleh, S. (2022), based on the results of data analysis there is a significant influence between academic supervision on teacher performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Direct Influence of Principal Leadership on Teacher Teaching Performance</head><p>Based on the results of the path analysis between the principal's leadership on teacher teaching performance, a path coefficient value of 0.146 is obtained with a t-count of 3.263 and a significance of 0.001 so that the significance value is less than 0.05. This shows the results that the principal's leadership has a direct positive and significant influence on teacher teaching performance. Sutanto argues (2016) that school principals as learning leaders are leadership that emphasizes components related to learning, including curriculum, learning processes, assessments, teacher development, excellent service in learning and building learning communities in schools. Regarding excellent service in learning, it refers to how to show optimal teacher teaching performance. Another opinion that is in line with the results of this study was put forward by Fauza (2010) that one of the factors that influence teacher performance is the leadership of the school principal. According to various sources that the researchers studied, there was a positive influence between the leadership of the school principal and teacher performance. Efi Eka Sari, et al (2021) stated that the principal through the influence of the principal's leadership can improve teacher performance. This is in line with research conducted by Hidayati (2023) which states that the leadership of the school principal directly has a direct influence on teacher performance. and a significant relationship with teacher performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. The Direct Influence of Teacher Pedagogic Competence on Teacher Teaching Performance</head><p>Based on the results of the path analysis between the principal's leadership on teacher teaching performance, the path coefficient value is 0.325 with t count 6.559 and a significance of 0.000 so that the significance value is less than 0.05. This shows the results that the teacher's pedagogical competence has a direct positive and significant influence on the teacher's teaching performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Influence of Academic Supervision, Principal Leadership, and Teacher Pedagogic Competence on Teaching Performance of Public Elementary School Teachers in Martapura District, Banjar Regency</head><p>According to <ref type="bibr">Lensiana (2009)</ref>, the application of competence possessed by teachers is one of the factors that influence the achievement of learning objectives. Teacher pedagogical competence is the teacher's ability to manage learning according to student characteristics. Understanding the characteristics of elementary school students is one of the factors that influence the success of learning objectives at the elementary school level. Therefore, the assignment of teacher pedagogic competence is very important for teacher teaching performance. The results of this study are supported by research conducted by Aprianti (2022) which states that there is a positive and significant relationship between pedagogical competence and teacher performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. The direct influence of Academic Supervision on Teacher Pedagogic Competence</head><p>Based on the results of the path analysis between the school principal's academic supervision of the teacher's pedagogic competence, a path coefficient value of 0.653 was obtained with a t-count of 10.647 and a significance of 0.000 so that the significance value was less than 0.05. This shows the results that the principal's academic supervision has a direct positive and significant influence on the teacher's pedagogical competence. The results showed that there was a positive influence on the implementation of the principal's supervision on pedagogic competence, so that the better the implementation of the principal's supervision, the teacher's pedagogical competence would also increase which would later affect the teaching performance of teachers in schools. implementation of teaching and learning activities. Carrying out regular supervision activities by the Principal will have a good impact on teacher pedagogic competence, where the Principal can monitor the progress of each teacher through the results of supervision, after which evaluation and follow-up can be carried out to correct mistakes or develop teacher competence even better . The quality of a good school also depends on the quality of good teacher competence. Maccording to Noorjani, et al (2022) concluded that academic supervision can improve teacher pedagogical competence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. The Direct Influence of Principal Leadership on Teacher Pedagogic Competence</head><p>Based on the results of the path analysis between the principal's leadership and the teacher's pedagogic competence, a path coefficient value of 0.252 is obtained with a t count of 4.105 and a significance of 0.000 so that the significance value is less than 0.05. This shows the results that the principal's academic supervision has a direct positive and significant influence on the teacher's pedagogical competence.</p><p>However the principal is a vital element for the influenceiveness of educational institutions. A good school principal will be dynamic in preparing various kinds of educational programs. In line with the opinion of Suyanto (2013) that school principals should plan various strategies in managing teacher abilities so that they affect teacher competence. Likewise the teacher's ability to guide learning, how to learn, make the right decisions in solving problems, will also support the success of himself, his students and his school. Elvi's research (2011) is in line with the results of this study which explains that principal leadership can influence teacher pedagogical competence</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F. Indirect Influence of Academic Supervision on Teacher Teaching Performance Through Teacher Pedagogic Competence</head><p>The calculation of the value of the indirect influence of the academic supervision variable on teacher teaching performance through pedagogical competence can be seen from the multiplication result of 0.726 x 0.313 = 0.227. This value indicates that the value is positive, meaning that there is an indirect positive influence of academic supervision through teacher pedagogic competence on teacher teaching performance. The results of this study are in line with the opinion of Barnawi &amp; Arifin (2012) that teacher performance does not just happen, but is influenced by certain factors, namely internal and external factors. Research conducted by Indra Prasetyo and C. Sri Hartati (2021) shows that the dependent variable, namely teacher performance, can be influenced by two independent variables, namely the academic supervision of the school principal and the teacher's pedagogical competence, which is equal to 50.2% so that together with the academic supervision of the head school and teacher's pedagogic competence influence teacher's teaching performance. This research is also supported by other studies such as Birhasani, et al (2022) that there is a joint influence between the academic supervision of school principals and teacher pedagogic competence on teacher teaching performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G. Indirect Influence of Principal Leadership on Teacher Teaching Performance through Teacher Pedagogic Competence</head><p>The calculation of the value of the indirect influence of the principal's leadership variable through the teacher's pedagogical competency variable on teacher teaching performance can be seen from the multiplication result of 0.263 x 0.313 = 0.082. This value indicates that the value is positive, meaning that there is an indirect influence of the principal's leadership through the teacher's pedagogical competence on teacher teaching performance.</p><p>The results of this study are supported by the research of Ika Nurmalasari (2018) in his research the results of multiple regression analysis show that teacher performance is influenced by the principal's leadership and teacher pedagogical competence. Based on these findings, the principal's leadership variable and pedagogical competence should be given more attention, because these two variables have a high enough contribution to improving teacher teaching performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Influence of Academic Supervision, Principal Leadership, and Teacher Pedagogic Competence on Teaching Performance of Public Elementary School Teachers in Martapura District, Banjar Regency</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. CONCLUSION</head><p>There is a direct influence of academic supervision on performance, principal leadership on teaching performance, teacher pedagogic competence on teaching performance, academic supervision on teacher pedagogic competence, school principal leadership on teacher pedagogic competence. This study also concludes that there is an indirect influence: academic supervision on teaching performance through teacher pedagogic competence and school principal leadership on teaching performance through teacher pedagogic competence.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Path Analysis Model X 1 , X 2 , Z and Y</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 . Summary of Hypothesis Testing Decisions H 1 H 2 H 3 H 4 H 5 hypothesis</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>0.000</cell><cell>Accepted</cell></row></table><note><p><p>Decision H 1</p>There is a significant positive influence of academic supervision on teacher teaching performance</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>The Influence of Academic Supervision, Principal Leadership, and Teacher Pedagogic Competence on Teaching Performance of Public Elementary School Teachers in Martapura District, Banjar Regency</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>H 2</cell><cell>There is a significant positive influence of the principal's leadership on teacher</cell><cell>0.001</cell><cell>Accepted</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>teaching performance</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H 3</cell><cell>There is a significant positive influence of teacher pedagogic competence on</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>Accepted</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>teacher teaching performance</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H 4</cell><cell>There is a significant positive influence of academic supervision on teacher</cell><cell>0.00 0</cell><cell>Accepted</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>pedagogical competence</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H 5</cell><cell>There is a significant positive relationship between the principal's leadership and</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>Accepted</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>the pedagogical competence of teachers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 . Summary of Hypothesis Testing Decisions H 6 and H 7</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>hypothesis</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Peran Guru Sebagai Model Dalam Pembelajaran Karakter Dan Kebajikan Moral Melalui Pendidikan Jasmani</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Dimyati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.21831/cp.v1i3.238</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.21831/cp.v1i3.238" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Cakrawala Pendidikan</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Principal Transformational Leadership, Work Discipline, and Emotional Intelligence on Teacher Work Performance at State Elementary Schools, North Banjarmasin District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ahmad</forename><surname>Fitroliana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Suriansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-29</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-29" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2223" to="2229" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The effect of Compensation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Habibi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Raharjo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rifa'i</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rusdarti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Pedagogic</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Model of Kyai&apos;s Leadership in Islamic Boarding Schools (Multi-Case Study in Modern Ummul Qura Islamic Boarding School and Ar-Raudhah Amuntai Islamic Boarding School)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Competency</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Haji Munirah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M R</forename><surname>Aslamiah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-93</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-93" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2612" to="2619" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Journal of Educational Development</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kemitraan Sekolah. Workshop Strategi Pengembangan Mutu Sekolah Bagi Kepala Sekolah Dan Pengawas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kuntoro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jurnal Nasional</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kusrini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Suriansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Education</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">-E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Of</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>U</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>the effect of Supervision of Academic Supervisor</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">With Commitment and Work Motivation on Performance of Teachers of the</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Education Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Correlation among Teacher Professionalism, Work Motivation and Work Discipline on Teacher Performance</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.1494160Martini</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-30" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Karyono Ibnu Ahmad</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2230" to="2235" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Model-model Pembelajaran: Mengembangkan Profesionalisme Guru</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rusman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>RajaGrafindo Persada</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Principal Situational Leadership, Teacher Work Climate and Teacher Job Satisfaction with Teacher Performance at SDN in Awayan District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Piet</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sahertian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-101</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-101" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pt</forename><forename type="middle">Rineka</forename><surname>Ciptasilfiati</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Aslamiah</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2667" to="2674" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010. 2022</date>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Konsep Dasar &amp; Teknik Supervisi Pendidikan</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motivation of Achievement as a Medium Variable in the Correlation among Technical Skill, Work Environment and Educational Staff Members Service Quality at Faculty of Teacher Training and Education Lambung Mangkurat University Banjarmasin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Solekah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Solekah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M R</forename><surname>Sulaiman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-64</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-64" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science And Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2389" to="2399" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship between Spiritual Intelligence and Work Motivation with Performance Through Work Discipline of State Vocational High School Teachers in Hulu Sungai Utara Regency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wahyu</forename><surname>Suratman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-43</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-43" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2328" to="2335" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Suriansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Strategi Pembelajaran. Rajawali Pers</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Principal Transformational Leadership, Work Ethic, through Organizational Commitment to the Performance of State Middle School Teachers in Hulu Sungai Tengah District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wais</forename><surname>Alkarni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sulaiman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-50</idno>
		<ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2278" to="2284" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>There is an Open Access article, distributed under the term of the Creative Commons Attribution -Non Commercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0. which permits remixing, adapting and building upon the work for non-commercial use, provided the original work is properly cited</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
