<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Evolution of large males is associated with female-skewed adult sex ratios in amniotes</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Hungarian Ministry of Human Capacities</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">IE160592</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_KqGhaAS">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_VUjajaW">
					<orgName type="full">National Research, Development and Innovation Fund of Hungary</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_7RsH9rZ">
					<orgName type="full">Hungarian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Royal Society Wolfson Merit</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_aR2eMCR #_C6qgARz">
					<orgName type="full">NKFIH</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_j4McKg6">
					<orgName type="full">János Bolyai Scholarship of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Royal Society-CNRS</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Ministry for Innovation and Technology from the source of the National Research, Development and Innovation Fund</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_C6Teftq">
					<orgName type="full">ÉLVONAL</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_ne8UXzN">
					<orgName type="full">Agence Nationale de la Recherche</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">ANR</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_kZxj7aX">
					<orgName type="full">National Research, Development and Innovation Office of Hungary (NKFIH</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">RPF</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">András</forename><surname>Liker</surname></persName>
							<email>aliker@almos.uni-pannon.hu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">MTA-PE Evolutionary Ecology Research Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pannonia</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Pf. 1158</addrLine>
									<postCode>H-8210</postCode>
									<settlement>Veszprém</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Natural Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Behavioral Ecology Research Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pannonia</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Pf. 1158</addrLine>
									<postCode>H-8210</postCode>
									<settlement>Veszprém</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Veronika</forename><surname>Bókony</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Plant Protection Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Centre for Agricultural Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Lendület Evolutionary Ecology Research Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eötvös Loránd Research Network</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Herman Ottó u. 15</addrLine>
									<postCode>H-1022</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ivett</forename><surname>Pipoly</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">MTA-PE Evolutionary Ecology Research Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pannonia</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Pf. 1158</addrLine>
									<postCode>H-8210</postCode>
									<settlement>Veszprém</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jean-Francois</forename><surname>Lemaitre</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab1">Laboratoire de Biométrie et Biologie Évolutive</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab2">UMR 5558</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Lyon 1</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F- 69622</postCode>
									<settlement>Villeurbanne</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jean-Michel</forename><surname>Gaillard</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab1">Laboratoire de Biométrie et Biologie Évolutive</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab2">UMR 5558</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Lyon 1</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F- 69622</postCode>
									<settlement>Villeurbanne</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tamás</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Milner Centre for Evolution</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Biology and Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bath</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>BA2 7AY</postCode>
									<settlement>Bath</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Evolutionary Zoology and Human Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Debrecen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>H-4032</postCode>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Freckleton</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Animal and Plant Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Sheffield</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Alfred Denny Building Western Bank</addrLine>
									<postCode>S10 2TN</postCode>
									<settlement>Sheffield</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">MTA-PE Evolutionary Ecology Research Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pannonia</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Pf. 1158.</addrLine>
									<postCode>H-8210</postCode>
									<settlement>Veszprém</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Evolution of large males is associated with female-skewed adult sex ratios in amniotes</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/evo.14273</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T21:19+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>sexual selection</term>
					<term>mating competition</term>
					<term>mating opportunity</term>
					<term>sex-biased mortality</term>
					<term>comparative method * Pagel&apos;s lambda statistically different from 0</term>
					<term>⧺ lambda statistically different from 1</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Body size often differs between the sexes (leading to sexual size dimorphism, SSD), as a consequence of differential responses by males and females to selection pressures. Adult sex ratio (the proportion of males in the adult population, ASR) should influence SSD because ASR relates to both the number of competitors and available mates, which shape the intensity of mating competition and thereby promotes SSD evolution. However, whether ASR correlates with SSD variation among species has not been yet tested across a broad range of taxa. Using phylogenetic comparative analyses of 462 amniotes (i.e. reptiles, birds and mammals), we fill this knowledge gap by showing that male bias in SSD increases with increasingly female-biased ASRs in both mammals and birds. This relationship is not explained by the higher mortality of the larger sex because SSD is not associated with sex differences in either juvenile or adult mortality. Phylogenetic path analysis indicates that higher mortality in one sex leads to skewed ASR, which in turn may generate selection for SSD biased towards the rare sex. Taken together, our findings provide evidence that skewed ASRs in amniote populations can result in the rarer sex evolving large size to capitalize on enhanced mating opportunities.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Sexual size dimorphism (SSD, measured as the size of males relative to females) is widespread in nature and is one of the most conspicuous phenotypic difference between the sexes <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Darwin 1871;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Andersson 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Fairbairn et al. 2007)</ref>. It is the consequence of different optimal body size for the sexes resulting from opposing selection forces (some of which may influence only one of the sexes) that equilibrate differently in males and females <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Blanckenhorn 2005)</ref>.</p><p>A large volume of research has focused on how sex-specific behavior (e.g. mating system, parental care), ecological processes (e.g. abundance and quality of resources), and life history traits (e.g. fecundity in indeterminate growers) can generate size differences between the sexes <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Andersson 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Blanckenhorn 2005</ref>). These studies have concluded that sexual selection is often a major driver of SSD evolution by either intra-sexual competition for access to mates or inter-sexual mate choice, although other evolutionary mechanisms (e.g. fertility selection and competition for resources) may also be important <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Jehl and Murray 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Andersson 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Blanckenhorn 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Fairbairn et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Clutton-Brock 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Strong sexual selection for large body size in one sex is particularly likely in species where that sex competes for mates by physical contests or endurance rivalry, as observed in several vertebrate taxa (e.g. reptiles, birds, and mammals; <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Jehl and Murray 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Andersson 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Cox et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b100">Székely et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Clutton-Brock 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Adult sex ratio (ASR), best measured as the proportion of males in the adult population <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Ancona et al. 2017</ref>) is a key demographic property of populations that influences both the number of competitors for mates and the number of mates available to an individual <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">(Murray 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr">Székely et al. 2014b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Jennions and Fromhage 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b93">Schacht et al. 2017)</ref>. For example, a male-skewed ASR means potentially more competitors and fewer available partners for males than for females. An increasing number of studies show that ASR covaries with several reproductive traits such as mating system, parental sex roles, divorce rate, extrapair mating and cooperative breeding both in non-human animals and humans <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Liker et al. 2013</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Liker et al. , 2014;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b94">Schacht et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Kappeler 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Komdeur et al. 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Eberhart-Phillips et al. 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Grant and Grant 2019)</ref>. However, whether and how ASR is related to the evolution of SSD is still poorly understood.</p><p>Theories suggest that ASR can drive the evolution of SSD in at least two ways. First, the intensity of sexual competition may increase with the number of competitors. <ref type="bibr">As Darwin wrote (1871, p. 217)</ref>: "That some relation exists between polygamy and development of secondary sexual characters, appears nearly certain; and this supports the view that a numerical preponderance of males would be eminently favourable to the action of sexual selection". According to his idea, highly skewed ASRs may intensify selection for competitive traits such as weapons and large body size in the more abundant sex. Thus this 'mating competition hypothesis' predicts that the extent of male-bias in SSD should increase with the degree of male skew in the ASR. Later work refined <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Darwin's (1871)</ref> original idea by suggesting that the operational sex ratio (OSR, the number of sexually active males per receptive female at a given time) rather than the ASR determines the intensity of mating competition in a population <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Emlen and Oring 1977)</ref>. Thus, according to this latter theory ASR would predict SSD if ASR covaries with OSR, for example because OSR is in part determined by ASR (together with sex differences in behavior like parental care; <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Kokko et al. 2012)</ref>. Although the relationship between ASR and OSR is yet to be fully explored, their positive association has been demonstrated both by theoretical models <ref type="bibr">(Kokko and Jennions 2008: Fig. 4a;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fromhage and Jennions 2016: Fig. 3c,d)</ref> and comparative analyses <ref type="bibr">(Mitani et al. 1996, correlation between ASR and OSR in 18</ref> primates: r = 0.4, P = 0.002; unpublished result using data from their Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). Empirical studies commonly use ASR and OSR interchangeably in testing their relationship with SSD <ref type="bibr" target="#b83">(Poulin 1997</ref>) and other proxies of sexual selection <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Janicke and Morrow 2018)</ref>.</p><p>Second, models of reproductive sex roles predict that ASR should influence the evolution of SSD because individuals of a given sex may allocate less to parental care when the sex ratio is skewed towards the opposite sex than when it is skewed towards their own sex <ref type="bibr" target="#b87">(Queller 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">McNamara et al. 2000)</ref>. According to these models, males in female-skewed populations display a higher reproductive success due to increased probability of breeding with multiple partners and therefore may evolve to reduce parental care <ref type="bibr" target="#b87">(Queller 1997</ref><ref type="bibr">: section 3., McNamara et al. 2000: section 'Sex ratio')</ref>. This association between ASR and parental sex roles can drive the evolution of SSD because more elaborate trait expression in males is evolutionarily linked to female-biased care and stronger sexual selection on males (the so called 'sex-role syndrome', <ref type="bibr">Janicke et al. 2016: Fig 3.</ref>). Thus, this 'mating opportunity hypothesis' predicts that the extent of male bias in mating competition, and hence in SSD, should decrease with increasing male skew in the ASR. A demographic analysis of mating systems by <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">Murray (1984)</ref> also predicts that female-skewed ASRs should be associated with both polygyny and male-biased SSD, whereas male-skewed ASRs should be associated with polyandry and female-biased SSD.</p><p>Alternatively, SSD may drive changes in sex ratios through sex differences in mortality resulting from sexual competition. According to this 'mortality cost hypothesis', the skewed ASR is a consequence rather than a cause of intense sexual selection, because when males allocate a lot to mating competition they may suffer increased mortality, which in turn leads to female-skewed ASR <ref type="bibr" target="#b104">(Trivers 1972;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Clutton-Brock et al. 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Liker and Székely 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Kalmbach and Benito 2007)</ref>. This hypothesis predicts that in species exhibiting SSD (1) the larger sex should have higher mortality due to the costs of being large, including the direct costs associated with competition (e.g. fights, displays); which leads to (2) decreasing male skew in the ASR with increasing degree of male bias in the SSD.</p><p>Studies that have investigated the relationships between sex ratios, SSD and sexspecific mortality have so far yielded inconsistent results. While some studies found a positive link between SSD and ASR or OSR (i.e. an increasing male bias in SSD with increasing male skew in the sex ratios; <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Mitani et al. 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b83">Poulin 1997)</ref>, others reported negative associations <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Clutton-Brock et al. 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b110">Wittenberger 1978;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Georgiadis 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Haro et al. 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Johansson et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Lovich et al. 2014)</ref>, or found no consistent relationships <ref type="bibr" target="#b78">(Owen-Smith 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Hirst and Kiørboe 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b72">Muralidhar and Johnson 2017)</ref>. Similarly, mortality costs paid by the larger sex in dimorphic species were reported in some studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Clutton-Brock et al. 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b84">Promislow 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b85">Promislow et al. 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Moore and Wilson 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Benito and González-Solís 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Kalmbach and Benito 2007)</ref>, whereas no consistent relationship between SSD and sex differences in mortality was found by others <ref type="bibr" target="#b79">(Owens and Bennett 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b103">Toïgo and Gaillard 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Lemaître and Gaillard 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Székely et al. 2014a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b102">Tidière et al. 2015)</ref>. Many of these studies focused on a narrow range of taxonomic groups and were based on a relatively small number of species (typically fewer than 50) in comparative analyses. Furthermore, none of the studies tested explicitly whether statistical models assuming that ASR drives variation in SSD (as proposed by the mating competition and mating opportunity hypotheses) or alternative models (like the mortality costs hypothesis) fit better to the data.</p><p>Here we investigate the strength and direction of the relationship between ASR and SSD in populations of wild amniotes, using the largest existing comparative dataset on ASR compiled to date (462 species). First, we investigate whether SSD increases or decreases with ASR across species, as predicted by the mating competition and mating opportunity hypotheses, respectively. We also test whether the relationship is consistent among three major amniote taxa (reptiles, birds, and mammals) because these taxa differ in multiple ecological, behavioral and life-history traits. Since the extent and direction of SSD can be influenced by ecological, life-history and behavioral factors besides mating competition, we also control for several potential confounding variables in the analyses. Second, we study whether SSD drives ASR variation by generating sex-biased mortality as proposed by the mortality cost hypothesis. We test this latter hypothesis by investigating whether SSD is related to sex differences in juvenile or adult mortality, and by comparing path models representing different structural relationships between SSD, ASR and sex-specific mortality.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data collection</head><p>Data were extracted from published sources (see Appendix S1 in Supporting Information).</p><p>The initial dataset was based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">Pipoly et al. (2015)</ref> that contains ASR and SSD for 344 amniote species. We excluded amphibians included in <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">Pipoly et al. (2015)</ref> because sexspecific mortality data (see below) are very scarce for this taxon, especially in juveniles. The initial dataset was augmented with additional reptile and mammal species, and with information on sex-specific mortality. These additional data were taken from existing comparative datasets <ref type="bibr">(Berger and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Gompper 1999 and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bókony et al. 2019</ref> for ASR in mammals and reptiles, respectively, and <ref type="bibr">Székely et al. 2014a</ref> for mortality in birds) or from primary publications. In the latter case we searched the literature through the search engines Web of Science and Google Scholar, using the search terms 'sex ratio', 'sex-specific mortality OR survival' or 'male female mortality OR survival' together with taxonomic names. Data for different variables for the same species were often available only from different populations or studies. The final dataset includes 462 species with both ASR and SSD available (155 reptiles, 185 birds, 122 mammals).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Body mass and SSD</head><p>Sex-specific body mass (g) was available for all birds and mammals in our dataset. Since body mass data were missing for many reptiles, we also collected body length data (mm) for this taxon in the form of snout-vent length for squamates and crocodilians and plastron or carapace length for turtles. We estimated body mass from body length using published allometric equations (Appendix S2). We used estimated body mass for reptiles instead of body length in the combined analyses of all species because (1) data on mass are more readily available than data on body length in birds and mammals, which provided the majority of species, and (2) body mass is measured in a standardized way in all taxa, whereas the measurement of body length varies because different parts of the body are recorded as a proxy for length in different taxa. If multiple mass or length data were available for a species, we used the mean value. Average adult body mass was calculated as log10-transformed mean mass of the sexes.</p><p>We calculated SSD as log10(male mass / female mass). Earlier studies criticized measures of SSD that are based on male/female (or female/male) ratios and suggested other approaches, for example to analyze male size as response variable in models that also include female size as a control variable (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b97">Smith 1999 and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Fairbairn 2007</ref> for reviews). In his seminal paper, however, <ref type="bibr">Smith (1999, p. 444</ref>) convincingly demonstrated that ratios can be safely used in the context of SSD analyses because "the risk of spurious correlation is negligible to non-existent" due to the statistical properties of male and female size variables (i.e. their high correlation and approximately equal coefficients of variation, leading to an isometric relationship). We checked the assumption of isometry between male and female body mass in our dataset and found that male and female body mass (on a log10 -log10 scale) are strongly correlated (r = 0.994) with a slope very close to and not different from 1 (phylogenetic generalized least squares, slope ± SE: 1.0096 ± 0.0102, 95% CI: 0.989 ≤ β ≤ 1.029, n = 462 species). Furthermore, <ref type="bibr">Smith (1999, pp. 439-440)</ref> demonstrated that the approaches based on the log ratios versus male mass as response variable are statistically equivalent and suggested that the correct method is using log SSD ratio as response and controlling for log size. We thus followed this latter approach. However, because the measures of SSD remains a controversial issue among evolutionary ecologists (see e.g. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> in <ref type="bibr" target="#b102">Tidière et al. 2015</ref> for a review of SSD metrics commonly used), we replicated the main analysis using an alternative method (i.e. male size as response variable while controlling for female size in the model) to check the robustness of our results. All results were qualitatively unchanged.</p><p>To test whether the results are sensitive to conversion of length to mass in reptiles, we replicated the main analyses (1) with SSD calculated from body length (log10(male length / female length)) of reptiles, and (2) with SSD calculated from body mass for a subset (31 species) of reptiles that has sex-specific mass data available from <ref type="bibr" target="#b74">Myhrvold et al. (2015)</ref>.</p><p>Whatever approach was used to assess the degree of SSD the results were qualitatively unchanged (see Results). In the main text we thus report results based on body mass estimated from body length for reptiles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sex ratio</head><p>We followed <ref type="bibr" target="#b108">Wilson and Hardy (2002)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Ancona et al. (2017)</ref> in expressing ASR as the proportion of males in the adult population. We defined the adult population here broadly as adult individuals living in the study area during ASR sampling. <ref type="bibr" target="#b108">Wilson and Hardy (2002)</ref> showed that analyzing sex ratios as a proportion variable is appropriate when sex ratios are estimated from samples of ≥ 10 individuals and the dataset has ≥ 50 sex ratio estimates. These conditions were more than fully met in our analyses because sample sizes for ASR estimates were always larger than 10 individuals per species (and typically much larger), and our overall dataset included nine times more than the requirement of 50 species.</p><p>ASR data from <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">Pipoly et al. (2015)</ref> were augmented with new species and updated with more recent and/or better quality information (e.g. based on a more reliable method or a larger sample size) for some reptiles. ASR estimates were collected by different observers for the different taxa: reptiles by V.B. and I.P. <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">(Pipoly et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bókony et al. 2019)</ref>, birds by A.L. <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Liker et al. 2014)</ref>, and mammals by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Berger and Gompper (1999)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Donald (2007)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Anile and Devillard (2018)</ref>. Details of data selection criteria are given in the original publications (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Ancona et al. 2017)</ref>. Mean values were calculated for species with multiple ASR data. ASR estimates are repeatable between populations of the same species as measured by the intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC), although the magnitude of repeatability varies among taxa: reptiles with genetic and environmental sex determination: ICC= 0.55 and 0.14, respectively <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Bókony et al. 2019)</ref>, birds: ICC= 0.64 <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Ancona et al. 2017)</ref>, mammals: ICC= 0.60 (Valentine Federico, J-F.L., J-M.G., A.L., I.P., T.S. unpublished result).</p><p>ASR estimates are not influenced by the sample size of the ASR studies <ref type="bibr">(Székely et al. 2014a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bókony et al. 2019)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sex-specific mortality</head><p>Annual mortality rates were collected from studies in which mortality (or survival) was estimated for each of both sexes. Juvenile and adult mortality refer to age classes before and after the age of first reproduction, respectively. For reptiles, data were collected by V.B. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Bókony et al. 2019)</ref>. Most adult mortality data on birds are taken from <ref type="bibr">Székely et al. (2014a)</ref> with the addition of new data for juvenile mortality by A.L. Reptile and bird mortality includes estimates by various methods (e.g. capture-recapture, return rates, demographic models), although we used better quality estimates (e.g. those from capture-recapture analyses) whenever we had a choice <ref type="bibr">(Székely et al. 2014a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bókony et al. 2019)</ref>. For mammals, all sex-specific estimates were collected by J-M.G. and J-F.L. <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">(Lemaître et al. 2020</ref>). Sex differences in juvenile and adult mortality rates were calculated as the magnitude of male-biased mortality (i.e. log10(juvenile or adult male mortality / juvenile or adult female mortality)), also referred to as 'mortality bias'. These measures of mortality bias are not related to the overall mortality rate of the species, as estimated by the average mortality rates of the sexes (phylogenetic generalized least squares models, juvenile mortality bias: slope ± SE = -0.068 ± 0.101, t = 0.7, P = 0.497, n = 100; adult mortality bias: slope ± SE = -0.05 ± 0.08, t = 0.7, P = 0.513, n = 230).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Other predictors</head><p>We controlled for the potential effects of ecological variables and life-history traits related to either ASR or SSD (or both) that may confound the assessment of their relationship. First, we collected data on the type of sex determination system because it is associated with both ASR <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">(Pipoly et al. 2015)</ref> and SSD (Adkins-Regan and Reeve 2014). We divided the species into three categories according to the Tree of Sex database <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Ashman et al. 2014</ref>): maleheterogametic (XY) or female-heterogametic (ZW) genetic sex determination, or temperaturedependent sex determination (TSD). For species that were not included in the Tree of Sex database we assumed the same type of sex determination as reported for the genus (or family, respectively; <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bókony et al. 2019)</ref> when the genus (or family) to which it belongs had invariable sex determination system. All birds were assigned to ZW, and all mammals to XY sex determination <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Ashman et al. 2014)</ref>.</p><p>Second, we controlled for the potential effects of environmental variation among species by using two measures. Breeding latitude correlates with life-history traits in many organisms (as shown in his pioneer work by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Dobzhansky 1950)</ref> and may also influence the potential for polygamy, hence also sexual selection <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Fischer 1960;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Isaac 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Balasubramaniam and Rotenberry 2016)</ref>. We used absolute values of the geographic latitude of the ASR studies included in our dataset (i.e. average values for species with multiple ASR estimates) to represent the distance from the Equator. When the authors did not report latitude, we used Google Earth to estimate it as the center of the study sites based on the site descriptions. For 30 birds and 10 mammals, accurate population locations were not reported, hence, we used the latitudinal midpoint of the breeding ranges of these species (birds: V.</p><p>Remeš, A. Liker, R. Freckleton and T. Székely unpublished data, mammals: PanTHERIA database).</p><p>In addition to latitude, we investigated environmental harshness as a second environmental variable, which also has been hypothesized to influence SSD <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Isaac 2005)</ref>. We quantified the harshness of the breeding environment using a proxy proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Botero et al. (2014)</ref>. This is the PC1 score extracted from Principal Component Analysis (PCA) performed on a set of climatic and ecological variables (e.g. temperature and precipitation, net primary productivity, habitat heterogeneity; see <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Botero et al. 2014</ref> for a detailed description of the variables and the analysis). The PC1 scores have higher values for a higher level of exposure to drier, less productive environments, with colder, less predictable and more variable annual temperatures (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Botero et al. 2014)</ref>. In birds and mammals, we used the data published in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Botero et al. (2014)</ref>, whereas for reptiles we calculated PC1 scores by performing a PCA with the same set of variables.</p><p>Third, we characterized courtship displays in birds because earlier studies showed that birds with aerial displays have less male-biased SSD compared to species with ground displays, probably because selection favors male agility in aerially displaying species constraining male body size <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Jehl and Murray 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b100">Székely et al. 2007</ref>). We followed <ref type="bibr" target="#b100">Székely et al. (2007)</ref> and divided species into two display groups: (1) mating displays that may favor male agility, including species that mainly have aerial displays (both non-acrobatic and acrobatic, categories 4 and 5 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b100">Székely et al. 2007)</ref>, and (2) displays that may not favor male agility, including all other display types, typically performed on ground (categories 1-3 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b100">Székely et al. 2007)</ref>. Although SSD can also be influenced by display type and display habitat in reptiles and mammals (e.g. see <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Agha et al. 2018)</ref>, we were not able to collect reliable data for these taxa, therefore we analyzed the effect of display type only in birds.</p><p>Fourth, we tested for the potential effect of social mating system, because the scope for mating competition may be more limited in monogamous than in polygamous species <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Andersson 1994)</ref>. Thus, although there is ASR variation among monogamous species that can generate some variation in mating competition and/or opportunity, the relationship between ASR and SSD is expected to be weaker in monogamous than in polygamous species.</p><p>To test this idea, we characterized social mating system for birds and mammals, because we found reliable information in these taxa for most species <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Liker et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Lukas and Clutton-Brock 2013)</ref>. Although socially polygamous mating systems differ from promiscuous mating system, we pooled these mating systems because sexual selection is consistently stronger in polygamous than in monogamous species, whereas the relative intensity of sexual selection in polygynous versus promiscuous species is not easy to assess. We thus categorized species as either socially monogamous or polygamous (most often polygynous) according to the sources, as previously done (see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Lukas and Clutton-Brock 2013)</ref>. In birds, social mating system was originally scored on a five point scale <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Liker et al. 2014)</ref>, and here we considered a species monogamous if it had score 0 or 1 (polygamy frequency &lt;1%) for both sexes.</p><p>Finally, in reptiles, the evolution of viviparity and reduced reproductive frequency are generally correlated with shifts toward female-biased SSD due to fecundity selection for large female size (Pincheira-Donoso and Hunt 2017). To control for its potential effect on SSD, we categorized the reproductive mode of reptiles as either viviparous or oviparous <ref type="bibr">(Uetz et al. 2019)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical analyses</head><p>Phylogenetic generalized least squares (PGLS) models were built to conduct bivariate and multi-predictor analyses. To control for phylogenetic relationships among taxa, we used the composite phylogeny applied in <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">Pipoly et al. (2015)</ref> with the addition of new species according to the family-level <ref type="bibr" target="#b91">(Sarre et al. 2011</ref>) and other recent phylogenies (Squamata: <ref type="bibr" target="#b75">Nicholson et al. 2012</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b86">, Pyron et al. 2013</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">, Gamble et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Testudines: Barley et al. 2010</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">, Guillon et al. 2012</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b98">, Spinks et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Crocodylia: Oaks 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">mammals: Fritz et al. 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b68">, Meredith et al. 2011)</ref>. Since composite phylogenies do not have true branch lengths, we used three methods to generate branch lengths (Nee's method, Pagel's method, and unit branch lengths, using the PDAP:PDTREE module of Mesquite; <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Midford et al. 2011)</ref>, and repeated key analyses with these alternative trees. We present results with Nee's branch lengths in the paper, except for the sensitivity analyses (see Results). <ref type="bibr">Freckleton et al. (2002)</ref> showed that PGLS is relatively insensitive to branch length assumptions. In each model we used the maximum-likelihood estimate of phylogenetic dependence (Pagel's λ). PGLS models were run using the 'caper' R package <ref type="bibr" target="#b77">(Orme et al. 2013)</ref>.</p><p>First, using all species, we applied bivariate PGLS models to test interspecific associations between ASR, SSD and sex differences in juvenile and adult mortality rates.</p><p>When SSD was the response variable in the model, we also included mean body mass as a second predictor, as recommended by Smith (1999) (hence we termed these models as 'separate predictor models' instead of bivariate models in the rest of the paper). Then we built two multi-predictor models. In Multi-predictor model 1, we tested the relationship between ASR and SSD while controlling for potential confounding effects of mean mass, sex determination system, and breeding latitude. In Multi-predictor model 2, we tested the ASR -SSD relationships while controlling for the effects of sex differences in juvenile and adult mortality rates, and mean mass. We built these two separate multi-predictor models because we have much lower sample sizes for sex-specific mortalities than for the other predictors, thus the statistical power would be reduced for variables of Multi-predictor model 1 if all predictors were combined in a single model. We ran the models in two alternative versions in which either SSD or ASR was the dependent variable, respectively, since we had no a priori knowledge about the cause-effect direction of these relationships and results may differ between these analyses if the two models have different values for Pagel's λ (see Appendix <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">S3</ref>).</p><p>We investigated whether the ASR -SSD relationship, which is the main focus of our study, differed among taxa by testing the interaction between ASR and the taxonomic class.</p><p>To explore differences among taxa in the multivariate relationships, we repeated all analyses separately for reptiles, birds and mammals. In taxon-specific Multi-predictor models 1, we included reproductive mode for reptiles and display type for birds as further predictors. In reptiles, we also tested whether the relationship between ASR and SSD is sensitive (1) to the inclusion of species that have environmental sex determination, because ASR shows low repeatability in such reptiles <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Bókony et al. 2019)</ref>, and (2) to the inclusion of species in which the type of sex determination was inferred from data on related species in the genus or family.</p><p>Finally, we ran two additional separate analyses to test whether social mating system and environmental harshness confounded the ASR -SSD relationship. All numeric variables were standardized before analyses to make parameter estimates comparable, and model assumptions were also checked and met. We report two-tailed statistics. Sample sizes differed between models because not all variables were available for all species (see Appendix S1).</p><p>In addition to PGLS models, we used phylogenetic path analyses <ref type="bibr">(Santos 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Gonzalez-Voyer and von Hardenberg 2014)</ref> to compare two sets of path models corresponding to different hypotheses for the relationships linking ASR, SSD and sex differences in mortality. Although path analysesunlike experimentscannot infer causality, it is a suitable method to compare alternative scenarios representing different causal relationships between variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b96">(Shipley 2016)</ref>. Model 1 assumes that sex-biased mortality influences ASR, which in turn influences SSD through its effects on mating competition (as proposed by the mating opportunity hypothesis; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). Three variants of this model were tested: Model 1a assumes that sex differences in both juvenile and adult mortality rates influence ASR, while Models 1b-c include only one of these mortality effects. Model 2 assumes that SSD has sex-specific effects on juvenile and/or adult mortality, which then drives ASR variation (representing the mortality cost hypothesis; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). We tested all the three variants of this latter scenario, assuming SSD effects on both juvenile and adult mortality (Model 2a) or only on one mortality component (Models 2b-c).</p><p>We followed the approach proposed by <ref type="bibr">Santos (2012)</ref> for phylogenetic path analyses.</p><p>In the first step, we conducted phylogenetic transformation on the data to control for effects of phylogenetic relatedness among species. For this purpose, we (1) determined λ separately for each variable by maximum likelihood, (2) used this variable-specific λ value to re-scale the phylogenetic tree to a unit tree, and (3) used the transformed tree to calculate phylogenetically independent contrasts for the variable (using 'pic' function of the R package 'ape'; Paradis 2012). We repeated this process for each variable, and the resulting phylogenetically transformed values were used for fitting path models. In the second step of the analyses, we evaluated model fit using d-separation method <ref type="bibr" target="#b96">(Shipley 2016)</ref> as implemented in the R package 'piecewiseSEM' <ref type="bibr">(Lefcheck 2016)</ref>. In this method, Fisher's C statistic is used to test the goodness of fit of the whole path model, and the model is rejected (i.e. it does not provide a good fit to the data) if the result of this C statistic is statistically significant (and conversely a statistically non-significant result means acceptable fit; <ref type="bibr">Lefcheck 2016</ref>). We compared model fit between the six path models by their AICc values. Note that this approach ensures that the same variables (i.e. the contrasts with the same phylogenetic signal) are used in each path model, and that the correlations are non-directional in the sense that for a pair of variables X and Y, rXY = rYX as assumed in path analysis (irrespective of the sign of the correlation, i.e. whether it is positive or negative).</p><p>To test the robustness of the results, we repeated the path analyses using two other methods. First, we repeated the above procedure (i.e. followed Santos 2012) except that we used the covariance matrix comparison method for model fit instead of d-separation, as implemented in the R package 'lavaan' <ref type="bibr">(Rosseel 2012)</ref>. Second, we repeated the analyses using the method developed by von Hardenberg and Gonzalez-Voyer (2013). Unlike Santos' (2012) method, in this latter approach a single value of Pagel's λ is estimated for the residuals of a regression of each pair of traits in a directional model, rather than a value of λ for each variable (see the Discussion and Appendix S3). We used the R package 'phylopath' (van der Bijl 2018) for this latter analysis, which relies on the d-separation method for model fitting (similarly to 'piecewiseSEM', see above). We provide additional analyses to test the robustness of the path analysis' results in Appendix S3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mating competition versus mating opportunity hypotheses</head><p>Consistent with the mating opportunity hypothesis, and in contrast to the mating competition hypothesis, we found a negative relationship between our measures of ASR and SSD: the size of males relative to females increases when ASR becomes more female-skewed (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). This correlation was statistically significant when all species were analyzed together and did not differ among the three amniote classes (ASR × class interaction on SSD: F2,456 = 0.935, P = 0.393). The increase of SSD with increasingly female-skewed ASR was statistically significant within birds and mammals but was not in reptiles when the three taxa were analyzed separately (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S1</ref>, Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">S1-4</ref>). These results remained consistent when we used SSD estimates based on length instead of estimated mass in reptiles (Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">S1, S2</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_10">S5</ref>), when SSD for reptiles were estimated from published body mass data (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">S5</ref>), and also when male mass was used as response variable (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">S5</ref>).</p><p>These results are robust because the sign of the slope of the ASR -SSD relationship and its statistical significance were not sensitive to branch length assumptions (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">S6</ref>), and to the inclusion of other predictors (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). In multi-predictor models (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>), mean body mass was positively related to SSD, supporting the Rensch rule <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Abouheif and Fairbairn 1997)</ref>, and the type of sex determination influenced ASR variation as previously reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">Pipoly et al. (2015)</ref>. Nevertheless, ASR remained negatively associated with SSD when the effects of mass and sex determination systems were accounted for (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). This result also did not change when environmental variation was included in the models using either breeding latitude (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>) or environmental harshness (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">S5</ref>). Finally, excluding reptiles with TSD (that have the lowest consistency in ASR; <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bókony et al. 2019)</ref> or with assumed sex determination also did not influence the relationship (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">S5</ref>).</p><p>The multi-predictor model for birds showed that species with aerial courtship displays have lowered SSD as found in earlier studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Jehl and Murray 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b100">Székely et al. 2007</ref>); however, the relationship between ASR and SSD remained statistically significant and negative when this effect was included in the model (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">S3</ref>). Furthermore, data in birds and mammals showed that, as expected, the relationship was weaker in monogamous than in polygamous species, although the same trend occurred in both mating systems (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_13">S7</ref>).</p><p>Finally, reproductive mode was not associated with SSD or ASR in reptiles in our dataset (Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">S1-2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mating opportunity versus mortality costs hypotheses</head><p>Both the mating opportunity hypothesis and the mortality cost hypothesis predict femaleskewed ASRs in species with male-biased SSD. However, our results are more consistent with the mating opportunity hypothesis for two reasons. First, ASR but not SSD was associated with the extent of sex differences in juvenile or adult mortality, and ASR remained strongly and negatively correlated with SSD when sex differences in juvenile and adult mortality were statistically controlled for (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). Second, phylogenetic path analyses showed that models of the mating opportunity hypothesis provided better fit to the data (Models 1a-c, Fisher' C statistic: P = 0.07 -0.97) than models corresponding to the mortality cost hypothesis (Models 2a-c, P &lt; 0.001; Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>). The strongest support was for Model 1a because it had the lowest AICc (ΔAICc = 4.1 -43.2; Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>). This model proposes that sexbiased mortality in both juveniles and adults generates skewed ASR, which in turn leads to SSD biased towards the rarer sex (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>). These results are robust because we obtained the same results when the analyses were repeated using two other implementations of the path analysis (see Table <ref type="table">S8</ref> for the results obtained using 'phylopath', and Appendix S3 for the results obtained using 'lavaan'). Finally, path analyses that excluded reptiles (for which the ASR -SSD relationship was not statistically significant, see above) also yielded results qualitatively consistent with the full dataset (Table <ref type="table">S9</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p>Our analyses provided three major findings: (1) adult sex ratio is related to sexual size dimorphism among amniote species, although the association is the opposite of the one proposed by Darwin; (2) sex-biased mortality is unrelated to the extent of SSD in amniotes; and (3) confirmatory path analyses indicate that sex-biased mortality influences ASR, which in turn induces changes in SSD. Collectively, these findings support the mating opportunity hypothesis, indicating that selection is likely to favor an increased resource allocation toward mating competition (by growing and maintaining a large body mass) in the rarer sex, which has a higher chance of getting mates than the other sex.</p><p>Theoretical models show that skewed ASRs can promote evolutionary changes that may generate this association between ASR and SSD. First, models of sex role evolution showed that skewed ASR can result in divergences in reproductive roles between the sexes leading to less parental care and more frequent desertion and remating in the rarer sex and opposite changes (i.e. more parental care and less frequent remating) in the more abundant sex <ref type="bibr" target="#b87">(Queller 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">McNamara et al. 2000)</ref>. Similarly, a demographic analysis based on the relationships between mating systems and sex ratio, sex-specific patterns of survivorship, age of first reproduction, and annual fecundity predicts that skewed ASRs promote the evolution of polygamy (i.e. polygyny and polyandry in female-biased and male-biased populations, respectively; <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">Murray 1984)</ref>. Since both frequent remating and polygamy can intensify sexual selection, the above effects of skewed ASR can promote the evolution of SSD by favoring increased body size in the rare sex. In line with the predictions of these models, an increasing number of recent studies in birds and humans show that polygyny is more frequent and parental care by males is reduced in female-skewed populations <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Liker et al. 2013</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Liker et al. , 2014</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">(Liker et al. , 2015;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b88">Remeš et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b92">Schacht and Borgerhoff Mulder 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Eberhart-Phillips et al. 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Grant and Grant 2019)</ref>. Our results are also concordant with experimental studies in voles and lizards, which reported that female-skewed ASRs exert directional selection for large body size in males <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Klemme et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Fitze and Le Galliard 2008)</ref>, and increase variance in male reproductive success <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Dreiss et al. 2010)</ref>.</p><p>Theoretical models predict that the effects of ASR may depend on other life-history and behavioral traits of the populations. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Fromhage and Jennions (2016)</ref> highlighted the importance of the specific processes generating ASR skews for the outcomes of sex role evolution, and that a coevolutionary feedback between parental care and sexually selected traits can greatly amplify sex role divergence. In addition, sexual competition for mates may favor different traits in species with distinct ecology and behavior, leading to inconsistent relationships between sex differences in mating competition and sexual dimorphisms in behavioral or morphological trait across species (Clutton-Brock 2017).</p><p>Collectively, these factors may account for the relatively low amount of variation in SSD explained by ASR in some of our analyses.</p><p>The association between intense sexual selection in males and female-skewed ASRs was proposed decades ago by avian evolutionary ecologists (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Mayr 1939</ref>), although it was usually explained by the mortality cost hypothesis <ref type="bibr" target="#b109">(Wittenberger 1976</ref>). Our analyses do not support this latter hypothesis because sex-biased SSD is not associated with sex-biased juvenile or adult mortality in the studied amniote species, and the results of the confirmatory path analyses are also inconsistent with the mortality cost hypothesis. We propose that the lack of relationship between SSD and sex differences in mortality may be explained by variation in the environmental context <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">(Lemaître et al. 2020)</ref>. Studies in birds and mammals showed that having a large body size may only be costly in terms of mortality in populations subjected to harsh environmental conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b103">(Toïgo and Gaillard 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Kalmbach and Benito 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Jones et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Clutton-Brock 2017)</ref>. The effect of SSD may thus be reduced or absent when the sex-specific mortality estimates correspond to average conditions, that may often be the case in wild populations.</p><p>The ASR -SSD relationship may also be influenced by sex differences in the time of maturation because longer maturation time in the larger sex can result in a shortage of that sex in the adult population <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(Lovich et al. 2014)</ref> because immature life stages are generally characterized by higher mortality (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Gaillard et al. 2000)</ref>. Furthermore, <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Fromhage &amp; Jennions (2016)</ref> showed that female-skewed sex ratios at maturation (MSR) can result in the evolution of increased female care and male allocation to traits facilitating mating success.</p><p>Thus, if variation in ASR is determined at least in part by MSR, then the effects of sex-biased MSR on sex roles can contribute to the observed association of ASR with the intensity of mating competition, and, hence, SSD. This latter mechanism would deserve further investigations.</p><p>Although the relationship between ASR and SSD is not statistically significant in reptiles, it is qualitatively consistent with our findings in birds and mammals. Other selective processes (e.g. fertility selection for large female size in indeterminate growers, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Cox et al. 2007</ref>) might have masked the influence of sexual selection on SSD in reptiles. Consistent with this explanation, selection often favors delayed maturation in female reptiles, which enables them to produce larger clutches, which in turn also influences their body size and the extent of SSD <ref type="bibr" target="#b95">(Shine 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Agha et al. 2018)</ref>. Follow-up studies using different proxies of sexual selection are needed to investigate further how sexual selection is related to ASR in reptiles.</p><p>Biased estimates of ASR may generate spurious relationship with SSD, which may potentially affect our results. For example, the larger sex may have lower detectability in polygamous species if some members of that sex are excluded from breeding sites <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Ancona et al. 2017</ref>). However, highly polygamous species in which populations have been thoroughly surveyed showed skewed ASR even when all individuals in the population were accurately counted <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Granjon et al. 2017)</ref>, and fairly consistent ASR estimates were obtained when both breeding and non-breeding individuals were included <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Emlen and Wrege 2004)</ref>. In general, ASR estimates show a moderate but statistically significant repeatability across populations in most of the studied taxa, except reptiles with temperature-dependent sex determination <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Ancona et al. 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bókony et al. 2019</ref>; Valentine Federico, J-F.L., J-M.G., A.L., I.P., T.S. unpublished result), and in 80% of bird species the direction of ASR skew is the same for all repeated estimates <ref type="bibr">(Székely et al. 2014a)</ref>.</p><p>The paths of causality in comparative data are difficult to untangle. Path analysis is a valuable tool for contrasting different causal models, although it cannot reveal causality <ref type="bibr" target="#b96">(Shipley 2016)</ref>. Path analysis assumes that each variable includes independent variations or 'errors' and that these errors are independent among variables. This is not true for comparative data, because the errors will be correlated across species. Our approach follows <ref type="bibr">Santos (2012)</ref>, an innovative but overlooked method that satisfies the assumptions of path analysis better than an alternative method based on phylogenetic regressions proposed by von <ref type="bibr">Hardenberg and Gonzalez-Voyer (2013)</ref>. This latter approach is problematic because it is not robust to changes in the specification of the model: if variable Y is regressed on X and  estimated, then the estimates of the partial correlations and  may be different from those obtained if Y is regressed on X with  estimated (Appendix 3). The approach we have taken avoids this problem. However, there is still room for methodological improvement. For instance, our approach has the drawback of being a 'subtractive' comparative method (sensu <ref type="bibr">Harvey and Pagel 1991)</ref>. The question of how to robustly fit complex path models for data on multiple traits with different levels of phylogenetic signal is not straightforward.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Concluding remarks</head><p>Our findings indicate that sex-specific selection for large body size is associated with skewed ASRs across amniotes, and this process appears to produce SSD biased towards the rare sex in birds and mammals. Although this conclusion contrasts with Darwin's initial suggestion that intense sexual selection among males occurs when there is a surplus of males in the population <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Darwin 1871)</ref>, theoretical and empirical work have suggested mechanisms that can favor large size in the rare sex <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">(Murray 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Klemme et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Fitze and Le Galliard 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Dreiss et al. 2010)</ref>. Further analyses of these processes and their application to species with differing mating systems offer exciting opportunities for future investigations of the interplay among sexual selection, SSD and ASR across the tree of life. as dependent variable also include log10(mean mass) as predictor (see Methods). Mortality biases were calculated as log10(male mortality/female mortality) for juveniles and adults, respectively. b ± SE is the model's parameter estimate with its standard error (intercepts are not shown), t and P are the associated test statistic and its significance, λ is Pagel's lambda, n is number of species. * λ statistically different from 0, ⧺ λ statistically different from 1.</p><p>1 Differences from species with XY sex determination; overall effect of sex determination on SSD: F2,451 = 3.411, P = 0.034; on ASR: F2,451 = 6.135, P = 0.002.  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S1</ref>. SSD: sexual size dimorphism, ASR: adult sex ratio, JMB and AMB: juvenile and adult mortality biases, respectively (variables are explained in footnotes of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). PC is P-value for Fisher's C statistic for model fit, with non-significant values (&gt; 0.05) indicating an acceptable fit. ΔAICc indicates difference in AICc values between the most supported model (lowest AICc, Model 1a) and the focal models. ΔAICc &gt; 2 indicates substantially higher support for the best model than for the other models. The analyses include 97 species of reptiles, birds and mammals with data for all for variables. 1 Path coefficient set to zero to keep the variable in the model.   SSD was calculated as log10(male mass/female mass); ASR is the proportion of males in the adult population. Each data point represents a species; the regression line is fitted by phylogenetic generalized least-squares (PGLS) model (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> for statistics).  <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>, n = 97 species of reptiles, birds and mammals). The model supports the scenario that sex-biased juvenile and adult mortalities lead to skewed adult sex ratio, which in turn results in increased size dimorphism by sexual selection. Width of the arrows is proportional to path coefficients (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref> for statistical details of the model). Bird pictures on the left illustrate the case when differential mortality generates female-skewed ASR, which then leads to a more malebiased SSD (i.e. larger body size in males relative to females). The path analyses were based on the approach proposed by <ref type="bibr">Santos (2012)</ref>, see Appendix S3 for details.</p><p>Electronic Supporting Information: tables and figures         To assess which of these models provides the best account of the data, first we calculated the AIC value for each model (in piecewiseSEM this is corrected for small sample size, i.e. AICc) using the real dataset. Second, we used simulated data to test which of the two methods produces less biased conclusions. For this latter purpose, we generated simulated datasets using the R function 'rnorm'. The simulated datasets have the same number of variables and sample size as the phylogenetically transformed real dataset. We fitted path models with both piecewiseSEM and lavaan to obtain the AIC (or AICc) values. Then we compared Model 1a</p><p>(the model that got the highest support for model fit by the global fit indices, see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">S10</ref>)</p><p>to the other five models <ref type="bibr">(Models 1b,</ref><ref type="bibr">1c,</ref><ref type="bibr">2a,</ref><ref type="bibr">2b,</ref><ref type="bibr">and 2c)</ref>, thus conducted five pairwise comparisons, repeated with the two methods. These paired comparisons between models mimic the comparison we conducted with the real dataset in our study <ref type="bibr">(Table 2</ref> in the main text). We calculated ΔAIC for each comparison as the difference between AIC values of the two models (i.e. AIC of compared model -AIC of Model 1a, thus a positive ΔAIC value indicates better fit for Model 1a). We repeated this procedure with 1000 simulated datasets that resulted in 1000 ΔAIC values for each pairwise comparison. To assess whether the comparison of two particular models produces biased results with simulated data we calculated (1) the mean ΔAIC value of the 1000 runs (ΔAICsimulation), and (2) the probability that the simulated ΔAIC was larger than the ΔAIC value we got with the real dataset (P≥ΔAIC_sim). and 2c in Table <ref type="table">S9</ref>). On the other hand, for nested model comparisons (i.e. with Models 1b and 1c) lavaan produced unbiased results similarly to those we got with piecsewiseSEM (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">S11</ref>).</p><p>These analyses suggest that the two methods gave consistent results for (1) path coefficients estimates and for (2) evaluating model fit of individual path models by global fit indices (using C statistics in piecewiseSEM, and χ 2 , TLI, CFI, RMSEA, and SRMR in lavaan). On the other hand, simulation results indicate that AIC-based model comparisons are less biased when performed by the piecewise structural equation modelling method, at least for comparisons between non-nested models.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Path models tested in the phylogenetic path analyses. SSD: sexual size dimorphism, ASR: adult sex ratio, JMB: juvenile mortality bias, AMB: adult mortality bias. Dashed arrows indicate paths with coefficients set to zero to keep the variable in the model. Models 1a-c and 2a-c represent relationships as predicted by the mating opportunity hypothesis and the mortality cost hypothesis, respectively.</figDesc><graphic coords="37,70.90,146.59,441.67,352.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Sexual size dimorphism (SSD) in relation to adult sex ratio (ASR) in amniotes.SSD was calculated as log10(male mass/female mass); ASR is the proportion of males in the adult population. Each data point represents a species; the regression line is fitted by phylogenetic generalized least-squares (PGLS) model (see Table1for statistics).</figDesc><graphic coords="38,70.90,146.59,452.70,327.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Path diagram of the best-fitting phylogenetic path model (Model 1a in Table2, n = 97 species of reptiles, birds and mammals). The model supports the scenario that sex-biased juvenile and adult mortalities lead to skewed adult sex ratio, which in turn results in increased size dimorphism by sexual selection. Width of the arrows is proportional to path coefficients (see Table2for statistical details of the model). Bird pictures on the left illustrate the case when differential mortality generates female-skewed ASR, which then leads to a more malebiased SSD (i.e. larger body size in males relative to females). The path analyses were based on the approach proposed bySantos (2012), see Appendix S3 for details.</figDesc><graphic coords="39,100.20,201.79,394.60,367.39" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure S1 .</head><label>S1</label><figDesc>Figure S1. Sexual size dimorphism in relation to adult sex ratio in (a) reptiles (PGLS, b ± SE = -0.123 ± 0.075, P = 0.103, n = 155 species), (b) birds (b ± SE = -0.242 ± 0.037, P &lt; 0.001, n = 185), and (c) mammals (b ± SE = -0.170 ± 0.058, P = 0.004, n = 122). Each data point represents a species, and lines show statistically significant regressions fitted by PGLS (see Tables S1-4 for further statistical details).</figDesc><graphic coords="51,70.90,160.39,452.35,214.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Phylogenetically corrected analyses of sexual size dimorphism (SSD) and adult sex 869 ratio (ASR) in amniotes (reptiles, birds and mammals).</figDesc><table><row><cell>870</cell></row></table><note><p>(PGLS) models with either (A) SSD (log10(male mass/female mass)) or (B) ASR (proportion 874 of males in the adult population) as dependent variable. Separate predictor models with SSD 875</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Response: sexual size dimorphism Separate predictor models:</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Model 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.119</cell><cell>0.868 * ⧺</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">ASR -0.168 ± 0. 035 4.835</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.515 ± 0. 086 5.980</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.129</cell><cell>0.703 * ⧺</cell></row><row><cell>Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell>0.041 ± 0.065 0.629</cell><cell>0.531</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.529 ± 0.131 4.051</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model 3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.095</cell><cell>0.932 *</cell></row><row><cell>Adult mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.021 ± 0.047 0.454</cell><cell>0.650</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.596 ± 0. 117 5.090</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Multi-predictor model 1:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.126</cell><cell>0.869 * ⧺</cell></row><row><cell>ASR</cell><cell>-0.160 ± 0.035 4.555</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.515 ± 0.087 5.950</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Latitude</cell><cell>0.004 ± 0.038 0.103</cell><cell>0.918</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sex determination, TSD 1</cell><cell>-0.297 ± 0.251 1.184</cell><cell>0.237</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sex determination, ZW 1</cell><cell>-0.685 ± 0.264 2.592</cell><cell>0.010</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Multi-predictor model 2:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.273</cell><cell>0.841 *</cell><cell>97</cell></row><row><cell>ASR</cell><cell>-0.271 ± 0.061 4.452</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.377 ± 0.134 2.824</cell><cell>0.006</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell>0.001 ± 0.060 0.011</cell><cell>0.992</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Adult mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.019 ± 0.067 0.277</cell><cell>0.783</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(B) Response: adult sex ratio</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Separate predictor models:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model 1: SSD</cell><cell>-0.234 ± 0.051 4.593</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell>0.042</cell><cell>0.359 * ⧺</cell></row><row><cell>Model 2: Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.214 ± 0.099 2.151</cell><cell>0.034</cell><cell>0.035</cell><cell>0.281 * ⧺</cell></row><row><cell>Model 3: Adult mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.257 ± 0.060 4.313</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell>0.071</cell><cell>0.288 * ⧺</cell></row><row><cell>Multi-predictor model 1:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.071</cell><cell>0.247 * ⧺</cell></row><row><cell>SSD</cell><cell>-0.188 ± 0.050 3.727</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>-0.106 ± 0.080 1.330</cell><cell>0.184</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Latitude</cell><cell>-0.095 ± 0.045 2.135</cell><cell>0.033</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sex determination, TSD 1</cell><cell>0.481 ± 0.221 2.178</cell><cell>0.030</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sex determination, ZW 1</cell><cell>0.712 ± 0.205 3.471</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Multi-predictor model 2:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.402</cell><cell>0.030 ⧺</cell><cell>97</cell></row><row><cell>SSD</cell><cell>-0.457 ± 0.120 3.794</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>-0.249 ± 0.108 2.316</cell><cell>0.023</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.146 ± 0.086 1.702</cell><cell>0.092</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Adult mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.259 ± 0.100 2.591</cell><cell>0.011</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Phylogenetic path models of the mating opportunity hypothesis (Models 1a-c) and the mortality cost hypothesis (Models 2a-c) in amniotes (reptiles, birds and mammals).</figDesc><table><row><cell>887</cell></row><row><cell>888</cell></row><row><cell>889</cell></row><row><cell>890</cell></row><row><cell>891</cell></row><row><cell>892</cell></row><row><cell>893</cell></row><row><cell>894</cell></row><row><cell>895</cell></row><row><cell>896</cell></row><row><cell>897</cell></row><row><cell>898</cell></row><row><cell>899</cell></row><row><cell>900</cell></row><row><cell>901</cell></row><row><cell>902</cell></row><row><cell>903</cell></row><row><cell>904</cell></row><row><cell>905</cell></row><row><cell>906</cell></row><row><cell>907</cell></row><row><cell>908</cell></row><row><cell>909</cell></row><row><cell>910</cell></row><row><cell>911</cell></row><row><cell>912</cell></row><row><cell>913</cell></row><row><cell>914</cell></row><row><cell>915</cell></row><row><cell>916</cell></row><row><cell>917</cell></row><row><cell>918</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table S1 .</head><label>S1</label><figDesc>Relationship between SSD, ASR and sex-biased mortalities in reptiles, using 958 estimated body mass data for SSD calculation. 959</figDesc><table><row><cell>957</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Predictors</cell><cell>b ± SE</cell><cell>t</cell><cell>P</cell><cell>R 2</cell><cell>λ</cell><cell>n</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">(A) Response: sexual size dimorphism</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Separate predictor models:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.082</cell><cell>0.948 *</cell><cell>155</cell></row><row><cell>ASR</cell><cell cols="2">-0.123 ± 0.075 1.641</cell><cell>0.103</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">0.668 ± 0.177 3.774</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.005</cell><cell>0.0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell cols="2">-0.414 ± 0.337 1.228</cell><cell>0.240</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">-0.500 ± 0.440 1.136</cell><cell>0.275</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model 3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.092</cell><cell>1.0 *</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Adult mortality bias</cell><cell cols="2">-0.151 ± 0.117 1.287</cell><cell>0.203</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">0.737 ± 0.317 2.324</cell><cell>0.024</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Multi-predictor model 1:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.116</cell><cell>0.956 *</cell><cell>153</cell></row><row><cell>ASR</cell><cell cols="2">-0.090 ± 0.075 1.203</cell><cell>0.231</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">0.715 ± 0.178 4.019</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Latitude</cell><cell cols="2">-0.175 ± 0.126 1.389</cell><cell>0.167</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reproductive mode 1</cell><cell cols="2">0.348 ± 0.313 1.112</cell><cell>0.268</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sex determination, TSD 2</cell><cell cols="2">-0.463 ± 0.384 1.206</cell><cell>0.230</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sex determination, ZW 2</cell><cell cols="2">-1.003 ± 0.313 2.344</cell><cell>0.020</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Multi-predictor model 2:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell>0.0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ASR</cell><cell cols="2">-0.022 ± 0.252 0.086</cell><cell>0.933</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">-0.452 ± 0.523 0.865</cell><cell>0.404</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell cols="2">-0.500 ± 0.374 1.339</cell><cell>0.205</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Adult mortality bias</cell><cell cols="2">0.284 ± 0.429 0.662</cell><cell>0.520</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(B)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Response: adult sex ratio Separate predictor models:</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Model 1: SSD</cell><cell>-0.074 ± 0.061 1.209</cell><cell>0.228</cell><cell>0.003</cell><cell>0.171 ⧺</cell><cell>155</cell></row><row><cell>Model 2: Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.480 ± 0.415 1.156</cell><cell>0.266</cell><cell>0.021</cell><cell>0.0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model 3: Adult mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.159 ± 0.092 1.732</cell><cell>0.088</cell><cell>0.032</cell><cell>0.155 ⧺</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Multi-predictor model 1:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.078</cell><cell>0.0 ⧺</cell><cell>153</cell></row><row><cell>SSD</cell><cell>-0.049 ± 0.055 0.891</cell><cell>0.374</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.173 ± 0.108 1.599</cell><cell>0.112</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Latitude</cell><cell>-0.001 ± 0.109 0.013</cell><cell>0.990</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reproductive mode 1</cell><cell>-0.140 ± 0.216 0.650</cell><cell>0.517</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sex determination, TSD 2</cell><cell>0.209 ± 0.224 0.934</cell><cell>0.352</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sex determination, ZW 2</cell><cell>0.667 ± 0.216 3.091</cell><cell>0.002</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Multi-predictor model 2:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.165</cell><cell>0.0 ⧺</cell><cell>17</cell></row><row><cell>SSD</cell><cell>-0.028 ± 0.331 0.086</cell><cell>0.933</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.929 ± 0.556 1.671</cell><cell>0.121</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.044 ± 0.459 0.095</cell><cell>0.926</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Adult mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.641 ± 0.465 1.377</cell><cell>0.194</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table S2 .</head><label>S2</label><figDesc>Relationship between SSD, ASR and sex-biased mortalities in reptiles, using body 966 length data for SSD calculation.</figDesc><table><row><cell>967</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Predictors</cell><cell>b ± SE</cell><cell>t</cell><cell>P</cell><cell>R 2</cell><cell>λ</cell><cell>n</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(A) Response: sexual size dimorphism</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Separate predictor models:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.073</cell><cell>0.935 *</cell><cell>155</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ASR</cell><cell cols="2">-0.008 ± 0.005 1.587</cell><cell>0.114</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">0.040 ± 0.011 3.562</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.073</cell><cell>0.0</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell cols="2">-0.035 ± 0.024 1.472</cell><cell>0.163</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">-0.046 ± 0.031 1.485</cell><cell>0.160</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model 3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.086</cell><cell>1.0 *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Adult mortality bias</cell><cell cols="2">-0.010 ± 0.007 1.402</cell><cell>0.166</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">0.044 ± 0.020 2.156</cell><cell>0.035</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Multi-predictor model 1:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.122</cell><cell>0.952 *</cell><cell>153</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ASR</cell><cell cols="2">-0.048 ± 0.042 1.126</cell><cell>0.262</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">0.391 ± 0.100 3.891</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Latitude</cell><cell cols="2">-0.103 ± 0.071 1.459</cell><cell>0.147</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Reproductive mode 1</cell><cell cols="2">0.179 ± 0.177 1.015</cell><cell>0.312</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Sex determination, TSD 2</cell><cell cols="2">-0.223 ± 0.216 1.032</cell><cell>0.304</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Sex determination, ZW 2</cell><cell cols="2">-0.633 ± 0.241 2.628</cell><cell>0.010</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Multi-predictor model 2:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell>0.0</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ASR</cell><cell cols="2">-0.059 ± 0.161 0.368</cell><cell>0.720</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">-0.347 ± 0.334 1.038</cell><cell>0.320</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell cols="2">-0.354 ± 0.239 1.484</cell><cell>0.164</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Adult mortality bias</cell><cell cols="2">0.092 ± 0.274 0.337</cell><cell>0.742</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(B) Response: adult sex ratio</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Separate predictor models:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model 1: SSD</cell><cell cols="2">-0.131 ± 0.109 1.209</cell><cell>0.229</cell><cell>0.003</cell><cell>0.169 ⧺</cell><cell>155</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model 2: Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell cols="2">-0.480 ± 0.415 1.156</cell><cell>0.266</cell><cell>0.021</cell><cell>0.0</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model 2: Adult mortality bias</cell><cell cols="2">-0.159 ± 0.092 1.732</cell><cell>0.088</cell><cell>0.032</cell><cell>0.155 ⧺</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Multi-predictor model 1:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.078</cell><cell>0.0 ⧺</cell><cell>153</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>SSD</cell><cell cols="2">-0.085 ± 0.098 0.870</cell><cell>0.386</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">0.172 ± 0.109 1.588</cell><cell>0.114</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Latitude</cell><cell cols="2">-0.001 ± 0.109 0.007</cell><cell>0.994</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Reproductive mode 1</cell><cell cols="2">-0.141 ± 0.216 0.654</cell><cell>0.514</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Sex determination, TSD 2</cell><cell cols="2">0.214 ± 0.223 0.958</cell><cell>0.340</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Sex determination, ZW 2</cell><cell cols="2">0.667 ± 0.216 3.089</cell><cell>0.002</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Multi-predictor model 2:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.174</cell><cell>0.0 ⧺</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>SSD</cell><cell cols="2">-0.188 ± 0.512 0.368</cell><cell>0.720</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">0.867 ± 0.570 1.522</cell><cell>0.154</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell cols="2">-0.096 ± 0.463 0.208</cell><cell>0.839</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Adult mortality bias</cell><cell cols="2">-0.624 ± 0.457 1.366</cell><cell>0.197</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>968</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>969</cell><cell cols="6">* Pagel's lambda statistically different from 0, ⧺ lambda statistically different from 1.</cell></row><row><cell>970</cell><cell cols="2">1 Differences from oviparous species.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table S3 .</head><label>S3</label><figDesc>Relationship between SSD, ASR and sex-biased mortalities in birds.</figDesc><table><row><cell>975</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Predictors</cell><cell>b ± SE</cell><cell>t</cell><cell>P</cell><cell>R 2</cell><cell>λ</cell><cell>n</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(A) Response: sexual size dimorphism</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Separate predictor models:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.250</cell><cell>0.812 * ⧺</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ASR</cell><cell>-0.242 ± 0.037</cell><cell>6.625</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.293 ± 0.105</cell><cell>2.798</cell><cell>0.006</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.130</cell><cell>0.095 *</cell><cell>47</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell>0.066 ± 0.073</cell><cell>0.898</cell><cell>0.374</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.735 ± 0.270</cell><cell>2.722</cell><cell>0.009</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model 3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.072</cell><cell>0.708 * ⧺</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Adult mortality bias</cell><cell>0.068 ± 0.051</cell><cell>1.335</cell><cell>0.184</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.372 ± 0.130</cell><cell>2.870</cell><cell>0.005</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Multi-predictor model 1:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.272</cell><cell>0.720 * ⧺</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ASR</cell><cell>-0.242 ± 0.038</cell><cell>6.390</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.261 ± 0.100</cell><cell>2.599</cell><cell>0.010</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Latitude</cell><cell>-0.020 ± 0.034</cell><cell>0.584</cell><cell>0.560</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Display type, agile 1 -0.338 ± 0.090</cell><cell>3.748</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Multi-predictor model 2:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.386</cell><cell>1.0 *</cell><cell>47</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ASR</cell><cell>-0.346 ± 0.080</cell><cell>4.318</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.424 ± 0.246</cell><cell>1.719</cell><cell>0.093</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.032 ± 0.065</cell><cell>0.489</cell><cell>0.627</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Adult mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.068 ± 0.089</cell><cell>0.763</cell><cell>0.450</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(B) Response: adult sex ratio</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Separate predictor models:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model 1: SSD</cell><cell>-0.746 ± 0.114</cell><cell>6.520</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell>0.184</cell><cell>0.480 * ⧺</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model 2: Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.354 ± 0.115</cell><cell>3.084</cell><cell>0.003</cell><cell>0.156</cell><cell>0.0 ⧺</cell><cell>47</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model 3: Adult mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.384 ± 0.079</cell><cell>4.866</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell>0.157</cell><cell>0.0 ⧺</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Multi-predictor model 1:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.239</cell><cell>0.244 ⧺</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>SSD</cell><cell>-0.717 ± 0.116</cell><cell>6.183</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>-0.191 ± 0.136</cell><cell>1.406</cell><cell>0.161</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Latitude</cell><cell>-0.127 ± 0.058</cell><cell>2.201</cell><cell>0.029</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Display type, agile 1 -0.589 ± 0.161</cell><cell>3.667</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Multi-predictor model 2:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.397</cell><cell>0.0 ⧺</cell><cell>47</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>SSD</cell><cell>-0.382 ± 0.153</cell><cell>2.499</cell><cell>0.016</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Mean body mass -0.128 ± 0.198</cell><cell>0.646</cell><cell>0.522</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.199 ± 0.109</cell><cell>1.831</cell><cell>0.074</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Adult mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.468 ± 0.139</cell><cell>3.368</cell><cell>0.002</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>976</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>977</cell><cell cols="5">* Pagel's lambda statistically different from 0, ⧺ lambda statistically different from 1.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>978</cell><cell>1 Difference from non-agile species.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>979</cell><cell cols="4">For further explanation, see the footnotes of Table 1 in the main text.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>980</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table S4 .</head><label>S4</label><figDesc>Relationship between SSD, ASR and sex-biased mortalities in mammals.</figDesc><table><row><cell>981</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Predictors</cell><cell>b ± SE</cell><cell>t</cell><cell>P</cell><cell>R 2</cell><cell>λ</cell><cell>n</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(A)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>982</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>983</cell><cell cols="5">* Pagel's lambda statistically different from 0, ⧺ lambda statistically different from 1.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>984</cell><cell cols="4">For further explanation, see the footnotes of Table 1 in the main text.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>985</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>986</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Response: sexual size dimorphism Separate predictor models:</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Model 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.143</cell><cell>0.313 * ⧺</cell><cell>122</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">ASR -0.170 ± 0.058</cell><cell>2.946</cell><cell>0.004</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.385 ± 0.129</cell><cell>2.979</cell><cell>0.004</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.078</cell><cell>0.233 ⧺</cell></row><row><cell>Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell>0.089 ± 0.123</cell><cell>0.719</cell><cell>0.477</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.515 ± 0.233</cell><cell>2.214</cell><cell>0.034</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model 3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.056</cell><cell>0.217 ⧺</cell></row><row><cell>Adult mortality bias</cell><cell>0.025 ± 0.103</cell><cell>0.244</cell><cell>0.809</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.424 ± 0.202</cell><cell>2.093</cell><cell>0.042</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Multi-predictor model 1:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.166</cell><cell>0.342 * ⧺</cell><cell>120</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">ASR -0.153 ± 0.058</cell><cell>2.646</cell><cell>0.009</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.418 ± 0.131</cell><cell>3.191</cell><cell>0.002</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Latitude</cell><cell>0.106 ± 0.053</cell><cell>2. 016</cell><cell>0.046</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Multi-predictor model 2:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.250</cell><cell>0.0 ⧺</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">ASR -0.374 ± 0.129</cell><cell>2.900</cell><cell>0.007</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>0.209 ± 0.237</cell><cell>0.880</cell><cell>0.386</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell>0.088 ± 0.116</cell><cell>0.762</cell><cell>0.452</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Adult mortality bias -0.016 ± 0.119</cell><cell>0.134</cell><cell>0.894</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(B) Response: adult sex ratio</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Separate predictor models:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Model 1: SSD -0.460 ± 0.130</cell><cell>3.539</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell>0.087</cell><cell>0.252 * ⧺</cell><cell>122</cell></row><row><cell>Model 2: Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.032 ± 0.166</cell><cell>0.195</cell><cell>0.847</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell>0.0 ⧺</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Model 3: Adult mortality bias -0.076 ± 0.155</cell><cell>0.493</cell><cell>0.624</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell>0.0 ⧺</cell></row><row><cell>Multi-predictor model 1:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.093</cell><cell>0.320 * ⧺</cell><cell>120</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">SSD -0.375 ± 0.140</cell><cell>2.670</cell><cell>0.009</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>-0.314 ± 0.209</cell><cell>1.500</cell><cell>0.136</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Latitude -0.075 ± 0.083</cell><cell>0.907</cell><cell>0.366</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Multi-predictor model 2:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.293</cell><cell>0.0 ⧺</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">SSD -0.617 ± 0.213</cell><cell>2.900</cell><cell>0.007</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell>-0.494 ± 0.294</cell><cell>1.678</cell><cell>0.104</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Juvenile mortality bias</cell><cell>-0.043 ± 0.150</cell><cell>0.285</cell><cell>0.778</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Adult mortality bias</cell><cell>0.022 ± 0.153</cell><cell>0.142</cell><cell>0.888</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Table S5 .</head><label>S5</label><figDesc>Sensitivity analyses of the relationship between sexual size dimorphism (SSD, dependent variable in all models) and adult sex ratio (ASR).</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Male body mass as response variable (all species):</head><label></label><figDesc>Tableshowsresults when (A) male mass (instead of log10(male mass / female mass) is used as response variable, (B) reptiles are included with SSD based on body length, (C) reptiles are included with SSD calculated from sex-specific body mass, (D) reptiles with temperature-dependent sex determination (TSD) are excluded, (E) reptiles with assumed sex determination, based on related species, are excluded, and (F) environmental harshness is included in the model.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Predictors</cell><cell>b ± SE</cell><cell>t</cell><cell>P</cell><cell>R 2</cell><cell>λ</cell><cell>n</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">(A) 0.957</cell><cell>0.846 *⧺</cell><cell>462</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">ASR -0.020 ± 0.004</cell><cell>4.953</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Female body mass 1.008 ± 0.010 100.658 &lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">(B) Reptiles' SSD calculated from body length (all species):</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.139</cell><cell>0.703 *⧺</cell><cell>462</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">ASR -0.234 ± 0.038</cell><cell>6.231</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Mean body mass 0.473 ± 0.085</cell><cell>5.575</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">(C) Reptiles' SSD calculated from body mass 1 (all species):</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.144</cell><cell>0.761 *⧺</cell><cell>338</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">ASR -0.271 ± 0.050</cell><cell>5.437</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Mean body mass 0.495 ± 0.112</cell><cell>4.426</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">(D) TSD reptiles excluded (all species):</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.132</cell><cell>0.791 *⧺</cell><cell>402</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">ASR -0.250 ± 0.043 5.767</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Mean body mass 0.507 ± 0.105</cell><cell>4.814</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">(E) Reptiles with assumed sex determination excluded 2 (all species):</cell><cell>0.125</cell><cell>0.860 *⧺</cell><cell>409</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">ASR -0.167 ± 0.036 4.669</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">0.502 ± 0.088 5.710</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">(F) Effect of environmental harshness 3 :</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>birds and mammals:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.141</cell><cell>0.763 * ⧺</cell><cell>219</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">ASR -0.164 ± 0.037 4.440</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Environmental harshness</cell><cell cols="2">0.039 ± 0.045 0.855</cell><cell>0.394</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">0.263 ± 0.088 2.966</cell><cell>0.003</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>reptiles:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.026</cell><cell>0.957 *</cell><cell>58</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">ASR -0.081 ± 0.144 0.562</cell><cell>0.576</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Environmental harshness</cell><cell cols="2">0.105 ± 0.064 1.624</cell><cell>0.110</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">0.294 ± 0.302 0.975</cell><cell>0.334</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>all species:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.111</cell><cell>0.867 * ⧺</cell><cell>277</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">ASR -0.153 ± 0.038 4.012</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Environmental harshness</cell><cell cols="2">0.076 ± 0.033 2.295</cell><cell>0.023</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">0.297 ± 0.091 3.256</cell><cell>0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="6">* Pagel's lambda statistically different from 0, ⧺ lambda statistically different from 1</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">1 Sex-specific body mass data from Myhrvold et al. (2015).</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="6">2 Sex determination mechanism assumed to be the same type as reported for the genus or</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>family (see Methods).</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>Table S6 .</head><label>S6</label><figDesc>Analyses of the relationship between SSD (dependent variable) and ASR with branch lengths calculated by three different methods for the phylogeny used in the PGLS models. The analyses included reptiles, birds, and mammals. Pagel's lambda statistically different from 0, ⧺ lambda statistically different from 1 1 See Methods for details of branch length calculations</figDesc><table><row><cell>Predictors</cell><cell>b ± SE</cell><cell>t</cell><cell>P</cell><cell>R 2</cell><cell>λ</cell><cell>n</cell></row><row><cell>(A) Nee's method</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.119</cell><cell>0.868 * ⧺</cell><cell>462</cell></row><row><cell>ASR</cell><cell cols="2">-0.168 ± 0. 035 4.835</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">0.515 ± 0. 086 5.980</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(B) Pagel's method</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.124</cell><cell>0.869 * ⧺</cell><cell>462</cell></row><row><cell>ASR</cell><cell cols="2">-0.166 ± 0. 034 4.826</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">0.564 ± 0. 090 6.282</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(C) Unit branch length</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.148</cell><cell>1.0 *</cell><cell>462</cell></row><row><cell>ASR</cell><cell cols="2">-0.179 ± 0. 032 5.577</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass</cell><cell cols="2">0.565 ± 0. 085 6.682</cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>*</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>Table S7 .</head><label>S7</label><figDesc>Analyses of the relationship between SSD (dependent variable) and ASR in socially monogamous and socially polygamous species, respectively. The analyses included birds and mammals.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Model/Path</cell><cell>Path coefficient ± SE</cell><cell></cell><cell>Z</cell><cell></cell><cell>P</cell></row><row><cell>Model 1a</cell><cell cols="3">PC= 0.991, df= 4, AICc= 15.9, ΔAICc= 0.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>AMB → ASR</cell><cell>-0.321 ± 0.121</cell><cell></cell><cell>-2.662</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.009</cell></row><row><cell>JMB → ASR</cell><cell>-0.210 ± 0.109</cell><cell></cell><cell>-1.920</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.059</cell></row><row><cell>ASR → SSD</cell><cell>-0.719 ± 0.122</cell><cell></cell><cell>-5.887</cell><cell></cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell></row><row><cell>Model 1b</cell><cell cols="3">PC= 0.142, df= 6, AICc= 23.7, ΔAICc= 7.8</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(AMB → ASR) 1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell>-</cell><cell></cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>JMB → ASR</cell><cell>-0.257 ± 0.112</cell><cell></cell><cell>-2.289</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.025</cell></row><row><cell>ASR → SSD</cell><cell>-0.719 ± 0.122</cell><cell></cell><cell>-5.887</cell><cell></cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell></row><row><cell>Model 1c</cell><cell cols="3">PC= 0.428, df= 6, AICc= 19.7, ΔAICc= 3.8</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>AMB → ASR</cell><cell>-0.358 ± 0.121</cell><cell></cell><cell>-2.958</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.004</cell></row><row><cell>(JMB → ASR) 1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell>-</cell><cell></cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>ASR → SSD</cell><cell>-0.719 ± 0.122</cell><cell></cell><cell>-5.887</cell><cell></cell><cell>&lt; 0.001</cell></row><row><cell>Model 2a</cell><cell cols="3">PC= 0.0, df= 4, AICc= 59.7, ΔAICc= 43.8</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>SSD → AMB</cell><cell>0.117 ± 0.077</cell><cell></cell><cell>1.503</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.137</cell></row><row><cell>SSD → JMB</cell><cell>0.102 ± 0.086</cell><cell></cell><cell>1.187</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.239</cell></row><row><cell>AMB → ASR</cell><cell>-0.321 ± 0.121</cell><cell></cell><cell>-2.662</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.009</cell></row><row><cell>JMB → ASR</cell><cell>-0.210 ± 0.109</cell><cell></cell><cell>-1.920</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.059</cell></row><row><cell>Predictors Model 2b</cell><cell cols="3">b ± SE PC= 0.0, df= 4, AICc= 50.5, ΔAICc= 34.6 t P</cell><cell>R 2</cell><cell>λ</cell><cell>n</cell></row><row><cell>(A) Monogamy SSD → JMB</cell><cell>0.102 ± 0.086</cell><cell></cell><cell>1.187</cell><cell>0.022</cell><cell>1.0 * 0.239</cell><cell>109</cell></row><row><cell>ASR AMB → ASR</cell><cell>-0.066 ± 0.038 1.717 -0.321 ± 0.121</cell><cell>0.089</cell><cell>-2.662</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.009</cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass JMB → ASR</cell><cell>0.087 ± 0.083 1.044 -0.210 ± 0.109</cell><cell>0.299</cell><cell>-1.920</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.059</cell></row><row><cell>(B) Polygamy Model 2c</cell><cell cols="2">PC= 0.0, AICc= 50.5, ΔAICc= 34.6</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.222</cell><cell>0.418 * ⧺</cell><cell>162</cell></row><row><cell>ASR SSD → AMB</cell><cell>-0.223 ± 0.048 4.607 0.117 ± 0.077</cell><cell cols="2">&lt; 0.001 1.503</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.137</cell></row><row><cell>Mean body mass AMB → ASR</cell><cell>0.399 ± 0.105 3.790 -0.321 ± 0.121</cell><cell cols="2">&lt; 0.001 -2.662</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.009</cell></row><row><cell>JMB → ASR</cell><cell>-0.210 ± 0.109</cell><cell></cell><cell>-1.920</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.059</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head>Table S10 .</head><label>S10</label><figDesc>Fit indices for the six path models, obtained by piecewiseSEM and lavaan. Values indicating acceptable fit are highlighted in bold.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Model</cell><cell cols="3">piecewiseSEM</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>lavaan</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>C</cell><cell>df</cell><cell>Pc</cell><cell>χ 2</cell><cell>df</cell><cell>Pχ2</cell><cell>TLI</cell><cell>CFI</cell><cell>RMSEA SRMR</cell></row><row><cell>1a</cell><cell cols="3">0.29 4 0.972</cell><cell cols="5">0.02 2 0.991 1.119 1.000</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>0.004</cell></row><row><cell>1b</cell><cell cols="3">11.6 6 0.065</cell><cell>8.9</cell><cell cols="4">3 0.031 0.764 0.858</cell><cell>0.143</cell><cell>0.101</cell></row><row><cell>1c</cell><cell cols="3">6.2 6 0.376</cell><cell>3.9</cell><cell cols="4">3 0.267 0.962 0.977</cell><cell>0.057</cell><cell>0.065</cell></row><row><cell>2a</cell><cell cols="3">34.7 4 0.000</cell><cell cols="5">30.6 2 0.000 -0.978 0.341</cell><cell>0.386</cell><cell>0.154</cell></row><row><cell>2b</cell><cell cols="3">34.7 4 0.000</cell><cell cols="5">30.6 2 0.000 -0.719 0.313</cell><cell>0.386</cell><cell>0.154</cell></row><row><cell>2c</cell><cell cols="3">34.7 4 0.000</cell><cell cols="5">30.6 2 0.000 -0.661 0.336</cell><cell>0.386</cell><cell>0.154</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">2.2. AIC-based model comparisons using real and simulated data</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>When monogamous and polygynous species are analyzed together, there is a statistically significant interaction between the effects of mating system and ASR (b ± SE = 0.218 ± 0.087, t =</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>2.510, P = 0.013).</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div><p>AL conceived the study. AL, <rs type="funder">RPF</rs> and TS designed the analyses. AL, IP, VB, JFL, JMG collected data. AL conducted the analyses with input from RPF. All authors wrote the paper. Acknowledgements: We thank <rs type="person">D. Gigler</rs>, <rs type="person">G. Milne</rs>, <rs type="person">H. Naylor</rs> and <rs type="person">E. Sebestyén</rs> for help in data collection, and <rs type="person">Z. Végvári</rs> for calculating environmental variables. A.L. was supported by the <rs type="funder">National Research, Development and Innovation Office of Hungary (NKFIH</rs>, grants <rs type="grantNumber">KH130430</rs> and <rs type="grantNumber">K132490</rs>), by the <rs type="funder">Hungarian Academy of Sciences</rs>, and by the <rs type="grantNumber">TKP2020-IKA-07</rs> project financed under the <rs type="grantNumber">2020-4.1.1-TKP2020</rs> Thematic Excellence Programme by the <rs type="funder">National Research, Development and Innovation Fund of Hungary</rs>. I.P. was supported by the <rs type="programName">ÚNKP-17-3 New National Excellence Program</rs> of the <rs type="funder">Hungarian Ministry of Human Capacities</rs>. V.B. was supported by an <rs type="funder">NKFIH</rs> grant (<rs type="grantNumber">K115402</rs>), the <rs type="funder">János Bolyai Scholarship of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences</rs>, and the <rs type="programName">ÚNKP-20-5 New National Excellence Program</rs> of the <rs type="funder">Ministry for Innovation and Technology from the source of the National Research, Development and Innovation Fund</rs>. J-F.L. and J-M.G. were supported by grants from the <rs type="funder">Agence Nationale de la Recherche</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">ANR-15-CE32-0002-01</rs>). T.S. and A.L. were supported by <rs type="funder">NKFIH</rs> grant <rs type="grantNumber">K116310</rs>. T.S. is funded by a <rs type="funder">Royal Society Wolfson Merit</rs> award and by <rs type="funder">ÉLVONAL</rs> <rs type="grantNumber">KKP-126949</rs>. T.S. and J-M.G. were supported by <rs type="funder">IE160592</rs> grant of the <rs type="funder">Royal Society-CNRS</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_kZxj7aX">
					<idno type="grant-number">KH130430</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_7RsH9rZ">
					<idno type="grant-number">K132490</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_KqGhaAS">
					<idno type="grant-number">TKP2020-IKA-07</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_VUjajaW">
					<idno type="grant-number">2020-4.1.1-TKP2020</idno>
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">ÚNKP-17-3 New National Excellence Program</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_aR2eMCR">
					<idno type="grant-number">K115402</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_j4McKg6">
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">ÚNKP-20-5 New National Excellence Program</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_ne8UXzN">
					<idno type="grant-number">ANR-15-CE32-0002-01</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_C6qgARz">
					<idno type="grant-number">K116310</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_C6Teftq">
					<idno type="grant-number">KKP-126949</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>* Pagel's lambda statistically different from 0, ⧺ lambda statistically different from 1. 1 Differences from oviparous species. 2 Differences from XY species; overall effect of sex determination on SSD: F2,146 = 2.8, P = 0.066; on ASR: F2,146 = 5.2, P = 0.006. For further explanation, see the footnotes of Table <ref type="table">1</ref> in the main text.</p><p>Table <ref type="table">S8</ref>. Results of the phylogenetic path analyses using the R package 'phylopath'. Models represent the mating opportunity hypothesis (Models 1a-c) and the mortality cost hypothesis (Models 2a-c). Analyses based on data of all species (birds, mammals, and reptiles; n= 97 species).</p><p>1028 Model structures are shown in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>. SSD: sexual size dimorphism, ASR: adult sex ratio, JMB and AMB: juvenile and adult mortality biases, respectively. The table shows the number of independence claims (k), the number of parameters (q), Fisher's C statistic (C) and its accompanying probability (P), C-statistic information criterion corrected for small sample sizes (CICc), and the difference in CICc from the top model (ΔCICc). A P-value less than 0.05 indicates a poor model fit (i.e. rejection of the model), whereas a ΔCICc &gt; 2 indicates substantial support for the top path model over the alternative models. Electronic Supporting Information: Appendix S1</p><p>References for data sources are provided in a separate excel file. The full dataset will be published together with references after the manuscript is accepted for publication.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Electronic Supporting Information: Appendix S2</head><p>Parameters of the allometric equations between body length and body mass (log10(mass in g) = a + b*log10(length in mm)) used for the calculation of mass estimates in reptiles. n is the number of species included in the analyses. Electronic Supporting Information: Appendix S3</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methodological notes on path analyses applied to comparative data</head><p>Several approaches have been proposed for applying path analysis in phylogenetic comparative studies <ref type="bibr">(von Hardenberg and Gonzalez-Voyer 2013)</ref>. However, some methodological aspects of this method still pose challenges for its phylogenetic applications.</p><p>Here we discuss two of such aspects: (1) the problem of using bivariate phylogenetic generalized least squares (PGLS) models to estimate correlations between variables in the path models, and (2) the reliability of AIC statistics to compare non-nested path models. We suggest ways to avoid these problems which may help further applications of path analysis to phylogenetic data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">The problem of using PGLS in path analyses</head><p>The analysis of multivariate dependent data is a notoriously thorny problem. In this dataset we, as in common with many similar analyses, had to deal with the problem of phylogenetic non-independence <ref type="bibr">(Harvey and Pagel 1991)</ref>. Techniques for analyzing cause-effect relationships using linear models are well developed <ref type="bibr" target="#b117">(Felsenstein 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr">Harvey and Pagel 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b119">Hansen and Martins 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b123">Pagel 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr">Freckleton et al. 2002)</ref>. These techniques are designed for analysis of data in which there is a dependent variable of interest, which is modelled as a function of independent predictors. In these models the effect of phylogeny is accounted for by modelling phylogenetic dependence in the residual term, and we have used these for several analyses (e.g. Table <ref type="table">1</ref> in the main text). However, analyses of data in which variables are treated as multivariate responses are much less common. Phylogenetic principal components analysis is one exception, although recent research has stressed that this may be more complex than previously realized <ref type="bibr" target="#b127">(Uyeda et al. 2015)</ref>.</p><p>Path analysis is a method of multivariate trait analysis that allows complex dependencies among variables to be modelled. von <ref type="bibr">Hardenberg &amp; Gonzalez-Voyer (2013)</ref> presented a method for performing path analysis on phylogenetically dependent data. This approach accounts for phylogenetic non-independence through constructing a series of bivariate PGLS models in which one variable is treated as the dependent variable, and the other is the independent variable. Importantly, this approach permits variable levels of dependence to be modelled through estimating Pagel's λ, which accounts for varying contributions of phylogeny to trait variation.</p><p>However the analysis of such data is complex. Consider a simple example, in which we have three variables x, y, and z. If we model x → y (i.e. where x is the predictor and y is the response variable) using the PGLS-λ approach, we might well estimate a different correlation than if we model y → x. This is because in PGLS the estimate of λ depends on the direction of the relationship, and this affects the estimate of the correlation. In path analysis correlations between pairs of variables are the input and the directionality of the statistical model should not be an issue. Specifically, the net correlation rxz should then be the product of the component pairwise correlations, i.e. rxz = rxy × ryz. However, if we use PGLS and λ  0 and λ  1 (as in most cases in our analyses, see Table <ref type="table">1</ref> in the main text), then in general rxz = rxy × ryz  ryx × ryz = rxz. We would therefore prefer to avoid an arbitrary decision about the directionality of the model to affect the estimate of the coefficient.</p><p>In our analyses we overcame the above difficulties by avoiding the use of bivariate PGLS models to estimate correlations between the variables in the path models. We followed the approach proposed by <ref type="bibr">Santos (2012)</ref>, in which first we calculated λ for each individual variable and conducted a phylogenetic transformation on the variable using that estimate of λ.</p><p>Then we fitted path models to these already transformed data using ordinary fitting methods developed for fitting path models to non-phylogenetic data. Details of the analyses are described in the Methods section of the main text.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">The problem of comparing non-nested path models by AIC statistics</head><p>In phylogenetic comparative studies the direction of causality between variables is often unknown, and different evolutionary hypotheses may propose opposing cause -effect relationships (like the mating competition and the mortality cost hypotheses in our study, see Fig. <ref type="figure">S1</ref>). These hypotheses may be represented by different path models, and then their fit to the data can be compared by some comparative fit indices, most commonly by AIC (West et al. 2012). However, simulations suggest that conclusions of path model comparisons based on information theory approach (like AIC) can be unreliable <ref type="bibr" target="#b124">(Preacher and Merkle 2012)</ref>. In addition the competing models can be non-nested (non-hierarchical) (e.g. Models 1a versus 2a in Fig. <ref type="figure">S1</ref>), for which AIC-based comparison should be applied with caution <ref type="bibr" target="#b121">(Kline 2015)</ref>.</p><p>To explore the problem of model comparison in the context of our study, first we fitted our path models to the real dataset by two alternative methods: (1) by covariance matrix comparison, as implemented in the R package lavaan (Rosseell 2012), and (2) by piecewise structural equation modelling (or d-separation) method, as implemented in the piecewiseSEM <ref type="bibr">(Lefcheck 2016)</ref> package. We compared path coefficient estimates and various model fit indices between these two methods to evaluate whether they produce consistent conclusions.</p><p>Second, we used the same two methods and R implementations to fit the models to simulated datasets, and tested which of the methods produces more reliable (less biased) model comparisons.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Fitting path models to real data</head><p>The general steps of model fitting procedure we followed in this study are described in the Methods section of the main text. We performed model fitting with the two R packages We found that the two methods produced highly consistent estimates for the standardized path coefficients in all path models (piecewiseSEM: Table <ref type="table">1</ref> in the main text, lavaan: Table <ref type="table">S9</ref> below). The effect of juvenile mortality on ASR was marginally not significant in most piecewiseSEM models whereas it was significant with all lavaan models.</p><p>For all other relationships the two methods produced consistent results.</p><p>The two methods also produced highly consistent results for model fit as evaluated by global fit indices (i.e. C and χ 2 statistics, respectively, see Table <ref type="table">S10</ref>). The only difference was that for Model 1b piecewiseSEM indicated 'marginally acceptable' model fit whereas lavaan indicated poor model fit for this path model. The other fit indices (TLI, CFI, RMSEA, and SRMR) suggest conclusions that are fully consistent with C statistics and χ 2 tests, i.e.</p><p>acceptable fit for Models 1a and 1c by all of these indices and unacceptable fit for all other models (Table <ref type="table">S10</ref>).  <ref type="table">S11</ref>), a result consistent with global model fit evaluation (see Table <ref type="table">S10</ref>). ΔAICc values suggested strong support for this model in all comparisons (ΔAICc ≥ 4.1, Table <ref type="table">S11</ref>). In contrast, lavaan results were inconsistent with global model fit evaluation because it gave very strong support for Model 2c (Table <ref type="table">S11</ref>), a model that had an unacceptable fit by all fit indices (see Table <ref type="table">S10</ref>). Using simulated data, we found that piecewiseSEM produced less biased results than lavaan.</p><p>First, in most cases mean simulated ΔAIC values were small and there was no strong bias in favour of one specific model (see ΔAICsimulation in Table <ref type="table">S11</ref>), as one would expect with random data. The only exception was the comparison between Model 1a and Model 2a in which simulated ΔAIC produced by piecewiseSEM was 7.4, favouring Model 1a. Importantly, however, these simulations indicated only a low probability for random data resulting in as large or larger AIC differences (43.2) in support for Model 1a than the ΔAIC values we obtained with real data (see low P≥ΔAIC_sim values in Table <ref type="table">S11</ref>), suggesting that support for Model 1a was unlikely the result of biased AIC estimates.</p><p>In </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparative analysis of allometry for sexual size dimorphism: assessing Rensch&apos;s rule</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Abouheif</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fairbairn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. Nat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">149</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="540" to="562" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sexual dimorphism in body size and the origin of sex-determination systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Adkins-Regan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Reeve</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. Nat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">183</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="519" to="536" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Macroecological patterns of sexual size dimorphism in turtles of the world</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Agha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ennen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Nowakowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sweat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Todd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Evol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="336" to="345" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating adult sex ratios in nature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ancona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Dénes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Krüger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Beissinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">372</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 20160313</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Sexual Selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Princeton, New Jersey</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Camera-trapping provides insights into adult sex ratio variability in felids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Anile</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Devillard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mamm. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="168" to="179" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T.-L</forename><surname>Ashman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bachtrog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Blackmon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Goldberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kitano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Mank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Mayrose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Otto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Peichel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Pennell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Perrin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Valenzuela</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Vamosi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Vamosi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tree of Sex: A database of sexual systems. Sci. Data</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">140015</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Elevation and latitude interact to drive lifehistory variation in precocial birds: a comparative analysis using galliformes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Balasubramaniam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Rotenberry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Anim. Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1528" to="1539" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fourteen nuclear genes provide phylogenetic resolution for difficult nodes in the turtle tree of life</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Barley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Spinks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Thomson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Shaffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Phylogenet. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1189" to="1194" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sex ratio, sex-specific chick mortality and sexual size dimorphism in birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Benito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>González-Solís</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Evol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1522" to="1530" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sex ratios in extant ungulates: products of contemporary predation or past life histories?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Berger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gompper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mammal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1084" to="1113" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Behavioral causes and consequences of sexual size dimorphism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Blanckenhorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ethology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1016</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="977" to="1016" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sex ratios and bimaturism differ between temperature-dependent and genetic sex-determination systems in reptiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Bókony</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Milne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Pipoly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Liker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Evol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">57</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Environmental harshness is positively correlated with intraspecific divergence in mammals and birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Botero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mccain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Safran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="268" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reproductive competition and sexual selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Clutton-Brock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">372</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 20160310</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Clutton-Brock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Mammal Societies. Wiley-Blackwell</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parental investment and sex differences in juvenile mortality in birds and mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Clutton-Brock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Albon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Guinness</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">313</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sexual dimorphism, socionomic sex ratio and body weight in primates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Clutton-Brock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Harvey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rudder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">269</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="797" to="800" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sex differences in ageing in natural populations of vertebrates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Clutton-Brock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Isvaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">274</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3097" to="3104" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evolution of sexual size dimorphism in reptiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>John-Alder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sex, Size and Gender Roles</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fairbairn</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Blanckenhorn</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="49" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Descent of Man, and Selection in Relation to Sex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Darwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1871">1871</date>
			<pubPlace>John Murray, London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolution in the Tropics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dobzhansky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="221" />
			<date type="published" when="1950">1950</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adult sex ratios in wild bird populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Donald</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ibis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">149</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="671" to="692" />
			<date type="published" when="1859">2007. 1859</date>
			<pubPlace>Lond</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Age-and sex-specific response to population density and sex ratio</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Dreiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cote</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Richard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Federici</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Clobert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behav. Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="356" to="364" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Demographic causes of adult sex ratio variation and their consequences for parental cooperation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Eberhart-Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Küpper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Carmona-Isunza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Vincze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zefania</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cruz-López</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kosztolányi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E X</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Barta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cuthill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Burke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Krüger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1651</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ecology, sexual selection, and the evolution of mating systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Emlen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Oring</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">197</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="223" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Size dimorphism, intrasexual competition, and sexual selection in Wattled jacana (Jacana jacana), a sex-role-reversed shorebird in Panama</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Emlen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Wrege</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Auk</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="391" to="403" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduction: The enigma of sexual size dimorphism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fairbairn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sex, Size and Gender Roles: Evolutionary Studies of Sexual Size Dimorphism</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fairbairn</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Blanckenhorn</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fairbairn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Blanckenhorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Sex, Size and Gender Roles</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Latitudinal variations in organic diversity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="81" />
			<date type="published" when="1960">1960</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Operational sex ratio, sexual conflict and the intensity of sexual selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Fitze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Le Galliard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecol. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="432" to="439" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetic analysis and comparative data: a test and review of evidence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Freckleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Harvey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pagel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. Nat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">160</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="712" to="726" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geographical variation in predictors of mammalian extinction risk: big is bad, but only in the tropics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">R P</forename><surname>Bininda-Emonds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Purvis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecol. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="538" to="549" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coevolution of parental investment and sexually selected traits drives sex-role divergence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fromhage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Jennions</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12517</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temporal Variation in Fitness Components and Population Dynamics of Large Herbivores</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Gaillard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Festa-Bianchet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Yoccoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Loison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Toïgo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Ecol. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="367" to="393" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anolis sex chromosomes are derived from a single ancestral pair</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gamble</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Geneva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Glor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zarkower</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1027" to="1041" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Growth patterns, sexual dimorphism and reproduction in African ruminants</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Georgiadis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Afr. J. Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An introduction to phylogenetic path analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gonzalez-Voyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hardenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Modern Phylogenetic Comparative Methods and their Application in Evolutionary Biology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Garamszegi</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="229" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating genetic capture-recapture using a chimpanzee population of known size</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A.-C</forename><surname>Granjon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rowney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Vigilant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Langergraber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Wildl. Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="279" to="288" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adult sex ratio influences mate choice in Darwin&apos;s finches</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Grant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Grant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12373" to="12382" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A large phylogeny of turtles (Testudines) using molecular data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Guillon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Guéry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Hulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Girondot</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. to Zool</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="158" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Body size and sex ratio in emergent stonefly nymphs (Isogenoides olivaceus: Perlodidae): variation between cohorts and populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Haro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Edley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wiley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Can. J. Zool</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1371" to="1375" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Harvey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Pagel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The comparative method in evolutionary biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Macroevolutionary patterns of sexual size dimorphism in copepods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hirst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kiørboe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">281</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Potential causes and life-history consequences of sexual size dimorphism in mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Isaac</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mamm. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="115" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Darwinian sex roles confirmed across the animal kingdom</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Janicke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Haderer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lajeunesse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Anthes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Adv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1500983</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Operational sex ratio predicts the opportunity and direction of sexual selection across animals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Janicke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Morrow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecol. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="384" to="391" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evolution of normal and reverse sexual size dimorphism in shorebirds and other birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Jehl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Ornithology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Johnston</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="86" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
			<publisher>Springer US</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boston, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Not all sex ratios are equal: The Fisher condition, parental care and sexual selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Jennions</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fromhage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">372</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sexual size dimorphism and sex ratios in dragonflies (Odonata)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Crowley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Brodin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. J. Linn. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="507" to="513" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Environmental sensitivity in relation to size and sex in birds: meta-regression analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nakagawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sheldon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. Nat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">174</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="122" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sexual size dimorphism and offspring vulnerability in birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kalmbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Benito</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sex, Size and Gender Roles</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fairbairn</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Blanckenhorn</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="142" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sex roles and adult sex ratios: insights from mammalian biology and consequences for primate behaviour</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kappeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">372</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 20160321</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reproductive success of male bank voles (Clethrionomys glareolus): the effect of operational sex ratio and body size</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Klemme</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ylönen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Eccard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behav. Ecol. Sociobiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1911" to="1918" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parental investment, sexual selection and sex ratios</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kokko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Jennions</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Evol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="919" to="948" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unifying cornerstones of sexual selection: operational sex ratio, Bateman gradient and the scope for competitive investment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kokko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Klug</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Jennions</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecol. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1340" to="1351" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adult sex ratios and their implications for cooperative breeding in birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Komdeur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kingma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">372</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">piecewiseSEM: Piecewise structural equation modelling in r for ecology, evolution, and systematics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lefcheck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Ecol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="573" to="579" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Male survival patterns do not depend on male allocation to sexual competition in large herbivores</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lemaître</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gaillard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behav. Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="421" to="428" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sex differences in adult lifespan and aging rates of mortality across wild mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lemaître</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ronget</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tidière</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Allainé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Berger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cohas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Colchero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Conde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Garratt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Liker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A B</forename><surname>Marais</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Scheuerlein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gaillard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8546" to="8553" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Liker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Freckleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Remeš</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sex differences in parental care: Gametic investment, sexual selection, and social environment</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2862" to="2875" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Divorce and infidelity are associated with skewed adult sex ratios in birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Liker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Freckleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="880" to="884" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evolution of sex roles in birds is related to adult sex ratio</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Liker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Freckleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1587</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mortality costs of sexual selection and parental care in natural populations of birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Liker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="890" to="897" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does the timing of attainment of maturity influence sexual size dimorphism and adult sex ratio in turtles?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Gibbons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Agha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. J. Linn. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="149" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evolution of social monogamy in mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lukas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Clutton-Brock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">341</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="526" to="530" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Sex Ratio in Wild Birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mayr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. Nat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="156" to="179" />
			<date type="published" when="1939">1939</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A dynamic gametheoretic model of parental care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mcnamara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Webb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Houston</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Theor. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">205</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="605" to="623" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impacts of the Cretaceous terrestrial revolution and KPg extinction on mammal diversification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Meredith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Janecka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gatesy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ryder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Teeling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goodbla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Eizirik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L L</forename><surname>Simao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Stadler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rabosky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Honeycutt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Flynn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ingram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Burk-Herrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Westerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ayoub</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Springer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">334</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="521" to="524" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Midford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Garland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Maddison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PDAP</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>PDTREE module of Mesquite</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sexual dimorphism, the operational sex ratio, and the intensity of male competition in polygynous primates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mitani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gros-Louis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Richards</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. Nat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="966" to="980" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parasites as a viability cost of sexual selection in natural populations of mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">297</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2015" to="2018" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sexual selection and sex ratios in Anolis lizards</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Muralidhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Zool</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">302</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="178" to="183" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A demographic theory on the evolution of mating systems as exemplified by birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolutionary Biology. Springer US</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hecht</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Prance</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
			<pubPlace>Boston, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Myhrvold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Baldridge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sivam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Freeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K M</forename><surname>Ernest</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">An amniote life-history database to perform comparative analyses with birds, mammals, and reptiles</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3109</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">It is time for a new classification of anoles (Squamata: Dactyloidae)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Nicholson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Crother</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Guyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Savage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Zootaxa</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3477</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="108" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A time-calibrated species tree of crocodylia reveals a recent radiation of the true crocodiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Oaks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3285" to="3297" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Orme</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Freckleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Petzoldt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Isaac</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Pearse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packa" />
		<title level="m">caper: Comparative Analyses of Phylogenetics and Evolution in R</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative mortality rates of male and female kudus: the costs of sexual size dimorphism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Owen-Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Anim. Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">428</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mortality costs of parental care and sexual dimorphism in birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">P F</forename><surname>Owens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">257</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Analysis of Phylogenetics and Evolution with R</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Paradis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fecundity selection theory: concepts and evidence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Pincheira-Donoso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="356" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The genetic sex-determination system predicts adult sex ratios in tetrapods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Pipoly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Bókony</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Donald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Liker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">527</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Covariation of sexual size dimorphism and adult sex ratio in parasitic nematodes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Poulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. J. Linn. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="567" to="580" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Costs of sexual selection in natural populations of mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E L</forename><surname>Promislow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">247</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b85">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mortality costs of sexual dimorphism in birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E L</forename><surname>Promislow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Montgomerie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">250</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="150" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b86">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A phylogeny and revised classification of Squamata, including 4161 species of lizards and snakes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pyron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Burbrink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wiens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Evol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">93</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b87">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why do females care more than males?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Queller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. R. Soc. London. Ser. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">264</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1555" to="1557" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b88">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evolution of parental cooperation in birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Remeš</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Freckleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tökölyi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Liker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13603" to="13608" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b89">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lavaan: An R package for structural equation modelling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Rosseel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stat. Softw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b90">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast molecular evolution associated with high active metabolic rates in poison frogs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2001" to="2018" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b91">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transitions between sex-determining systems in reptiles and amphibians</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Sarre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ezaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Georges</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Genomics Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="391" to="406" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b92">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sex ratio effects on reproductive strategies in humans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schacht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Borgerhoff</forename><surname>Mulder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">R. Soc. Open Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">140402</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b93">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adult sex ratios and reproductive strategies: A critical re-examination of sex differences in human and animal societies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schacht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kramer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kappeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">372</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 20160309</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b94">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Too many men: the violence problem?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schacht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rauch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Borgerhoff</forename><surname>Mulder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Ecol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="214" to="222" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b95">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Life-history evolution in reptiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Shine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Ecol. Evol. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b96">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cause and correlation in biology: a user&apos;s guide to path analysis, structural equations, and causal inference with R. 2nd editio</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shipley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b97">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistics of sexual size dimorphism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Hum. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="423" to="458" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b98">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multilocus phylogeny of the New-World mud turtles (Kinosternidae) supports the traditional classification of the group</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Spinks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Thomson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gidiş</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">Bradley</forename><surname>Shaffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Phylogenet. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="254" to="260" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b99">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2014a. Sex-biased survival predicts adult sex ratio variation in wild birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Liker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Freckleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fichtel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kappeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">281</biblScope>
			<date>20140342</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b100">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sexual size dimorphism in birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lislevand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Figuerola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sex, Size and Gender Roles</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fairbairn</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Blanckenhorn</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="37" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b101">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adult sex ratio variation: Implications for breeding system evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Székely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Weissing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Komdeur</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Evol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1500" to="1512" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b102">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does sexual selection shape sex differences in longevity and senescence patterns across vertebrates? A review and new insights from captive ruminants</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tidière</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gaillard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W H</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Lackey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Gimenez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Clauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lemaître</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3123" to="3140" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b103">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causes of sex-biased adult survival in ungulates: Sexual size dimorphism, mating tactic or environment harshness?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Toïgo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gaillard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oikos</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="376" to="384" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b104">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Parental investment and sexual selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Trivers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
			<publisher>Heinemann</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="136" to="179" />
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in In: Sexual Selection and the Descent of Man (ed. Campbell B</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b105">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Uetz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Hošek. 2019. The Reptile Database</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Freed</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b106">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">phylopath: Easy phylogenetic path analysis in R</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bijl</forename><surname>Van Der</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PeerJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">4718</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b107">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disentangling evolutionary cause-effect relationships with phylogenetic confirmatory path analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Von Hardenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gonzalez-Voyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="378" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b108">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical analysis of sex ratios: an introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">C W</forename><surname>Hardy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sex Ratios</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">C W</forename><surname>Hardy</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="48" to="92" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b109">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The ecological factors selecting for polygyny in altrical birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Wittenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. Nat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="779" to="799" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b110">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evolution of mating systems in grouse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Wittenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Condor</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="126" to="137" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b111">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">For further explanation, see the footnotes of Table 1 in the main text</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b112">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The influence of environmental harshness was tested in birds and mammals using data from Botero et al. (2014), in reptiles using data calculated in this study (following the method of Botero et al 2014), and in all species by pooling the harshness scores from the two studies</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b113">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PC is P-value for Fisher&apos;s C statistic for model fit, with non-significant values (&gt; 0.05) indicating an acceptable fit. ΔAICc indicates difference in AICc values between the most supported model (lowest AICc, Model 1a) and the focal models. ΔAICc &gt; 2 indicates substantially higher support for the best model than for the other model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S9</forename><surname>Table</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ΔAICc= 0.0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Phylogenetic path models representing the mating opportunity hypothesis (Models 1a-c) and the mortality cost hypothesis</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1042">1042 1043 1044 1045 1046 1047 1048 1049 1050 1051 1052 1053 1054 1055 1056 1057 1058 1059 1060 1061 1062 1063 1064 1065 1066 1067 1068 1069 1070 1071 1072</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ASR: adult sex ratio, JMB and AMB: juvenile and adult mortality biases, respectively (variables are explained in footnotes of Table 1). Path coefficient set to zero to keep the variable in the model. Model/Path Path coefficient ± SE Z P Model 1a PC= 0.991, df= 4, AICc= 15.9</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b114">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Length-mass allometry in snakes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Feldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Meiri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. J. Linn. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="172" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b115">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Length-weight allometries in lizards</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Meiri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Zool</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">281</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="218" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b116">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Allometry of sexual size dimorphism in turtles: a comparison of mass and length data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Regis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Meik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PeerJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 2914</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b117">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenies and the comparative method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Felsenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. Nat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b118">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetic analysis and comparative data: a test and review of evidence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Freckleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Harvey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pagel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. Nat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">160</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="712" to="726" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b119">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Translating between microevolutionary process and macroevolutionary patterns: the correlation structure of interspecific data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Martins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1404" to="1417" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b120">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The comparative method in evolutionary biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Harvey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Pagel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b121">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principles and practice of structural equation modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>Guilford</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b122">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">piecewiseSEM: Piecewise structural equation modelling in r for ecology, evolution, and systematics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lefcheck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Ecol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="573" to="579" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b123">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inferring evolutionary processes from phylogenies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pagel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Zool. Scr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="348" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b124">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The problem of model selection uncertainty in structural equation modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Preacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Merkle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b125">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lavaan: An R package for structural equation modelling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Rosseel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stat. Softw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b126">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast molecular evolution associated with high active metabolic rates in poison frogs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2001" to="2018" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b127">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative analysis of principal components can be misleading</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Uyeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Caetano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Pennell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="677" to="689" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b128">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disentangling evolutionary cause-effect relationships with phylogenetic confirmatory path analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Von Hardenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gonzalez-Voyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="378" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
