<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Generalized Simple Graphical Rules for Assessing Selection Bias</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2025-02">th February, 2025</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yichi</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale School of Public Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Haidong</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
							<email>haidong.lu@yale.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Internal Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Internal Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Generalized Simple Graphical Rules for Assessing Selection Bias</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2025-02">th February, 2025</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2502.00924v3[stat.ME]</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T19:34+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>selection bias</term>
					<term>causal inference</term>
					<term>causal diagrams</term>
					<term>SWIG</term>
					<term>inverse probability weighting</term>
					<term>epidemiologic research</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Selection bias is a major obstacle toward valid causal inference in epidemiology. Over the past decade, several simple graphical rules based on causal diagrams have been proposed as the sufficient identification conditions for addressing selection bias and recovering causal effects.</p><p>However, these simple graphical rules are usually coupled with specific identification strategies and estimators. In this article, we show two important cases of selection bias that cannot be addressed by these simple rules and their estimators: one case where selection is a descendant of a collider of the treatment and the outcome, and the other case where selection is affected by the mediator. To address selection bias in these two cases, we construct identification formulas by the g-computation and the inverse probability weighting (IPW) methods based on single-world intervention graphs (SWIGs). They are generalized to recover the average treatment effect by adjusting for post-treatment upstream causes of selection. We propose two IPW estimators and their variance estimators to recover the average treatment effect in the presence of selection bias in these two cases. We conduct simulation studies to verify the performance of the estimators when the traditional crude selected-sample analysis returns erroneous contradictory conclusions to the truth.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Selection bias is one of the fundamental obstacles to causal inference. The concept of selection bias encompasses various forms stemming from different mechanisms for individuals being selected into the study or analysis. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> The complexity of these selection mechanisms poses difficulty in a structural definition of selection bias, which has been continually evolving over the past two decades. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> Recently, a refined definition of selection bias that unifies different types of selection bias was proposed 3 by considering the true causal effect in the population prior to the selection process as the reference. This definition can be decomposed into two types: type 1 selection bias due to restricting to at least one level of a collider or its descendant, and type 2 selection bias due to restricting to at least one level of an effect measure modifier. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> With a clearer understanding of selection bias in place, recent methodological developments have also been dedicated to recovering causal effects in the presence of selection bias. Specifically, based on the fundamentals of causal diagrams, including directed acyclic graphs (DAGs) and singleworld intervention graphs (SWIGs), simple graphical rules were proposed to account for selection bias, alone or possibly combined with other issues (e.g., confounding bias or missing data). <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> However, there are still important cases of selection bias that cannot be addressed by these existing graphical rules. For example, in the graphical rules proposed by Mathur and Shpitser, one premise is that post-treatment variables cannot be conditioned on in their selected-sample analysis estimator. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> In addition, they focus on the conditional average treatment effect (CATE) rather than the average treatment effect (ATE, which is arguably more widely used). Some other existing graphical rules do not prohibit adjustments for post-treatment variables, but they are rather stringent to avoid confounding bias. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> In some cases, the covariate information available to address selection bias may only include post-treatment variables. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> In these cases, the identification of ATE may still be possible despite the rejection by the existing graphical rules. This highlights the importance of applying fundamental graphical rules to search for identification strategies. For example, approaches such as inverse probability weighting (IPW) methods and g-computation are powerful tools for recovering treatment effects if external information beyond the selected sample is available. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> In this article, we discuss two important cases of selection bias unaddressed by existing graphical rules. The first one represents the selection bias where a descendant of a collider of the exposure and the outcome is being conditioned on. The other is an example where sample selection is affected by the mediator. We prove that the average treatment effect (ATE) in both cases can be recovered by the g-computation or IPW methods if the external information on the covariates is available in the general population. The conditions for proving these identification strategies are provided and can also be used for addressing selection bias in similar cases. We propose two specific IPW estimators and their variance estimators for the ATE. We conduct simulation studies to verify the statistical properties of the proposed IPW estimators. In our hypothetical simulation settings, we show that the conventional crude complete-case analysis using the selected sample yields conclusions contradictory to the truth and can mislead decision-making.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Two cases of selection bias unaddressed by simple graphical rules</head><p>To detect and control for selection bias, researchers usually consider some simple graphical rules along with a specific class of identification formulas, and then define 'identifiability' (or 'recoverability') in a narrow sense of whether the treatment effect of interest can be identified by that class of formulas. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> Simple graphical rules are usually sufficient conditions for verifying that the treatment effect can be identified (or recovered) by a particular class of identification formulas. If these conditions are violated, it does not rule out the possibility that the effect of interest can still be identified by other formulas. In this section, we show two important cases of selection bias that cannot be addressed by the previously proposed graphical rules. The identification of treatment effects for similar causal structures by modified formulas will be discussed in later sections.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Setting</head><p>Consider n individuals (hereafter called "unit") in a randomized clinical trial whose outcomes are observed only among selected units. The selection is directly affected by a post-treatment variable observable among all units. Specifically, let A i be the binary treatment for unit i, Y i be the binary outcome, and S i be the selection. There are no other variables as confounders of A i and Y i . We define the direct upstream cause of the selection to be L i , which can be either a common effect of the treatment and the outcome (Case 1 in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>), or a mediator of the treatment on the outcome (Case 2 in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). When a unit is selected, i.e. S i = 1, we observe all variables (A i , Y i , L i ). When a unit is not selected, i.e. S i = 0, we observe its direct upstream cause L i along with the knowledge of A i or the rule of treatment assignment p(A i = 1) while the outcome Y i remains unobserved. We denote potential responses to a particular treatment A i = a i by (Y i (a i ), L i (a i ), S i (a i )), which are affected by the treatment in both cases. Under the consistency assumption, (Y</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">i (a i ), L i (a i ), S i (a i )) = (Y i , L i , S i ).</formula><p>Both Case 1 and Case 2 are important as they represent scenarios that may occur in real-world settings. For example, consider Case 1, where the study is a randomized trial of a prophylactic medication for malaria among susceptibles. The treatment A is a binary variable indicating assignment to the medication or not. The outcome of interest Y is the incidence of malaria or not.</p><p>The incidence of fever or not, L, directly affects the receipt of the blood test for malaria or not, S, for the outcome to be detected. It was suggested that the selection bias in this exact causal graph cannot be addressed to recover the ATE by the selection-backdoor criteria. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> In Case 2, the study is a randomized trial of a vaccine for an infectious disease with multiple endpoints. The treatment A indicates assignment to the vaccine or not. The outcome Y is the symptom of having a headache or not. The outcome is mediated by the incidence of infection, L, which also affects whether a unit reports the outcome status, S.</p><p>Assume that our goal is to recover the average treatment effect (ATE) in the general population prior to the selection process:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">δ ATE = E[Y (1) -Y (0)].</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">The failure by existing simple graphical rules</head><p>We focus on three existing simple graphical rules (i.e., the selection-backdoor criterion, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> the generalized adjustment criterion, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> and Mathur and Shpitser's graphical rules 8 ) proposed over the past decade. In Appendix A, we show that the two cases as discussed above violate these existing simple graphical rules, and the identification by their corresponding formulas is not guaranteed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Identification by the fundamentals of graphical rules</head><p>In this section, we first introduce a g-computation formula that can be used to recover the ATE by conditioning on post-treatment variables. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> Then we propose the inverse probability weighting for Case 1 and Case 2 of sample selection directly affected by a post-treatment variable L. When a unit is selected into the sample (i.e. S i = 1), we observe all variables (A i , Y i , L i ). When a unit is not selected (i.e. S i = 0), external information on L i among unselected units, along with the knowledge of A i or the rule of treatment assignment p(A i = 1), might still be available, but the outcome Y i is unobserved. In Case 1, the direct upstream cause of selection, L, is the common effect (i.e., collider) of both the treatment A and the outcome Y . In Case 2, the direct upstream cause of selection, L, is the mediator of the treatment A on the outcome Y .</p><p>to allow (i) observed confounders for the relationships between the treatment and post-treatment variables, (ii) unobserved confounders for the relationships between post-treatment variables and the outcome, and (iii) selection that is directly affected by the treatment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">G-computation formulas</head><p>In Breskin et al., <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> a special-case g-formula conditioning on a post-treatment variable Z was derived for identifying the ATE in a practical example of randomized controlled trials, demonstrating the utility of SWIGs. We extend their results by allowing the existence of confounders in an observational setting.</p><p>Specifically, we propose the following theorem.</p><p>Theorem 1 (Identification of the ATE by the g-formula under selection bias). Given a SWIG G(a)</p><p>containing the random treatment component A, the fixed treatment component a, the post-treatment variables Z(a), the selection variable S(a), the outcome variable Y (a), the observed pre-treatment variables X, and the unobserved pre-treatment variables U , the ATE is identified by</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">δ ATE,g = x ( z E[Y |A = 1, Z = z, S = 1, X = x]p(Z = z|A = 1, X = x)- E[Y |A = 0, Z = z, S = 1, X = x]p(Z = z|A = 0, X = x))p(X = x),<label>(1)</label></formula><p>i.e. δ ATE = δ ATE,g , if the following conditions hold:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">(C1) Y (a) ⊥ ⊥ S(a)|Z(a), X (C2) Y (a) ⊥ ⊥ A|Z(a), S(a), X (C3) Z(a) ⊥ ⊥ A|X.<label>(2)</label></formula><p>Intuitively, the first condition assumes that all paths between Y (a) and S(a) are blocked by Z(a) and X. This motivates the adjustment of some post-treatment variables Z(a) if it helps separate the outcome from the selection. The next two conditions assume that the effect of the treatment on both Y (a) and Z(a) are unconfounded by conditioning on different sets of variables.</p><p>Therefore, despite being motivated by an ad-hoc estimator for a special case, the g-formula</p><p>(1) will recover the ATE when some post-treatment variables can be conditioned on to address selection bias. The conditions can be viewed as derived graphical rules in this specific context. The example by Breskin et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> is a special case of our theorem (where they denote the post-treatment variable by W instead of L) by the following corollary.</p><p>Corollary 1 (Identification of the ATE by the g-formula given SWIG <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> ). The ATE is identified by</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">δ ATE,g = w E[Y |A = 1, W = w, S = 1]p(W = w|A = 1)- E[Y |A = 0, W = w, S = 1]p(W = w|A = 0),</formula><p>i.e. δ ATE = δ ATE,g , for the SWIG in Breskin et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> Taking Z = L, our Case 2 can be considered as a modification of the graph in <ref type="bibr">Breskin et al. 11</ref> where the derivation of the formula still applies. Moreover, it is straightforward to verify that the conditions (2) are satisfied in both of our cases by the SWIGs in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. We have the following corollary as examples.</p><p>Corollary 2 (Identification of the ATE by the g-formula given Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). The ATE is identified by</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">δ ATE,g = l E[Y |A = 1, L = l, S = 1]p(L = l|A = 1)- E[Y |A = 0, L = l, S = 1]p(L = l|A = 0),</formula><p>i.e. δ ATE = δ ATE,g , for the two SWIGs in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</p><p>The theorem implies that the ATE can still be recovered if we extend the two cases in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> to allow observed confounders X = (X 1 , X 2 , X 3 ) for A and (Y, L, S) (i.e., treatment-post-treatmentvariable confounders) in the full population, respectively, and unobserved confounders U for L and Y (i.e., collider-outcome confounders, or mediator-outcome confounders) as in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>.</p><p>Corollary 3 (Identification of the ATE by the g-formula given Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>). The ATE is identified by</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">δ ATE,g = x ( l E[Y |A = 1, L = l, S = 1, X = x]p(L = l|A = 1, X = x)- E[Y |A = 0, L = l, S = 1, X = x]p(L = l|A = 0, X = x))p(X = x),</formula><p>i.e. δ ATE = δ ATE,g , for the two SWIGs in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>.</p><p>Note that the ATE is identified even when X = (X 1 , X 2 ). In other words, the treatmentselection confounders, X 3 , are not required to be observed for recovering the ATE for the two cases in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> by this g-formula. The intuition is that, if there exists some post-treatment variable L(a)</p><p>as the direct cause of selection that helps separate Y (a) from S(a), the selection S(a) becomes a collider on the backdoor paths from the treatment A to L(a) and Y (a) that go through X 3 .</p><p>Therefore, these backdoor paths</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">(A ← X 3 → S(a) ← L(a) and A ← X 3 → S(a) ← L(a) ← Y (a))</formula><p>are blocked without the need to adjust for X 3 to correct confounding bias.</p><p>Proofs of Theorem 1 and its corollaries are given in Appendix B.</p><p>For estimation and inference by the g-formulas, plug-in estimators can be applied and the variances can be derived using the delta method or bootstrap. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Inverse probability weighting</head><p>Inverse probability weighting (IPW) methods intuitively create a pseudo-population where the distributions of covariates are balanced across treatment groups to fix the endogeneity of treatment and recover its effects. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> They have also been recognized and applied for the generalizability and transportability of study results to a target population of interest that is different from the study sample. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> In the context of selection bias, if external information on the distribution of the post-treatment variable L, is available, it is also possible to reweight the distributions of post-treatment variables such that they are not skewed by sample selection among the pseudo-population, thereby addressing selection bias. We propose a theorem to formalize the idea.</p><p>Theorem 2 (Identification of the ATE by the IPW method under selection bias). Given a SWIG G(a) containing the random treatment component A, the fixed treatment component a, the posttreatment variables Z(a), the selection variable S(a), the outcome variable Y (a), the observed pretreatment variables X, and the unobserved pre-treatment variables U , the ATE is identified by</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">δ ATE,IPW = E[ ASY p(S = 1|Z, X, A)p(A = 1|X) ] -E[ (1 -A)SY p(S = 1|Z, X, A)p(A = 0|X) ],<label>(3)</label></formula><p>i.e. δ ATE = δ ATE,IPW , if the following conditions hold:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">(C1) Y (a) ⊥ ⊥ S(a)|Z(a), X (C2) (Y (a), S(a)) ⊥ ⊥ A|Z(a), X (C3) Z(a) ⊥ ⊥ A|X (4) A Y L S X 1 X 2 X 3 U A a Y (a) L(a) S(a) X 1 X 2 X 3 U L A Y S X 1 X 2 X 3 U A a L(a) Y (a) S(a) X 1 X 2 X 3 U Case 1</formula><p>Case 2</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DAG SWIG</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>: Causal directed acyclic graphs (DAGs) and single-world intervention graphs (SWIGs) for Case 1 and Case 2 of sample selection directly affected by a post-treatment variable L with observed covariates X = (X 1 , X 2 , X 3 ) and unobserved covariates U . When a unit is selected (i.e. S i = 1), we observe all variables (X i , A i , Y i , L i ). When a unit is not selected (i.e. S i = 0), external information on (X i , A i , L i ) among unselected units might still be available. Case 1: The direct upstream cause of selection, L, is the common effect (i.e., collider) of the treatment A and the outcome Y . Case 2:</p><p>The direct upstream cause of selection, L, is the mediator on the causal pathway from treatment A to the outcome Y .</p><p>The first condition assumes that all paths between Y (a) and S(a) are blocked by Z(a) and X.</p><p>The next two conditions assume that the treatment and the potential responses of post-treatment variables (including the outcome, covariates, and selection) can be sequentially separated. The second condition for the IPW method ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>) is slightly different from that for the g-formula (2). The requirement by the IPW method that S(a) should be conditionally separated from A is due to the inclusion of the inverse probability weighting model for the selection to recover the ATE.</p><p>The ATE can be recovered through the IPW method in all causal graphs in Breskin et al., <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, and Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. They are special cases of Theorem 2 by the following corollaries.</p><p>Corollary 4 (Identification of the ATE by the IPW method given SWIG <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> ). The ATE is identified by</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">δ ATE,IPW = E[ ASY p(S = 1|W )p(A = 1) ] -E[ (1 -A)SY p(S = 1|W )p(A = 0) ],</formula><p>i.e. δ ATE = δ ATE,IPW , for the SWIG in Breskin et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> Corollary 5 (Identification of the ATE by the IPW method given Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). The ATE is identified by</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">δ ATE,IPW = E[ ASY p(S = 1|L)p(A = 1) ] -E[ (1 -A)SY p(S = 1|L)p(A = 0) ],</formula><p>i.e. δ ATE = δ ATE,IPW , for the two SWIGs in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</p><p>Corollary 6 (Identification of the ATE by the IPW method given Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>). The ATE is identified by</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">δ ATE,IPW = E[ ASY p(S = 1|L, X, A)p(A = 1|X) ] -E[ (1 -A)SY p(S = 1|L, X, A)p(A = 0|X) ],</formula><p>i.e. δ ATE = δ ATE,IPW , for the two SWIGs in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>.</p><p>The treatment-selection confounders X 3 cannot be omitted by the IPW method for recovering the ATE because the model for the selection deems it necessary to collect and adjust for these variables for correct causal model specification. This is different from the requirements by the g-formula for the same graph.</p><p>Proofs of Theorem 2 and its corollaries are given in Appendix B.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Estimation and inference by IPW estimators</head><p>Based on the identification result in Theorem 2, an unbiased estimator of the ATE is the Hovitz-Thompson (HT) estimator. We also propose an alternative IPW estimator, the Hájek estimator, which is a biased estimator of the ATE but reduces variance compared to the HT estimator. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref> We propose closed-form sandwich estimators of their variances to enable statistical inference of the ATE. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref> We use the two cases in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> as demonstrative examples by Corollary 5. We outline the steps of estimation and inference in Appendix C.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Simulation</head><p>We conduct simulation studies to verify the performance of our IPW estimators in both cases of Fig.</p><p>1</p><p>. The null hypothesis of the treatment effect is set to be true in the first case, but not in the second case. For each case, we generate datasets with varying sample sizes of n = 100, n = 1000, n = 10000.</p><p>The two IPW estimators are compared to the crude selected-sample analysis which only includes the observed treatment A in the simple linear regression of the observed outcome Y . In each setting, we simulate K = 10000 datasets and fit the models. We show that the crude analysis yields biased and misleading conclusions but our IPW methods accurately recover the true effect.</p><p>In Case 1, consider a randomized trial of a prophylactic medication for malaria among susceptible individuals. The treatment (A) is a binary variable indicating whether an individual is randomly assigned to the medication or not. The outcome of interest (Y ) indicates the incidence of malaria or not, which is detected by a blood test. The ground truth is that the medication has a null effect on the outcome. However, both the medication and malaria increase the risk of fever.</p><p>The incidence of fever or not (L) will be reported by these individuals. It affects participants'</p><p>willingness to receive the blood test for malaria or not (S). Those who have a fever are more likely to receive the blood test, while those who do not have a fever feel less motivated to be tested.</p><p>Specifically, We simulate observed data from the following distributions:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">A i ∼ Bernoulli(0.5) Y i |A i = a i ∼ Bernoulli(0.4) L i |A i = a i , Y i = y i ∼ Bernoulli(0.1 + 0.3a i + 0.5y i ) S i |L i = l i ∼ Bernoulli(0.1 + 0.8l i ).</formula><p>The true ATE of the treatment is 0, meaning that the medication on average has a zero impact on reducing the risk of malaria.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>: Case 1: simulation results of average point estimates of ATE, mean squared error, confidence intervals, coverage rates of the true ATE by the 95% confidence interval, and the type I error rate by the crude selected-sample analysis using the selected sample and the two proposed IPW estimators under different sample sizes. The true ATE is 0 for Case 1.</p><p>The crude selected-sample analysis (i.e., crude complete-case analysis) in Case 1 (red colored in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>) erroneously concludes a beneficial effect of the medication on reducing the risk of malaria.</p><p>The 95% confidence interval only contains the truth when the sample size is small due to substantial uncertainty. The coverage rates of the truth, zero effect, by its 95% confidence interval drops to zero as the sample size increases. In this null effect case, it implies that the rejection rate rises to 100% as the sample size increases. The intuition is that, with a low probability of measuring the outcome among those who do not have a fever, individuals who are not assigned to the medication and do not have malaria are unlikely to be selected. Without information from these healthy individuals, the effect of the medication is overestimated, leading to selection bias. As a result, the crude selected-sample analysis yields a misleading result by exaggerating the impact of the medication.</p><p>The results by the IPW estimators are summarized for Case 1 in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> (green and blue colored). Point estimates by both methods are correctly centered around zero. The mean squared error quickly drops and approaches zero. The coverage rates of the truth by the 95% confidence intervals converge towards 95% as the sample size increases. Equivalently, the type I error rate of rejecting the null hypothesis approaches 5%. Both methods are expected to fail to reject the null hypothesis at the intended size. The Hájek estimator has slightly smaller variances and narrower confidence intervals than the HT estimator.</p><p>In Case 2, consider a randomized trial of some vaccine for an infectious disease that assigns half of the individuals to the treatment group. One of the endpoints in this trial is the risk of having a headache within a certain period. The treatment (A) is random assignment to the vaccine or the placebo group. Its effect on the outcome of having a headache or not (Y ), can be directly through its side effects by increasing the risk. It can also be indirectly, mediated by the risk of being infected. The incidence of infection (L) affects the chance that they report whether they had a headache (S) during that period. Infected individuals are more likely to have a hospital encounter and report their symptoms in terms of headache, but those uninfected are less likely to report having headache symptoms or not unless through follow-up contacts. The data-generating process is</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">A i ∼ Bernoulli(0.5) L i |A i = a i ∼ Bernoulli(0.7 -0.5a i ) Y i |A i = a i , L i = l i ∼ Bernoulli(0.1 + 0.1a i + 0.5l i ) S i |L i = l i ∼ Bernoulli(0.1 + 0.8l i ).</formula><p>By Corollary 2, the true ATE is -0.15, indicating that the vaccination on average reduces the risk of headache by 15%.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>: Case 2: simulation results of average point estimates of ATE, mean squared error, confidence intervals, coverage rates of the true ATE by the 95% confidence interval, and the type II error rate by the crude complete-case analysis using the selected sample and the two proposed IPW estimators under different sample sizes. The true ATE is -0.15 for Case 2.</p><p>The crude selected-sample analysis of Case 2 (red colored in Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>) exhibits biased estimates of the ATE as small as -0.03. The 95% confidence intervals contain zero across all three settings.</p><p>Similar to Case 1, the coverage rate of the true ATE also drops to zero when the sample size increases. The rejection rate is lower than 10% when the sample size is 1000 or smaller, indicating a type II error rate higher than 90%. When the sample size reaches 1000, the type II error rate is still higher than 50%. The explanation is that the decreased chance of reporting whether an individual has a headache among those uninfected partly masks the beneficial indirect effect of the vaccine on reducing headaches through reducing their risk of infection. Therefore, the crude selected-sample analysis fails to reveal the actual beneficial impact of the vaccination on reducing the overall risk of headaches.</p><p>Tabel 4 shows the results of the IPW estimators for Case 2 (colored in green and blue). Both methods successfully recover the true ATE around -0.15 across all sample sizes. The mean squared error converges to zero. The coverage rates of the true ATE by the 95% confidence interval increase to the intended level. The rejection rates increases to 100% when the sample size is large enough.</p><p>The power of the two methods with a sample size of 1000 is greater than that of the crude selectedsample analysis with a sample size of 10000 by over 10%.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Discussion</head><p>Our work assesses and extends the utility of existing graphical rules for addressing selection bias.</p><p>Derived based on the fundamental principle of reading conditional independence using d-separation, existing simple graphical rules are inherently coupled with certain identification formulas and applicable to resolving selection bias for a specific subset of selection mechanisms. We show that, some important existing rules <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> can have stringent requirements on covariate adjustment to avoid confounding bias while correcting selection bias. For example, the adjustment for post-treatment variables is generally discouraged by these rules even if it helps separate the selection from the outcome. It is worth noting that while post-treatment variables should not be adjusted for in addressing confounding bias, these variables can indeed be accounted for when dealing with selection bias. We use two concrete examples using causal diagrams to demonstrate the limitations of existing rules and their identification strategies in addressing selection bias.</p><p>Specific to the two examples, we theoretically prove the identifiability of the ATE by the gformula and the IPW method when relevant external information in the full population is avail-able. The g-formula relies on adjusting for the post-treatment upstream cause of selection using a conditional distribution, while the IPW method seeks to balance the distributions of variables by modeling the probability of selection in the full population. The characteristics of these approaches are related to different sufficient conditions that we propose for recovering the ATE. They can be applied to complex observational settings with observed confounders for the relationships between the treatment and post-treatment variables, and unobserved confounders for the relationships between the upstream cause of selection and the outcome. For the IPW method, we also propose two estimators and their variance estimators for the statistical inference of the ATE. We outline the procedures and conducte simulation analysis to verify the performance of our estimators, which correct the serious bias by a complete-case analysis using the selected sample.</p><p>Beyond the two examples, our approach to correcting the selection bias validates and suggests possible directions for recovering the ATE when conventional approaches fail. First, researchers have shown that the g-formula and the IPW method are reliable alternatives to the oftentimes biased selected-sample analysis, for addressing selection bias and beyond. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref> Second, it is possible to adjust for post-treatment variables to recover the intended treatment effect without incurring overadjustment bias. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> The adjustment is in a broader sense that its conditional distribution might be marginalized, or it might be included in a model for the selection, rather than a simple inclusion of it in the outcome regression.</p><p>In conclusion, selection bias will continue to be a key topic in epidemiological research. Recent advancements in conceptualizing and addressing selection bias, along with future developments, will bring us closer to a comprehensive understanding of this critical issue.</p><p>the outcome Y and the selection S must be blocked by the conditioned variables, does not hold.</p><p>To summarize, by selection-backdoor criterion, conditioning on L violates the strong condition for ensuring no confounding bias, while not conditioning on L fails to address selection bias. The ATE is unidentified by formula (5).</p><p>A.2 The Generalized Adjustment Criterion by Correa et al. The first two conditions control confounding bias and the last condition controls selection bias.</p><p>The identification formula is</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">∆ ATE,2 = z (E[Y |A = 1, Z = z, S = 1] -E[Y |A = 0, Z = z, S = 1]) p(Z\Z T = z\z T |Z T = z T , S = 1)p(Z T = z T ),<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where Z is the full set of variables being conditioned on, and Z T is a subset of Z that requires external measurement. If we condition on Z = L, in either of both cases, condition (a) in GACT3 is violated. If the conditioning set is empty, Case 1 violates condition (b) and (c) while Case 2 violates condition (c). It proves that the ATE can not be identified by formula (6).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.3 Simple graphical rules under SWIG by Mathur and Shpitser</head><p>Graphical rules based on SWIGs were also proposed for addressing selection bias. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> It involves two sufficient conditions to analyze whether a conditional average treatment effect (CATE) can be identified by their formula. A premise of the two conditions in their framework is that the conditioning is on pre-treatment variables only. The first rule ensures no unadjusted confounding by conditioning on the selection and a set of adjusted covariates, and the second rule ensures no selection bias by conditioning on the same set of covariates. On its basis, a direct extension of their formula for the CATE to the ATE also follows formula (5). Despite changing the graphical rules, the ATE still fails to be identified in both cases when there is no conditioning, because the second condition that tries to separate between S(a) and Y (a) does not hold. Identification by conditioning on L is not accommodated in these simple graphical rules because L is a post-treatment variable. Therefore, the ATE is not identified by formula (5), again.</p><p>Appendix B Proof of theoretical results</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.1 Proof of Theorem 1</head><p>Proof of Theorem 1.</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">E[Y (a)] = x E[Y (a)|X = x]p(X = x) = x z E[Y (a)|Z(a) = z, X = x]p(Z(a) = z|X = x)p(X = x) = x z E[Y (a)|Z(a) = z, S(a) = 1, X = x]p(Z(a) = z|X = x)p(X = x) = x z E[Y (a)|Z(a) = z, S(a) = 1, X = x, A = a]p(Z(a) = z|X = x, A = a)p(X = x) = x z E[Y |Z = z, S = 1, X = x, A = a]p(Z = z|X = x, A = a)p(X = x),</formula><p>where the third equation is by (C1) in conditions (2), the fourth equation is by (C2) and (C3), and the last equation is by consistency.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.2 Proof of Corollary 1</head><p>Proof of Corollary 1. Let X be an empty set. The conditions (2) hold for the SWIG in Breskin et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> where Z = W . By Theorem 1, the g-formula is reduced to</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">δ ATE,g = z E[Y |A = 1, Z = z, S = 1]p(Z = z|A = 1)- E[Y |A = 0, Z = z, S = 1]p(Z = z|A = 0),</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.3 Proof of Corollary 2</head><p>Proof of Corollary 2. Let X be an empty set and Z = L. The conditions (2) hold for the SWIGs in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. By Theorem 1, the g-formula is reduced to</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">δ ATE,g = z E[Y |A = 1, Z = z, S = 1]p(Z = z|A = 1)- E[Y |A = 0, Z = z, S = 1]p(Z = z|A = 0),</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.4 Proof of Corollary 3</head><p>Proof of Corollary 3. Let Z = L. The conditions (2) hold for the SWIGs in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> taking X = (X 1 , X 2 , X 3 ) or X = (X 1 , X 2 ). By Theorem 1, the g-formula is</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">δ ATE,g = x ( z E[Y |A = 1, Z = z, S = 1, X = x]p(Z = z|A = 1, X = x)- E[Y |A = 0, Z = z, S = 1, X = x]p(Z = z|A = 0, X = x))p(X = x),</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.5 Proof of Theorem 2</head><p>Proof of Theorem 2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E[</head><formula xml:id="formula_20">1(A i = a, S i = 1)Y i p(S i = 1|Z i , X i , A i )p(A i = a|X i ) ] = E[ 1(A i = a, S i (a) = 1)Y i (a) p(S i (a) = 1|Z i (a), X i , A i = a)p(A i = a|X i ) ] = E[E[ 1(A i = a, S i (a) = 1)Y i (a) p(S i (a) = 1|Z i (a), X i , A i = a)p(A i = a|X i ) |Z i (a), X i ]] = E[ E[1(A i = a, S i (a) = 1)Y i (a)|Z i (a), X i ] p(S i (a) = 1|Z i (a), X i , A i = a)p(A i = a|X i ) ] = E[ E[1(A i = a)|Z i (a), X i ]E[1(S i (a) = 1)Y i (a)|Z i (a), X i ] p(S i (a) = 1|Z i (a), X i , A i = a)p(A i = a|X i ) ] = E[ E[1(A i = a)|Z i (a), X i ]E[1(S i (a) = 1)|Z i (a), X i ]E[Y i (a)|Z i (a), X i ] p(S i (a) = 1|Z i (a), X i , A i = a)p(A i = a|X i ) ] = E[ E[1(A i = a)|X i ]E[1(S i (a) = 1)|Z i (a), X i , A i = a]E[Y i (a)|Z i (a), X i ] p(S i (a) = 1|Z i (a), X i , A i = a)p(A i = a|X i ) ] = E[E[Y i (a)|Z i (a), X i ]] = E[Y i (a)].</formula><p>The first equation is by consistency. The fourth equation is by (C2) in conditions (4). The fifth equation is by (C1). The sixth equation is by (C2) and (C3).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.6 Proof of Corollary 4</head><p>Proof of Corollary 4. Let X be an empty set. The conditions (4) hold for the SWIG in Breskin et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> where Z = W . By Theorem 2, the IPW formula is reduced to</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">δ ATE,IPW = E[ ASY p(S = 1|W, A)p(A = 1) ] -E[ (1 -A)SY p(S = 1|W, A)p(A = 0) ] = E[ ASY p(S = 1|W )p(A = 1) ] -E[ (1 -A)SY p(S = 1|W )p(A = 0) ],</formula><p>where the second equation is by S ⊥ ⊥ A|W , i.e. there is no direct effect of A on S, for the DAG in Breskin et al. 11</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.7 Proof of Corollary 5</head><p>Proof of Corollary 5. Let X be an empty set and Z = L. The conditions (4) hold for the SWIGs in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. By Theorem 2, the IPW formula is reduced to</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">δ ATE,IPW = E[ ASY p(S = 1|L, A)p(A = 1) ] -E[ (1 -A)SY p(S = 1|L, A)p(A = 0) ] = E[ ASY p(S = 1|L)p(A = 1) ] -E[ (1 -A)SY p(S = 1|L)p(A = 0) ],</formula><p>where the second equation is by S ⊥ ⊥ A|L, i.e. there is no direct effect of A on S, for the DAG in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.8 Proof of Corollary 6</head><p>Proof of Corollary 6. Let Z = L. The conditions (4) hold for the SWIGs in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. By Theorem 2, the IPW formula is reduced to</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">δ ATE,IPW = E[ ASY p(S = 1|L, X, A)p(A = 1|X) ] -E[ (1 -A)SY p(S = 1|L, X, A)p(A = 0|X) ].</formula><p>propensity score or an estimated model from observed data. For simplicity of demonstration, we plug in the true propensity score. However, it has been shown that using the estimated propensity score model instead of the true model reduces asymptotic variances of the ATE. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref> For the propensity score model for sample selection, we may fit a logistic regression model among all units, both selected ones and unselected ones, enabled by available external information on L, to predict the propensity of being selected by its direct upstream cause:</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">p(S i = 1|L i ) = e β 0 +β 1 L i 1 + e β 0 +β 1 L i , i = 1, ..., n.<label>(7)</label></formula><p>As we obtain estimates β0 and β1 , we also get the estimated probability of being selected for each unit p(S i = 1|L i ).</p><p>Step 2 We compute an empirical estimate of the ATE by our choice of the IPW estimator.</p><p>The Hovitz-Thompson (HT) IPW estimator is</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">∆ ATE,HT = Ê[Y (1)] -Ê[Y (0)] = 1 n n i=1 A i S i Y i p(S i = 1|L i )p(A i = 1) - 1 n n i=1 (1 -A i )S i Y i p(S i = 1|L i )p(A i = 0) .<label>(8)</label></formula><p>An alternative IPW estimator is the Hájek estimator, which normalizes the weights to sum up to one. The formula is</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">∆ ATE,Hájek = Ê[Y (1)] -Ê[Y (0)] = n i=1 A i S i Y i p(S i =1|L i )p(A i =1) n i=1 A i S i p(S i =1|L i )p(A i =1) - n i=1 (1-A i )S i Y i p(S i =1|L i )p(A i =0) n i=1 (1-A i )S i p(S i =1|L i )p(A i =0) .<label>(9)</label></formula><p>In a randomized trial where p(A i = 1) is a constant, the Hájek estimator does not necessarily require the input of p(A i = 1) and p(A i = 0) in the formula since they get canceled in computation.</p><p>The Hájek estimator is also equivalent to the estimated slope from fitting a weighted least square regression of the outcome Y using the treatment A among all selected samples by the estimated probability of selection, p(S i = 1|L i ). However, the variance estimate of the regression slope does not properly account for the uncertainty in estimating the weights in the first stage.</p><p>Step 3 We calculate the variances for the two IPW estimators by the M-estimation theory. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref> Step 3.1 The first step is to compute a system of equations, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32</ref> where the parameters of interest,</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">denoted by θ = (β 0 , β 1 , E[Y (1)], E[Y (0)]), are estimated from n i=1 Ψ(A i , L i , S i , Y i ; θ) = n i=1    Ψ S (A i , L i , S i , Y i ; θ) Ψ Y (A i , L i , S i , Y i ; θ)    = 0,<label>(10)</label></formula><p>where Ψ S (•) denotes the subset of equations for fitting the selection model, and Ψ Y (•) denotes the equations for the IPW estimator of average potential outcomes. They are derived as follows.</p><p>Suppose we fit a logistic regression (7) for modeling selection, its estimating equations are</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">Ψ S (A i , L i , S i , Y i ; θ) =    S i -p(S i = 1|L i ) L i (S i -p(S i = 1|L i ))    .</formula><p>The estimating equations for average potential outcomes vary by the IPW estimator we choose.</p><p>For the HT estimator, the equations are</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">Ψ Y (A i , L i , S i , Y i ; θ) =    A i S i Y i p(S i =1|L i )p(A i =1) -Ê[Y (1)] (1-A i )S i Y i p(S i =1|L i )p(A i =0) -Ê[Y (0)]    .</formula><p>For the Hájek estimator, the equations are</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">Ψ Y (A i , L i , S i , Y i ; θ) =    A i S i (Y i -Ê[Y (1)]) p(S i =1|L i )p(A i =1) (1-A i )S i (Y i -Ê[Y (0)]) p(S i =1|L i )p(A i =0)    .</formula><p>Step 3.2 The second step is to estimate the asymptotic variance of the parameter estimates.</p><p>As n goes to infinity, the estimated parameters from equations (10)  </p><p>For the HT estimator, the average negative Jacobian matrix is</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">Â(θ) = 1 n n i=1         </formula><p>p(S i = 1|L i )p(S i = 0|L i ) L i p(S i = 1|L i )p(S i = 0|L i ) 0 0 L i p(S i = 1|L i )p(S i = 0|L i ) L 2 i p(S i = 1|L i )p(S i = 0|L i ) 0 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">A i S i Y i p(A i =1) • p(S i =0|L i ) p(S i =1|L i ) A i S i Y i L i p(A i =1) • p(S i =0|L i ) p(S i =1|L i ) 1 0 (1-A i )S i Y i p(A i =0) • p(S i =0|L i ) p(S i =1|L i ) (1-A i )S i Y i L i p(A i =0) • p(S i =0|L i ) p(S i =1|L i ) 0 1         </formula><p>.</p><p>For the Hájek estimator, it is</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">Â(θ) = 1 n n i=1          p(S i = 1|L i )p(S i = 0|L i ) L i p(S i = 1|L i )p(S i = 0|L i ) 0 0 L i p(S i = 1|L i )p(S i = 0|L i ) L 2 i p(S i = 1|L i )p(S i = 0|L i ) 0 0 A i S i (Y i -Ê[Y (1)])p(S i =0|L i ) p(S i =1|L i ) A i S i L i (Y i -Ê[Y (1)])p(S i =0|L i ) p(S i =1|L i ) A i S i p(S i =1|L i ) 0 (1-A i )S i (Y i -Ê[Y (0)])p(S i =0|L i ) p(S i =1|L i ) (1-A i )S i L i (Y i -Ê[Y (0)])p(S i =0|L i ) p(S i =1|L i ) 0 (1-A i )S i p(S i =1|L i )          .</formula><p>For both estimators, B( θ) can be directly computed by plugging in their respective estimating equations (10).</p><p>Step 3. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Remark</head><p>The above IPW estimators and their variance estimators can be similarly extended to observational settings in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> by Corollary 6. The estimation of the propensity score model for treatment becomes a necessity. Suppose we fit a logistic regression model p(A i = 1|X i ) = e α 0 +α 1 X i 1 + e α 0 +α 1 X i , i = 1, ..., n.</p><p>For IPW estimation, we replace p(A i = 1) by p(A i = 1|X i ) in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_25">8</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_26">9</ref>) to compute the </p><formula xml:id="formula_36">)<label>13</label></formula><p>It is updated by having an extra subset of equations for the propensity score model,</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">Ψ A (A i , L i , S i , Y i ; θ) =    A i -p(A i = 1|X i ) X i (A i -p(A i = 1|X i ))    ,</formula><p>and replacing all p(A i = 1) by p(A i = 1|X i ) in Ψ Y . Following the definition of the sandwich estimator (11), the variance estimators can also be derived.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>(Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure1: Causal directed acyclic graphs (DAGs) and single-world intervention graphs (SWIGs) for Case 1 and Case 2 of sample selection directly affected by a post-treatment variable L. When a unit is selected into the sample (i.e. S i = 1), we observe all variables (A i , Y i , L i ). When a unit is not selected (i.e. S i = 0), external information on L i among unselected units, along with the knowledge of A i or the rule of treatment assignment p(A i = 1), might still be available, but the outcome Y i is unobserved. In Case 1, the direct upstream cause of selection, L, is the common effect (i.e., collider) of both the treatment A and the outcome Y . In Case 2, the direct upstream cause of selection, L, is the mediator of the treatment A on the outcome Y .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Following 7 Definition 2 (</head><label>72</label><figDesc>the selection-backdoor criterion based on DAGs, the Generalized Adjustment Criteria were proposed as sufficient and necessary conditions for the assertion of identification or not by certain formulas. Among them, Generalized Adjustment Criterion Type 3 (GACT3) provides the most general conditions for recovering the ATE by a flexible formula that allows the combination of external data and biased selected data. The Generalized Adjustment Criterion Type 3 (GACT3) 7 ). Given a causal diagram G augmented with selection variable S, disjoint sets of variables A, Y , Z and a set Z T ⊆ Z; (Z, Z T ) is an admissible pair relative to A, Y in G if: (a) No element in Z is a descendant in G Ā of any W / ∈ A lying on a proper causal path from A to Y (b) All non-causal paths in G from A to Y are blocked by Z and S (c) Z T d-separates Y from S in the proper backdoor graph, where the first edge of every proper causal path from A to Y is removed.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Definition 3 (</head><label>3</label><figDesc>The graphical rules for assessing selection bias 8 ). Given a single-world intervention template G(a), the graphical rules are (C1) Y (a) ⊥ ⊥ A|S(a), Z (C2) Y (a) ⊥ ⊥ S(a)|Z.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>-</head><label></label><figDesc>converge in distribution to a normal distribution, θ d -→ N (θ, V (θ)/n). The covariance matrix, V (θ), is estimated by a sandwich estimator V ( θ) = Â( θ) -1 B( θ)( Â( θ) -1 ) T , ∇Ψ(A i , L i , S i , Y i ; θ), i , L i , S i , Y i ; θ)Ψ(A i , L i , S i , Y i ; θ) T .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>3 Step 4</head><label>34</label><figDesc>The final step is to estimate the variance of the estimated ATE,V ar( Ê[Y (1) -Y (0)]) = V ar( Ê[Y (1)]) + V ar( Ê[Y (0)]) -2 Ĉov( Ê[Y (1)], Ê[Y (0)]),based on the asymptotic covariance matrix estimate Ĉov( θ) = V ( θ)/n. Based on the asymptotic distribution, it is feasible to perform hypothesis testing andconstruct 100 * (1 -γ)% confidence intervals by Ê[Y (1) -Y (0)] ± Z 1-γ/2V ar( Ê[Y (1) -Y (0)]).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Ψ</head><label></label><figDesc>HT estimator and the Hájek estimator. The parameters to be estimated are updated by θ= (α, β, E[Y (1)], E[Y (0)]). Their estimating equations become n i=1 Ψ(A i , L i , S i , Y i ; θ) = A (A i , L i , S i , Y i ; θ) Ψ S (A i , L i , S i , Y i ; θ) Ψ Y (A i , L i , S i , Y i ; θ)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="14,131.52,197.09,298.36,397.81" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="17,131.52,197.09,298.36,397.81" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			
			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>This section has been temporarily removed from the manuscript for peer review.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Appendix A Failure of identification by existing simple graphical rules A. 1 The selection-backdoor criterion</p><p>The backdoor criterion was proposed to address confounding bias based on DAGs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30</ref> It was extended to be the selection-backdoor criterion to assess whether conditioning on certain variables Z simultaneously fixes selection bias and confounding bias. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> The criterion conditions are as follows.</p><p>Definition 1 (The selection-backdoor criterion <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31</ref> ). Let a set Z of variables be partitioned into The first two conditions extend the backdoor criterion to control for confounding. The third and fourth conditions allow recoverability from selection bias. If the criterion holds, the identification formula for ATE is given by</p><p>For each of the two cases in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>, we consider two estimators, conditioning on L (Z = L), or not (Z empty). For both cases, when we condition on L, condition (ii) in the selection-backdoor criterion does not hold. This condition requires that any path between the post-treatment variable L, if it is conditioned on, and the outcome Y must be blocked by the treatment or other pre-treatment variables. In other words, there must not be any causal paths between the post-treatment variable that we condition on, and the outcome. Alternatively, when there is no conditioning on any variable Z, condition (iii) in the selection-backdoor criterion, which requires any path between</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix C Steps of IPW estimation and inference</head><p>Step 1 Two models for the treatment and selection are required. The propensity score model in the randomized trial, p(A = 1), is to our knowledge. Researchers have the flexibility to plug in the true</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A structural approach to selection bias</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hernán</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hernández-Díaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="615" to="625" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Invited commentary: selection bias without colliders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hernán</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">185</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1048" to="1050" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>American journal of epidemiology</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward a clearer definition of selection bias when estimating causal effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="699" to="706" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A potential outcomes approach to selection bias</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kenah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="865" to="872" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Evolution of Selection Bias in the Recent Epidemiologic Literature-A Selective Overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Zivich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">282</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recovering from selection bias in causal and statistical inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bareinboim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Twenty-Eighth AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the Twenty-Eighth AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2410" to="2416" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalized adjustment under confounding and selection biases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Correa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bareinboim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simple graphical criteria for selection bias in general-population and selected-sample treatment effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mathur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Shpitser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://osf.io/65dju.2023" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Preprint re</note>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Graphical tools for detection and control of selection bias with multiple exposures and samples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Schnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kenah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2407.20027.2024</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causal effect identification by adjustment under confounding and selection biases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Correa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bareinboim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A practical example demonstrating the utility of single-world intervention graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Breskin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hudgens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="e21" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Models, reasoning and inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge university press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Single world intervention graphs SWIGs: A unification of the counterfactual and graphical approaches to causality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Center for the Statistics and the Social Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2013</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A general approach to causal mediation analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Imai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Keele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tingley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">309</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The central role of the propensity score in observational studies for causal effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rosenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rubin</forename><surname>Db</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moving towards best practice when using inverse probability of treatment weighting (IPTW) using the propensity score to estimate causal treatment effects in observational studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Austin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stuart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistics in medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3661" to="3679" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalizing evidence from randomized clinical trials to target populations: the ACTG 320 trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stuart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American journal of epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">172</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="115" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The use of propensity scores to assess the generalizability of results from randomized trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stuart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Bradshaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society Series A: Statistics in Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">174</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="386" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalizing study results: a potential outcomes perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Lesko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Buchanan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Westreich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="553" to="561" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Generalizing causal inferences from randomized trials: counterfactual and graphical identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dahabreh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Haneuse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1906.10792</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extending inferences from a randomized trial to a new target population</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dahabreh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Steingrimsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistics in medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1999" to="2014" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A review of generalizability and transportability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Degtiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Statistics and Its Application</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="501" to="524" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient estimation of average treatment effects using the estimated propensity score</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hirano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Imbens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ridder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1161" to="1189" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stratification and weighting via the propensity score in estimation of causal treatment effects: a comparative study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Lunceford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Davidian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistics in medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2937" to="2960" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new approach to causal inference in mortality studies with a sustained exposure period-application to control of the healthy worker survivor effect</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mathematical Modelling</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1393" to="1512" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The consequences of adjustment for a concomitant variable that has been affected by the treatment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rosenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society Series A: Statistics in Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="656" to="666" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Overadjustment bias and unnecessary adjustment in epidemiologic studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Schisterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Platt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="488" to="495" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Revisiting overadjustment bias</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Platt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="e23" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Principal stratification in causal inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Frangakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rubin</forename><surname>Db</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Causality</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge university press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Confounding equivalence in causal inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Paz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Causal Inference</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On variance of the treatment effect in the treated when estimated by inverse probability weighting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Reifeis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hudgens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">191</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1092" to="1097" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
