<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">In ation Transmission Diagnostics via a Bayesian Graph Vector Autoregressive Model with Markov Switching</title>
				<funder ref="#_yyW99yx #_5Kz9cP8">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_C5seFkd">
					<orgName type="full">Zhejiang Provincial Natural Science Foundation of China</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_c9tgG9T">
					<orgName type="full">Australian Research Council Discovery Project</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2024-04-01">April 1st, 2024</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jiali</forename><forename type="middle">•</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Fengjing</forename><forename type="middle">•</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-9518-7159</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jinran</forename><forename type="middle">•</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-2388-3614</idno>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Shangrui</forename><forename type="middle">•</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
							<email>zhaosr@whut.edu.cn.</email>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0001-7272-046X</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">You-Gan</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0003-0901-4671</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Jinran</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Mathematics and Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Wenzhou University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Wenzhou University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Australian Catholic University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Wuhan University of Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">Australian Catholic University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit6">Wenzhou University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>325035</postCode>
									<settlement>Wenzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Positive Psychology and Education</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Australian Catholic University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>4014</postCode>
									<settlement>Banyo</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">School of Mathematics and Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Queensland</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>4067</postCode>
									<settlement>St Lucia</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">School of Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wuhan University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>430070</postCode>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">In ation Transmission Diagnostics via a Bayesian Graph Vector Autoregressive Model with Markov Switching</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2024-04-01">April 1st, 2024</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.21203/rs.3.rs-3222276/v2</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: x x 2023 / Revised: x x 2023</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T20:22+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>In ation transmission</term>
					<term>Markov Switching</term>
					<term>Contemporaneous causality</term>
					<term>G7 Inflation t ransmission</term>
					<term>M arkov S witching</term>
					<term>C ontemporaneous c ausality</term>
					<term>G7</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The transmission of inflation i s a w idespread o ccurrence, a nd m anaging i nflationary pressures is a crucial macroeconomic challenge. Although inflation is a typical macroeconomic variable, its contemporaneous and lagged causal relationships have not been thoroughly investigated, which could result in missing important policy insights. The Bayesian graph vector autoregression (BGVAR) model can identify contemporaneous and lagged causal relationships among economic variables, but it lacks practical research on inflationary i nflation. To account for the structural transformation in the inflation transmission process, we propose a Bayesian graph vector autoregressive model with Markov switching (MS-BGVAR), which considers both regime switching and contemporaneous causality among macroeconomic variables. Our study focuses on analyzing the dynamics of inflation transmission relationships among G7 countries under different r egimes, a s t hese c ountries r epresent d eveloped n ations. W e use inflation data from 1971-2019, which shows two distinct inflation regimes within the sample pe riod. We conduct simulation experiments to generate moderately dimensional simulated data for both regimes and indicators, demonstrating the theoretical reliability of our model in accurately identifying graph structures. Finally, we apply the proposed model to identify structural breaks and causal transmission relationships in the inflation t ransmission p rocess o f G 7 e conomies, d emonstrating t hat t he proposed model has significant economic significance and good explanatory power in the selected target countries.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Inflation is a major issue involving political stability, economic development, and social harmony <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> . Maintaining a low and stable inflation rate is an important issue for macroeconomic management in most countries <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> . Since the outbreak of the oil crisis, it has been common for inflation to spread from one country to another country through international capital and trade channels <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> . A country's inflation management should not only take full account of the reality of domestic inflation but also pay close attention to the trend of global inflation <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> . Therefore, clarifying the dynamic transmission mechanism of inflation is of great importance for central banks and monetary authorities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Literature review</head><p>Many scholars have discussed and argued for an international transmission theory of inflation <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref> , which has now been applied to several economies. Many studies have looked at the Group of Seven (G7) countries, pointing to the existence of significant inflationary transmission relationships within the G7 <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref> , and have found that the United States is a major exporter of inflation <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> . Some studies focus on Eurozone countries <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and find that peripheral countries receive inflation from core zone countries while exporting inflation to them <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> ; in addition, a few Chinese scholars study the Greater China region and find that inflation in the Greater China region exists has a long-run equilibrium relationship <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> . Most of the above studies are based on impulse correspondence functions and variance decomposition methods to determine the correlation of inflation across countries, and such methods face the challenge of limited or undetermined reliability.</p><p>In contrast to traditional methods, the graphical model approach is a probabilistic model that uses a graph structure to describe conditionally independent relationships among multiple random variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> . Graphical models are powerful tools for studying multivariate time series <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> . Bayesian Graphical Structural Vector Autoregression (BGVAR) as a Gaussian graphical model (GGM) and structural vector autoregression (SVAR) model set, the variable relationships were divided into contemporaneous causal and lagged causal structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> . Also, the MCMC algorithm is adopted to estimate the graph structure, overcoming the limitation of traditional models that rely on residual terms for contemporaneous structure inference <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> . In addition, the BGVAR model allows researchers to understand the relationship between variables without economic theory support. Currently, BGVAR has been used to conduct empirical studies in finance, such as house price linkage <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> , financial risk transmission <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref> , crude oil and exchange rate transmission <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> , and stock price transmission <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> .</p><p>The BGVAR model has proven to be effective in dealing with model identification and selection for multivariate time series of moderate dimensionality <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> . Inflation is an important macroeconomic variable, but no research on constructing dynamic inflation transmission relationships based on BGAVR exists. This paper intends to fill this academic gap. In fact, the transmission relationship of inflation between countries is nonlinear, which is highly correlated with the economic environment and monetary policy <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> and evolves in different ways under different economic states <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23]</ref> . Markov Switching (MS) is the classical method for dealing with time series analysis influenced by regimes. Depending on the number of regimes given, the MS approach can efficiently identify the structural change points and variable relationships under each regime <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> . Thams [25] and Burdekin and Tao [26] have found evidence of structural breaks in the transmission process of inflation based on the MS model. However, it should be noted that they did not consider the contemporaneous causality of inflation under different regimes, which could reflect the impact and direction of policy actions <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">The motivation</head><p>According to the above literature review, it is important to consider regime switching when studying the inflation transmission relationship. However, there are still some shortcomings in the existing studies: (1) In the analysis of regime-switching of inflation, researchers have only considered lagged causality and neglected to examine contemporaneous causality. (2) The BGVAR method can identify causal relationships among economic variables and has been used in empirical studies in the field of finance, but there is almost a gap in the research in the field of inflation. (3) Currently, no relevant studies are combining MS and BGVAR methods to deal with structural breaks in the inflation transmission process and contemporaneous causality.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3">The contribution</head><p>To fill this gap, this paper combines MS with BGVAR to construct a new model for identifying inflationary transmission relationships. The main contributions of this study are as follows:</p><p>• In this paper, we established a Markov Switching Bayesian Graphical Vector Autoregressive (MS-BGVAR) model that considers both contemporaneous causality and structural transformations of inflation. The MS-BGVAR model on the one hand avoided pre-specifying the timing of shifts and allowed regime changes to be determined by potentially unobservable stochastic processes. On the other hand, it provided insight into the simultaneous and dynamic dependence of inflation under different regimes through causal interpretation.</p><p>• Simulation experiments were conducted to compare the graph structure, graph coefficients, and state transfer probability matrix with the real values, and the results showed that our proposed method performs well. Our study extended the BGVAR model at the algorithmic level.</p><p>• At the application level, G7 countries were selected, and real inflation data for these seven countries were used to verify the accuracy of the proposed model. We estimate a two-regime MS-BGVAR model in which the lagged causal structure reveals the linkage of inflation in different regimes and the contemporaneous causal structure reveals the impact of policy actions implemented in one country in different regimes on inflation in other countries. This study extended the research frameworks of the inflation transmission relationship and the application fields of the BGVAR model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4">The structure of the paper</head><p>The rest of the paper is organized as follows. Section 2 introduces the basic theory of MS and BGVAR. Section 3 describes the definition of the MS-BGVAR model and the inference scheme. Section 4 conducts simulation experiments to evaluate the proposed model on a simulated data set. Section 5 conducts a case study to analyze the identification results on real data. Finally, Section 6 concludes the paper. In addition, some symbols of this paper are given in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G+</head><p>The graph structure corresponding to A+(k). s 1:T The state sequence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>X(k)</head><p>The lagged data matrix under regime k. D(i) 2 The preliminaries</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">The Bayesian graphical structural vector autoregression</head><p>Bayesian Graphical Structural Vector Autoregression is an econometric model that combines Structural Vector Autoregression (SVAR) with a graph model and uses the MCMC algorithm to approximate the graph structure and parameters. Suppose Y t is a d-dimensional response vector, then the SVAR generation process is as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Y t = p s=0 B s Y t-s + ε t , t = 1, • • • , T,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where p is the lag order; B s , 0 ≤ s ≤ p is a d × d matrix of coefficients that represent the dependencies between variables. For s = 0, B s = B 0 represents the contemporaneous dependence between the variables. For 1 ≤ s ≤ p, B s represents the lagged dependence between variables; ε t is a d-dimensional vector of structural error terms, independent and identically normal, i.e., ε t ∼ N (0, Σ ε ). However, it is not possible to estimate the true value of B s directly from the data. Therefore, Ahelegbey et al. [15] proposed a method based on graphical models and Bayesian inference to identify the coefficient matrix of the SVAR model. Specifically, assume that there is a oneto-one correspondence between the coefficient matrix B s and a directed acyclic graph (DAG). The correspondence is expressed as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">Y j,t-s → Y i,t ⇐⇒ B s,ij ̸ = 0, 0 ≤ s ≤ p,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where Y j,t-s is the value of the j-th variable at ts moments and Y i,t is the value of the i-th variable at t moments. B s,ij , 0 ≤ s ≤ p is the value of the i-th row and j-th column of the coefficient matrix B s . For s = 0, B 0,ij ̸ = 0 indicates a contemporaneous causal relationship between Y j,t and Y i,t . For 1 ≤ s ≤ p, B s,ij ̸ = 0 indicates a lagged causal relationship between Y j,t-s and Y i,t . Then, according to the representation of the Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">2</ref>), B s can be decomposed into a connection matrix and a coefficient matrix. The decomposition is as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">B s = G s • Φ s , 0 ≤ s ≤ p,</formula><p>where G s , Φ s , 0 ≤ s ≤ p are the connectivity matrix and coefficient matrix of d × d, respectively. For s = 0, G s = G 0 represents the contemporaneous causal structure; for 1 ≤ s ≤ p, G s represents the lagged causal structure; the operator • represents the Hadamard product (i.e., B s,ij = G s,ij Φ s,ij ). When G s is known, Φ s has a one-to-one correspondence with B s as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">B s,ij =    0, if G s,ij = 0 -→ Y j,t-s ̸ → Y i,t Φ s,ij ∈ R , if G i,j|s = 1 -→ Y j,t-s → Y i,t .</formula><p>Thus, the estimation of B s can be converted into an inference for G s and Φ s , then the BGVAR model is generated. The standard equation of the BGVAR model is given as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Y t = (G 0 • Φ 0 )Y t + p i=1 (G i • Φ i )Y t-i + ε t , ε t ∼ N (0, Σ ε ).</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">The Markov switching</head><p>The Markov transition model is an extension of the simple transition regime model, which is more suitable for regime analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> . The basic idea of the MS is to capture the change from one regime or state to another through an unobserved Markov chain. The generation of Markov chains depends on the unobservable regime (state) variables and the state transition probability matrix. The Markov chain generation process is as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">P rob (s t = j | s t-1 = i) = p ij , i, j = 1, • • • , K,</formula><p>where p ij is the transfer probability of state i to state j. For convenience, only the bivariate regression model for the two regimes is briefly presented here, and the other MS models are</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">FU ET AL.</formula><p>based on this model <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29]</ref> . The basic definition of the bivariate Markov switching model is as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">y t = α st + x t βs t + v t , v t ∼ N 0, σ 2 st , with P =   p 11 p 12 p 21 p 22   ,</formula><p>where y t is the response variable; x t is the explanatory variable with a state correlation coefficient of beta st ; α st is the regime-dependent intercept; v t is an error term submitted to a normal distribution with a regime-dependent variance σ 2 st . The duration of the regime k (k=1 and 2) is calculated as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">D(k) = 1 1 -p kk .</formula><p>3 The proposed method</p><p>In this paper, we assume that there are no exogenous explanatory variables. Based on the theoretical knowledge in Section 2, the main idea of MS-BGVAR is to combine data under the same regime into new samples at each iteration and to identify causal relationships for each new sample until a predetermined number of iterations is reached.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">The model formulation</head><p>Y t is the d-dimensional response vector, and the form of the SVAR model with structural transformation is as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">Y t = B 0 (s t ) Y t + p i=1 B i (s t ) Y t-i + ε t , ε t ∼ N (0, Σ ε (s t )), t = 1, • • • , T,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where Y t is the d-dimensional response vector; p is the optimal lag order; s t is the regime (state) variable; B 0 (s t ) is the regime-dependent structural coefficient matrix of d×d. B i (s t ) , 1 ≤ i ≤ p is the regime dependent lag coefficient matrix of d × d; ε t is the d-dimensional structural error vector associated with the regime.</p><p>In the discussion of this paper, only two regimes (states) are considered, i.e. s t = 1 and 2, then the simplified form of Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">3</ref>) is as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">Y t = B 0 (k)Y t + p i=1 B i (k)Y t-i + ε t , B 0 (k) = 2 k=1 B 0 (s t )I {k} (s t ), B i (k) = 2 k=1 B i (s t )I {k} (s t ), Σ ε (k) = 2 k=1 Σ ε (s t )I {k} (s t ),<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where k = 1 and 2, and I {k} (s t ) is an indicator function that takes the value 1 when the state s t takes the value k at time t. Similar to the meaning and treatment of the variables in Eq. (1), B s (k), s = 0, 1, • • • , p is the coefficient matrix under regime k in Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">4</ref>), which can be decomposed as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">B s (k) = G s (k) • Φ s (k), 0 ≤ s ≤ p,</formula><p>where G s (k) and Φ s (k) are the d × d matrices that represent the causal graph structure and graph coefficient matrix between variables in regime k, respectively. Conditional on G s (k), the correspondence between Φ s (k) and B s (k) is as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">B s,ij (k) =    0, if G s,ij (k) = 0 -→ Y j,d k -s (k) ̸ → Y i,d k (k) Φ s,ij (s t ) ∈ R, if G s,ij (k) = 1 -→ Y j,d k -s (k) → Y i,d k (k),</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">Y = (Y 1 , • • • , Y T ) is a d-dimensional observation data matrix of length T , Y (k) is a d k × d-dimensional</formula><p>data matrix consisting of observations with state values equal to k. After the above steps, the MS-BGVAR model is defined as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">Y t = (G 0 (k) • Φ 0 (k)Y t + p i=1 (G i (k) • Φ i (k))Y t-i + ε t , ε t ∼ N (0, Σ ε (k)),</formula><p>where </p><formula xml:id="formula_15">G 0 (k) and G * (k) = (G 1 (k), • • • , G p (k)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_16">Y t = p i=1 A i (k)Y t-i + u t , u t ∼ N (0, Σ u (k)),</formula><p>where A i (k), 1 ≤ i ≤ p is the coefficient matrix of the reduced form of the dependent regime and</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">A i (k) = (I ny -B 0 (k)) -1 B i (k); u t = (I ny -B 0 (k)) -1 ε t , Σ u = I ny -B 0 (k) -1 Σ ε (k) I ny -B 0 (k) -1 ′</formula><p>and u t is the error term in the reduced form associated with the regime. Such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">A + (k) = (A 1 (k), • • • A p (k)), and G + (k) is the graph structure corresponding to A + (k).</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">The reasoning scheme</head><p>Statistical inference of graph models is a challenging task, and this study uses Bayesian inference methods as the basis for parameter inference <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> . In the Bayesian framework, since the marginal likelihood function of the graph structure can be obtained by integrating the graph coefficients, the sampling estimation of the graph structure can be achieved by directly relying on the observation data matrix divided by the state sequence. After estimating the graph structure, variable selection can be performed based on the conditional independence relationship between variables, and this practice can further improve the efficiency and accuracy of coefficient estimation. Bayesian inference consists of two steps: setting the prior distribution and MCMC sampling. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">A priori and posterior distributions</head><p>The prior distribution of the lag order p is discrete and homogeneous, and the optimal value of p can be eventually determined by the Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> . The specific form of the prior distribution of p is as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">p ∼ U (p min , p max ),</formula><p>where p min and p max are the minimum lag order and maximum lag order, respectively. p can only take integer values between p min and p max . In this study, we set p min = 1, p max = 4.</p><p>A graph G consisting of n nodes has a total of n(n-1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">2</formula><p>possible edges, so a graph G containing n nodes has 2</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">n(n-1)<label>2</label></formula><p>possibilities in the structure. It is assumed that each graph in the graph space has the same probability of being selected, that is, the prior distribution of the graph G is uniformly distributed. The specific form of this distribution is as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">P (G) = 2 -n(n-1) 2 , with: G ij ∼ Ber(n ij ),</formula><p>where n ij is the probability of the existence of a directed edge (G ij = 1) between node i and node j. The probability of each edge existing is generally considered to be 0.5, i.e., n ij = 0.5. Since the estimation of the state sequence s 1:T = (s 1 , • • • , s T ) relies on the Kalman filter, the inverse matrix of the covariance matrix, also known as the accuracy matrix Σ -1 u (k), is the key to the Kalman filter. Therefore, this study translates the estimation process of B 0 (k), B i (k), 1 ≤ i ≤ p and Σ -1 ε (k) into statistical inference on A + (k) and Σ u (k). In addition, since this paper is concerned with contemporaneous causality, the algorithm design process is based on</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">G 0 (k), G i (k), 1 ≤ i ≤ p to infer G + (k).</formula><p>To evaluate A + (k) and Σ -1 u (k), we considered two typical prior distributions widely used in the Bayesian VAR literature, Minnesota prior (MP) and the Normal-Wishart (NW) prior. Due to space constraints, we describe only the NW prior, and for Minnesota prior, we show the estimation results in numerical simulations. According to the NW prior, A + (k) and Σ -1 u (k) prior distributions are as follows <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> :</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">A + (k) ∼ N (A(k), V (k)), Σ -1 u (k) ∼ W ν(k), S -1 (k) ,</formula><p>where A(k) and V (k) are the prior expectation and prior covariance of A + (k), respectively. S(k) is the prior sum of squares, v(k) is the associated degree of freedom.</p><p>Since the prior distribution of A + (k) is conjugate to the posterior distribution, the posterior expectation and posterior covariance of A i (k) conditional on G + (k) are expressed as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">A i (k) = V i (k) V -1 i (k)A i (k) + σ -2 i (k)W ′ i (k)Y i (k) , V i (k) = V -1 i (k) + σ -2 i (k)W ′ i (k)W i (k) -1 ,</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">W i (k), i = 1, • • • , d are the explanatory variables of Y i (k) and Y i (k) is the i-th variable in Y (k). σ 2 i (k), i = 1, • • • , d are the residuals of the posterior of Σ u (k). The posterior distribution of Σ -1 u (k)</formula><p>is also the Wishart distribution, and its corresponding posterior parameters are as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">S(k) = S(k) + Y ′ (k) -X(k)A ′ (k) ′ Y (k) -X(k)A ′ (k) , v(k) = v(k) + (d k -p),</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">X(k) = (Y p+1-s (k), • • • , Y d k -s (k)) ′ , 1 ≤ s ≤ p is the (d k -p) × dp lagged data matrix.</formula><p>A(k) is the posterior mean of A + (k) with dimension d × d such that the elements of the relevant variables in A(k) store the corresponding elements in A i (k), i = 1, • • • , d and the rest (representing the unrelated variables) are restricted to 0 <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> . In addition, define</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">π k = (p i1 , • • • , p ij )</formula><p>′ as the variable consisting of the elements of the k-th row of the transfer matrix P , and the prior distribution of π k as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">π k ∼ Dir(c k1 , • • • , c kK ),</formula><p>where c ki , i = 1, • • • , K is the hyperparameter of the Dirichlet distribution. Since the focus of this study is on two regimes, the Dirichlet distribution degenerates to a Beta distribution, and the posterior distribution of π k is as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">[π k | s 1:T ] ∼ Beta(c k1 + count k1 , • • • , c k2 + count k2 ),</formula><p>where count k1 is the number of observations filtered from state k to state 1, count k2 is the number of observations filtered from state k to state 2, and this study sets c 11 = 1, c 12 = 1, c 21 = 1, and c 22 = 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">The MCMC Sampling</head><p>The previous subsection sets up the parameters to be estimated and the prior distribution of the graph. This subsection combines Bayesian inference with the sampling algorithm to solve the estimation problem of the parameters of interest. The joint posterior distribution of the parameters is</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">f (G 0 , G * , A + , s 1:T , Σ u , P | Y ) ∝ f (G 0 , G * , A + , s 1:T , Σ u , P, Y ) = f (Y | G 0 , G * , A + , s 1:T , Σ u , P ) f (G 0 , G * , A + , s 1:T , Σ u , P ),<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">f (G 0 , G * , A + , s 1:T , Σ u , P ) = f (s 1:T )f (G 0 , G * | s 1:T ) f (A + | G 0 , G * , s 1:T ) f (Σ u | G 0 , G * , s 1:T , A + ) • f (P | G 0 , G * , s 1:T , A + , Σ u ).</formula><p>To obtain the joint posterior distribution of (G 0 , G * , A + , s 1:T , Σ u , P ), one needs to compute Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_32">5</ref>), but solving Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_32">5</ref>) is very complicated, therefore, this paper uses the MCMC method to give its posterior distribution. The principle is to sample Monte Carlo simulation to obtain a set of samples from f (G 0 , G * , A + , s 1:T , Σ u , P | Y ), and to give the joint posterior distribution of (G 0 , G * , A + , s  The above procedure is a combination of Gibbs sampling and the MH algorithm. the MH algorithm is applied to update the graph structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> , i.e., a new graph G new is generated in each iteration based on the proposed distribution Q. The acceptance probability of G new is calculated as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">P (G new | G) = min P (Y | G new ) P (G new ) Q (G | G new ) P (Y | G)P (G)Q (G new | G) , 1 ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where P (Y | G) is the likelihood function, i.e., how well the graph G matches the observation Y , P (G) is the prior distribution of the graph G, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">Q (G new | G) is the proposed distribution.</formula><p>Assuming that all graph structures G in the graph space G exist with equal probability, P (G) = P (G new ), while taking the proposed distribution satisfying symmetry, i.e., Q <ref type="formula" target="#formula_34">6</ref>) can be simplified as</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">(G new | G) = Q (G | G new ), Eq. (</formula><formula xml:id="formula_37">P (G mew | G) = min P (Y | G new ) P (Y | G) , 1 .</formula><p>Let α be the result of the computation of P (G new | G) and compare the values of α and u, u being random numbers from a uniform distribution u(0, 1). If u &lt; α, the update from graph G to graph G new is acceptable, and graph G new becomes a sample in the Markov chain, otherwise, graph G new is "rejected". This process continues iteratively, and when the Markov chain converges to a smooth distribution, the samples subsequently generated are very close to those generated from the posterior distribution of the graph P (G | Y ). Based on these samples, the posterior probability e ij is calculated for each element G ij = 1 in the graph structure G, and G ij = 1 when e ij &gt; 0.5 and G ij = 1, vice versa.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">The numerical simulation</head><p>In this paper, we illustrate the performance of our model on a simulated data set, which is generated by the following processes:</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">Y t = p s=0 B s (s t )Y t-s + ε t , ε t ∼ N (0, Σ ε (s t )), t = 1, • • • , T,</formula><p>where Y t is an d-dimensional vector. p is the lag order, s t is a state variable and  <ref type="table"></ref>and<ref type="table" target="#tab_9">6</ref> .</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">s t = 1 or 2. B s (s t ), s = 0, • • • , p</formula><p>Table <ref type="table">2</ref>: Parameter setting in the data generation process.</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">Regime 1 Regime 2 B0 B0(1) =           0 0 -0.8 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0.5 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0           B0(2) =           0 0.8 0 0 -0.9 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0           B1 B1(1) =           -0.8 0 0 0 0 0.6 0 0.5 0 0 0.7 0 -0.5 0 0 0 0 0.5 0.7 0 0 -0.6 0 0 0.6           B1(2) =           0.6 0 0 0.8 0 -0.9 0 0 0 0 0 0 0.7 0 0 0 0.6 0 0 0 0 0 -0.7 0 0           Σε,ij Σε,ij(1) ∼ N (0, 1) Σε,ij(2) ∼ N (0, 100)</formula><p>Based on the above settings, a simulated dataset was generated. According to Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref> of the sampling steps, 10,000 iterations were performed in this study, and the latter 5,000 iterations were taken for estimation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>FU ET AL.</head><p>We verified the robustness of the proposed model using the two previously mentioned prior distributions, Minnesota prior(MP) and Normal-Wishart prior(NW). The recognition results of the simulated data are shown in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">5</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_9">6</ref>.</p><p>First, the inference method proposed in this paper can effectively identify the periods when Markov transformations occur in the simulated data. The estimated values of the transition probabilities are less different from the true transfer probabilities in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">7</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_11">8</ref>, in particular, the NW prior in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_11">8</ref>.</p><p>Second, since the graph structure is a data matrix with elements consisting of only zeros and ones, the accuracy can be used to measure the recognition of the graph. The formula for the accuracy rate is as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">Acc =</formula><p>True positive + True negative True positive + True negative + False positive + False negative .</p><p>For the simulated data, we find that the average recognition accuracy of the model corresponding to the NW prior is higher than the accuracy corresponding to the use of the MP, in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">3</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_5">4</ref>.</p><p>When using the NW prior, our proposed model identifies the causal graphs well under both regimes and has higher accuracy for lagged causal graphs than for contemporaneous causal graphs. Under Regime 1, the estimation accuracy of the lagged causal graph and the contemporaneous causal graph are 100% and 95%, respectively. Under Regime 2, the estimation accuracy of lagged causal graphs and contemporaneous causal graphs are 96% and 85%, respectively.</p><p>When using the MP, the recognition accuracy of contemporaneous causality graphs under both regimes is high, 95% and 85%, respectively, while the recognition accuracy of lagged causality is only 60%. We find that the NW prior is more accurate than the MP in identifying G1 because the idea of the MP deviates from the relationship between the variables in the simulated data.</p><p>Additionally, our model has a good estimation of the regression coefficients under NW prior, due to the small difference between the estimated and true values of the coefficients as reported in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">6</ref>. This good coefficient estimation is reflected in two ways: on one hand, the elements that are zero in the true coefficient matrix are also essentially zero in the estimated coefficient matrix. And on the other hand, the specific values of the non-zero elements of the estimated coefficient matrix are close to the values taken by the non-zero elements in the true coefficient matrix.   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Actual setup Estimated results</head><p>Regime 1 </p><formula xml:id="formula_43">G 0 G 0 (1) =           0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0           G 0 (1) =           0 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0           G 1 G 1 (1) =           1 0 0 0 0 1 0 1 0 0 1 0 1 0 0 0 0 1 1 0 0 1 0 0 1           G 1 (1) =           1 0 1 1 0 1 0 0 1 0 0 0 1 0 1 0 1 1 0 0 0 0 1 0 1           A + A + (1) =           -0</formula><formula xml:id="formula_44">          Regime 2 G 0 G 0 (2) =           0 1 0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0           G 0 (2) =           0 1 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0           G 1 G 1 (2) =           1 0 0 1 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 1 0 0           G 1 (2) =           1 0 0 0 1 1 0 1 0 0 1 0 1 0 0 0 0 1 1 0 0 1 0 0 1           A + A + (2) =          </formula><p>-0.12 0.00 0.63 0.80 0.00 -0.90 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.70 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.60 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.00 -0.70 0.00 0.00  </p><formula xml:id="formula_45">          A + (2) =           -0.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Actual setup Estimated results</head><p>Regime 1</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">G 0 G 0 (1) =           0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0           G 0 (1) =           0 1 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0           G 1 G 1 (1) =           1 0 0 0 0 1 0 1 0 0 1 0 1 0 0 0 0 1 1 0 0 1 0 0 1           G 1 (1) =           1 0 0 0 0 1 0 1 0 0 1 0 1 0 0 0 0 1 1 0 0 1 0 0 1           A + A + (1) =          </formula><p>-0.36 0.00 0.40 0.00 0.00 0.60 0.00 0.50 0.00 0.00 0.70 0.00 -0.50 0.00 0.00 0.30 0.00 0.75 0.70 0.00 0.00 -0.60 0.00 0.00 0.60</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">          A + (1) =          </formula><p>-0.80 0.00 -0.05 0.00 0.00 0.62 0.00 0.51 0.00 0.00 0.67 0.00 -0.49 0.00 0.00 -0.02 0.00 0.48 0.67 0.00 0.00 -0.50 0.00 0.00 0.56</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">          Regime 2 G 0 G 0 (2) =           0 1 0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0           G 0 (2) =           0 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 1 0 0           G 1 G 1 (2) =           1 0 0 1 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 1 0 0           G 1 (2) =           1 0 0 1 0 1 0 0 1 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 1 0 0           A + A + (2) =          </formula><p>-0.12 0.00 0.63 0.80 0.00 -0.90 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.70 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.60 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.00 -0.70 0.00 0.00</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">          A + (2) =          </formula><p>0.55 0.00 0.00 0.74 0.00 -0.80 0.00 0.00 0.12 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.57 0.00 0.00 -0.01 0.55 0.00 -0.04 0.00 0.00 0.00 -0.64 0.00 0.00  Finally, the estimated effect of this paper is valid for the graph structure. To assess the convergence of the graph structure, two indicators are used, namely the potential scale reduction factor (PSRF) and the multivariate PSRF (MPSRF), which are formulated in Gelman and Rubin [30] and Brooks and Gelman [31], respectively. If the value of either PSRF or MPSRF is 1.2 or less, then the Markov chain has achieved convergence, indicating that the graph structure has converged. Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">9</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_13">10</ref> reveal that the values of PSRF and MPSRF in both regimes are less than 1.20, and the convergence of the graph structures corresponding to the two prior distributions is confirmed <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> . In other words, the model proposed in this paper is robust under both prior distributions, MP and NW. However, the NW prior is better than the MP prior, therefore, in the experimental stage, we use the NW prior to estimating the parameters.  5 The case study</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">         </formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">The data</head><p>The Group of Seven (G7) is the representative of the developed countries and is composed of the seven most developed industrialized countries, the United States (US), Japan (JAP), Germany (GE), the United Kingdom (UK), France (FR), Italy (IT) and Canada (CAN). As of 2020, the G7's share of world GDP remains close to 50%. The G7, which plays a pivotal role in the world economy, has been closely linked in various political, economic, and cultural aspects since its establishment in 1976. However, it is this close connection that makes inflation within FU ET AL.</p><p>the G7 transmit to each other <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> . Standing in the long history, G7 economies have experienced not only periods of hyperinflation but also periods of low and stable normal inflation. Therefore, in this study, G7 is chosen as the target country to test the validity of the proposed model.</p><p>Since the consumer price index (CPI) is an important indicator of inflation, this paper uses CPI to represent the change in inflation (Inflation). However, there is a certain seasonality in CPI data. Then, in order to avoid the possible experimental results from this seasonality factor, the data chosen in this paper is the month-on-month CPI data of G7 economies. Moreover, due to the availability of data, the time range of the selected sample is January 1971 to December 2019. Data are obtained from the IFIND database. The range and magnitude of changes in inflation in the G7 countries within the sample are large. From a statistical point of view, there may be a regime shift in the level of inflation in these seven countries. Therefore, in the empirical analysis reported in the next subsection, we use the MS-BGVAR to explore the inflation transmission relationship in the G7 economies. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref> and Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">11</ref> show the time series plots and statistical indicators for these seven countries, respectively. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">The regime switching</head><p>In this paper, the MS-BGVAR model is applied to the inflation data of G7 economies. We first determine the lag order p = 1 according to the BIC criterion, in other words, only the effect of past period inflation on only current period inflation needs to be considered. Based on the relevant theoretical basis <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> , we name the two regimes as "high inflation regime" and "low inflation regime". The experiment was conducted with 10,000 samples and the statistical inference was made based on the remaining 5,000 samples. It should be noted that, in order to eliminate the error caused by the trend, we take a first-order differencing of the data in this paper before formal modeling.</p><p>The dates of regime switches identified in this study are highly correlated with the economic environment. The period 1971-1983 was extremely unstable for the world economy, and inflation levels were high during this period. At the same time, between 1972 and 1982, the inflation transmission relationship in the G7 countries was in Regime 2 (high inflation regime in Figure <ref type="figure">3(a)</ref>). While from 1990 on-wards, some countries made maintaining price stability the primary goal of macroeconomic regulation. Since then, most countries have entered a period of declining FU ET AL. inflation levels, remaining at a more reasonable level of inflation until 2019. Meanwhile, after 1990, the inflation transmission relationship in G7 countries has been in Regime 1 (low inflation regime in Figure <ref type="figure">3(a)</ref>) for a long time.</p><p>Moreover, the stability and duration of the high inflation regime in this experiment are lower than those of the low inflation regime, which is consistent with Thams [25]. The duration of the low and high inflation regimes is 52 months and 11 months, respectively. If the duration is higher than that of the low-inflation regime, there will be serious negative political, economic, and social impacts. The transfer probability matrices for the two inflation regimes are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_15">12</ref>, and their posterior probability densities are shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">4</ref>.   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">The causality relationship</head><p>In the previous subsection, we identified regime shifts in the transmission of inflation in the G7 economies. Then, this subsection specifically identifies the causal relationships between inflation in each country under both regimes, including contemporaneous and lagged causality, as shown in Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">8</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">9</ref>. Meanwhile, our node characteristics calculated based on the complex network analysis method are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_16">13</ref>. Also, the posterior probability density of the coefficients is shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">5</ref>. Based on the proposed model, it is found that the existence and strength of contemporaneous and lagged causality varies across regimes. This also reveals that the transmission relationship between inflation in G7 countries is regime dependent.</p><p>The values in Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">6</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">7</ref> show the probability of the existence of directed edges between countries, and the red ones are the values with a probability greater than 0.5. If the probability of the existence of a directed edge is greater than 0.5, then it means that there is a directed edge between nodes, i.e., there is a causal relationship between countries. In Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">8</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">9</ref>, we visualize the causality between countries.   From the perspective of lagged causality, network linkages are higher in the high inflation regime than in the low inflation regime, and lagged inflation in the U.S. has a strong spillover according to Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_16">13</ref>. In the high-inflation regime, lagged inflation in the U.S. points to Japan and France. Lagged inflation in Japan points to the U.S., Italy, France, and Canada. Lagged inflation in the U.K. points to Germany and Canada. Lagged inflation in Italy points to Japan. Neither France nor Canada issues a directional edge, suggesting that their lagged inflation does not affect other countries as illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">8(a)</ref>. In contrast, only the U.S. and France export directed edges in the low-inflation regime. The US points to Japan and the UK, while France points to Italy and Germany from Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">9(a)</ref>.  From the perspective of contemporaneous causality, the relevant policies adopted by one country may have an immediate impact on the inflation levels of other countries, and this immediate impact will be more pronounced in the low inflation regime. Under a high inflation regime, policies or actions implemented in Canada and France immediately affect the level of inflation in the United States in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_16">13</ref>. In contrast, under a low-inflation regime, the United States is the country that exports the most contemporaneous inflation according to Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">9(b)</ref>. The level of inflation in Japan, the U.K., Germany, and Italy are all affected by U.S. policy. At the same time, inflation in the U.K., Germany, and Italy reacts to French economic policy as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">9(b)</ref>.</p><p>In addition, according to Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">6</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">7</ref>, we also observe information on the strength of the causal relationship between countries. On the one hand, we find that regardless of whether it is a high or low inflation regime, a country's own level of inflation at the previous moment almost always has a strong effect on the level of inflation in that country at that moment, and this can be found in Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">6(a</ref>) and 7(a), where the values represent the probability of the existence of a directional edge between countries, i.e. the strength of the causal relationship. At the same time, we also find that the lagged level of inflation in the U.S. can have a large impact on the current level of inflation in Japan. On the other hand, the number of causal relationships between the current level of inflation in one country and the current level of inflation in other countries is small and the probability of an impact is low according to Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">6(b</ref>) and 7(b).</p><p>Last but not least, based on the causality analysis above, we find that the U.S., Japan <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> , the U.K., and France play an important role in the inflation transmission network, and this performance is related to their economic status. Also, this experiment obtains evidence of weaker homogeneity of Germany in the lagged inflation transmission network, which is consistent with Thams [25]. Regardless of the inflation regime, Germany is only affected by lagged inflation in one country.  The degree is calculated without taking into account its own lagged inflation Out-degree: the amount of national inflation exported to other countries. In-degree: the amount of inflation that the country receives from other countries. Total-degrees: the number of countries directly connected to the country.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">General discussion</head><p>The above experiments show that our proposed model has good explanatory power and that the conclusions drawn are of academic and economic interest. On one hand, the period of regime switching identified in this paper is similar to the study by Thams [25], which supports their findings to some extent. On the other hand, the study finds a large lag in the inflation linkage across countries in the high inflation regime, with nine directed edges in the lagged inflation transmission network as displayed in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">8</ref>. In contrast, the direct impact of a country's policies or actions on inflation in other countries is not evident in the high inflation regime, with only three directed edges in the contemporaneous inflation transmission network in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">8</ref>(b). Interestingly, U.S. actions in the low-inflation regime have an immediate effect on inflation in other countries. There are a total of 7 directed edges in the contemporaneous causal diagram for the low inflation regime, 4 of which come from the U.S. according to Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">9(b)</ref>.</p><p>Besides analyzing the regime shift in the inflation transmission process and specifying the specific direction of transmission, the proposed model can also help the central banks and monetary authorities of the sample countries to develop feasible inflation control measures. Since inflation is closely correlated across countries, we suggest that countries should consider not only their own actual situation but also the inflation situation of the countries related to them when controlling inflation. Otherwise, their own efforts may be undermined by others. In further, there is a strong contemporaneous causality due to the low inflation regime. Therefore, we recommend that countries should intensify their research on the past policies of other countries in order to develop corresponding inflation control methods more quickly and systematically. These recommendations apply to inflation management not only in the countries discussed in this paper but also in other countries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Conclusion</head><p>This study proposes a novel model for analyzing the inflation transmission relationship based on regime transformation and causality, defined as the MS-BGVAR model. The model combines Markov switching and Bayesian graph vector autoregression methods to solve the problem of estimating multivariate causality under different regimes. In addition, through simulation experiments, the proposed model can accurately identify contemporaneous and lagged causal relationships between simulated data with regime transitions and passes the convergence diagnosis. The G7 economies are selected as the target countries, and the proposed model is applied to the analysis of inflation transmission relationships in these seven countries to construct lagged inflation transmission diagrams and contemporaneous inflation leads under different regimes, and the proposed model is found to have better economic explanatory power on the inflation data. After obtaining the direction of inflation transmission, the central banks and monetary authorities of each country can accordingly formulate relevant initiatives in line with this pattern. In addition, this paper finds that the U.S. and Japan are the main exporters in the inflation transmission network and that inflation in the U.S. has the greatest causal impact on the level of inflation in other countries, especially the stronger causality between the U.S. and Japan. The relevant economic initiatives in the U.S. are more likely to affect the current inflation level in other countries under the low inflation regime. The main findings of this study are as follows.</p><p>• The proposed MS-BGVAR model considers both regime switching and contemporaneous causality among economic variables, realizing a theoretical extension of the existing approach.</p><p>• The constructed model was validated by simulation experiments and performed well in the identification of contemporaneous and lagged causal structures under both regimes.</p><p>• Applying the proposed model to the G7 economies, it is found that there is a significant regime shift in the inflation transmission relationship for these seven countries within the sample and that inflation linkages are higher in the high inflation regime than in the low inflation regime.</p><p>In fact, there are three possible inflation regimes, i.e., a high inflation regime, a medium inflation regime, and a low inflation regime. Therefore, future studies should give due consideration to increasing the number of regimes rather than just two regimes. Due to the availability of data, developing countries such as Brazil, Russia, India, China, and South Africa are not considered in this paper. In future work, the proposed model can be considered for application to developing countries. Furthermore, the experiments in this paper are based on month-onmonth data for G7 economies from 1971-2019, and the empirical results obtained may only be applicable to the sample countries. In the study of the inflation transmission relationship, the proposed model is validated by simulated data and is effective at the algorithmic level. Moreover, the proposed model can be applied to other financial areas, such as stock market linkage FU ET AL. first, financial riskiness, and exchange rate linkage, and may have better economic explanatory power for the available data, thus extending the research framework in the corresponding areas.</p><p>Only two regimes are included in the inflation transmission relationship among the G7 countries discussed in this paper, the high inflation regime and the low inflation regime. Therefore, in designing the program, we only code the MSBGVAR model for both regimes. However, among other economic problems, there may be more than two states, and our model can only identify the causal relationships between the families of economic variables under both regimes, which is a limitation of this paper. It should be noted that the number of regimes ex-ante is unknown which may cause a misspecification problem if we incorrectly assume the number of regimes, and we can determine the number of states using a restriction on state identification based on weighted feature vector centrality before applying the MS-BGAVR model <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> . If the state number is more than 2, we will extend our work to study three or four regimes in the future as follows: As the number of regimes increases, the dimensionality of the transfer probability matrix also increases. The elements of the rows in the transfer matrix follow the prior distribution of the Dirichlet distribution (when multidimensional, the Dirichlet distribution cannot be regarded as a Beta distribution), however, the remaining steps remain the same as those for the two states.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>are the connection matrices of d × d and d × (dp), respectively, and represent the contemporaneous causal structure and lagged causal structure under the representative regime k, respectively.Finally, by shifting to Eq. (3), we can carry the reduced form of the regime-transformed SVAR model, which is the Markov switching vector autoregressive model (MSVAR). The MSVAR model is as follows:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FU</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: The specific inference process of the MS-BGVAR model.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>is the sequence of d × d coefficient matrices. In this study, we set T = 600, d = 5, p = 1, and the settings of B s (s t ) and Σ ε,ij (s t ) are shown in Table2. The state transition probability matrix between the two regimes is P = Moreover, due to the A 1 (s t ) = (I -B 0 (s t )) -1 B 1 (s t ), we calculate A + = A 1 from B 0 , B 1 as shown in Tables5</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Trend graph of monthly inflation in G7 economies.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>2 Figure 3 :</head><label>23</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Probability of filtering between two inflation regimes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Posterior density plot of the transition matrix P of the inflation transmission relationship.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Posterior probability density map of the partial diagonal elements of the regression coefficient (A + ).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: The strength of causality among G7 countries under high-inflation regime</figDesc><graphic coords="21,269.88,158.10,184.25,66.62" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7: The strength of causality among G7 countries under low-inflation regime</figDesc><graphic coords="21,70.27,155.40,184.25,69.31" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8: Causality diagram under high inflation regime.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9: Causality diagram in a low inflation regime.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>22 FU</head><label>22</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1: Table of notation.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Symbol</cell><cell>Definition</cell><cell>Symbol</cell><cell>Definition</cell></row><row><cell>Yt</cell><cell>Response vector.</cell><cell>d</cell><cell>Dimension of the response vector Yt.</cell></row><row><cell>p</cell><cell>Optimal lag order.</cell><cell>Bs</cell><cell>Coefficient matrix, 0 ≤ s ≤ p.</cell></row><row><cell>B0</cell><cell>Coefficient matrix of contemporaneous dependencies.</cell><cell>εt</cell><cell>Structural error terms.</cell></row></table><note><p><p>Y Y = (Y1, • • • , Y T )</p>is the observation data matrix. T The Length of Y . Bi Coefficient matrix of lagged dependencies,1 ≤ i ≤ p. Gs The connectivity matrix, 0 ≤ s ≤ p. G0 contemporaneous causal structure. Gi Lagged causal structure, 1 ≤ i ≤ p. Φs The coefficient matrix corresponding to the graph Gs. yt The Response variables in MS model. xt The explanatory variables in MS model. st Regime (state) variables. pij The probability of transition from state i to state j. αs t The intercept in MS model. βs t The regression coefficients in MS model. vt The error terms in MS model. G0(k) Contemporaneous causal graph structure under regime k. n Number of nodes in the graph G. A+(k) Coefficient matrix in MSVAR model. ut The error term in MSVAR model.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Accuracy of graph structure inference(MP).</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Regime 1</cell><cell>Regime 2</cell></row><row><cell>G0</cell><cell>85%</cell><cell>90%</cell></row><row><cell>G1</cell><cell>60%</cell><cell>60%</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Accuracy of graph structure inference (NW prior).</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Regime 1</cell><cell>Regime 2</cell></row><row><cell>G0</cell><cell>95%</cell><cell>85%</cell></row><row><cell>G1</cell><cell>100%</cell><cell>96%</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Inference results for relevant parameters (MP).</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Inference results for relevant parameters(NW prior).</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Table 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Estimates of the transfer probability of simulated data(MP).</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Regime 1</cell><cell>Regime 2</cell></row><row><cell>Regime 1</cell><cell>0.9689</cell><cell>0.0311</cell></row><row><cell>Regime 2</cell><cell>0.2763</cell><cell>0.7237</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Estimates of the transfer probability of simulated data(NW prior).</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Regime 1</cell><cell>Regime 2</cell></row><row><cell>Regime 1</cell><cell>0.9353</cell><cell>0.0647</cell></row><row><cell>Regime 2</cell><cell>0.0456</cell><cell>0.9544</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>Table 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>The results of Model diagnostic (MP).</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Regime 1</cell><cell></cell><cell>Regime 2</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>G0</cell><cell>G1</cell><cell>G0</cell><cell>G1</cell></row><row><cell>PSRF</cell><cell>1.0001</cell><cell>1.0003</cell><cell>0.9997</cell><cell>1.0000</cell></row><row><cell>MPSRF</cell><cell>1.0051</cell><cell>1.0045</cell><cell>1.0064</cell><cell>1.0049</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>Table 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>The results of Model diagnostic (NW prior).</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Regime 1</cell><cell></cell><cell>Regime 2</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>G0</cell><cell>G1</cell><cell>G0</cell><cell>G1</cell></row><row><cell>PSRF</cell><cell>0.9995</cell><cell>1.0002</cell><cell>1.0001</cell><cell>1.0000</cell></row><row><cell>MPSRF</cell><cell>0.9995</cell><cell>1.0002</cell><cell>1.0001</cell><cell>1.0086</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head>Table 11 :</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Statistical indicators of inflation data for seven countries.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Min</cell><cell>Max</cell><cell>Mean</cell><cell>Std.dev</cell></row><row><cell>US</cell><cell>-2.100</cell><cell>14.760</cell><cell>3.963</cell><cell>2.976</cell></row><row><cell>JAP</cell><cell>-2.500</cell><cell>24.900</cell><cell>2.510</cell><cell>4.393</cell></row><row><cell>UK</cell><cell>0.200</cell><cell>26.870</cell><cell>5.472</cell><cell>2.800</cell></row><row><cell>GE</cell><cell>-1.000</cell><cell>7.920</cell><cell>2.636</cell><cell>1.922</cell></row><row><cell>FR</cell><cell>-0.730</cell><cell>15.160</cell><cell>4.169</cell><cell>4.063</cell></row><row><cell>IT</cell><cell>-0.560</cell><cell>25.240</cell><cell>6.254</cell><cell>6.027</cell></row><row><cell>CAN</cell><cell>-4.550</cell><cell>23.380</cell><cell>4.327</cell><cell>4.872</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head>Table 12 :</head><label>12</label><figDesc>The posterior transition probability of inflation environment.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>High inflation regime</cell><cell>Low inflation regime</cell></row><row><cell>High inflation regime</cell><cell>0.9772</cell><cell>0.0228</cell></row><row><cell>Low inflation regime</cell><cell>0.1134</cell><cell>0.8866</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_16"><head>Table 13 :</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Nodes Characteristics of Lagged Inflation Transmission Networks.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>high inflation regime</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>low inflation regime</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="6">Out-degree In-degree Total-degrees Out-degree In-degree Total-degrees</cell></row><row><cell>US</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>JAP</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>UK</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>GE</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>FR</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>IT</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>CAN</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>8</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>(a) The strength of lagged causality (b) The strength of Contemporaneous causality</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div><p>* This work was supported in part by the <rs type="funder">Australian Research Council Discovery Project</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">DP160104292</rs>), <rs type="funder">Zhejiang Provincial Natural Science Foundation of China</rs> (Grant No: <rs type="grantNumber">LY19A010014</rs>), "<rs type="programName">Chunhui Program" Collaborative Scientific R esearch P roject</rs> ( <rs type="grantNumber">202202004</rs>), a nd t he S cience a nd T echnology I nnovation A ctivity P lan for University Students in Zhejiang Province (Grant No: <rs type="grantNumber">2021R429049</rs>).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_c9tgG9T">
					<idno type="grant-number">DP160104292</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_C5seFkd">
					<idno type="grant-number">LY19A010014</idno>
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">Chunhui Program&quot; Collaborative Scientific R esearch P roject</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_yyW99yx">
					<idno type="grant-number">202202004</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_5Kz9cP8">
					<idno type="grant-number">2021R429049</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does inflation affect economic growth? The relevance of the debate for Indonesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chowdhury</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Asia Pacific Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inflation in Malaysia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M-Y And</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H-B</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="425" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oil price shocks and the macroeconomy: What has been learned since 1996</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Leiby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I K</forename><surname>Paik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Energy Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What is the globalisation of inflation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Altansukh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bratsiotis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Osborn D R</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Dynamics and Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Imported inflation, 1973-74 and the accommodation issue</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Money, Credit and Banking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kolodko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International transmission of inflation: Its economics and its politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1131" to="1138" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">International transmission of inflation under alternative exchange rate regimes: Empirical evidence and its implications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-G</forename><surname>Jeong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lee</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global Finance Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="137" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The spillover of inflation among the G7 countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Istiak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Tiwari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Husain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sohag</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Risk and Financial Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">International transmission of inflation among G-7 countries: A data-determined var analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wang</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Banking &amp; Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2681" to="2700" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysing the spillover of inflation in selected Euro-area countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tiwari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shahbaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hasim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M M</forename><surname>Elheddad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Quantitative Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="551" to="577" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inflation linkages within the Eurozone: Core vs. Periphery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Magkonis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scottish Journal of Political Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="289" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inflation transmission in greater China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M-H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Margaritis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">China &amp; World Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Remarks concerning graphical models for time series and point processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Brillinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brazilian Review of Econometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A graphical modelling approach to time series</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Reale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Lancaster</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian graphical models for structural vector autoregressive processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Ahelegbey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Billio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Casarin</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Econometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="357" to="386" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graph theory-based network analysis of regional uncertainties of the US economy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C-K M</forename><surname>Lau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Sheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">540</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">123064</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does global fear predict fear in BRICS stock markets? Evidence from a bayesian graphical structural VARr model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bouri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hosseini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C-K M</forename><surname>Lau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Emerging Markets Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="124" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network VAR models to measure financial contagion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Ahelegbey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Giudici</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S Q</forename><surname>Hashem</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The North American Journal of Economics and Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101318</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causality between oil shocks and exchange rate: A Bayesian, graph-based VAR approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">508</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="434" to="453" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Ahelegbey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Billio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Casarin</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Modeling turning points in the global equity market, Econometrics and Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Bojanic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Markov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2021</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="37" />
			<pubPlace>Bolivia, Economies</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inflation in the G7 countries: Persistence and structural breaks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Caporale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gil-Alana L A</forename><surname>Poza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economics and Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="493" to="506" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural breaks in the international dynamics of inflation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bataa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Osborn D R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sensier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Van Dijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Economics and Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="646" to="659" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of time series subject to changes in regime</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Econometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Inflation transmission in the emu: A Markov-switching VECM analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Thams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>SSRN 1032108</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chinese influences on inflation determination in Australia and the ASEAN group: A Markov-switching analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Burdekin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Asia and the Global Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2022</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100037</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How Covid-19 upturns the hedging potentials of gold against oil and stock markets risks: Nonlinear evidences through threshold regression and Markov-regime switching models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Adekoya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Oliyide</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G O</forename><surname>Oduyemi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Resources Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101926</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling systemic risk with Markov switching graphical SUR models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bianchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Billio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Casarin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Guidolin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Econometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">210</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="58" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Markov-switching vector autoregressions: Modelling, statistical inference, and application to business cycle analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H-M</forename><surname>Krolzig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">454</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="28" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inference from iterative simulation using multiple sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D B</forename><surname>Rubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistical Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="472" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">General methods for monitoring convergence of iterative simulations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S P</forename><surname>Brooks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gelman</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="434" to="455" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
