<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Original Research: CT-derived Body Composition Associated with Pulmonary Nodule Malignancy and Growth</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MS</roleName><forename type="first">Tong</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Bioengineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Radiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MS</roleName><forename type="first">Xiaoyan</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Radiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>BS</roleName><forename type="first">Grant</forename><surname>Kokenberger</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Radiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Joseph</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Leader</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Radiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MS</roleName><forename type="first">Jing</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Radiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MS</roleName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Thoracic Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vanderbilt University Medical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>37232</postCode>
									<settlement>Nashville</settlement>
									<region>Tennessee TN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Xin</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Radiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Kammer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Allergy</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Pulmonary</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD, MPH</roleName><forename type="first">Eric</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Grogan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Thoracic Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vanderbilt University Medical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>37232</postCode>
									<settlement>Nashville</settlement>
									<region>Tennessee TN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Herman</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD, MPH</roleName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Jiantao</forename><surname>Pu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Bioengineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Radiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ophthalmology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3240 Craft Place Pittsburgh</addrLine>
									<postCode>15213 15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Critical Care Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vanderbilt University Medical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>37232</postCode>
									<settlement>Nashville</settlement>
									<region>Tennessee TN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Original Research: CT-derived Body Composition Associated with Pulmonary Nodule Malignancy and Growth</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1101/2024.10.14.24315476</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T20:22+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>AI: artificial intelligence BC: body composition CI: confidence interval LDCT: low-dose computed tomography LASSO: least absolute shrinkage and selection operator LR: logistic regression PI: permutation importance pulmonary nodules</term>
					<term>body tissue composition</term>
					<term>malignancy</term>
					<term>machine learning</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We found that body composition were critical indicators for discriminating malignant nodules from benign ones and for evaluating the nodule growth in both males and females.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Key Results:</head><p>1. Univariate analysis revealed a significant association between body composition and nodule malignancy in both males and females. Multivariate analysis further demonstrated the predictive ability of body composition features.</p><p>2. Feature importance analysis and causal graph analysis identified skeletal muscle density as one of the leading features associated with nodule malignancy.</p><p>3. Skeletal muscle density and intramuscular adipose tissue density were identified as nodule growth indicators in both males and females.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Lung cancer is the leading cause of cancer-related mortality worldwide <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, which highlights the need for efficient screening programs to ensure early detection. The American Cancer Society (ACS) recommends annual screening with low-dose computed tomography (LDCT) for at-risk adults <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. The National Lung Screening Trial (NLST) has shown that LDCT can reduce lung cancer-related mortality by 20% compared to chest radiography (CXR) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. A crucial step in the screening process is determining the malignancy of lung nodules detected on LDCT scans. However, LDCT frequently detects lung nodules, 96.4% of which are benign or false positives <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. This high false positive rate often leads to unnecessary follow-up procedures, including additional imaging and invasive procedures such as biopsies and surgeries, causing anxiety and potential complications for patients.</p><p>To differentiate between benign and malignant nodules using CT images, nodule characteristics, such as size, solidness, shape, and density, are widely used by radiologists as the primary indicators of malignancy in clinical practice <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. A radiologist's performance heavily depends on their experience with these features, leading to high inter-and intra-reader variability <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</p><p>Consequently, significant effort has been dedicated to developing computational approaches, which generally fall into two categories. The first approach employs traditional machine learning methods, such as support vector machines and random forests <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, to identify significant handcrafted radiographic features similar to those used by radiologists. These features are integrated with patients' clinical data, such as age and smoking history <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>, to classify nodules into different categories. The second approach is based on deep learning (DL) technologies, such as convolutional neural networks (CNN) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. DL models require large, diverse datasets with ground truth and lack interpretability because DL models implicitly learn intricate image textures and patterns, functioning as a "black box".</p><p>Body composition has been explored as a potential biomarker for therapy response <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> and for predicting survival time and hospitalization <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. However, its relationship with lung nodule malignancy has not been investigated. We believe that body composition could serve as an effective biomarker for assessing lung nodule malignancy and offer insights into the development and progression of lung nodules. The rationale is that body composition can create a conductive environment for tumor growth, which in turn can affect metabolism and, in turn, alter body composition. As the tumor progresses toward malignancy, these changes in body composition may become more pronounced <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>.</p><p>In this study, we investigated the association between body composition and lung nodule malignancy, evaluating whether the inclusion of body composition features could improve the assessment of nodule malignancy when combined with nodule characteristics and clinical features. We also examined how body composition changes correlate with nodule growth, with particular attention to gender differences. Both statistical and machine learning approaches were employed to identify body composition features associated with nodule malignancy and growth.</p><p>Additionally, state-of-the-art causal AI technology was utilized to uncover the underlying causal relationships between body composition, lung nodule characteristics, and nodule malignancy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Methods and Materials</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Study datasets</head><p>A dataset of 216 subjects (male: 113 (52.3%), Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>) from the Pittsburgh Lung Cancer Screening Study (PLuSS) cohort <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> was selected for this study (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). The selection criteria were: (1) the presence of an indeterminate pulmonary nodule on baseline CT scans, and (2) follow-up CT scans available. Cases with small nodules on the baseline CT scans that showed significant growth on the follow-up scans were also included in the study. Nodule malignancy was confirmed either through biopsy or additional follow-up imaging. Follow-up times ranged from 0.30 to 13.19 years, with a median of 2.34 years and a mean of 4.25 years. For each subject, the largest nodule observed on the initial CT scans was involved in analyses. In the 216 pairs of CT scans, nodules size ranged from 4.00 to 25.32 mm in diameter. This study was approved by the University of Pittsburgh Institutional Review Board (IRB 011171).</p><p>An external validation dataset originated from the Vanderbilt University Medical Center (VUMC), denoted as the Vanderbilt dataset <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> (Supplementary Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). This dataset consisted of 162 patients (male: 94 (58.0%)) who were enrolled in the VUMC study between 2003 and 2017. These subjects had lung nodules with the largest axial diameter ranging from 6.00 to 30.00 mm. Diagnoses were confirmed through a biopsy or a 2-year longitudinal follow-up imaging showing no signs of growth for benign nodules.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Image acquisition</head><p>The chest LDCT scans in PLuSS were acquired at an end-inspiration during a single-breath-hold using a helical technique at 20-40 mA and 120/140 kVp. These images were reconstructed with a high spatial frequency algorithm specifically for lung tissue. The images encompassed the entire lung field in a 512×512 pixel matrix with slice thickness ranging from 1.25 to 2.5 mm. The inplane pixel dimensions ranged from 0.55 to 0.83 mm. Radiologists reviewed the images using standard lung windows on an imaging workstation, adjusting window width and level as needed to detect nodules and assess mediastinal structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">CT image features</head><p>In-house software was used to automatically segment five types of body tissues related to body composition depicted on chest LDCT images (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">1(g-j</ref>)) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. The five tissue types included visceral adipose tissue (VAT), subcutaneous adipose tissue (SAT), intermuscular adipose tissue (IMAT), skeletal muscle (SM) and bones. Volume, mass, and density (i.e., average Hounsfield Unit (HU) value) were computed for each segmented tissue <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>.</p><p>Lung nodules were automatically segmented and quantified on chest LDCT images using inhouse software <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> based on the following features: 1) volume, 2) mean density, 3) surface area, 4) maximum diameter, 5) mean diameter, 6) mean diameter of the solid portion, 7) solidness, 8) calcification volume, 9) irregularity (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">1 (a-f</ref>)). Solidness was determined using a threshold of -300 HU. Calcification volume was computed as the volume in the nodule with a HU value greater than 200. Irregularity was computed as the ratio between nodule surface area and volume <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Statistical analyses</head><p>Logistic regression (LR) was used to analyze the impact of body composition, nodule, and clinical features on lung nodule malignancy using baseline data (from the first CT scan).</p><p>Univariate LR was implemented on unstandardized data and multivariate LR was implemented on standardized data to classify nodules as benign or malignant. Different multivariate LR models were developed based on body composition, nodule, and clinical features.  <ref type="formula">6</ref>) Composite (BC + Clinical + Nodule). To construct these models and mitigate potential overfitting, all features were initially included, and then a multi-strategy feature selection approach was applied. First, Least Absolute Shrinkage and Selection Operator (LASSO) regularization was utilized to select features by shrinking and reducing certain LASSO regression coefficients to zero. This procedure was performed using a 10-fold cross-validation (CV) approach to fine-tune the optimal regularization parameter to ensure robustness. Features with LASSO coefficients equating to zero were excluded. Then, variance inflation factor (VIF) selection and backward stepwise selection were applied iteratively. Specifically, features with a VIF larger than a threshold of 3.0 were further removed. This process continued until all remaining features exhibited a p-value less than 0.05.</p><p>The performance of the classification models was evaluated in both the model development and external validation datasets using the area under (AUC) the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve with 95% confidence intervals (CIs). These CIs were computed using the 10-fold CV method. To compare the performance of two models, the DeLong test was used for independent models, while the likelihood ratio test (LRT) was used for nested models. All statistics were performed in Python 3.11.4 and RStudio 4.3.1.</p><p>Body composition indicators associated with nodule growth were analyzed. Changes in body composition and nodules were quantified between baseline and last CT scans. Absolute changes in both body composition and lung nodule features were computed between these two scans.</p><p>Paired t-tests were used to identify nodule features with significant changes (p &lt; 0.05), and unpaired t-tests were used to compare body composition changes between malignant and benign groups. Pearson correlation analysis was employed to examine the correlation between changes in body composition and nodule features. Person correlation analysis was also used to examine the correlations between baseline body composition features and nodule malignancy univariately.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.">Feature importance analysis</head><p>Feature importance was evaluated using permutation importance (PI) and Shapley Additive Explanations (SHAP) <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. To model classifiers for nodule malignancy, Support Vector Machine (SVM), Random Forest (RF) and Multi-layer Perceptron (MLP) were used in addition to LR.</p><p>Feature importance scores provided by each method were standardized using min-max scaling, and then average feature importance scores were calculated. The SVM classifier was developed using a linear kernel with a regularization parameter of 1.0. The RF classifier was constructed with 100 trees and used the Gini impurity criterion. The MLP classifier was trained with 100 hidden layers, a constant learning rate of 0.001, and a maximum of 1,000 iterations until convergence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.">Causal relationship analysis</head><p>To evaluate the statistical findings and reveal the underlying causal relationships between features, a novel causal discovery method called "Grouped Greedy Equivalence Search" (GGES) <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> was used to generate directed graphs. This allowed the visualization of the causal relationships between clinical features, CT image features, and nodule malignancy. Initially, all features were included in the causal discovery graph, after which only features that have paths leading to the node 'malignancy' were retained. Features directly connected to the node 'malignancy' were identified as the most crucial predictive factors for nodule malignancy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Body composition at baseline CT scans and nodule malignancy</head><p>There were 120 (55.56%) malignant and 96 benign nodules in the PLuSS training dataset. The mean age of the benign and malignant groups were 61.51 (± 7.47) and 63.20 (± 6.38) years, respectively. The results of univariate logistic regression analysis of clinical features, body tissues, and nodule features are presented in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>. Among the clinical features, only Emphysema was found to be significant (p &lt; 0.05). Subjects with emphysema had an increased odds of malignancy of 82.2% (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). Regarding body composition features across all genders, VAT density, IMAT density, SM density, and Bone density, showed statistically significant negative associations with nodule malignancy (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>, Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref>). SM density demonstrated the strongest correlation with nodule malignancy (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">3</ref>). When considering gender differences, different body composition features were associated with malignancy (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref>; Supplementary Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2,</ref><ref type="table">3</ref>). Specifically, SM density maintained a strong negative correlation with malignancy in both males and females, while bone features were associated only in males and VAT features only in females. Nodule features, including Mean Intensity, Max Diameter, Mean Diameter, Solidness, and Irregularity, were significantly associated with nodule malignancy in males, females, and all subjects (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>, Supplementary <ref type="bibr">Table 4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5)</ref>. Mean Intensity showed a negative correlation with malignancy, while the other features showed positive correlations.</p><p>The multivariate logistic regression results of various integrative nodule malignancy models are illustrated in Table <ref type="table">3</ref>. The Composite model and the BC + Nodule model retained the same parameters -body composition features IMAT, SM, and SAT, and nodule features Irregularity and Mean Intensity -after feature selection and achieved the best discrimination performance with an AUC of 0.87 (95% CI: 0.82 -0.91). The BC + Clinical model and the BC model also maintained the same parameters and exhibited suboptimal performance with an AUC of 0.77 (95% CI: 0.71 -0.84), incorporating body composition features IMAT, SM, VAT, SAT. This was followed by the Nodule model, which had an AUC of 0.71 (95% CI: 0.64 -0.78) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">3a</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Feature importance</head><p>The BC + Nodule/Composite model constructed using LR and RF methods achieved the highest performance, with an AUC of 0.87 (95% CI: 0.82 -0.92), closely followed by SVM method with an AUC of 0.86 (95% CI: 0.81 -0.91), and MLP method with an AUC of 0.81 (95% CI: 0.76 -0.87) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">3b</ref>). Feature importance analysis was conducted based on these four wellperforming ML methods. Among all body composition features, SM density was identified as the most important indicator and retained its significance even with the inclusion of Nodule features (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">6</ref>).</p><p>Another crucial body composition feature is IMAT (Intermuscular adipose tissue), including both its density and mass. It is noteworthy that feature selection methods were not applied to the BC (body composition) feature importance analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Causal analysis of body composition feature and lung nodule malignancy</head><p>Three features -body composition SM density, nodule features Irregularity and Mean Intensity -were directly linked to 'malignancy' (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4</ref>). These variables demonstrated statistical significance in both univariate and multivariate logistic regression models and were highlighted as key indicators of nodule malignancy in feature importance analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Body composition features and nodule changes</head><p>Nodule growth metrics were evaluated by identifying nodule features with significant changes between the baseline and the last LDCT scan date (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">7</ref>). These features were then used to analyze body composition changes. The correlations between changes in body composition and the identified nodule features are demonstrated in Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4</ref> for males and Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref> for females. Body composition indicators related to nodule growth were identified for both genders (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">4</ref>). Specifically, IMAT density and SM density were found to be important indicators of nodule growth in both males and females. Bone features were indicators of nodule growth in males. SAT features were identified as indicators in females.</p><p>Comparing the body composition changes from baseline to the last LDCT scans between malignant and benign groups (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">8</ref>), IMAT and SM features showed significant differences between the two groups in females. In males, all 3 IMAT features, VAT density, and Bone density were significantly different.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5.">External validation</head><p>VUMC validation dataset included 112 (69.14%) malignant and 50 benign nodules, showing a higher malignancy rate than the 55.56% observed in the training dataset. Patients with malignant nodules in the external dataset were older, with an average age of 69.84 (± 8.41) years, compared to 63.20 (± 6.38) years in the training dataset. The average age of patients with benign nodules was similar across both datasets. While smoking status in the external dataset did not show a significant association with nodule malignancy, the number of cigarettes smoked per year showed a significant association.</p><p>Standardizing the external dataset using the same scales as the training dataset, we validated the trained baseline multivariate LR prediction models (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>) -including the individual BC model, Nodule model, and integrative BC + Nodule model -on the external dataset. All three models achieved very similar discrimination performance with AUCs of 0.64 (95% CI: 0.54 -0.74), 0.63 (95% CI: 0.54 -0.72), and 0.62 (95% CI: 0.53 -0.72), respectively (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">3c</ref>). The performance of the three models was not significantly different (p &gt; 0.05).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p>A comprehensive study was conducted to investigate the associations between nodule malignancy, growth, and various image-based body composition features. Several critical body composition features were found to be associated with nodule malignancy and growth. Our main findings were validated on an external VUMC dataset and showed a lower but reasonable performance. To our knowledge, this is the first study to explore the potential relationships between body composition and nodule malignancy and growth using radiomic data, with a particular emphasis on gender differences.</p><p>We employed a robust feature selection procedure that combined LASSO regularization with iterative VIF selection and backward stepwise selection. This approach enhances predictive accuracy and mitigates overfitting issues, thereby improving model explainability. We validated this feature selection method through comprehensive feature importance analyses of body composition features without a pre-selection procedure (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">6</ref>). This strategy ensures the reliability of our procedure for feature selection. Additionally, we utilized a causal graph to analyze and visualize the causal relationships between body composition features and malignancy.</p><p>The CT-derived body composition features were consistently and significantly associated with nodule malignancy in all analyses. Most notably, the loss of SM (Skeletal muscle) and IMAT (Intramuscular adipose tissue) were highlighted. Muscle wasting (sarcopenia) is recognized as a prominent phenotype in lung cancer patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>. However, previous research has either characterized muscle loss by comparing lung cancer and non-lung cancer groups or studied its association with the overall survival of lung cancer patients. Our study suggests that muscle wasting is crucial for indicating a lung nodule's malignancy on LDCT scans.</p><p>Clinical and CT-derived nodule features are widely studied and acknowledged biomarkers for nodule malignancy <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Key clinical features, such as age, sex, smoking history, and nodule features, especially nodule size, are commonly utilized in lung cancer prediction models <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</p><p>However, in our analysis, only Emphysema was found to be significant univariately (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</p><p>None of the clinical features were retained in the integrative models after feature selection (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>). Potential reasons for this could be: (1) the models retained body tissue features over age because the aging process is often paralleled by decreases in muscle and increases in fat mass <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>; (2) gender, age, BMI, and smoking history was balanced between the malignant and benign groups in our dataset, which could reduce the bias and effects of these features on malignancy assessment. Additionally, previous studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30]</ref> have suggested that the existence of emphysema could help predict lung cancer risk among smokers. In our study, after the inclusion of body tissue features (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>), emphysema was excluded because tissue features were more significant for nodule classification. Multiple nodule features were found to be associated with nodule malignancy both univariately and multivariately. The causal graph (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4</ref> Specifically, the PLuSS training dataset had more balanced clinical characteristics compared to the VUMC validation dataset (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, Supplementary Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</p><p>Body composition differs significantly between males and females, prompting the need for gender-specific analyses in lung cancer studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>. Our study similarly accounted for these gender differences to ensure a more accurate assessment. Specifically, in the analysis of malignancy, SM density remained a malignancy indicator for both males and females, while Bone features were significant only for males and VAT, IMAT features only for females. In the analysis of nodule growth indicators (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">4</ref>, Supplementary Table <ref type="table">8</ref>), the significance of IMAT and SM features was highlighted again for both genders. Additionally, Bone features (bone loss) were identified as an indicator of nodule growth in males, given that males tend to have higher bone density than females <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>. We observed that SM density (Skeletal muscle density) change was negatively correlated with nodule Mean intensity in males but positively correlated in females. Two possible explanations: (1) different body composition in males and females, such as denser muscles with more intramuscular fat in males than in females, might influence these correlations; and (2) although nodule Mean intensity can provide important clues about the likelihood of malignancy (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>) and nodule growth (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">7</ref>), it is important to note that a sole change in nodule density does not necessarily indicate malignant nodule growth. For example, a nodule density increase can indicate either calcification <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> (a benign process) or malignant nodules growing from partly solid to more solid <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, while a nodule density decrease can indicate either inflammation of benign nodules <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> or cavitation of malignant nodules <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref> as they grow. When considering nodule malignancy, it is necessary to combine nodule density with other features, such as nodule size and irregularity (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>).</p><p>Overall, nodule density change is still an important indicator of nodule growth.</p><p>The primary limitation of this study is the inability to validate the relationship between body composition and nodule growth in the external dataset. This limitation arises from the lack of follow-up CT scans in the external dataset. Additionally, although our models revealed a potential relationship between body composition and nodule malignancy on the external dataset, the prediction performance was relatively lower compared to the internal dataset. This discrepancy may be due to variations in CT acquisition protocol, participant enrollment criteria, and population characteristics. Nonetheless, our results indicate a strong connection between body composition and nodule malignancy, as well as their changes over time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p>We performed a comprehensive investigation of the body composition as a potential biomarker for assessing pulmonary nodule malignancy and growth. We found that body composition, especially skeletal muscle density and intermuscular adipose tissue density, were critical indicators for discriminating malignant nodules from benign ones and for evaluating the nodule growth in both males and females. These findings can help significantly improve lung cancer screening by improving the assessment of the malignancy of screen-detected lung nodules.</p><p>Given the high prevalence of false positive nodule detections during lung cancer screening, our findings have significant clinical implications. Additionally, our findings can help evaluate nodule progression or stability, leading to more accurate prognoses and personalized management strategies.       </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>These models included: ( 1 )</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Body composition (BC) model, (2) Nodule model, (3) Clinical model, (4) BC + Clinical model, (5) BC + Nodule model, and (</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Clinical features were not included in any of the models, and the Clinical model is not presented due to its low performance. The individual Nodule model did not exhibit a significant performance difference compared to BC model (DeLong test: p = 0.151). Additionally, combining body composition features and nodule features, the BC + Nodule model demonstrated superior performance compared to the Nodule model alone (Likelihood ratio test: p &lt; 0.0001).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>) underscored the significance of skeletal muscle density, as nodule features serve as direct indicators of nodule malignancy. The graph links two nodule features, Irregularity and Mean Intensity, along with SM density, directly to node 'malignancy'. The performance of the Nodule and BC models did not show a significant performance difference, whereas the BC + Nodule model demonstrated superior performance over the Nodule model. These findings suggest: (1) body composition can serve as a novel biomarker of nodule malignancy assessment; and (2) combining body composition with nodule features could enhance nodule malignancy assessment. The first finding was validated in an external dataset. Despite the BC model not achieving high performance, its performance was comparable to that of the Nodule model, indicating the classification ability of body composition features based on LDCT image data. The relatively low performance in the VUMC dataset could be attributed to the variations in image protocols and patient characteristics between the two datasets.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. An example illustrating the automated segmentations of lung nodules and five tissues</figDesc><graphic coords="20,72.00,72.00,461.52,364.86" type="vector_box" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Correlation visualization between baseline body composition and nodule malignancy</figDesc><graphic coords="21,72.00,72.00,489.98,252.18" type="vector_box" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Cross-validated (10-fold) ROC-AUCs of (a) logistic regression integrative models</figDesc><graphic coords="22,77.76,72.00,456.66,431.82" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Graph-based causal relationship modeling among the variables. Only features with</figDesc><graphic coords="23,90.90,97.38,430.20,422.82" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Subject demographic and clinical characteristics of the PLuSS training dataset (n=216).</figDesc><table><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Malignant (n=120)</cell><cell>Benign (n=96)</cell><cell>Coefficient (95% CI)</cell><cell>P-value</cell></row><row><cell>Age (year)</cell><cell>63.20 (6.38)</cell><cell>61.51 (7.47)</cell><cell>0.04 (0.00, 0.08)</cell><cell>0.076</cell></row><row><cell>Gender</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell>61</cell><cell>52</cell><cell>-0.17 (-0.70, 0.37)</cell><cell>0.543</cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>59</cell><cell>44</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Race</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Non-white</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0.12 (-1.06, 1.30)</cell><cell>0.842</cell></row><row><cell>White</cell><cell>113</cell><cell>91</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>BMI</cell><cell>27.47 (4.07)</cell><cell>27.67 (4.35)</cell><cell>-0.01 (-0.08, 0.05)</cell><cell>0.726</cell></row><row><cell>BMI category</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>\</cell><cell>0.874</cell></row><row><cell>&lt; 20.0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>20.0 to 24.9</cell><cell>34</cell><cell>27</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>25.0 to 29.9</cell><cell>55</cell><cell>40</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>≥ 30.0</cell><cell>31</cell><cell>27</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Smoking Status</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Current</cell><cell>87</cell><cell>59</cell><cell>0.50 (-0.07, 1.08)</cell><cell>0.086</cell></row><row><cell>Former</cell><cell>33</cell><cell>37</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Cigarette (day)</cell><cell>25.50 (8.49)</cell><cell>25.21 (8.91)</cell><cell>0.00 (-0.03, 0.03)</cell><cell>0.805</cell></row><row><cell>Pack (year)</cell><cell>57.88 (21.93)</cell><cell>53.51 (22.38)</cell><cell>0.01 (0.00, 0.02)</cell><cell>0.152</cell></row><row><cell>Emphysema</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Yes</cell><cell>83</cell><cell>53</cell><cell>0.60 (0.04, 1.16)</cell><cell>0.036 *</cell></row><row><cell>No</cell><cell>37</cell><cell>43</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Mean (Standard deviation (SD)) and Count for continuous and categorical variables respectively.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Coefficient and p-value from univariate logistic regression model on unstandardized data.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>* , indicates p-value &lt; 0.05.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Values of 0.00 are non-zero but are truncated due to rounding.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Summary statistics of CT-derived body composition and nodule features in lung cancer and non-cancer groups and their univariate logistic regression results. Mean (Standard deviation (SD)) for continuous variables. Coefficient and p-value from univariate logistic regression model on unstandardized data. , ** , *** , indicate p-value &lt; 0.05, &lt; 0.001, &lt; 0.0001. Values of 0.00 are non-zero but are truncated due to rounding. VAT: visceral adipose tissue, SAT: subcutaneous adipose tissue, IMAT: intermuscular adipose tissue, SM: skeletal muscle.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Malignant (n=120)</cell><cell>Benign (n=96)</cell><cell>Coefficient (95% CI)</cell><cell>P-value</cell></row><row><cell>Body composition features</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>VAT volume (L)</cell><cell>1.14 (0.81)</cell><cell>1.05 (0.66)</cell><cell>0.16 (-0.21, 0.53)</cell><cell>0.389</cell></row><row><cell>VAT density (HU)</cell><cell>-90.24 (5.96)</cell><cell>-88.49 (5.4)</cell><cell>-0.05 (-0.10, -0.01)</cell><cell>0.028 *</cell></row><row><cell>VAT mass (kg)</cell><cell>1.17 (0.83)</cell><cell>1.08 (0.68)</cell><cell>0.15 (-0.20, 0.51)</cell><cell>0.399</cell></row><row><cell>SAT volume (L)</cell><cell>4.03 (1.66)</cell><cell>4.17 (1.79)</cell><cell>-0.05 (-0.20, 0.11)</cell><cell>0.573</cell></row><row><cell>SAT density (HU)</cell><cell>-89.48 (10)</cell><cell>-87.14 (8.65)</cell><cell>-0.03 (-0.06, 0.00)</cell><cell>0.074</cell></row><row><cell>SAT mass (kg)</cell><cell>4.17 (1.69)</cell><cell>4.32 (1.83)</cell><cell>-0.05 (-0.20, 0.11)</cell><cell>0.536</cell></row><row><cell>IMAT volume (L)</cell><cell>0.46 (0.24)</cell><cell>0.46 (0.24)</cell><cell>0.00 (-1.12, 1.12)</cell><cell>0.998</cell></row><row><cell>IMAT density (HU)</cell><cell>-90.1 (12.12)</cell><cell>-86.49 (13.12)</cell><cell>-0.02 (-0.05, 0.00)</cell><cell>0.040 *</cell></row><row><cell>IMAT mass (kg)</cell><cell>0.47 (0.25)</cell><cell>0.47 (0.24)</cell><cell>-0.04 (-1.14, 1.06)</cell><cell>0.944</cell></row><row><cell>SM volume (L)</cell><cell>4.16 (1.15)</cell><cell>4.4 (1.17)</cell><cell>-0.18 (-0.41, 0.05)</cell><cell>0.131</cell></row><row><cell>SM density (HU)</cell><cell>28.98 (7.2)</cell><cell>34.27 (6.05)</cell><cell>-0.12 (-0.16, -0.07)</cell><cell>0.000 ***</cell></row><row><cell>SM mass (kg)</cell><cell>4.87 (1.35)</cell><cell>5.17 (1.38)</cell><cell>-0.17 (-0.36, 0.03)</cell><cell>0.102</cell></row><row><cell>Bone volume (L)</cell><cell>1.56 (0.37)</cell><cell>1.5 (0.33)</cell><cell>0.49 (-0.29, 1.26)</cell><cell>0.217</cell></row><row><cell>Bone density (HU)</cell><cell>272.63 (35.65)</cell><cell>287.21 (45.51)</cell><cell>-0.01 (-0.02, 0.00)</cell><cell>0.010 *</cell></row><row><cell>Bone mass (kg)</cell><cell>2.24 (0.52)</cell><cell>2.18 (0.48)</cell><cell>0.24 (-0.30, 0.78)</cell><cell>0.383</cell></row><row><cell>Nodule features</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Volume (ml)</cell><cell>0.54 (1.17)</cell><cell>0.37 (1.23)</cell><cell>0.13 (-0.13, 0.39)</cell><cell>0.328</cell></row><row><cell>Mean intensity (HU)</cell><cell>-373.33 (188.3)</cell><cell>-261.42 (249.42)</cell><cell>-0.00 (-0.00, -0.00)</cell><cell>0.001 **</cell></row><row><cell>Surface area (cm 2 )</cell><cell>3.23 (4.25)</cell><cell>2.18 (4.45)</cell><cell>0.07 (-0.01, 0.15)</cell><cell>0.097</cell></row><row><cell>Max diameter (mm)</cell><cell>10.08 (5.97)</cell><cell>7.56 (4.78)</cell><cell>0.01 (0.00, 0.02)</cell><cell>0.002 *</cell></row><row><cell>Mean diameter (mm)</cell><cell>7.43 (4.14)</cell><cell>5.99 (3.40)</cell><cell>0.11 (0.03, 0.19)</cell><cell>0.009 *</cell></row><row><cell>Mean diameter (Solid)</cell><cell>6.60 (14.75)</cell><cell>4.63 (3.31)</cell><cell>0.05 (-0.02, 0.13)</cell><cell>0.190</cell></row><row><cell>Solidness</cell><cell>0.07 (0.13)</cell><cell>0.01 (0.04)</cell><cell>10.27 (4.41, 16.13)</cell><cell>0.001 **</cell></row><row><cell>Calcification volume</cell><cell>44.53 (189.32)</cell><cell>56.39 (284.17)</cell><cell>-0.00 (-0.00, 0.00)</cell><cell>0.715</cell></row><row><cell>Irregularity (%)</cell><cell>0.34 (0.28)</cell><cell>0.16 (0.18)</cell><cell>3.64 (2.16, 5.11)</cell><cell>0.000 ***</cell></row></table><note><p>* </p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Identified nodule growth indicators.A sign (+)/ (-) indicates positive/negative correlations between Body Composition and Nodule features.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Gender</cell><cell>Nodule</cell><cell>Body Tissue Composition</cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell>Irregularity</cell><cell>Bone mass (-), Bone volume (-)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean diameter, Mean diameter (Solid)</cell><cell>IMAT mass (+), IMAT density (+)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean intensity</cell><cell>SM density (-)</cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>Irregularity, Surface area, Max diameter</cell><cell>IMAT density (+)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean diameter</cell><cell>SAT mass (+), SAT volume (+)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean intensity</cell><cell>SM density (+)</cell></row></table><note><p>SAT: subcutaneous adipose tissue, IMAT: intermuscular adipose tissue, SM: skeletal muscle.</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">CA: a cancer journal for clinicians</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Siegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Giaquinto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024. 2024</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="49" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Cancer statistics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">American Cancer Society lung cancer screening guidelines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wender</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="117" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>CA: a cancer journal for clinicians</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Reduced Lung-Cancer Mortality with Low-Dose Computed Tomographic Screening</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>New England Journal of Medicine</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">365</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="395" to="409" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Results of the National Lung Cancer Screening Trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Chudgar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thoracic Surgery Clinics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="153" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A multi-task CNN approach for lung nodule malignancy classification and characterization. Expert Systems with Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Marques</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">184</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">115469</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intra-and Inter-Reader Variations in Lung Nodule Measurements: Influences of Nodule Size, Location, and Observers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diagnostics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2319</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comprehensive analysis of clinical logistic and machine learning-based models for the evaluation of pulmonary nodules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JTO Clinical and Research Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100299</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computer aided diagnosis of pulmonary nodules on CT scans: Improvement of classification performance with nodule surface features</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Way</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Medical Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3086" to="3098" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LUNGx Challenge for computerized lung nodule classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Iii</forename><surname>Armato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Medical Imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44506" to="044506" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factors that influence physician decision making for indeterminate pulmonary nodules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vachani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of the American Thoracic Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1586" to="1591" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pulmonary nodule classification with deep residual networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nibali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wollersheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Computer Assisted Radiology and Surgery</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1799" to="1808" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Body composition in patients with non-small cell lung cancer: a contemporary view of cancer cachexia with the use of computed tomography image analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Baracos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American journal of clinical nutrition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1133S" to="1137" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Body composition and inflammation impact in non-small-cell lung cancer patients treated by first-line immunotherapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Baldessari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunotherapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1501" to="1519" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CT-derived body composition values and complications after pneumonectomy in lung cancer patients: time for a sex-related analysis?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rizzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Oncology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">826058</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cancer cachexia in the age of obesity: skeletal muscle depletion is a powerful prognostic factor, independent of body mass index</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of clinical oncology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1539" to="1547" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Skeletal muscle radiodensity is prognostic for survival in patients with advanced non-small cell lung cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sjøblom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical Nutrition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1386" to="1393" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The prognostic value of early onset, CT derived loss of muscle and adipose tissue during chemotherapy in metastatic non-small cell lung cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Degens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lung Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="130" to="135" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-glass opacity nodules: histopathology, imaging evaluation, and clinical implications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of thoracic imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="118" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Pittsburgh Lung Screening Study (PLuSS) outcomes within 3 years of a first computed tomography scan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">178</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="956" to="961" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>American journal of respiratory and critical care medicine</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing the Transportability of Radiomic Models for Lung Cancer Diagnosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Translational Lung Cancer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<publisher>In Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automated segmentation of five different body tissues on computed tomography using deep learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Medical Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="178" to="191" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating 3-D whole-body composition from a chest CT scan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7108" to="7117" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting benign, preinvasive, and invasive lung nodules on computed tomography scans using machine learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Ashraf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">163</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1496" to="1505" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shape &quot;break-and-repair&quot; strategy and its application to automated medical image segmentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A unified approach to interpreting model predictions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lundberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-I</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in neural information processing systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 30</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graphical modeling of causal factors associated with the postoperative survival of esophageal cancer subjects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Medical Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1997" to="2006" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Body composition and lung cancer-associated cachexia in TRACERx</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Al-Sawaf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="846" to="858" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sarcopenia: aging-related loss of muscle mass and function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Larsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiological reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="427" to="511" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of emphysema on lung cancer risk in smokers: a computed tomography-based assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer prevention research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">COPD, emphysema and the onset of lung cancer. A systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mouronte-Roibas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">382</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="240" to="244" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Males have larger skeletal size and bone mass than females, despite comparable body size</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Nieves</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Bone and Mineral Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="535" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The calcified lung nodule: What does it mean?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of thoracic medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of baseline nodule density and changes in density and nodule features in the discrimination between benign and malignant solid indeterminate pulmonary nodules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Radiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="492" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kurtosis and skewness assessments of solid lung nodule density histograms: differentiating malignant from benign nodules on CT</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kamiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Japanese journal of radiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characteristic CT findings after percutaneous cryoablation treatment of malignant lung nodules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chaudhry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1672</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
