<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">An Interregional SAM Construction focused on Institutional Sectors and Structural Path Analysis in Japan</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Asian Development Bank since July 2010</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Department of City and Regional Planning, Cornell University</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Hidekazu</forename><surname>Itoh</surname></persName>
							<email>hito@kwansei.ac.jp</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Business Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kwansei Gakuin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="JP">JAPAN</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">An Interregional SAM Construction focused on Institutional Sectors and Structural Path Analysis in Japan</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T21:28+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>input-output table</term>
					<term>interregional social accounting matrix</term>
					<term>structural path analysis</term>
					<term>Japan</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The aim of this research is to build a multiregional social accounting matrix in Japan to evaluate the regional spillover effects of economic impacts. While research on national and regional SAM has become common, examples of interregional SAM are rare currently. This study points out that there is a substantial need to build a small regional SAM because of economic sensitivity. Our work evaluates the economic effects of national and regional government behavior, such as changes of the local tax system and decentralization of power, on the regional economy by structural path analysis.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Input-Output (I-O) analysis (Miller and Blair, 1995), developed by the Russian economist Wassily W. Leontief (1906-1999), is an effective tool to evaluate the mutual spatial effects of regional economies. I-O analysis is a systematic tool to analyze the relationship between industries through the production activities of each industry in a nation and region. To this day, the tool is used for empirical and advanced research. In Japan, the I-O table is compiled by prefectures, government-designated cities, and the national government, and analysis based on the I-O table is used widely. Because the main purpose of I-O analysis is to discuss the money flows or exchanges between industries, this analysis does not consider all money flows, such as money exchanges with institutional sectors (household, company, and central and local governments) and fund flows with capital accounts (savings/investments) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">1</ref> .</p><p>To meet this challenge, the social accounting matrix (SAM), developed by Sir J. Richard N. Stone (1913-1991) 2 , uses the I-O table as a basis to indicate all money exchanges at the same point in time with all economic agents: industry, household, company, government, and the rest of the world (ROW). Therefore, the SAM at the level of a country or region shows the economic size and money exchanges in that country or region.</p><p>The aim of this study is to propose an analytical framework of interregional SAM (ISAM) focusing on institutional sectors based on data availability in Japan. In addition, the study aims to evaluate SAM multipliers and the regional spillover effects of economic impacts by using (spatial) structural path analysis (SPA) for an ISAM construction.</p><p>The following two points summarize the contribution of this study. First, the construction of ISAM focuses on detailed institutional sectors. SAM constructed in early research essentially has three main categories as institutional sectors: household, company, and government. On the other hand, the SAM proposed in this study has much more detailed categories, especially for companies and governments. For example, by applying this SAM for empirical analysis, we can analyze the interdependent relationships between, for example, social security funds, taxes, and subsidies in governments. In addition, because the SAM constructed in this empirical analysis is based on the lists of income/expenditure following the system of national accounts (SNA) in Japan, balanced adjustments of the data gaps of sectors are quite easy using ISAM. The second contribution is that this study applies SPA for ISAM in the analysis of spillover effects for regional incomes. This study undertakes a comparative analysis of regional economic spillover mechanisms for household incomes in regions by using the ISAM database with Hokkaido prefecture and other regions in Japan.</p><p>The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. Section 2 explains the purpose and orientation of this research. Section 3 shows the frameworks of intraregional and interregional SAMs, and proposes an ISAM with detailed institutional sectors by discussing the data possibilities of SNA in Japan. Moreover, this section provides an ISAM with two regions, focusing on Hokkaido prefecture. Next, Section 4 explains the method of (spatial) SPA, discusses the detailed regional economic spillover effects, and analyzes the results of the numerical example of the Hokkaido ISAM. Lastly, Section 5 concludes the research and gives direction for further research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Research Motivation</head><p>SAM is a comprehensive, disaggregated, consistent, and complete data system that captures the interdependent relationships within a social economic system. The sectoral classifications in most research using SAM are very rough because of data limitations. For example, a typical SAM has only household, company, and government as institutional sectors. However, detailed classification would be needed for analysis on issues that involve decentralization of power, like taxes, subsidies, and social security funds.</p><p>In this research, we attempt to construct an ISAM with detailed institutional sectors-including local governments, or local agencies of central government, prefectures, and municipalities-social security funds, direct and indirect taxes, and subsidies in each region.</p><p>Moreover, we evaluate the regional economic spillover effects for household income and discuss the differences of economic spillover mechanisms by applying spatial SPA for an ISAM construction. This study presents an analytical framework of ISAM with detailed classification for Japan.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Research purpose</head><p>At the project level, like public investment, specific sectoral costs are changed. Thus, the traditional partial equilibrium model, for example, cost-benefit analysis (CBA), which is applied for policy evaluation, has some implications for the local evaluation of financial and economic efficiency of the relevant sectors. However, these methods cannot provide policy evaluation for the important structural changes to various other sectors; the methods can evaluate only the relevant sectors, and cannot evaluate the interdependent relationships between production, price, consumption, and the money flows of income/expenditure. Therefore, computable general equilibrium (CGE)<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">foot_2</ref> models based on the SAM database are applied as a useful tool for the evaluation of all sectors of the regional economy by economic policy above the project level, like regulation and interposition, relaxation of regulations, liberalization of trade, labor market, public finance, banking, transportation, and environment. Over the past few decades, CGE models have been adapted in many research fields other than economics, such as civil engineering, and research output has accumulated <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">4</ref> . Moreover, interregional models are needed for the analysis to consider temporal and spatial factors, like trade and transportation, because of the limitations with the model analysis using SAM and CGE with a single country and a single region. That is, although goods and services represent primary demand, in general, transportation demand is derivative demand.</p><p>Therefore, the networks of freight movements at home and abroad change drastically according to transport infrastructure investment and efforts toward transport efficiencies and CO 2 emissions reduction by companies. For example, the interregional models for economic impact analysis are needed for policy discussion. This is because their economic impacts shift policy to freight rail and domestic sea transport in order to reduce greenhouse gas emissions and relocates logistics facilities to reduce logistics costs. These are important recent challenges as cargo movement networks are vast.</p><p>The purpose of this research is to construct an analytical framework of ISAM and to undertake numerical analysis based on the SAM database to discuss economic spillover mechanisms. This study confirms the importance and challenges of ISAM. The analysis based on the SAM database can deal with income transfers in detail by considering not only the money flows between industries but also the money flows between institutional sectors, namely, household, company, and government, and production factors, namely, capital and labor.</p><p>However, most of the early research using SAM, including CGE models, is for single international countries because of data limitations and the difficulty of analytical tools. This research discusses an evaluation method for regional economic policy, whose importance is increasing for the progress of local governments, by providing the analytical frameworks of intraregional and interregional SAM below the national level. Moreover, the characteristics of a (relatively small) regional economy are affected more than the national economy by price changes, including transportation costs, offshore leakages, transfer of production factors, and interregional spillovers. Therefore, there is an increasing need for an analytical tool evaluating regional economic policy with consideration for various economic characteristics of regions. In this study, we discuss the analytical framework of ISAM for prefectures and government-designated cities as well as the method for constructing the SAM database. In addition, we discuss the analytical availability or effectiveness of ISAM using SAM multiplier analysis and SPA for the ISAM with two regions as a numerical example.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Research orientation</head><p>There is much early research for economy-wide model analysis (EMA), like SAM analysis and CGE models based on a SAM database, which analyzes the interdependent effects between industries and institutional sectors at the national level. However, although the need for intraregional and interregional models is quite high, the research excluding theoretical and virtual numerical analyses is limited, except for a few foreign studies. Although the need for empirical analysis in Japan is also high, the empirical research on prefectures and cities is limited, particularly for comparatively closed regional economies, like Okinawa and Hokkaido prefectures 5 . The reason is the lack of data. SNA, or national economic accounting , is used for making a national-level SAM the main information source in Japan. Similarly, regional (or prefectural) economic accounting is used for making regional SAMs. However, the data from this economic accounting is not sufficient for constructing a detailed regional SAM database. <ref type="bibr">5</ref> For example, Doi et al. (2006) constructed a CGE model for Hokkaido prefecture.</p><p>Therefore, there is limited empirical research on detailed regional (or interregional) SAM below the national level. In this research, we discuss the data availability of regional economic accounting in Japan, and propose an empirical framework of ISAM that records the institutional sectors of household, company, and government in detail.</p><p>Reviews of earlier studies show the following two challenges. First, EMA at the national level in Japan and elsewhere cannot provide effective policy implications for a specific regional economy. Second, I-O analysis that cannot model important factors endogenously-like price changes and the movements of production factors between industries on regions, which have big impacts for national and regional economies, including small regions-is insufficient. However, in addition, as stated in Subsection 2.1, earlier studies could not construct ISAM with detailed sectors, except for production activities from the I-O table, because of insufficient regional economic accounts; this is the challenge for EMA on prefectures and government-designated cities in Japan. There is some early research (Miyagi, 1998; Takeda and Ban, 2008) that applies Japanese ISAMs constructed for CGE analysis. However, because their main focus is CGE modeling, they do not provide detailed information sources for their ISAM database construction.</p><p>Therefore, the discussion on data availability is one of this study's contributions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Construction of ISAM and empirical analysis in Japan</head><p>In this section, first, we explain the general SAM structure for a single country or region. Then, we broaden the normal intraregional SAM to interregional SAM, and discuss the characteristics and analytical possibilities of ISAM. The ISAM proposed in this research is constructed using an Isard-type I-O table. The Isard-type I-O table, that is, the interregional I-O table with noncompetitive domestic imports, considers intermediate goods from other regions and foreign countries as different goods to those from the relevant (own) region. Second, this section introduces the structure of the interregional I-O table and the characteristics of available regional economic accounting, or regional SNA, in Japan as the main databases for the construction of ISAM. Finally, this section proposes a structural framework of ISAM in Japan considering data availability, and produces an ISAM with two regions, Hokkaido and another region, based on the year 2000, which is discussed in the next section as a numerical example.</p><p>The original interregional I-O table for ISAM is based on year 1995, which has 9 regions and 46 sectors. The input coefficients of ISAM are updated by the RAS method (Bacharach, 1970;   Lynch, 1986) to 2000. The case study aggregates 10 industrial sectors for SAM multiplier and SPA estimation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">1 Structure of SAM (1) Intraregional SAM</head><p>SAM provides rich information on not only the economic situation of each sector but also comprehensive (or global) economic circulation. The matrix is constructed by economic sectors, like production activities, value added (or production factors), and institutional sectors as the rows and columns of the matrix, following three rules (Pyatt and Thorbecke, 1976):</p><p>A) A row and column with the same number (of matrix) is the same economic sector.</p><p>B) The sum of a row and column with the same number is the same. C) Expenditure of a sector is a row and income of a sector is a column, with the value reported at their intersection.</p><p>SAM simultaneously provides information on sectoral balance of payments and sectoral income/expenditure on transactions. Therefore, SAM clarifies actual economic circulation, including the distribution structure of value added, by constructing SAM with the abovementioned three conditions. Moreover, because the production activities of SAM are the same as the structure of the I-O table, SAM clarifies not only the entire economic circulation but also the detailed structure of production activities by incorporating the I-O table's ratio(s) or the structure of supply and demand by goods and services for each sector (or industry). The construction of SAM with detailed economic circulation provides the relationship between supply and demand of goods and services, and the principle of three equivalence of (national) income of value added (with final demand).</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">1</ref> shows the structure of simplified intraregional SAM, including the ROW for a single county or region. The lengthwise direction is income and the crosswise direction is expenditure. Here, we show the economic spillover mechanisms (by arrows) from the demand increase of exports by the "ROW." "Industry" produces value added by producing goods or services for export demand. The purchase of goods and services for production and consumption from the "ROW" is treated as imports, without distinguishing between intermediate goods and final goods. Some of the value added of "Capital" is redistributed to households of "Institute" as income from the reward for the labor of "Capital." Moreover, there is a transfer of money through taxes and subsidies within "Institute," after which households of "Capital" consume goods and services from posttax income, and the production of "Industry" is reinduced by the consumption demand of households. The SAM analysis can provide the paths of the economic spillover mechanism. Here, because the shaded areas in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">1</ref> are considered in the analysis of the I-O table, such analysis cannot discuss the economic spillover mechanisms through income redistribution by institutes (or governments).</p><p>(Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">1</ref>, insert here)</p><p>(2) Interregional SAM Here, we provide a possible framework of ISAM for a number of regions. This discussion supposes an ISAM in Japan, as we see later in this section. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> presents the structure of interregional SAM simplified for two regions, including the ROW. Based on Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref>, there are two differences between the models for a single region (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">1</ref>) and two regions (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref>).</p><p>One difference is the interregional distribution of value added of industry, or the rewards of labor and the operational surpluses of capital. For example, the value added by production of industry in Region 1 is distributed to Regions 1 and 2 based on the locations of suppliers of labor and capital for production. The second difference is the treatment of exports and imports.</p><p>Goods or services purchased from Region 1 by Region 2 as intermediate goods (or final consumption goods) are considered as inputs for production (or imports for consumption). On the other hand, purchases of goods and services (intermediate goods and final goods) from the ROW are reported as imports. As discussed, one of the characteristics of interregional SAM is the detailed reports of money flows between industries and institutes in Regions 1 and 2.</p><p>Similar to Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">1</ref>, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref> shows the economic spillover mechanisms (by arrows) for Region 1 of an export demand increase from the ROW. Again, similar to Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">1</ref>, the shaded areas in (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref>, insert here)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">2 Utilization data for interregional SAM construction</head><p>This subsection explains the main data sources needed for constructing an intraregional (interregional) SAM. We show (1) the interregional I-O table providing information about input structure (technical coefficient) of each industrial sector and (2) the regional economic accounting (or regional SNA) providing information about income/expenditure of institutions, for example, household, company, and government.</p><p>(</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1) Interregional input-output table in Japan</head><p>The interregional I-O table, which is the basic data for constructing ISAM for many regions at the same time, is constructed for interregional economic spillover analysis through interdependent interregional relationships. In Japan, the intraregional I-O tables are a joint project by the Ministry of Economy, Trade and Industry (METI), Cabinet Office, governments of Japan, Okinawa General Bureau, and Okinawa prefecture. The intraregional I-O tables, divided by nine Japanese regions 6 , has been constructed at 5-year intervals after 1960. In addition, METI's research and statistics department has connected the interregional I-O table to 6 Hokkaido, Tohoku, Kanto, Chubu, Kinki, Chugoku, Shikoku, Kyushu, and Okinawa (nine regions). the abovementioned regional I-O tables.</p><p>The intraregional I-O table shows the trade (money) flows of goods and services for a specific region within a certain period, similar to the I-O table for a single country or prefecture.</p><p>The analysis based on the table is limited to the trade flows in the relevant region. On the other hand, the interregional I-O table includes the economic activities of some regions on a single table and shows the trade flows of goods and services not only in the relevant region but also between regions. In particular, in the intraregional I-O table, the goods and services provided to other domestic regions from the relevant domestic region are accounted for as "exports," and the sum of exported goods and services is noted only on each sector. However, the goods and services produced in each sector of regions are accounted as the volume inputted or consumed by each sector in regions on the interregional I-O table 7 ; alternatively, these goods and services show the quantity of goods and services consumed by industries of each region. Thus, the interregional I-O table enables us to discuss not only the industrial trade flow structures between sectors of regions but also some interregional spillover effects, which are never discussed in the intraregional I-O table.</p><p>(2) National (or regional) economic accounting</p><p>The SNA (national economic accounting) is an international standard that systematically records both the flows of production, consumption, and investment, and the stocks of assets and debt for the national (or prefectural) economy.</p><p>For constructing the regional (or interregional) SAM at the level of prefectures, the economic accounting at the level of prefecture (or regional SNA) is needed as the main data and includes the regional I-O table of the relevant prefecture. Moreover, each dataset is required for the construction of intraregional SAM at the level of the municipality, which is lower than the prefecture. In addition to the regional I-O table, because regional economic accounting is undertaken in all Japanese prefectures, the basic data source for constructing regional SAMs is available. In particular, we are able to use the following table that is included in prefectural economic accounting: "income-expenditure transactions of general governments (IET table )."</p><p>Here, for example, the IET table is needed to construct the detailed regional (or interregional) SAMs. The table reflects the distinctive characteristics of this SAM analysis and has rich information on income-expenditure transactions in four institutional sectors; 1) local agencies of central government, 2) prefectural governments, 3) municipal governments, and 4) social security funds 8 .</p><p>The general basic rule for constructing regional economic accounting at the level of <ref type="bibr">7</ref> This interregional I-O table is known as the Isard-type I-O table. For detailed interregional I-O analysis, see Chapter 3 of Isard et al. (1998). In addition, the interregional I-O table is officially made up only in Japan; therefore, the discussion in this research provides useful information. <ref type="bibr">8</ref> See Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> in Itoh (2008b) for an actual table for Hokkaido prefecture.</p><p>prefectures is standardized by the Economic and Social Research Institute (ESRI) in Japan.</p><p>However, there is no confirmed rule for constructing an IET table. Therefore, this table comprises only 13 of 47 prefectures in Japan<ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">foot_4</ref> for regional economic accounting. In addition, for government-designated cities, whose level is lower than that of prefectures, only Osaka city comprises a part of this kind of table. Many government-designated cities make neither the IET table not their regional economic accounting per se, including the regional I-O table. If such a table is available, we can construct regional SAMs that indicate the money flows between central and regional governments or more detailed institutional sectors, and the economic impacts can be analyzed by the transfer of tax revenue sources from central to regional governments on the regional or interregional SAM.</p><p>(3) Challenges for regional (interregional) SAM construction</p><p>In general, this study constructs ISAM shown basically in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref> by using the interregional I-O table and regional and national economic accounting in Japan. Because the total income and expenditure of each sector must be the same under a characteristic of SAM conditions, as discussed in Subsection 3.1, the sums of each sectoral row and column in ISAM must also be the same. However, owing to differences of data estimation methods in various yearbooks of Japan, the total expenditure does not match the total income in some sectors. For example, although the I-O table is based on the calendar year, national economic accounting (i.e., SNA) is based on the fiscal year in Japan. Therefore, there is a natural gap of a quarter of a year. In addition, the data estimation methods of indirect taxes differ from Japanese yearbooks. In this research, we apply the RAS method, which is a sequential matrix modification method, for adjusting these gaps of values at each sector on ISAM for empirical analysis.</p><p>The challenges in the application of economic accounting data for SAM construction are the gaps of data estimation methods used to construct statistical yearbooks, and the differences between data listings in national and regional statistical yearbooks. For example, some Japanese prefectural governments do not compile and provide IET tables publicly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Analytical framework of ISAM construction and empirical example in Japan (1) Analytical framework of ISAM construction</head><p>In this research, we propose a detailed analytical framework, or structure, of ISAM focusing on income/expenditure, or money flows, of institutional sectors in (two) endogenous regions and "other part" (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>), and the ROW (exogenous). The basic steps for the ISAM construction with more than two regions are the same as this one; however, the volumes of data required for them make it difficult to construct ISAM.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> shows the (simplified) framework of ISAM with two regions (Hokkaido and another region in Japan), for the empirical example in Section 4. Each region has "production activities (industry, goods, and services)," "production factors (labor and capital)," and "institutional sectors." Moreover, this ISMA has "other part (endogenous sectors at the national level, see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>)," including direct tax, indirect tax, property income, other sectors (other current transfers), central government, which does not form part of each region, and lastly, foreign accounts (exogenous sectors, export and import of goods and services)<ref type="foot" target="#foot_5">foot_5</ref> .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(Table 1, insert here)</head><p>A rather important characteristic of ISAM proposed in this research is the creation of the trade flows of institutional sectors in precise detail following the SNA in Japan. The institutional sectors are divided into "current accounts (in general, household, company, and local government)" and "capital accounts (savings/investments)." Moreover, the current accounts are classified into five sectors (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>).</p><p>We can consider the detailed money flows of social costs and benefits by specifying four categories (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>) of local government (prefectures) based on an IET table." In addition, we can discuss the distributional structure of taxes in detail using indirect taxes (taxes for production and imported goods) and direct taxes (ordinary taxes for incomes and wealth) as independent terms on "other part."</p><p>(2) Empirical analysis of Hokkaido ISAM For empirical analysis, we construct the ISAM database with two regions by using the interregional I-O table and national and prefectural economic accounting in Japan. In particular, the two regions on ISAM are Hokkaido prefecture and another region of 46 prefectures. This is because Hokkaido prefecture is an independent region on the interregional I-O table in Japan and its IET table is publicly available. Therefore, Hokkaido prefecture would be a better region for construction of the ISAM proposed in this research. The ISAM for empirical analysis is based on the year 2000. Moreover, the case study of Hokkaido would be a very good example to understand the characteristics of this SAM framework because transportation and commerce systems are very important in this isolated region. In addition, the Hokkaido economy suffers from a very difficult economic situation. Meanwhile, the interregional I-O table for 2000 is not publicly available 11 . Therefore, we apply technology coefficients between industries on regions (or input coefficients in the interregional I-O table) from the database in 1995, and other information in 2000<ref type="foot" target="#foot_7">foot_7</ref> .</p><p>The difference between the proposed ISAM (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>) and Hokkaido ISAM for this empirical analysis is the treatment of local government (prefectural level). Because the IET table of Hokkaido is publicly available (see footnote 9), detailed information is available about the four sectors in local and central government. However, the breakdown of classified information for local government is not available for the other region(s) because we have to apply essentially the information on SNA (or national economic accounting), which includes only the central government, regional government, and social security funds, and this is a different classification to the prefectural information on regional economic accounting. Therefore, the Hokkaido ISAM for this empirical analysis has an aggregated "local government" of three sectors (local agency of central government, prefecture, and municipality) and social security funds for both regions in our comparative analysis in the next section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Analysis of economic spillover mechanism on Hokkaido ISAM</head><p>In this section, we analyze the economic spillover impacts by applying SAM multipliers for the Hokkaido ISAM developed in Section 3 as an empirical example. Next, we show the analytical challenges of SAM multipliers and introduce the SPA, which is an advanced analytical tool for studying economic structures, by using the ISMA. As a numerical example, this section discusses the differences of economic spillover mechanisms of Hokkaido and the other Japanese region by comparing in detail the economic impacts on their household incomes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">SAM multiplier analysis</head><p>This subsection shows the possibility of ISAM analysis by undertaking empirical analysis of the economic interdependence of both regions for the Hokkaido ISAM constructed in this study. For the classification of industrial sectors representing the input structure of the interregional I-O table of ISAM, this research uses the 10 aggregated industrial sectors based on the 46 interregional I-O tables in Japan that are publically available (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>). In this numerical example, we apply the decomposition method of the degrees of interregional economic interdependence by Round (1985) and Pyatt and Round (1979)  <ref type="bibr">13</ref> .</p><p>Here, y is the column vector of total expenditure (= total income) of each sector, x is the column vector of (total) exogenous sector(s), and B is the component matrix of SAM, which is similar to the input coefficient matrix of the I-O table. In addition, to match the empirical analysis of this study, we decompose each vector, y and x , and matrix B into two regions (parts), which, finally, allows us to construct the three required parts, including "other part" (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>). By solving Equation ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) for y , we take Equation (2). M shows the interregional "Global Multiplier Effects (GME)," or SAM multiplier(s). That is, the components of this matrix ( M ) indicate the increase of income of each sector for a unit increase of exogenous demand (i.e., exports).</p><p>x By y  </p><p>(1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">  Mx x B I y    1 (2)</formula><p>Moreover, considering ii B , which indicates a submatrix with expenditure from region i to each sector of region i , and ij b ˆ, which indicates a submatrix with expenditure from region i to each sector of region j , Equation ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) is converted to Equation (3). (3) to y , we can obtain Equations ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>) and (5). In this empirical analysis, subscript 1 is Hokkaido prefecture, 2 is the other region, and 3 is "other part 14 ." </p><formula xml:id="formula_1">                                         </formula><formula xml:id="formula_2">                                                           </formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">  ij ii ij b B I D 1    . Or, x M M y r r 1 2  (5) In Equation (5), 2 r M is constructed by "Interregional Multiplier Effects (IEME)"</formula><p>between Regions 1 and 2, and the multiplier (spillover) effects between each region (1 and 2) and "other part," and 1 r M is constructed by "Intraregional Multiplier Effects (IAME)" within each region (1 and 2) and the multiplier (spillover) effects within "other part."</p><p>14 See Appendix 3 in Itoh (2008b) for a detailed mathematical explanation about the decomposition method of the degree of interregional interdependence. For example, although the "household (H)" in Hokkaido has a 1.314 (income) increase by a unit (expenditure) increase by the "regional government (H)" in Hokkaido prefecture, the spillover effects from Hokkaido (own) region within the 1.314 (income) increase is just 0.940, based on the results of the matrix calculation for Hokkaido ISAM 15 .</p><p>Based on this, we can understand the income expanding mechanism ( 2 r M ) of households in Hokkaido through economic linkages with the other region and "other part" with taxes and subsidies (or the "household" row for Hokkaido in 2 r M ) after the (income) increase in each sector (or the "regional government" column for Hokkaido in 1 r M ) by the unit (expenditure) increase of "regional government (H)" in Hokkaido prefecture <ref type="bibr">16</ref> . In particular, the income via households, furthermore other services, and local government, are comparatively large. Similarly, "household (O)" in the other region has a 8.698 (income) increase by a unit (expenditure) increase by the "regional government (O)" of the other region. In this income increase (8.698), because the economic impacts of the economic linkages inside the (own) region is just 1.600, the impacts on another region, Hokkaido, and "other part" is bigger than the case in Hokkaido 17 . In particular, the income via household, nonfinance company, and local government are comparatively large.</p><p>As previously discussed, the advantage of SAM analysis is that it can evaluate in detail the transfers of income (distribution) in institutional sectors, including households. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref> summarizes the sectors that have economic impacts on the households of Hokkaido (H) and the other region (O) based on the size of the SAM multipliers (or GME) in decreasing order. The economic impacts from service sectors, including "commerce (H)" and "transportation (H)," for "household (H)" are comparatively large in Hokkaido prefecture. In addition, the capital sectors ("labor (H)" and "capital (H)") directly have economic impacts on "household (H)." On the other hand, the economic impacts on "household (O)" from "property income," "other sectors," and "central government" are large in the other region. Moreover, "household (O)" in the other region is affected economically by not only "finance company (O)" in other regions but also "finance company (H)" in Hokkaido prefecture focusing on finance companies in "current accounts."</p><p>(Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>, insert here) <ref type="bibr">15</ref> Because of the huge matrix with 43 rows and 43 columns, this paper does not insert the table of matrix. <ref type="bibr">16</ref> In particular, this is the sum of products of the row vector (1-by-43) of "household (H)" for Hokkaido with the column vector (43-by-1) of "local government (H)" for Hokkaido. <ref type="bibr">17</ref> The SMA multipliers of other regions are much bigger than those of Hokkaido because these multipliers depend on the SAM structure (economic size). The difference in economic size of both regions (the gross regional product of Hokkaido is just 3.9% of the national total, based on the I-O table in 2000) produces the differences of components in the SAM structure (economic size).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Structural Path Analysis of ISAM (1) Tool of Structural Path Analysis 18</head><p>We evaluated the economic spillover effects by SAM multipliers in Subsection 4.1. SAM multipliers indicate the (total) economic impacts through the direct and indirect spillover impacts on some economic agent (or household) by a unit (expenditure) increase on some sector (or agent). For example, an income increase of "household (H)" in Hokkaido is 1.314 for a unit (expenditure) increase of "local government (H)" in Hokkaido prefecture. Similarly, an income increase of "household (O)" in the other region is 8.698 for a unit (expenditure) increase of "local government (O)" in the other region. Even though it would be possible to decompose the SAM multiplier into intraregional (IAME) and interregional (IEME) spillover effects separately, we cannot distinguish the paths of these effects. If we can determine the paths of economic impacts, or spillover effects, we can discuss and understand which economic policy is effective, or identify sectors that are bottlenecks for regional economic development.</p><p>SPA is the analytical tool for this challenge. It can decompose the SAM multiplier(s) from some sector i (origin) to some sector j (destination) into each sectoral connection (paths or economic links). For example, we can know the path from the expenditure of the Hokkaido local government (origin) to the increasing household income (destination) in Hokkaido prefecture and which sector contributes to the income increase. In other words, SAM multiplier(s) do not clarify the "black box," that is, the economic structure and behavioral mechanism that is responsible for the effects (or, GME). SPA provides a detailed method of decomposing multipliers and of identifying the whole network of paths whose influence is transmitted from one sector of origin to the ultimate destination, thereby opening the "black box."</p><p>Here, this part explains the analytical tool of SPA by using the empirical results for Hokkaido ISAM. Once again, the economic impacts on "household (H)" in Hokkaido of a unit (expenditure) increase of "local government (H)" in Hokkaido prefecture, or the SAM multiplier (GME), is 1.314. For example, we pick up the spillover effects, as an example, via "other services (H)" and "labor (H)" within this (total) multiplier, and define the effects as "Direct Effects" (DE). Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">3</ref> shows this structural relationship. c is "Marginal Expenditure Propensity," which is a concept of input coefficients. In particular, c xi , or the expenditure on "other services (H)" within the unit expenditure of "local government (H)," is 0.526, which is from the results of the Hokkaido ISAM. Similarly, c yx , the expenditure on "labor (H)" within the unit expenditure of "other services (H)," is 0.342, and c jy , the expenditure on "household (H)" within the unit expenditure of "labor (H)," is 1.000. Finally, the spillover effect on "household (H)" from a unit expenditure increase of "local government (H)" via "other services (H)" and "labor (H)" is c xi ×c yx ×c jy = 0.526×0.342×1.000=0.179; this is equal to DE.</p><p>(Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">3</ref>, insert here) However, the effects on "household (H)" from "other services (H)" and "labor (H)" are not only this DE but also the other paths. For example, it is possible that effects are brought indirectly to "household (H)" via other sectors during the path from "other services (H)" to "labor (H)." Therefore, we define this effect as "Path Effects" (PE). In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">3</ref>, these PE are c xy and c zy ・c xz . The aggregated path effects with direct and indirect effects are defined as "Total Effects" (TE). In this empirical analysis, the TE from "local government (H)" to "household (H)" is 0.456; then the PE is 2.591, which is 0.465 divided by 0.179 <ref type="bibr">19</ref> . In general, the PE is proportionate to the number of sectors going through origin (i) to destination (j). This is understood economically as the duration time of economic impacts.</p><p>Moreover, the economic impacts (or spillover effects) from "local government (H)" to "household (H)" are not only via "other services (H)" and "labor (H)" but also other sectors. For example, the spillover effects on "household (H)" via "social security funds (H)" from "local government (H)" has a TE of 0.027. In this way, there are various paths for economic effects from "local government (H)" as the origin i to "household (H)" as the destination j. The sum of all TE(s) is GME, which is the same for the SAM multiplier discussed in Subsection 4.1.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> shows the spillover effects from "local government (H)" to "household (H)" in decreasing order of TE(s). The TE via "other services (H)" and "labor (H)" is 0.465, which is 35.4% for the SAM multiplier. In addition, the TE from "local government" directly (or no other connection with this sector) to "household (H)" is 0.344, which is 26.1% for the SAM multiplier.</p><p>The sum of the top six paths occupies about 80% of the SAM multiplier. We can observe the economic spillover mechanism by applying SPA in detail.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(Table 3, insert here) (2) Results of empirical analysis</head><p>This subsection compares and discusses the differences of economic spillover mechanisms on Hokkaido (H) and the other region (O) based on the SPA results. We decompose the SAM multipliers for "household(s)" of Hokkaido (H) and the other region (O) as the final destination. Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> summarizes the economic spillover mechanisms, or structural paths, for household <ref type="bibr">19</ref> The "Total Effects (TE)" is defined as (HH) in each region in decreasing order of TE(s) until the top 30 paths. To understand them easily, Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> is simplified by grouping some sectors with similar paths. Moreover, the &lt;number&gt; with a sector in the figure shows the order of TE of the sector as the origin for "household (H)" in Hokkaido. Similarly, the [number] with a sector in the figure shows the order of TE of the sector as the origin for "household (O)" in another region. For example, we can find a spillover path (the order of TE is 19 th ) to "household (H)" via "savings/investments (H)" and "construction (H)" from "nonfinance company (H)" as the origin. On the other hand, we can find a direct path (the order of TE is 26 th ) to "household (H)" from "nonfinance company (H). Moreover, "nonfinance company (H)" affects not only "household (H)" but also "household (O)" in the other region via "property income" (the order of TE is 24 th ).</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">    1 1   </formula><p>(Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>, insert here)</p><p>In this result, the comparison of spillover mechanisms for household incomes between Hokkaido and another region provide similar paths. Distinctively, there are significant spillover effects via "other services (H) and (O)" from "local government (H) and (O)," "social security funds (H) and (O)," and "private nonprofit organization (NPO) for household (H) and (O)" as the origins<ref type="foot" target="#foot_10">foot_10</ref> . Because "other services" include other public services and medical, healthcare, and social security services in the detailed 46 industrial sectors, these paths are quite reasonable.</p><p>Moreover, there is a significant path via "savings/investments (H) and (O)" and "construction (H) and (O)" from "nonfinance company (H) and (O)" as the origins to household income. This result shows that much of company savings flow to construction investments in both regions.</p><p>However, for the different spillover mechanisms, the economic impacts via industrial sectors on Hokkaido are relatively higher than those in the other region. For example, service industries, like "commerce (H)" and "transportation (H)," affect household income not only directly via "labor (H)" and "capital (H)" but also via "other services (H)." However, although "commerce (H)" has high TE(s) via both "labor (H)" and "capital (H)," "transport (H)" has high TE only via "labor (H)." The order of the TE via "capital (H)" from "transport (H)" is lower than 30 th because the transportation industry is typified by labor-intensive truck carriers. In addition, although the economic impact is not so high (30 th ), the spillover effect from "capital (H)" as the origin going though "nonfinance company (H)," "savings/investments (H)," "construction (H)," and "labor (H)" to household income in Hokkaido is distinguishable and different from the case in other regions. Hokkaido's regional economy, or economic spillover mechanism, depends much more on construction investments.</p><p>On the other hand, the economic impacts from "other part" as the origin to household income in the other region are higher than those in Hokkaido. For example, the "indirect tax" and "central government" as the origins affect household income via "local government (O)" and "social security funds (O)," respectively. Moreover, the function of "property income" for the economy in the other region differs from the case of Hokkaido. Although this sector directly affects "household (O)" (the order of TE is 8 th ), the sector is a hub of the economic impacts from not only "nonfinance company (O)" (29 th ) and "finance company (O)" (11 th ) in the other region but also from "nonfinance company (H)" (24 th ) and "finance company (H)" (13 th ) in Hokkaido as the origins indirectly affect household (O) to some extent. That is, the money from Hokkaido companies flows out of the intraregional economy (Hokkaido) to the external economy, or to the other region. Therefore, the size of income transfers (or subsidies) to households from not only central government and the other region's sectors but also intraregional companies in Hokkaido is relatively small compared to the case in the other region. Conversely, the size of economic impacts via service sectors, including commerce, transportation, and construction, on households in Hokkaido is relatively larger than the case in the other region or sectors, including updates on logistics infrastructure and the introduction of modern distribution systems, which have more potent multiplier effects for Hokkaido's economy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p>This study proposed an ISAM framework with detailed institutional sectors by discussing the structure and availability of data in Japan. In particular, we constructed an ISAM with Hokkaido prefecture and another region based on the interregional I-O table for 2000 and national and prefectural economic accounting. This ISAM was built based on an Isard-type I-O table and considered in detail monetary exchanges of institutional sectors, especially local and central governments, social security funds, and some taxes. Moreover, this study conducted a comparative analysis of the economic spillover mechanisms for household income of each region by applying an analytical tool of SPA for the ISAM database as a case study, which enabled a discussion on the differences of economic multiplier mechanisms in both regions.</p><p>For further research, we propose the following two directions. The first direction involves construction of a multiregional SAM based on the analytical framework of this research. Because the original interregional I-O table is for nine regions (there are two regions in the database for this study), construction of a multiregional SAM with regional characteristics of each region is needed. The second proposed research direction involves modeling multiregional (or spatial) CGE by applying the database of ISAM. An EMA that endogenizes price (or cost) mechanisms is available by incorporating the functions of income transfers between institutional sectors, especially central and regional governments, and the decision making of shippers and transport companies who use transportation and commercial services in SCGE. For example, the result of model shift analysis (see Itoh, 2008a, for Japanese shippers), or the elasticity of transport models by discrete choice analysis would be incorporated in the functions of shippers (or manufacturers, wholesalers, and retailers) in the SCGE model. Because the regional economy has quite different characteristics compared with the national economy, differences of transportation and distribution systems would affect much more than the regional economy. However, because of data limitations, most ISAM analyses, including CGE analyses, are for international and national levels.</p><p>Liberalization: Computable general equilibrium analysis based on an inter-regional input-output One of the advantages of economy-wide model analysis is its ability to evaluate the economic impacts on the regional economy by the difference between trade patterns. For discussing the impacts on regional economies of their differences of distribution systems, this SAM uses the commercial sector (commerce margin) and transportation sector (transport margin) as sectors that are independent from other service sectors. See Itoh (2008b) for details.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Direct tax</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Indirect tax</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Property income</head><p>Other sectors Central Gov.     Source: Author's construction. Notes: ROW is "rest of the world" and VA is "value added." As in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">1</ref>, this model does not consider a "savings/investments" function as a subsidiary unit of the institutional sector. Therefore, this model assumes that the sector, including households, must consume all disposable income in a year, in other words, there are no savings. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2 are considered only for the analysis of the interregional I-O table.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>zoning a) the part of income/expenditure within the own region, b) the part of income/expenditure with the other region, and c) the part of income/expenditure with "other part (or taxes and money transfers of governments in this framework)," and solving Equation</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 3, and   1 *  is the "Path Effects (PE)." See Defourny and Thorbecke (1984) for details.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: The structure of Intraregional SAM</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: The structure of Interregional SAM</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Direct Effect, Path Effect and Total Effect</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>table , "</head><label>,</label><figDesc>Research Institute of Economy, Trade and Industry (RIETI), Discussion</figDesc><table><row><cell>Tables and Figures</cell></row><row><cell>Paper Series, 08-J-053, pp.1-35. (in Japanese)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 : Classification of accounts on ISAM</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="4">(a) Endogenous Sectors, Each Region (Hokkaido pref. and other region)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Normal SAM</cell><cell>SAM in this research</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Industry</cell><cell>Industry (see, table below in details)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Production Activities</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Goods and services</cell><cell>Goods and services</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Labor</cell><cell>Labor</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Production Factors</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Capital</cell><cell>Capital</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Household</cell><cell>Household (single category)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Private NPO for household</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Company</cell><cell>Non-finance company</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Current</cell><cell></cell><cell>Finance company</cell></row><row><cell>Institution</cell><cell>Accounts</cell><cell></cell><cell>Local agency of central Gov.</cell></row><row><cell>Sectors</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Prefecture</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Local Government (Prefecture)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>City, town and village</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Social security funds</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Capital Accounts</cell><cell>Saving/Investment</cell><cell>Saving/Investment</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">(b) Endogenous Sectors, "other part" (not included in each region)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">(c) Exogenous Sectors</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Export / Import</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">(d) 10 Industrial Sectors</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sector 1</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Agriculture, forestry and fisheries industry</cell></row><row><cell>Sector 2</cell><cell></cell><cell>Mining</cell></row><row><cell>Sector 3</cell><cell></cell><cell>Non-durable goods manufacturing</cell></row><row><cell>Sector 4</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Infrastructure equipment manufacturing</cell></row><row><cell>Sector 5</cell><cell></cell><cell>Durable goods manufacturing</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Sector 6</cell><cell>Construction</cell></row><row><cell>Sector 7</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Electric, gas, heat and water supply, and waste</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Sector 8</cell><cell>Commerce</cell></row><row><cell>Sector 9</cell><cell></cell><cell>Transportation</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Sector 10</cell><cell>Other services</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Source: Author's construction.</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>Note: In this analysis, 10 industrial classifications are obtained by aggregating the publicly available interregional I-O table with 46 industrial sectors.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 : SAM Multipliers focused on household (HH) incomes by Hokkaido ISAM</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Hokkaido (H)</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Other regions(O)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Sectors</cell><cell>SAM Multiplier</cell><cell>Sectors</cell><cell>SAM Multiplier</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>Labor (H)</cell><cell>1.997</cell><cell>Labor (O)</cell><cell>9.561</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>Commerce (H)</cell><cell>1.502</cell><cell>Social security funds (O)</cell><cell>9.134</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>Transportation (H)</cell><cell>1.434</cell><cell>Commerce (O)</cell><cell>9.095</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>Other services (H)</cell><cell>1.374</cell><cell>Property Income</cell><cell>8.991</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>Capital (H)</cell><cell>1.320</cell><cell>Other sector</cell><cell>8.989</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>Local government (H)</cell><cell>1.314</cell><cell>Finance company (O)</cell><cell>8.867</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>Construction (H)</cell><cell>1.267</cell><cell>Capital (O)</cell><cell>8.858</cell></row><row><cell>8</cell><cell>Utilities (H)</cell><cell>1.261</cell><cell>Central government</cell><cell>8.790</cell></row><row><cell>9</cell><cell>Social security funds (H)</cell><cell>1.234</cell><cell>Other services (O)</cell><cell>8.774</cell></row><row><cell>10</cell><cell>Agriculture etc (H)</cell><cell>1.128</cell><cell>Direct tax</cell><cell>8.758</cell></row><row><cell>11</cell><cell>Private NPO for HH (H)</cell><cell>1.111</cell><cell>Indirect tax</cell><cell>8.733</cell></row><row><cell>12</cell><cell>Infrastructure Manu. (H)</cell><cell>1.084</cell><cell>Local government (O)</cell><cell>8.698</cell></row><row><cell>13</cell><cell>Saving/Investment (H)</cell><cell>1.037</cell><cell>Finance company (H)</cell><cell>8.665</cell></row><row><cell>14</cell><cell>Non-durable Manu. (H)</cell><cell>0.925</cell><cell>Construction (O)</cell><cell>8.658</cell></row><row><cell>15</cell><cell>Non-finance company (H)</cell><cell>0.899</cell><cell>Private NPO for HH (O)</cell><cell>8.499</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Source: Author's construction.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3 : Economic Spillover Mechanism Local Gov. (H) i  HH (H) j via sectors Direct Effects Path effects</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Total effects</cell><cell>% (Accu. %)</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>See Itoh (2005)  and<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Itoh and Doi (2008)</ref> for the endogenizing consumption model in the I-O analysis.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>See Stone and Croft-Murray (1959)  for early research by Stone on SAM.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_2"><p>SAM is a very useful analytical tool. However, similar to I-O analysis, SAM assumes that the prices of goods and production factors, production technology (input efficient), and allocation of production factors are stable. Thus, SAM analyzes only the regional economic spillover effects by an increase in final demand under a constant (stable) production structure in the short term.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_3"><p>See Donaghy (2009)  for a recent survey of CGE models and<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Doi (2006)</ref> for recent empirical analyses using CGE models.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="9" xml:id="foot_4"><p>The 13 prefectures in Japan are Hokkaido, Aomori, Iwate, Akita, Miyagi, Ibaraki, Niigata, Nagano, Aichi, Hyogo, Okayama, Saga, and Okinawa.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="10" xml:id="foot_5"><p>See Appendix 1 in<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Itoh (2008b)</ref> for the value elicitation of each cell in the ISAM database.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="11" xml:id="foot_6"><p>However, currently, the interregional I-O table in 2005 is available publicly. http://www.meti.go.jp/statistics/tyo/tiikiio/.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="12" xml:id="foot_7"><p>Because of space constraints, this paper omits an actual Hokkaido ISAM database: there are, in total, 45 rows and 45 columns.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="13" xml:id="foot_8"><p>See Roberts (1998)  for a recent empirical analysis discussing the decomposition method for the degree of interregional interdependences. The case study of this paper is for the northeast region in Scotland.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="18" xml:id="foot_9"><p>See Defourny and Thorbecke (1984)  for initial research about SPA. Moreover, see<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Sonis and Hewings (1998)</ref> for recent research discussing SPA for interregional I-O tables.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="20" xml:id="foot_10"><p>The spillover paths via industrial sectors go through the capital sector (capital and labor) just after the industry because of the structure of ISAM.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The original research appears in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Itoh (2008b)</ref> in Japanese. Because of space constraints, the current paper essentially focuses on SPA for the conference. Refer to the original paper for the construction of the Japanese ISAM.</p><p>The idea for this research is based on a discussion during my sabbatical leave in 2006-2008 at the <rs type="institution">Regional Science Group</rs>, the <rs type="funder">Department of City and Regional Planning, Cornell University</rs>, with <rs type="person">Prof. Iwan J. Azis</rs>, <rs type="person">Prof. Kieran P. Donaghy</rs>, <rs type="person">Emeritus Prof. Sidney Saltzman</rs>, and <rs type="person">Emeritus Prof. Walter Isard</rs>, a founder of regional science who passed away on November 6, 2010. Moreover, I am extremely grateful for support with the numerical analysis of SPA by <rs type="person">Prof. Azis</rs>, the head of regional economic integration at the <rs type="funder">Asian Development Bank since July 2010</rs>. I am responsible for any remaining errors.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Bacharach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Biproportional Matrices and Input-Output Change</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural Path Analysis and Multiplier Decomposition within A Social Accounting Matrix Framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jacques</forename><surname>Defourny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Erik</forename><surname>Thorbecke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Economic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">373</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Computable General Equilibrium Approaches in Urban and Regional Policy Studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Masayuki</forename><surname>Doi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>World Scientific Publishing Co. Pte. Ltd</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Singapore</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Analysis of Economic Impacts of Transportation Improvement for the Remote Hokkaido Region</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Masayuki</forename><surname>Doi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hiroshi</forename><surname>Kimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hidekazu</forename><surname>Itoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Japan Research Center for Transport Policy</title>
		<title level="s">Nikkoken Series A-417</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CGE Modeling in Space, A Survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kieran</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Donaghy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Regional Growth And Development Theories</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Capello</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Nijkamp</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cheltenham</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Edward Elgar Publishing</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="66" to="85" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Isard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Iwan</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Walter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Matthew</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Azis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ronald</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Drennan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sidney</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Erik</forename><surname>Saltzman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Thorbecke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Methods of Interregional and Regional Analysis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Vermont</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Ashgate Publishing Company</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Study based on the Miyazawa Framework of Endogenizing Consumption Model in the Input-Output Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hidekazu</forename><surname>Itoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Administration Kwansei Gakuin University</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hidekazu</forename><surname>Itoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">An Analysis of Route Choice Model on Cargo Transport for Modal Shift Policy: An Application of Random Parameter Logit Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2008</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="208" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Interregional SAM Building focused on Institutional Sectors and Structure Path Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hidekazu</forename><surname>Itoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Administration Kwansei Gakuin University</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008b</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Endogenizing Consumption in the Input-Output Model: Theory and Application</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hidekazu</forename><surname>Itoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Masayuki</forename><surname>Doi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Urban &amp; Regional Development Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="151" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Assessment of the RAS Method for Updating Input-Output Tables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lynch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Readings in Input-Output Analysis</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sohn</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ronald</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Peter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Blair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Input-Output Analysis: Foundations and Extensions</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New Jersey</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Spatial Computable General Equilibrium Approach for Measuring Multiregional Impacts of Large Scale Transportation Projects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Miyagi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Network Infrastructure and the Urban Environment</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lundqvist</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mattsson</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin, Springer</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="224" to="241" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accounting and Fixed Price Multipliers in a Social Accounting Framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pyatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Round</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Economic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="850" to="873" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Planning Techniques for a Better Future</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pyatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Thorbecke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
			<publisher>International Labour Organization (ILO)</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Geneva</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rural-urban interdependencies: Analysis using an inter-regional SAM model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Deborah</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Review of Agricultural Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="506" to="527" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decomposing Multipliers for Economic Systems Involving Regional and World Trade</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jeffery</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Round</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Economic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="383" to="399" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Economic Complexity as Network Complication: Multiregional Input-Output Structural Path Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Sonis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Geoffery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hewings</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Annals of Regional Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="407" to="436" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Croft-Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Social Accounting and Economic Models</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Bowes &amp; Bowes Publisher</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1959">1959</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shiro</forename><surname>Takeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kanemi</forename><surname>Ban</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Regional Disparities in the Effects of Trade [1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Agri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Forestry Etc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Non-durable Manu</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Other services &lt;8: via LG / IS6&gt; Finance company (O) Finance company (H) &lt;24: via LG / Capital&gt; Social security funds</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Construction 7: Electric, gas etc</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
