<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Effects of Social Capital on Fertility in Indonesia Path Analysis of Susenas 2014</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lidya</forename><surname>Sri</surname></persName>
							<email>lidya_sy@yahoo.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master Program in Population and Labor Economics Faculty of Economics and Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitas Indonesia Depok</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Omas</forename><surname>Bulan Samosir</surname></persName>
							<email>omasbr@yahoo.co.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master Program in Population and Labor Economics Faculty of Economics and Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitas Indonesia Depok</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Effects of Social Capital on Fertility in Indonesia Path Analysis of Susenas 2014</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T21:29+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>social capital</term>
					<term>family planning</term>
					<term>fertility</term>
					<term>path analysis</term>
					<term>Indonesia</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This research aims to study the direct and indirect effects of social capital forming sub-dimensions on fertility seen from number of children ever born (CEB) through the practice of family planning by applying path analysis with generalized structural equation modeling (GSEM) method. The formation of sub-dimensional variables of social capital is performed by using factor analysis, forming 7 (seven) factors, i.e. participation in group, social network, religious tolerance, ethnic tolerance, collective action, trust and reciprocity. The control variables are urban status, education level, work status and age. This research uses the National Socio-Economic Survey in 2014 for Indonesian, with the analysis unit of women aged at 15-54 years who have ever married. The result of the analysis shows that subdimensions of social capital and control variables have direct and indirect effects on fertility from CEB through the practice of family planning of ever married woman aged 15-54 years. Older and higher educated women have the highest total effect, followed by the low religion tolerance and high network.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Population with its various characteristics is a main factor that influences all aspects of development. Large population without good quality will be a burden for development. The high rate of population growth and the unequal distribution of population have been problems faced generally by developing countries, including Indonesia. The family planning program and awareness on controlling population that have been done by the Government of Indonesia through the national family planning program in the past have been successful in reducing fertility level and the population growth.</p><p>The results of the Indonesian Demographic and Health Survey (IDHS) show that fertility in Indonesia is still relatively high, although it has declined. Even in the period of 2002-2007 the birth rate in Indonesia showed a slight increase and had been stagnant. The fertility level of Indonesia indicated by the total fertility rate (TFR), has decreased from 3.03 children per women at childbearing age in 1991 to 2.56 in 2002. Furthermore, in 2007 the TFR experienced slight increase to 2.59 children and then stalled at 2.59 in 2012. Source: BKKBN <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> Many studies have attempted to explain the phenomenon causing fertility, primarily seen from the condition of individual characteristics, health conditions and program socialization. But, so far there is no study involving the relationship of fertility and social capital in households. The relationship between social capital and fertility is not a direct relationship <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref>.</p><p>In addition, some experts proposed the theory of fertility. Davis and Blake <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> argued that social, economic and cultural factors will affect fertility through the intermediate variables, which are variables that directly affect the size of fertility such as the practice of family planning. Furthermore, Freedman <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> proposed that norms prevailing in society also have effects on fertility by looking at the number of children. Further, Balbo and Mills <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> investigated how the family network, one of the core of social capital, has a relationship with fertility.</p><p>Although theories linking fertility and social capital have been growing in number, existing researches are likely to ignore the condition that individuals, or couples, do not make fertility decisions independently but are actually affected by the people in their environment. Therefore, this study attempts to examine that fertility is determined by the decision to have children formed through social capital seen from its subdimensions of family planning practice. This research is expected to reveal how significant the sub-dimension factors of social capital formation and control variables will affect fertility either directly or indirectly through the practice of family planning. Moreover, social capital research is an interesting and important research to be discussed, although the materials and study in Indonesia is still very limited. Besides, the sub-dimension of social capital formation as one of the components is not easy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. LITERATURE REVIEW</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Fertility</head><p>Fertility (birth) in the development of demographic science is defined as the result of real reproduction (children ever born) from a woman or group of women <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. In general, fertility measurement is usually indicated by the total fertility rate (TFR). Davis and Blake <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> conducted a sociological analysis of fertility and proposed that social, economic and cultural factors affect fertility through the intermediate variables. Later, Freedman <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> developed a concept of variables of Davis and Blake <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and argued that the norms prevailing in society also have effects on fertility. Bongaarts <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> proposed that fertility is influenced by indirect factors and direct determinants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Social Capital</head><p>Social capital has a very important role in affecting individuals or couples on fertility decision. Buhler and Philipov <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> described the relationship of social capital and fertility based on the mutual exchange relationship; in which there is information and experience exchanges of fertility, which implicitly also contain subjective perceptions and mindsets. Each individual, family and environment has fertility norms and attitudes based on the background characteristics of individual, family and environment, such as perceptions of children's values, religion, settlement conditions, education, employment status, age at first marriage, income, infant/child mortality <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</p><p>Hasbullah <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> argued that the real identity of social capital is guided values and norms taken as references to act and behave. They connect to other parties that bind to the process of change and to the efforts of society to achieve a goal. These values and elements are manifested in participatory attitudes, mutual caring attitudes, mutual giving and receiving, mutual trust, the willingness of the community or group to be constantly proactive in maintaining values, formation cooperation networks and creation of new ideas, and overall reinforced by the values and norms that support them.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Approaches or indicators recommended by Grootaert and</head><p>Bastelaar <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> to represent social capital appropriately at the micro level are attitudes of trust and compliance with norms, membership in local associations and networks, and collective actions covering various activities undertaken by a group of people.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Fertility and Social Capital</head><p>Balbo and Mills <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> proposed that in addition to economic and cultural factors, social capital has an important effect associated with fertility decisions. The high level of family social capital has negative effect on the number of children; which means the higher the social capital level of a family, the lower the possibility of realizing the intention to have children or to add the number of children. Bongaarts &amp; Watkins <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> proved the effect of one of social capital dimensions which is social interaction, on the fertility decision. Kuziemko <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> conducted a study on micro data related to the effects of social interactivity on fertility, by proving the chances of having a child will increase substantially after a sibling has a child.</p><p>Bernardi et.al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> conducted an investigation of social interaction on family formation. The purpose was to obtain evidence of the importance of informal social interaction on fertility and family behavior. Furthermore, Keim et.al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> conducted a research on the effects of social interaction on individual fertility decisions. This study shows that social interactions and partner fertility, subjective perceptions, and networks have effects on fertility.</p><p>Rossier &amp; Bernardi <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> proposed how the theory planned behavior (TPB) can explain fertility event by integrating three social networking mechanisms; those are social effect, social learning, and social support. Billari et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> conducted a study on low fertility cases in 2002 and stated that the TPB that relies on attitudes, norms and behaviors has relationship to individual fertility.</p><p>Based on the above empirical studies, it can be concluded that the TPB <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> integrating family network with fertility decision can be used as the basis in this study to examine the relationship of social capital and fertility. However, in assessing the problem of fertility and social capital, it is not enough to merely view social capital from the side of family networks. It should be studied comprehensively, especially related to the elements of social capital formation, including how dimensions of groups and networks, trust and solidarity and tolerance can affect fertility behavior.</p><p>In analytical framework of this study, measurements are made on women aged at 15-54 who have ever married by looking at control variables through the family planning practice to determine the direct and indirect effects of each subdimension of social capital on the number of children ever born (CEB) by measurement stages performed simultaneously.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. METHODOLOGY</head><p>This study used data sources derived from the 2014 National Socioeconomic Survey on the selected households spread throughout Indonesia and consisted household information and social security module <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. The analysis units in this study are ever married women aged 15-54 years in each selected sample household. The number of samples in this study is 79,754 of ever married women aged 15-54 years.</p><p>The formation of sub-dimension is performed by using factor analysis method, which aims to get stock of every sub dimension of social capital on ever married women aged at 15-54 years all over Indonesia. From a series of statistical tests conducted on 29 (twenty-nine) question-items, there were 24 (twenty-four) question items that fulfilled and formed 7 (seven) sub-dimensional factors of social capital formation, which are participation in groups, networks, religious tolerance, ethnic tolerance, collective action, trust and reciprocity relationships. The stock values of each sub-dimension of social capital formation are in the form of a numerical scale, then the stock values will be grouped into two categories: low (&lt;average) and high (≥ average). In this study control variables are also used in determining the effects of social capital on fertility, i.e urban status, education level, work status and age. The analytical methods used are descriptive analysis and path analysis. Path analysis is employed to find out how significant direct, indirect and total effects of independent variables on the dependent variable are. Most of the path theory pathway approaches are conducted using the ordinary least squares (OLS) method <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. But, one method that can be used when the data are dichotomous is the logistic regression method by measuring relationships using maximum likelihood <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Karima <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> stated that the measurement coefficients of each path analysis model are carried out separately based on logistic methods to measure the direct and indirect effects between exogenous and endogenous variables represented in the path diagram. Data processing for dependent variable of dichotomous or binary type is performed by generalized structural equation model (gsem) method.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Inferential Models</head><p>In general, the inferential models for fertility used in this study are as follows.</p><p>• Model 1 Y = Effect of sub dimension of social capital and control variable on the practice of family planning  </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">              religi</formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">                    </formula><formula xml:id="formula_2">                 KB</formula><p>• Model 3 Y = Effect of sub dimension of social capital and control variables on fertility </p><formula xml:id="formula_3">              religi netw group</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Calculation of Direct, Indirect and Total Effects</head><p>The calculation of total effect on the number of children ever born can be illustrated as follows. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Descriptive Analysis</head><p>An overview of respondents' characteristics based on main independent variables used is the sub-dimension values of social capital. It can be seen that the majority of ever married women aged 15-54 years are those in high participation of a group (56,79%), having low network (70.64%), low religious tolerance (51.11%), high ethnic tolerance (74.50%), high action (56.71%), high trust (63.54%) and a high reciprocity (62.61%). Based on the control variables, most of the women in the sample live in rural area (57.70%), the highest level of education is being graduated from primary or junior high school (48.81%), employment status (59.26%) and adult (26-45 years) (64.96%).</p><p>The stock values of social capital in Indonesia have a range from 57.97 to 65.84, with an average of 52.99. These values indicate that women in Indonesia have relatively good or moderate social capital. Based on the sub dimensions of social capital formation, the sub-dimension of action has a fairly high contribution compared to sub dimensions of other social capital (8.38%), and the sub dimension of network has the lowest contribution (6.23%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Path Model of Fertility</head><p>From the path analysis, it can be seen that there is variable that has no significant effect on the predisposition of family planning practice and the small number of children (3 children or less). Therefore, in order to obtain the best model, variables that have no significant effect on the practice of family planning or the small number of children will not be included in the path analysis, i.e. the religious tolerance variable. The same result was obtained from the research by Pauline et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> in religious and ethnic effects on family approval on the practice of family planning in the case of women in Kenya. In the model resulting from his research, it shows that religious indicator has insignificant effect on family planning practice. Then, trust variable also has insignificant effect on the predisposition to have small number of children. This is because women have different perceptions of trust about women's ease of trust and fear of risks, such as believing that having many children is future investment. On the other hand having many children has health risk such as cervical cancer and heart disease, and other maternal and child health problems.</p><p>The results of the significance test on the best model of fertility path analysis to determine whether all independent variables can be used together in forming the model can be seen in Akaike's information criterion and Bayesian information criterion table of log (likelihood) value (67.511,78). Thus, it can be concluded that the model consisting of all explanatory variables is statistically significant and can be used together in forming the model. The model shows that variables of participation in groups, networks, ethnic tolerance, action, trust, reciprocity, residential area, education level, employment status and age statistically make significant direct effects on the decision to do family planning with p value &lt;0,05. Similarly, variables of participation in groups, networks, religious tolerance, ethnic tolerance, action, reciprocity, residential area, education level, employment status and age, including decisions on practicing family planning have statistically significant effects on predisposition of having small number of children (3 children or less) with p &lt;0.05.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Direct, Indirect and Total Effects</head><p>In order to estimate the total effect of each independent variable on the number of children ever born, the calculation of direct and indirect effects was performed. This calculation can be performed when b coefficient for each variable is standardized by using Microsoft Excel function/formula <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. For example, the calculation for sub-dimensional variable of participation in group was estimated to have direct effect on the small number of children and indirect effect on the practice of family planning. The significant of direct effect of the subdimension of participation in groups on the small number of children is 0.0059, whereas the indirect effect was obtained by multiplying b coefficient of sub-dimension of participation in group that directly affects the practice of family planning (0.0160) with b coefficient of the effect of the practice of family planning on the small number of children (0,0122). So, the value of indirect effect of the sub dimension of participation in the group obtained is 0.0160 x 0.0122 = 0.0002. The total effect of sub-dimensions of participation in groups on the small number of children is 0.0059 + 0.0002 = 0.0061. Similarly, the same calculation was performed for all variables used.</p><p>Based on the sub-dimensions of social capital formation, participation in group has positive total effect on the decision to have small number of children (3 children or less) with b coefficient of 0.0061. This means that participation in a high group will be likely to make women have small number of children. In simple terms, organizations promote active roles for women in social and economic life, both within family and society. The integration of three mechanisms of social networking, namely social effect, social learning, and social support is well explained through the Theory Planned Behavior (TPB) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</p><p>Of all sub dimensions of social capital formation, ethnic tolerance has the greatest total effect, but has negative effect on the decision to have small number of children that is equal to -0.028. The greatest total positive effect on the decision to have small number of children is in the sub dimension of network that is equal to 0.0187, greater than the sub dimensions of other social capital formation. This is in line with previous researches using networking concept to determine relationships with fertility <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1]</ref>.</p><p>Viewed from all the independent variables used, the total effect of age variable is greater in affecting the decision to have small number of children, where the effect is negative, i.e. women with adult age (26-45 years) and elderly age (46-54 years) have total effect of -0.4203 and -0.397 respectively. This means that elderly women are more likely to have large number of children (more than 3 children). The greatest total effect is then followed by the variables of high education (graduated from senior high school or more) and intermediate levels of education (graduated from elementary and junior high) with total effect values of 0.1194 and 0.0575 respectively. This means that women ever married aged around 15-54 years with higher level of education are more likely to have small number of children (3 children or less).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. CONCLUSION</head><p>The predisposition of ever married women aged at 15-54 to practice family planning is higher among women with high group participation, high networking, low ethnic tolerance, high collective action, high trust, and high reciprocity, and who are rural residents, highly educated, unemployed and adult (26-45 years). The predisposition for women aged15-54 years to have small number of children (3 children or less) among women with high group participation, high networking, high religious tolerance, low tribal tolerance, low collective action, high trust, and high reciprocity, and are urban residents, highly educated, unemployed and youth <ref type="bibr">(15-26 years)</ref>. Meanwhile the sub-dimensional variable of religious tolerance has no significant effect on the use of family planning, and the sub dimensional variable of trust does not have a significant effect to have small number of children (3 children or less).</p><p>In addition, there are direct effects (participation in groups, networks, ethnic tolerance, collective action, trust, reciprocity, residence, education and age) and indirect effects through the practice of family planning (participation in groups, networks, religion tolerance, ethnic tolerance, collective action, reciprocity, residential area, education and age) of the number of children ever born. Based on the calculation of the total effect of standardized b coefficient value of each independent variable on the small number of children, it was found that the age and high education level (graduated from high school or higher) have the greatest total effect, followed by sub dimensions of low ethnic tolerance and high network.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIGURE 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>FIGURE 1. TOTAL FERTILITY RATE (TFR) IN INDONESIA, 1991 -2012 (CHILDREN PER WOMAN).</figDesc><graphic coords="1,331.90,243.85,205.85,98.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Model 2 Y = Effect of the practice of family planning on</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>having; small number of children (3 children or less) 1-πi : Probability of having; large number of children (more than 3 children)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>FIGURE 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>FIGURE 2. ILLUSTRATION OF DIRECT, INDIRECT AND TOTAL EFFECT ON THE NUMBER OF CHILDREN EVER BORN</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>FIGURE 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>FIGURE 3. PATH ANALYSIS MODEL OF FERTILITY</figDesc><graphic coords="4,306.70,134.40,249.40,263.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>describes</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>* We gratefully acknowledge financial support from statistics of Indonesia.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of The Family Network on The Realization of Fertility Intentions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">F G</forename><surname>Balbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mills</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vienna Yearbook of Population Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social influences on fertility: a Comparative Mixed Methods Study in Eastern and Western Germany</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bernardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Keim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Von</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Der Lippe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Mixed Methods Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Attitudes, norms and perceived behavioural control: Explaining fertility intentions in Bulgaria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Billari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Philipov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Testa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Population</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="439" to="465" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Framework for Analyzing the Proximate Determinants of Fertility</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Bongaarts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Population and Development Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social Interactions and Contemporary Fertility Transitions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bongaarts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Watkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Population and Development Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="639" to="682" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Survei Sosial ekonomi Nasional</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Indonesia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>BPS</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2015. 2014. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Social Capital Related to Fertility: Theoretical Foundations and Empirical Evidence from Bulgaria. Vienna Yearbook of Population Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christoph</forename><forename type="middle">&amp;</forename><surname>Buhler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Philipov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Dimiter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="81" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Path Analysis Using Logistic Regression: Interpretational and Methodologic Issues</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Curtis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Salman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Strickland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Edmonston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Dan Erb</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 5th International Symposium on Veterinary Epidemiology and Economics</title>
		<meeting>the 5th International Symposium on Veterinary Epidemiology and Economics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social Structure and Fertility: An Analytic Framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Blake</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Economic Development and Cultural Change</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="211" to="235" />
			<date type="published" when="1956">1956</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Dasar-Dasar Demografi</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>LD FEUI</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Demographic Institute University of Indonesia (LD FEUI</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Principles of Demography</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Fertility Revolution: A Supply-Demand Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Easterlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eileen</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Crimmins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985. 1985</date>
			<publisher>The University of Chicago Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="31" />
			<pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Freedman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Sociology of Human Fertility: An Annotated Bibliography</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Irvington Publishers, Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">283</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Grootaert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Bastelaer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Role of Social Capital in Development. An Empirical Assesment</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Social Capital: Menuju Keunggulan Budaya Manusia Indonesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jousairi</forename><surname>Hasbullah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>MR-United Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Jakarta</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Profil Kependudukan dan Pembangunan di Indonesia Tahun 2013 [Population and Development Profile in Indonesia</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 2013</date>
			<publisher>BKKBN</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Indonesia</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Indonesia&apos;s National Population and Family Planning Board (BKKBN)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Path Analysis for the Adoption of Modern Contraception in Morocco. An Evaluation of Women&apos;s Status, Husband&apos;s Approval and Mass Media on the Use of Modern Contraeption among the Moroccan Married Women</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gholzouri</forename><surname>Karima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Public Health and Tropical Medecine of Tulae University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Keim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Klarner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bernardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Qualifying Social Influence on Fertility Intentions: Composition, Structure, and Meaning of Fertility-Relevant Social Networks. Current Sociology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009. 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jason</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Standardized coefficients in logistic regression. Paper presented at the annual meeting of the Southwest Educational Research Association</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Antonio, TX</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Is Having Babies Contagious? Fertility Peer Effects Between Adult Siblings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kuziemko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>Princeton University Working Paper</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Religion and Ethnicity on Family Planning Approval: A Case for Women in Rural Western Kenya</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Pauline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mutombo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mukiira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kamande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ezeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Muga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Reli Heal</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social Interaction Effects on Fertility: Intentions and Behaviors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rossier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bernardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Population</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="467" to="485" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why do Americans want children?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schoen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nathanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fields</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Astone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Population and Development Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
