<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Multiple paths of green and low-carbon development in industrial parks: group analysis based on the TOE framework</title>
				<funder ref="#_5SxPQqU">
					<orgName type="full">Five-Year Plan of Educational Science in Guangxi Province of China</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_54reGr7">
					<orgName type="full">Threshold of Public Governance</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_Z5RUsV5">
					<orgName type="full">National Natural Science Foundation of China</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NSFC</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_CTQMD7E">
					<orgName type="full">Scientific Research Capacity of Young and Middle-aged Teachers in Colleges and Universities in Guangxi Province of China</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2024-03-11">11 March 2024</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Xin</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Party and Government Office</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Guangxi Health Science College</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nanning</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yue</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Public Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Guangxi University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nanning</settlement>
									<region>China</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yuanhua</forename><surname>Xuan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">School of Intelligence and Information Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Guangxi Economic and Trade Vocational Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nanning</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Teresa</forename><forename type="middle">Maria</forename><surname>Dias</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Paiva</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Ridwan Ibrahim</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Guarda Polytechnic Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="PT">Portugal</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Otilia Manta</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Lagos</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Romanian Academy</addrLine>
									<country>Nigeria Romania</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Multiple paths of green and low-carbon development in industrial parks: group analysis based on the TOE framework</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2024-03-11">11 March 2024</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fenvs.2024.1361598</idno>
					<note type="submission">RECEIVED 26 December 2023 ACCEPTED 26 February 2024</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T21:30+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>green low-carbon development</term>
					<term>group analysis</term>
					<term>industrial park</term>
					<term>multiple path</term>
					<term>TOE framework REVIEWED BY</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The green and low-carbon development of industrial parks plays an important role in promoting industrial and technological agglomeration, How to optimise their green and low-carbon development pathways is an important management question to be answered, requiring the examination of multiple path based on a histological perspective. Based on the technology-organisation-environment framework, this study selected 29 state-level economic and technological development zones (ETDZs) in China as research objects, and explored multiple sets of paths using fuzzy set qualitative comparison and necessitycontribution analysis. The study found that: 1) four promotion paths can be adopted for green low-carbon development of the zones: endogenous drive, balanced promotion, core support drive and comprehensive drive; 2) single environmental factor does not constitute a bottleneck hindering the green low-carbon development of the zones, which should be combined with the actual situation of the zones, and the balanced enhancement of the effectiveness of green and low-carbon should be realised through measures such as industrial policy, environmental risk prevention, and performance assessment of green policies. Finally, the study proposes the following policy recommendations: industrial parks should focus on the key role of environmental risk prevention, apply a combination of measures in accordance with their own realities, and appropriate external pressure can help promote green and low-carbon development.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Industrial parks are crucial to the advancing regional industrial and technological clusters, enhancing economic growth and fortifying global supply chains, but they also create growing problems of resource depletion and environmental pollution <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Mathews et al., 2018)</ref>. Under the principles of green and low-carbon development, the implementation of green and low-carbon practices must be fostered within industrial parks. This process entails cultivating an "inclusive economy" that combines economic growth with environmental protection. By ensuring the sustainable provision of diverse resources and services from natural assets, industrial parks can overcome their developmental challenges and effectively contribute to regional economic and social</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>OPEN ACCESS EDITED BY</head><p>Athanasios Angelis-Dimakis, University of Huddersfield, United Kingdom progress. However, given the complexity of the explanatory mechanism of industrial parks to promote green and low-carbon development and the influence of multiple factors, theoretical research has not kept pace with the actual progress. The world's major developed and developing countries have carried out useful explorations in recent years. US has launched a pilot programme of eco-industrial parks to finance the design and development of eco-industrial parks in Maryland and other regions, so as to change the structure of industrial development in industrial parks. Japan has begun pilot projects in Hokkaido and other areas through the construction of intravenous industrial parks, the adoption of resource recycling and waste treatment technologies, and the development of environmental industries and intravenous industries to promote the reduction of carbon emissions in industrial parks <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Chen et al., 2021)</ref>. Developing countries such as Indonesia, Turkey and Brazil have also carried out a great deal of practical exploratory work to promote the transformation of the industrial structure of their industrial parks in the direction of green and low-carbon <ref type="bibr">(Bank, 2019)</ref>.</p><p>China is the world's largest industrialised country and the largest carbon emitter, with carbon emissions reaching 11.477 billion tonnes by 2022. On 22 September 2020, at the 75th United Nations General Assembly, China formally proposed the goal of achieving peak carbon by 2030 and carbon neutrality by 2060. In order to achieve this goal, China has adopted large-scale construction of a carbon market for trading <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Wang and Lyu, 2024)</ref>, promoted the green transformation of its industrial structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Wang and Zhou, 2023)</ref>, and established ecological civilization demonstration zones in an effort to honour its goal of carbon neutrality <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Zhang and Fu, 2023)</ref>, and has achieved significant results: China's carbon emissions are expected to fall to 249 megatonnes by 2024 and it will peak carbon ahead of schedule by 2030. Achievements in promoting green and lowcarbon development in industrial parks provide a key impetus and an important guarantee for achieving this goal. Since their establishment in 1984, China's national-level economic and technological development zones (ETDZs) have emerged as a key pillar driving China's economic development. However, early stages of their development witnessed resource overexploitation, reliance on a linear growth model, and uncontrolled industrial expansion, leading to resource scarcity and environmental degradation in host regions <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Mathews and Tan, 2016)</ref>. In response, the Chinese government has prioritised the promotion of green and lowcarbon development within industrial parks. Since 2017, annual lists of 'green industrial parks' have been compiled, and industrial parks that are awarded the national green park status are offered support. This approach aims to foster the growth of green industrial parks, improve their development environment and stimulate neighbouring regions to enhance their own level of green development. The green industrial parks established in China have witnessed substantial advancements, with significant improvements in industry safety and green development. Green industrial parks now boast an average solid waste disposal utilisation rate exceeding 95% whilst strengthening their green supply capacity <ref type="bibr">(CCID, 2023)</ref>. Moreover, China's formal proposal during the 75th United Nations General Assembly on 22 September 2020, i.e., to achieve carbon peaking by 2030 and carbon neutrality by 2060, has received substantial impetus and a vital guarantee from the achievements made in promoting green and low-carbon development in industrial parks. Therefore, research on the green and low-carbon development path of China's industrial parks will not only help to explore the experience of how the world's most carbon-emitting countries promote the green and low-carbon development of their industrial structure, but also help to provide new perspectives on the green and low-carbon development of developing countries in global policymaking and to provide lessons learned from their experience.</p><p>Current research on promoting green and low-carbon development in industrial parks primarily focuses on the macroeconomic level, encompassing areas, such as the development of indicator systems and assessment methods for measuring green and low-carbon progress <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Zeng and Shang, 2017)</ref>, the adoption and implementation of green technology innovations <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Sacirovic et al., 2019)</ref>, and the assessment of environmental benefits achieved <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(He and An, 2019)</ref>. However, these studies often examine the influence of individual factors on green and low-carbon development in industrial parks independently, overlooking the integrated nature and complex interactions of the associated mechanisms <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Murray et al., 2017)</ref>. Therefore, exploring further the multiple modes of operation of industrial parks to promote green and low-carbon development from a configuration perspective is a key breakthrough in exploring their complex mechanisms.</p><p>This study focuses on the following two major questions: 1) From the perspective of group analysis, what are the mechanisms and factors influencing the green and low-carbon development of industrial parks? 2) How do different factors synergistically contribute to green and low-carbon development? To address the aforementioned issues, this study opts for industrial parks in China, recognized as the world's foremost industrial powerhouse and the leading contributor to global carbon emissions, as the primary research sample. The focal point is an examination of "China's performance in a global context," specifically emphasizing how industrial parks operating within the framework of the "China model" can achieve both management innovation and advancements in the green economy. Selecting China's national ETDZs as samples, we constructed a model of the influencing factors on the green and low-carbon development of industrial parks from the perspective of the technology-organisation-environment (TOE) framework. Then, we combined the necessity-contribution analysis (NCA) method and the fuzzy-set qualitative comparison analysis (fsQCA) method to explore the multiple influencing paths to gain an in-depth understanding of which resource factor configurations can affect the effectiveness of the green and low-carbon development of industrial parks. Thus, this study can provide theoretical basis and practical guidance for industrial parks to implement efficient synergistic innovations and promote green and low-carbon development.</p><p>The innovation and possible contribution of this study to existing research is twofold:</p><p>The first aspect is innovation in the combination of research object and research method. Academic research on regional green and low-carbon development paths are mostly concentrated in provinces (states), cities and counties and other traditional local administrative areas, while there are very few cases in which industrial parks, which have special administrative competence and a high degree of concentration of industrial development factors and a more urgent need for green development, have been the object of research, Moreover, most of them use quantitative methods such as correlation analysis and regression analysis, thus ignoring the complex and variable combination of factors that influence them. In view of this, the article creatively takes industrial parks as the entry point, combines the QCA method and NCA method, and systematically analyses the improvement paths of the green and low-carbon development effectiveness of industrial parks driven by a variety of factors through different equivalent paths, which makes up for the research gaps on the paths and grouping theories of green and low-carbon development.</p><p>Most of the previous studies explored the policy path of green and low-carbon development from a single perspective, such as environmental protection and industrial transformation. This study used the TOE framework to construct a framework of influencing factors, the framework addresses the limitation of analysing single factors in isolation and neglecting the joint influence of multiple complex factors. It also enriches the existing research field from the perspective of technology adoption and innovation. The results of the study can provide policymakers and managers of industrial parks with suggestions on the use of a combination of policy tools to promote the effectiveness of green and low-carbon development management in industrial parks.</p><p>Focusing on the above discussion, this paper intends to carry out the research in accordance with the following process: firstly, through combing and analysing the academic literature, the analytical framework of influencing the green and low-carbon development of industrial parks under the perspective of technology adoption and innovation is determined. Subsequent steps involved the identification and categorization of condition and outcome variables, followed by their respective value assignments. A comprehensive analysis ensued, employing a combination of NCA and QCA methods to explore both individual variables and combinations of conditions. Through this approach, the study aimed to delineate pathways characterized by high-performance as well as those exhibiting non high-performance, with a particular emphasis on the robustness testing of the outcomes. Finally, the collation draws conclusions and suggests policy path responses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Literature review and research framework</head><p>The behaviour of industrial parks in promoting green and low carbon is a phenomenon of interaction and interactions between different subjects, and is a kind of technological adoption and innovation behaviour, which may be influenced by technological characteristics, internal factors of the organisation and external environmental conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Shipan and Volden, 2008)</ref>. Introduced by Tornatizky and Fleischer, the TOE framework provides a comprehensive analytical framework that focuses on the factors influencing technology adoption and innovation across technological, organisational and environmental dimensions. It offers insights into organisations' behaviours related to technology integration and adoption <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Tornatzky and Flelscher, 1991)</ref>. The TOE framework not only fits the actual situation of the complex multifactorial role of green and low-carbon development in industrial parks but also effectively identifies how different factors play a role and constructs a framework idea for group analysis. The next section further explores the factors influencing the green and low-carbon development of regions and industrial parks from the perspective of technology adoption and innovation.</p><p>2.1 Impact of technology adoption and innovation on regional green and lowcarbon development</p><p>Empirical studies have shown that the majority of regional green and low-carbon development behaviours have technological, organisational and environmental dimensions. Firstly, at the level of technological conditions, enterprises, as the key body to achieve carbon emission reduction targets, can gain green advantages through green innovation and its spillover effects to improve energy use efficiency and reduce carbon emission intensity <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Liang and Luo, 2022)</ref>; it can also reduce carbon emissions from the source by driving the transformation of traditional industries in the direction of greening and promote the overall effectiveness of green and low-carbon development in the region where it is located <ref type="bibr">(Chen and Zhang, 2023)</ref>. Secondly, at the organisational level, the achievement of green and low-carbon development in a region is also influenced by governmental administrative interventions. By effectively allocating resources, the government can assume the risks associated with technological innovation and emission reduction in relevant industries. This approach facilitates the transition of high-carbon industries within the jurisdiction to a low-carbon development trajectory, stimulating a clustering effect and fostering a cohesive force for carbon emission reduction <ref type="bibr">(Liang et al., 2022)</ref>. Lastly, the environmental conditions at the regional level can also impact the success of green and low-carbon development. Factors, such as environmental regulations and industrial restructuring, are crucial. Moreover, variations in environmental characteristics, such as the imposition of carbon taxes, the allocation of energy tax revenue and the contribution of the tertiary industry, can significantly foster the advancement of green and low-carbon practices <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Zhao et al., 2022)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Pathways to green and low-carbon development in industrial parks</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1">Elements for green and low-carbon development of industrial parks</head><p>China's Green and Low Carbon Development Path for Industrial Parks primarily centres around policy and system formulation, innovative management mechanisms, environmental risk management and control and the establishment of a performance assessment system for green development. In terms of policy system formulation, the implementation of green industrial policies by managers of industrial parks can trigger adaptive cyclic interactions between enterprises and its stakeholders and improve the green total factor productivity of the region <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Cheng et al., 2021)</ref>; Clearly define the direction of green and low-carbon development in the formulation of policies at the overall level, and realise the green development of industrial parks through the implementation of policy tools such as encouraging industrial restructuring, supporting the clean energy industry, and strengthening environmental regulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(He and Li, 2023)</ref>. In terms of management mechanism innovation, a good management system innovation can regulate the production behaviour of enterprises, obtain a new competitive advantage in green development with the supply of high-quality and exclusive public products <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Wang, 2015)</ref>. or change a single management system for industrial development, and integrate the environmental protection management system, the EIA management system, the engineering management system and the development and construction system to promote the enhancement of the green effectiveness <ref type="bibr">(Cai, 2014)</ref>. In terms of environmental risk control, the construction of the environmental performance evaluation index system, the strengthening of the coprocessing of enterprise organic waste and the monitoring of pollutant emissions, the establishment of the industrial parks' enterprise pollutant prevention appraisal system and the development of the Green Investment Promotion Evaluation Indicator System not only serve as the driving force for the green and low-carbon development of industrial parks but also play a positive role in promoting the effectiveness of the green development of industrial parks <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Xiao et al., 2023)</ref>. Lastly, enhancing the inclusion of ecological environmental protection and green low-carbon development in the performance appraisal system of industrial parks can effectively encourage the enforcement of environmental regulations by the governing department. The resulting pressure from the environmental performance appraisal serves as a catalyst for promoting green innovation amongst enterprises within industrial parks, leading to overall improvements in the parks'green development performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Guan et al., 2023)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2">Empirical research on the relationship between factors and green and low-carbon development paths</head><p>Well-crafted green industrial policies play a pivotal role in fostering the positive impact of industrial parks on green and low-carbon development. Zhou and Zhang conducted a comprehensive analysis of the emotional preferences associated with green industrial policies implemented in industrial parks within China's Yangtze River Delta region from 2010 to 2019. The findings underscore that a judiciously designed content for green industrial policies significantly contributes to enhancing the effectiveness of carbon emission reduction efforts and overall impact <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Zhou and Zhang, 2023)</ref>. The results of empirical research on the Suzhou Industrial Park in China and some industrial parks in the western region of China point out that: the innovation of the management system can be adopted to stimulate the synergy of the government, enterprises, universities, the public and other innovation bodies <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Zhang and Xing, 2023)</ref>; or the top-level design can be clear about the "zero-carbon strategy" of lowcarbon development and intensive expansion, and based on this, the cultivation of green and low-carbon development paths can be carried out in accordance with the functional forms and development stages of different types of industrial parks <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(Zheng et al., 2023)</ref>. Designing a multi-level superimposed and interlocking environmental risk prevention and control system, such as a system for preventing and controlling water pollution emergencies, can significantly enhance the environmental risk prevention and control capacity and green sustainable development of industrial parks <ref type="bibr">(Chen.Y et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr">Chen et al., 2023</ref> and others point out in their empirical study of industrial parks in China's Yangtze River Economic Zone that the implementation of dynamic management of environmental risk grading in the parks and the establishment of a working mechanism for dealing with emergencies and accidents can help to prevent, control and dissolve the environmental risks of industrial parks in a systematic way and to achieve green and lowcarbon development <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Zhang et al., 2022)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Review of research</head><p>The above studies have made many useful explorations, but there are still the following areas that need to be strengthened: firstly, the existing empirical analysis of the literature mainly explores the single value of a number of potential elements, i.e., based on regression analysis, correlation analysis and other ways to test the correlation effect of a single element, neglecting the integration of the analysis of the driving mechanism of the green and low-carbon industrial parks, organisational processes and the institutional environment, and the lack of synergistic effects of the synergies between the multiple conditions of the system. Secondly, the existing research predominantly targets provinces (states), cities, counties, and other conventional local administrative areas. Although there are studies focusing on the administrative bodies of industrial parks, the majority of qualitative research tends to gravitate towards singlecase studies or single-factor quantitative research, often delving into environmental protection and institutional design. The research landscape lacks a robust exploration of industrial parks as the central subject, specifically in unraveling the complex interplay of factors influencing the efficacy of green and low-carbon construction. Strengthening efforts in understanding the multifactorial dynamics contributing to the role of industrial parks is imperative. Therefore, it is necessary to integrate the formation of a composite framework that influences the common role of multiple factors in the green and low-carbon development of industrial parks based on the framework of technology adoption and innovation, and to further explore the construction of multiple paths in combination with the group theory.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Research framework design</head><p>We embeds the TOE framework into the context of green and low-carbon development of industrial parks in China to explore its path mechanism in a multifaceted and systematic way.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.1">Theoretical analysis of factors influencing green and low-carbon development in industrial parks from the perspective of technology adoption and innovation</head><p>In the TOE framework, the technological condition pertains to the characteristics of the technology itself and its alignment with the organisation. This aspect emphasises whether the technology is compatible with the structural attributes and application capabilities of the organisation, as well as its potential benefits for the organisation <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Tan et al., 2019)</ref>. The technological condition is further delineated into three subcategories: the establishment of recycling industries, mitigation of environmental risks and evaluation of green policy performance. Strategically rationalising and proactively adjusting the industrial structure in industrial parks can significantly improve the efficiency of green and lowcarbon development. Notably, the implementation of recycling industries not only optimises the composition of industries but also alleviates resource demand by enhancing the economic, resource and environmental benefits of industrial parks (Qi, 2013). China's National Development and Reform Commission and the Ministry of Finance have announced and released six batches of national parks' recycling demonstration pilot park lists from year 2012-2017, using selection criteria, including whether industrial parks have a complete recycling industry layout plan, land-use assessment for project entry into the parks, measures for environmental supervision and enforcement and pollutant management programmes. Drawing from national standards, Chinese provinces have incorporated provincial-level pilot recycling demonstration parks as part of their assessment protocols to measure the effectiveness of recycling initiatives within industrial parks. Given the concentrated nature of industrial parks, the implementation of appropriate environmental regulations can effectively incentivise enterprises to adopt technological innovations. This proactive approach helps prevent environmental pollution and promotes the greening of industries within the park, ultimately achieving sustainability objectives <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Yin et al., 2023)</ref>. By developing an environmental performance evaluation index system, enhancing financial investment in environmental protection and supervision, and intensifying environmental oversight, enterprises can be encouraged to regulate their high-energy-consuming and highly polluting production practices (Shang and <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Zeng, 2015)</ref>. A reliable risk monitoring and early warning system serves not only as a crucial reference for industrial parks in formulating effective management measures but also assists in determining the threshold of resource and environmental carrying capacity within a specified timeframe. Such information can guide the scope, intensity, and scale of economic development <ref type="bibr">(Jia et al., 2018</ref>). China's industrial parks have been given varying degrees of administrative power by local government agencies, and it is crucial to implement a performance evaluation system, including effectiveness evaluation and appraisal of leading cadres <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Han et al., 2015)</ref>. In the context of China's sectional system, the performance appraisal of local officials serves as an important motivator. By increasing the proportion of green appraisal within comprehensive evaluations, regional environmental pollution can be reduced <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Han and Zhang, 2018)</ref>. The establishment of local regulations to mandate green performance appraisal and linking the use of park funds to green performance requirements <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Jiang, 2014)</ref> further strengthen the foundation of industrial parks and ensure green growth.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.2">Organisational condition: institutional measures support</head><p>Technology has the potential to re-engineer organisations; however, organisations can also exert influence and even shape technology in the opposite direction <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Mergel and Desouza, 2013)</ref>.</p><p>Factors, such as an organisation's resource capacity, the level of centralisation in its structure and interorganisational pressures amongst others, significantly influence the trajectory of technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Grimmelikhuijsen and Feeney, 2017)</ref>. This study specifically examines the role of institutional measures support. In China's hierarchical administrative system, decision-makers within industrial parks possess significant political decisionmaking power. When considering the adoption and promotion of green and low-carbon policies, they consider the economic situation and resource mobilisation capacity of their jurisdiction <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Rogers, 2003)</ref>. Moreover, decision-makers provide financial support to industrial parks in areas, such as eco-environmental management, green technological innovation, energy technological innovation and industrial restructuring and upgrading, through targeted financial expenditures <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(Zhang and Yang, 2019)</ref>. In addition, complete institutional measures support for green and low-carbon development is closely related to whether the administrative body has sufficient capacity to implement the programme rules and regulations; this relationship helps ensure the implementation of the measures in accordance with the correct direction and accurate technical guidelines to enhance the implementation of the region's policy strength and effectiveness <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Huang and Li, 2023)</ref>. This support will have a significant impact on the green and low-carbon activities of industrial parks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.3">Environmental conditions: policy signals and competition from neighbouring regions</head><p>Environmental conditions, including factors, such as the market structure and external government regulations, play a significant role in shaping an organisation's ability to adopt and implement new technologies effectively <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Oliveira and Martins, 2011)</ref>. As administrative pressure operates within a hierarchical system, the implementation of policies driven by higher levels of government, as well as the signalling of policy intentions, can prompt lower levels of government to adopt a more conscientious and proactive approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Zhang et al., 2022</ref>). China's industrial parks are considered local "quasiadministrative organisations"; hence, the "policy signals" imposed by higher-level authorities to promote green and low-carbon development affect the macroexternal environment of industrial park development and become one of the motivating factors for them to promote green and low-carbon development. The competition amongst industrial parks also affects the external environment, given that administrative entities at the same level are subject to the jurisdiction of a common superior administrative subject. Consequently, competition and imitation amongst neighbouring administrative subjects arise as they adopt new policies <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Xufeng and Hui, 2018)</ref>. This process leads to the diffusion of policy innovations and in turn, generates competition amongst neighbouring regions. Therefore, the existence of similar administrative entities in the neighbourhood of industrial parks that have achieved good results in green and low-carbon development may have a positive impact on the formulation of measures to promote green development in industrial parks.</p><p>In summary, the constructed TOE framework for green and low-carbon development in industrial parks encompasses six secondary conditions that supplement the primary conditions of technology-organisation-environment (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Research methodology for fsQCA combined with NCA</head><p>This paper proposed to use Fuzzy-Set Qualitative Comparative Analysis (fsQCA) to carry out the empirical test. Based on the multiple path, fsQCA approach uses Boolean operations and set relations to conduct comparative analyses at the case level, focusing on exploring the relationship between antecedent complexity and causal asymmetry; moreover, it can fully tap into the complex interactions and synergistic effects amongst multiple elements <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Du and Jia, 2017)</ref>, Compared to quantitative studies based on regression analyses and qualitative studies based on case analyses, the advantage of the QCA methodology is that it allows for the identification of conditional groupings with equivalent results through cross-case comparisons across samples such as large, medium and small (Equifinality), It helps researchers to understand the differentiated driving mechanisms that lead to the outcomes in different case scenarios and the fit and substitution relationships between the conditions discussed, broadening the dimensions of theoretical explanations for specific research questions <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Tan et al., 2019)</ref>. In addition, the use of the fsQCA methodology fits with the problem studied in this paper: Firstly, the green and low-carbon construction of industrial parks results from the synergistic linkage and joint action of external and internal factors. However, traditional linear regression analysis hardly explores the influence of multiple factors on the outcome variables. By contrast, fsQCA can analyse interactions amongst elements whilst tapping into the nonlinear relationship between different combinations of elements. Secondly, the fsQCA method integrates the strengths of qualitative and quantitative analyses and is suitable for medium-sized samples of approximately 10-50 <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Du et al., 2020)</ref>. Hence, the number of industrial parks selected for this study (i.e. 29) is compatible with fsQCA, and the depth and uniqueness of the case study can be considered. Finally, fsQCA can be used to identify the typical cases covered by each equivalent grouping accurately <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Zhang and Du, 2019)</ref>. It can also analyse the differences in the green and low-carbon development paths of different industrial parks, making it easy to summarise and generalise the efficient strategies that can be replicated. Finally, in recent years, the fsQCA method has been widely used in empirical studies in the fields of strategic management and technology application in organisations <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Huang and Gui, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Hao et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wang et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Wang and Wang, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Fan et al., 2018)</ref>, which is in line with the logic of the TOE framework's technologyadoption-innovation (TIAI) analysis used in the present study, which has strengthened the scientific validity and reasonableness of the results of the analyses.</p><p>The Analysis of necessary conditions(NCA) is an analytical approach introduced by Professor Dul <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Dul, 2020)</ref>. It can be used specifically to analyse how necessary relationships and antecedent conditions constitute necessary conditions for outcomes. The reason for the combination of NCA and fsQCA methods in this study is that the QCA method focuses on qualitatively identifying the necessary conditions for the sufficiency analysis, The NCA method can analyse the degree of necessity of antecedent conditions from a quantitative point of view, thus representing the degree of necessity more accurately and effectively compensating for the shortcomings of the fsQCA method in the process of analysing the necessary conditions, The NCA method enables a quantitative analysis of the necessity degree of antecedent conditions, thereby providing a more accurate representation of necessity. This quantitative perspective effectively compensates for the deficiencies observed in the fsQCA method during the analysis of necessary conditions, contributing to an improved understanding of the subject matter, The combination of the two methods is more valuable and the results of the analyses are more scientifically sound <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Du et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Vis and Dul, 2018)</ref>. Therefore, this study firstly adopts the NCA method to analyse the necessity relationship between the influencing factors and the effectiveness of green low-carbon development; then, the QCA method is used to test the robustness of the necessity analysis results and to analyse the adequacy relationship between the influencing factors and the effectiveness of green low-carbon development, so as to further understand the complexity of promoting the green low-carbon development in industrial parks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Selection of case samples and data sources</head><p>To ensure the scientific nature of the case samples, this study selected the top 30 national-level economic development zones amongst the 230 national-level economic development zones in China in the "2019 Comprehensive Assessment and Evaluation Results of National-level Economic Development Zones" as the case samples. However, the Caohejing Economic Development Zone in Shanghai was excluded because it is a "market subject" (i.e., managed by a state-owned enterprise according to the entrepreneurial market-oriented management) and not a "regional subject". Thus, a total of 29 case samples were included. These 29 national-level economic development zones Analysis framework.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Frontiers in Environmental Science</head><p>frontiersin.org all belong to the "first level" of China's industrial park development, and their levels of economic development do not significantly vary; the case samples are distributed in the eastern, central and western parts of China, which can compensate for the shortcomings of comparability caused by geographical differences and meets the requirements of the selection of homogeneous and diversified research cases.</p><p>The empirical data for this study were sourced primarily from policy documents: one is to find relevant policy documents in the official website of the Chinese government, and to judge whether the variables exist or not through the government documents and interpretations; the other is to search for keyword terms on mainstream search engines such as Google and Baidu. In this study, a team consisting of three members who are often engaged in text mining and text quantification research was set up to combine the two approaches mentioned above, adopting the methods of proofreading, identifying, giving opinions and revising each other by the three persons, and repeatedly checking and revising in order to improve the accuracy of the selection of policy texts. Excluding the policy texts that do not involve variable observation content, a total of 56 policy texts with valid variable observation content, such as the "13th Five-Year Plan for the Economic and Social Development of Industrial Park" and the "13th Five-Year Plan for the Green and Low-Carbon Development of Industrial Park", have been collected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Data measurement and calibration</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.1">Outcome variables</head><p>This study focused on the assessment of green manufacturing system construction by China's National Ministry of Industry and Information Technology during the period of 2017-2021. The outcome variable used in this study was whether industrial parks are designated as national green parks. These assessments were considered authoritative and scientifically rigorous, providing a comprehensive reflection of the effectiveness of China's industrial parks in green and low-carbon development. In this study, the 29 industrial parks were assigned values of 1 or 0 based on their inclusion in the five batches of national green parks. Given the time lag of 2-4 years in policy implementation, a lag period was incorporated, with the outcome variable adopting data from year 2017-2021.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.2">Conditional variables</head><p>Policy signals (PS). This variable primarily assesses whether industrial parks receive administrative pressure and PS from higher authorities. Textual indicators, such as 'implementing the spirit of instructions from higher authorities' or 'formulated in accordance with documents from higher authorities', in the locally formulated policies promoting green and low-carbon development by industrial parks determine the assignment of values. If these indicators are present, the value is 1; otherwise, the value is 0.</p><p>Competition from neighbouring regions (NR). It is mainly based on whether another industrial park in the jurisdiction of the city has been awarded a national green park before the sample is assessed. If there is one, the value is 1, with the value increasing by 1 for each additional park awarded; otherwise, the value assigned is 0.</p><p>Institutional measures support (MS). The promotion of green and low-carbon development policies at the industrial park level relies on three fundamental criteria: the provision of financial support, effective organisational leadership and the formulation of a comprehensive green development preparation programme. Each criterion, when met, is assigned a value of 1. Moreover, the cumulative presence of multiple criteria increases the assigned value. Conversely, if none of the criteria is met, the value designated is 0.</p><p>Construction of recycling industries (RI). The promotion of green and low-carbon development policies at the industrial park level is primarily based on three key elements: financial support, effective organisational leadership and the formulation of a comprehensive green development preparation programme. Each aspect, when present, contributes a value of 1. Additionally, if multiple elements are satisfied, the value increases accordingly.</p><p>Conversely, if none of the elements are fulfilled, the value assigned is 0.</p><p>Prevention of environmental risks (ER). Assessment largely hinges on the existence of a policy within industrial parks that explicitly outlines the establishment of an environmental monitoring and early warning mechanism. If such a policy has been implemented, it is assigned a value of 1; otherwise, a value of 0 is given.</p><p>Assessment of green policy performance (GP): This variable is based on whether industrial parks incorporate green development into the comprehensive performance appraisal and supervision system at this level. If it does, the value is 1; otherwise, it is 0.</p><p>The antecedent conditions were analysed using data from year 2013-2019, in consideration of the 2-4 years time lag in the introduction of the policy and the fact that the outcome variable uses data for the period 2017-2021.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.3">Data calibration</head><p>According to the analytical steps of the qualitative comparison analysis (QCA) method, three nonclear dichotomous variables, i.e., NR, MS and RI, must be conditionally calibrated. In accordance with Tan and <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Du et al. (Tan et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Du et al., 2020)</ref>, the raw data were calibrated using the direct calibration method by setting the three calibration anchors to be the 90% quartile (full affiliation), the median (crossover point) and the 10% quartile (no affiliation at all) of the descriptive statistics of the case data, with the advantage of using the median, which is less sensitive to outliers compared with the mean <ref type="bibr">(Greckhamer and Gur, 2021)</ref>. Calibration anchors and descriptive statistics for the antecedent conditions are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Analysis of results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Univariate sufficiency-necessity analysis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.1">NCA</head><p>The determination of the necessary conditions in the NCA method must simultaneously satisfy two conditions: 1) the effect size (d) is not less than 0.1, and 2) the Monte Carlo simulation replacement test results show that the effect size is significant <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Dul et al., 2020)</ref>. The effect size ranges from 0 to 1, with 0-0.1 indicating a low level of impact, 0.1-0.3 indicating a medium level of impact and 0.3-0.5 indicating a high level of impact. In this study, we used the NCA software in R software for the NCA method, the effect sizes of the six conditioning variables were analysed using two estimation methods: cap regression analysis (CR) and cap envelopment analysis (CE). The results are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>.</p><p>The results in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> show that the effect sizes of the six conditional variables are not significant, suggesting that these conditions individually do not constitute a necessary condition for industrial parks to achieve green and low-carbon development. Thus, the combined impact effects of these conditions should be further analysed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.2">QCA</head><p>The necessity analysis within the QCA method is utilised to determine the dependence of the results on a specific variable. This determination is commonly derived from two primary indicators: consistency and coverage. An indicator value exceeding 0.9 for consistency indicates the essential nature of the conditional variable. Furthermore, coverage primarily depicts the explanatory power of the conditional variable on the outcome variable. In this study, fsQCA 3.0 software was used to calculate the "sufficiency-necessity" results of individual explanatory variables for high-performance and nonhigh-performance data, respectively, as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>.</p><p>The results show that except for the consistency of ER, which is above 0.9 in the high effectiveness results, and the lack of coverage of ~ER, which is above 0.9 in the low effectiveness results, the remaining variables fail to reach the desired level of 0.9 as necessary conditions for the outcome variables. The rest of the variables do not reach the desired level of 0.9 and cannot be considered necessary conditions for the outcome variables. The above results also confirm that the realisation of green development in industrial parks requires the interaction of all variables with each other; therefore, different combinations of conditional variables must be analysed further to explore the multiple paths of influence on the green development of industrial parks.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Conditional portfolio analysis</head><p>Conditional combination analysis can reveal the effect of combinations of conditions on the results, in general, the level of consistency of the combination of sufficient conditions should not be less than 0.75 <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Schneider, C. Q and Wagemann, C, 2012)</ref>. On the basis of the truth table constructed in the previous section and in accordance with the steps of QCA, the consistency threshold and frequency threshold must be determined. Given the small sample size of this study, we referred to the study of <ref type="bibr">Zhang et al. (2019)</ref>; hence, the frequency threshold was set to 1, and the consistency threshold was set to 0.8. The setting of the 'PRI consistency threshold' can avoid the simultaneous subset relationship of a certain grouping in the result and the result negation, and generally its threshold should not be lower than 0.5, according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Patala et al., 2021</ref>, who set it to 0.6.</p><p>The standard analysis in QCA is considered to produce higher confidence analyses due to the inclusion of counterfactual analyses. Thus, standard analysis was used in this study to calculate the results of high and nonhigh effectiveness separately. The parsimonious solution, complex solution and intermediate solution are obtained through operations. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Fiss (2011)</ref>, the conditions appearing in the simple solution are categorised as core conditions, and the conditions appearing in the intermediate solution but not in the simple solution are categorised as auxiliary conditions, which are presented in a table and categorised in accordance with the core conditions. Amongst them are four high-performance paths and more nonhigh-performance paths to facilitate the analysis of the original coverage of the four paths selected for analysis to avoid the coverage of small paths to interfere with the analysis of the results, the results are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.1">High-performance paths</head><p>The results in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref> reveal four paths to high green and lowcarbon development effectiveness ("*" denotes "and").</p><p>(1) Internal drive type path-Group 1 "Policy signals*Construction of recycling industries*Prevention of environmental risks". In which the elements of each dimension do not exist as core conditions and there is no serious lack of them; moreover only the elements of NR and other external factors belong to the missing state, indicating that although the external influencing factors are missing, the high effectiveness of the green development of industrial parks can still be achieved through MS, RI and other types of internal factors. This result shows that despite the absence of external factors, the high effectiveness of green development in industrial parks can still be achieved through MS, RI and other types of internal factors that complement and synergise with each other. Industrial parks with such a combination of elements, regardless of whether their superiors have released PS to them or there is no NR, can help enhance the effectiveness of green and lowcarbon development by creating a good policy guarantee for green and low-carbon development and an environment with a good industrial structure, This paper therefore names such paths "Internal drive type path". Typical cases, such as the Tianjin, Dalian and Zhenjiang Economic Development Zones, whose higher authorities have not released specific PS for green and low-carbon development and lack the competition from neighbouring green zones, have developed complete institutional measures for green and low-carbon development and have achieved outstanding results in the construction of recycling industries. Moreover, the prevention of environmental risks has been stipulated in a separate chapter in the 5-year economic and social development plan. The above industrial parks reveal that under the influence of more complete internal factors, high green and low-carbon effectiveness can still be achieved despite missing core elements and the influence of external factors.</p><p>(2) Balanced promotion type path-Group 2 "Policy signals*Institutional measures support*Prevention of environmental risks*Assessment of green policy performance". The conditions it possesses are all auxiliary conditions, with all external and internal factors distributed. Moreover, no case of missing core or auxiliary conditions is noted. This path shows that industrial parks mainly focus on their own positioning and industrial development and promote green development in a balanced and steady manner. The industrial park actively responds to the policy signals of the higher authorities and puts them into practice, Remarks: Calculations based on fsQCA3.0 software. As the value of these two data exceeds 0.8, which is high compared to other variables, to a certain extent, it indicates that these indicators have a high degree of influence on the outcome variables, which should be focused on and reflected as important explanatory variables of the outcome variables of all the cases in the path analyses below. Therefore, we have bolded these two data here.</p><p>and pays attention to system support and industrial safety, recycling to carry out the structural optimisation of the original industry, and formulates a complete mechanism to prevent all kinds of risks and hidden dangers, and ensures the implementation of green and low-carbon transformation. This paper therefore names such paths "Balanced promotion type path". Typical cases include the Suzhou Industrial Park and the Hefei and Guangzhou Economic Development Zones. These three industrial parks are all located in the metropolitan area of developed regions along the eastern coast of China. The cities in which they are located have a strong demand for the implementation of green and low-carbon development, and all of them have conveyed PS in their policy documents, thus forming the influence of external factors. In addition, the areas in which these industrial parks are located are densely populated, and the requirements for the prevention of environmental risks are high; hence, these industrial parks have been separately listed in their respective 5-year plans for economic and social development and have formulated in detail systems for preventive measures, emergency response and accountability, thus maximising the safety and security of industrial construction. Although the resource advantages in other aspects are not too prominent, the green and orderly development of industries through the creation of a balanced green and low-carbon environment can enhance the effectiveness of development  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.1">Nonhigh-performance paths</head><p>Given the asymmetry of cause and effect, this study also analyses the grouping pathways that generate nonhigh green and low-carbon development effectiveness, as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>. It also summarises three types of driving pathways: RI*ER*GP, RI*GP and ER (inhibition paths). The first pathway, consisting of Group 1, suggests that lower RI effects, ER, and shortfalls in GP combine to inhibit the industrial parks to produce high levels of green and low-carbon development. The second pathway consists of Group 2, which suggests that the lack of RI and GP are not conducive to green low-carbon development. The third pathway, consisting of Groups 3a and 3b, suggests that the absence of ER is not conducive to high green and low-carbon performance. By combining the previous NCA analysis and the univariate necessity analysis of QCA, the absence of ER is also found in the two paths of the nonhighperformance group, and both of them are missing the core condition, indicating that any path of the industrial park grouping without this element will have a greater inhibitory effect on the generation of high-performance green and lowcarbon development.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Robustness test</head><p>The robustness test in QCA analysis is an important basis for judging whether the results are stable or not. Drawing on the existing research practices of <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Shipan and Volden, 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">, Cheng et al., 2021</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">, Cheng and Wang, 2022</ref> and other studies on evaluating result stability, we firstly adjusted the value of the consistency domain to 0.85, the frequency number was kept at 1, and the two groupings of high-efficacy and nonhigh-efficacy products were basically the same as that of the existing groupings. The solution coverage and solution consistency are small. Secondly, a high-effectiveness and low-effectiveness case, i.e., Shanghai Jinqiao Economic Development Zone (municipalities directly under the central government) and Dalian Economic Development Zone (cities with separate municipalities under the central government), respectively were deleted after comparison with the analysis of the groups, and carried out the analyses of the high-effectiveness and low-effectiveness. The results showed that the group solutions were the same, and the differences in the solution coverage and solution consistency were negligible. The above test shows that the results of this study are relatively robust.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Conclusion and policy implications</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Research conclusion</head><p>Taking 29 national development zones in China as case studies and using a combination of the QCA and NCA methods, this study analyses the complex causal relationship between urban talent ecosystem and scientific and technological talent agglomeration from a group perspective. The following conclusions are drawn:</p><p>Firstly, individual environmental factors are not necessary for high green and low-carbon development in industrial parks, but strengthening the prevention of environmental risks plays a pervasive role in generating high levels of green and low-carbon development, reflecting the need to continue to optimise the safety environment in development zones to promote green and lowcarbon development in industrial parks. Secondly, this study finds four kinds of grouping paths for industrial parks to generate a high level of green and low-carbon development. They reflect the multiple paths that different industrial parks have taken to achieve green and low-carbon development based on their own environments through internal drive, balanced promotion, core support drive and all-round drive. They also reflect that the development and different driving mechanisms for green and low-carbon development in China's industrial parks undergo different stages. Three pathways inhibit the high effectiveness of green and lo-carbon development in industrial parks, and they are asymmetrically related to the pathways that drive high effectiveness.</p><p>The absence of prevention of environmental risks plays an important role in the inhibition pathways. Finally, the effective green and low-carbon development of industrial parks is closely related to the degree of economic and social development of the region in which they are located. Highly effective industrial parks are mainly clustered in the Yangtze River Delta Region, Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area, the Beijing-Tianjin-Hebei Economic Circle and other eastern coastal urban agglomerations, suggesting that an increase in the level of economic development of the city is related to the improvement of the level of green and low-carbon development of the industrial parks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Insights and policy implications</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.1">Theoretical implications</head><p>Firstly, based on the fact that the green low-carbon development of industrial parks is a comprehensive and complex system, this paper adopts the TOE framework and the group perspective to analyse the complex causal relationships among the influencing elements from a finer granularity. The results support the complex system view that there are multiple paths rather than a single optimal path for green low-carbon development in industrial parks. The results of the study reveal multiple modes of regional green low-carbon development under the perspective of complex system and provide a positive theoretical basis.</p><p>Second, this study responds to the complex systems view's call for "combinatorial" methodologies. The complex systems view argues that economic systems include multiple factors that are interdependent and require new methodologies such as "combinatorial" mathematics <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Arthur, W. B, 2018)</ref>. This paper analyses the complex relationship between the elements that interact with each other, describes what kind of combination of green development elements (ecological) promotes or hinders the achievement of effective green and low-carbon development in industrial parks, and provides new ideas and methods for researching complex systemic issues.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.2">Policy implications</head><p>Firstly, we focus on the key role of prevention of environmental risks. Different industrial parks should consider the stage of economic development of the region and the leading industries to optimise the rule of law to ensure environmental protection in industrial parks; accelerate the construction of environmental protection, risk prevention and other policies and regulations; and create a safe production environment in line with the region' s own endowment. Secondly, it is necessary to improve and perfect the early warning mechanism and supervision system of environmental risk prevention, industrial parks can establish the mechanism of environmental quality analysis meeting for the linkage of various management functions, and the target assessment mechanism of environmental management and pollution prevention and control, etc., so as to strengthen the capacity of ecological and environmental risk prevention and enhance the effectiveness of the synergistic management of the ecological and environmental environment.</p><p>Secondly, various measures must be combined with their own actual situation to promote the balanced promotion of green and low-carbon performance of industrial parks. 1) First, for industrial parks that lack external policy signals and neighbourhood competition effects, we should focus on our own institutional support, recycling industry construction and environmental risk prevention, accelerate the establishment of a full-time green lowcarbon development executive team, and prepare a complete implementation plan for promoting green development, so as to improve the synergy of the work of synergistic promotion; in addition, we should pay attention to the formulation of recycling and transformation type of industrial policies and the creation of a safe production environment, and promote synergy between industrial policies and environmental policies. 2) Industrial parks with relatively weak resource endowments should focus on building essential elements like environmental risk prevention and green performance appraisal. It is crucial to timely optimize and enhance the "green performance" appraisal mechanism. In the performance appraisal target system for the park's management team, additional targets and indices should be incorporated in the areas of risk prevention, resource utilization, environmental protection, and green manufacturing to ensure the effective implementation of green and low-carbon measures.</p><p>Thirdly, appropriate external pressure can help promote the green and low-carbon development of industrial parks. Industrial parks should respond to the signals from higher authorities or market players in a timely manner whilst paying attention to the experiences of neighbouring regions in the creation of green industrial parks. They should also organise regular meetings and exchanges, exchange staff and collate experiences and promotions to enhance the mechanism of exchanges and communication and promote the complementation of strengths and weaknesses so as to avoid falling behind or being overtaken by other industrial parks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Research shortcomings and prospects</head><p>This study suffers from the following shortcomings that must be improved in future studies. Firstly, the theoretical model constructed is limited to grouping and analysing the antecedent conditions of industrial parks to promote green and low-carbon development; these are generally discussed in the existing literature. In the future, it can be considered based on the relevant theoretical basis, and matching analysis with the pilot factors of the national low-carbon industrial parks and eco-industrial demonstration park policy in the existing research. Secondly, given the availability of data on industrial parks, only 29 industrial parks were selected as cases. The sample can be further expanded in the future to improve the generalisability and replicability of the conclusions. Finally, only static data were used to explore the complex relationship between green and low-carbon development in industrial parks; in the future, data can be collected from multiple industrial parks over time, and the dynamic QCA methodology can be selected to investigate the impact mechanisms further. Effectiveness of construction.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIGURE 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>FIGURE 1</figDesc><graphic coords="6,314.59,94.28,221.26,199.84" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Calibration and descriptive statistics of data.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Sets</cell><cell></cell><cell>Fuzzy set calibration</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Descriptive analysis</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Full affiliation Intersection</cell><cell>Fully</cell><cell>Mean</cell><cell>Standard</cell><cell>Minimum</cell><cell>Maximum</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">unaffiliated</cell><cell></cell><cell>deviation</cell><cell>value</cell><cell>value</cell></row><row><cell>PS</cell><cell>\</cell><cell>\</cell><cell>\</cell><cell>0.586</cell><cell>0.493</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>NR</cell><cell>0.98</cell><cell>0.02</cell><cell>0.02</cell><cell>0.655</cell><cell>1.026</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>MS</cell><cell>0.98</cell><cell>0.98</cell><cell>0.02</cell><cell>0.759</cell><cell>0.567</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>RI</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0.98</cell><cell>0.02</cell><cell>0.965</cell><cell>0.928</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>ER</cell><cell>\</cell><cell>\</cell><cell>\</cell><cell>0.655</cell><cell>0.475</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>GP</cell><cell>\</cell><cell>\</cell><cell>\</cell><cell>0.586</cell><cell>0.493</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Remarks: PS, RI, and GP, are denoted by '\' because they do not need calibration.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Analysis of necessary conditions for green and low-carbon development of industrial parks based on NCA.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>TABLE 3 "</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Sufficiency-necessity" analysis results of univariate.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Conditional variable</cell><cell cols="2">High-performance</cell><cell>Conditional variable</cell><cell cols="2">Nonhigh-performance</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Consistency</cell><cell>Coverage</cell><cell></cell><cell>Consistency</cell><cell>Coverage</cell></row><row><cell>PS</cell><cell>0.583333</cell><cell>0.411765</cell><cell>~PS</cell><cell>0.411765</cell><cell>0.583333</cell></row><row><cell>NR</cell><cell>0.340000</cell><cell>0.311450</cell><cell>~NR</cell><cell>0.469412</cell><cell>0.501887</cell></row><row><cell>MS</cell><cell>0.823333</cell><cell>0.498486</cell><cell>~MS</cell><cell>0.415294</cell><cell>0.769063</cell></row><row><cell>RI</cell><cell>0.830000</cell><cell>0.615575</cell><cell>~RI</cell><cell>0.634118</cell><cell>0.840874</cell></row><row><cell>ER</cell><cell>0.916667</cell><cell>0.578947</cell><cell>~ER</cell><cell>0.529412</cell><cell>0.900000</cell></row><row><cell>GP</cell><cell>0.750000</cell><cell>0.529412</cell><cell>~GP</cell><cell>0.529412</cell><cell>0.750000</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>TABLE 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Condition configuration for high and nonhigh performance cases.  indicates that the core condition exists,  indicates that the core condition does not exist.  indicates that the auxiliary condition exists,  indicates that the auxiliary condition does not exist. A blank space indicates that the condition may or may not be present.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Conditional variable</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">High-performance paths</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Nonhigh-performance paths</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="6">Group 1 Group 2 Group 3 Group 4 Group 1 Group 2</cell><cell cols="2">Group 3</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Group 3a Group 3b</cell></row><row><cell>Policy signals</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Competition from neighbouring regions</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Institutional measures support</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Construction of recycling industries</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Prevention of environmental risks</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Assessment of green policy performance</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Consistency</cell><cell>0.973941</cell><cell>0.995</cell><cell>0.942308</cell><cell>0.990196</cell><cell>0.994924</cell><cell>0.990196</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Raw coverage</cell><cell>0.498333</cell><cell>0.331667</cell><cell>0.163333</cell><cell>0.168333</cell><cell>0.230588</cell><cell>0.118824</cell><cell>0.116471</cell><cell>0.116471</cell></row><row><cell>Unique coverage</cell><cell>0.328333</cell><cell>0.163333</cell><cell>0.081667</cell><cell>0.080000</cell><cell>0.169412</cell><cell>0.056470</cell><cell>0.114118</cell><cell>0.115294</cell></row><row><cell>Solution coverage</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.903333</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.922353</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Solution consistency</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.978339</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.99115</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Remarks:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Frontiers in Environmental Science frontiersin.org</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>We are very grateful to the <rs type="institution">School of Public Administration of Guangxi University</rs> for its careful guidance and valuable suggestions.The guidance and advice provided us with valuable assistance in the revision process.valuable assistance during the revision process.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><head>Funding</head><p>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This research was funded by: 1.the <rs type="funder">National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC)</rs>: Research on the <rs type="institution">Mechanism of Collaborative Development of Multiple Subjects in Cross-Regional Collaborative Innovation Networks</rs> under the <rs type="funder">Threshold of Public Governance</rs> (grant number: <rs type="grantNumber">72164002</rs>) (YC); 2.the <rs type="funder">National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC): Research on the Mechanism of Interactive Evolution of Dynamic Capabilities of Enterprise Networks and Collaborative Innovation Ecosystems-Taking the Case of New and Emerging Technology Industries</rs> (grant number: <rs type="grantNumber">71762003</rs>) (YC); 3.2023 Project on Upgrading the <rs type="funder">Scientific Research Capacity of Young and Middle-aged Teachers in Colleges and Universities in Guangxi Province of China</rs>: "<rs type="projectName">Applied Research on the Innovative E-commerce Mode of Hengzhou City's "Lili Flower" Industry in the Context of Rural Revitalisation</rs>" (grant number: <rs type="grantNumber">2023KY1336</rs>) (YX). 4.Special topic for research on financial literacy education in the 14th <rs type="funder">Five-Year Plan of Educational Science in Guangxi Province of China</rs> for the year 2023: Research on the integrated teaching system of financial literacy education and innovation and entrepreneurship in the whole process of talent cultivation (No. <rs type="grantNumber">2023ZJY898</rs>) (XM).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_54reGr7">
					<idno type="grant-number">72164002</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_Z5RUsV5">
					<idno type="grant-number">71762003</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_CTQMD7E">
					<idno type="grant-number">2023KY1336</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Applied Research on the Innovative E-commerce Mode of Hengzhou City&apos;s &quot;Lili Flower&quot; Industry in the Context of Rural Revitalisation</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_5SxPQqU">
					<idno type="grant-number">2023ZJY898</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data availability statement</head><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/Supplementary Material, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Conditional variable (1)  Method Precision (%) </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest</head><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Publisher's note</head><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary material</head><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ref type="url" target="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fenvs.2024.1361598/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fenvs.2024.1361598/ full#supplementary-material</ref> </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Enhancing China&apos;s regulatory framework for eco-industrial parks comparative analysis of Chinese and international green standards</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Arthur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2018. 2019. 2014</date>
			<publisher>World Bank</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Washington, DC, USA, Cai, J. N.</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The economy as an evolving complex system II. Innovate working mechanism to construct ecological zone. Environ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Prot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.14026/j.cnki.0253-9705.2014.07.014</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="61" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">International experience of green and low-carbon development in industrial parks and its enlightenment to China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Deng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.16868/j.cnki.1674-6252.2021.06.040</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chin. J. Environ. Manag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="40" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How do green industrial policies accelerate regional sustainability transition? A spatiotemporal evaluation of policy with a relationalist perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jclepro2023.136797</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clean. Prod</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">404</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">136797</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research on the construction of three-level prevention and control system for sudden water pollution incidents in industrial parks: a case study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Digital economy, spatial spillover and regional innovation capability enhancement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.19808/j.cnki.41-1408/F.2023.0007</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Manag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="84" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What kinds of entrepreneurial ecosystem can produce country-level female high entrepreneurial activity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.16192/j.cnki.1003-2053.2021.04.008</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stud. Sci. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="695" to="702" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research on the lnfluence of lnnovation resources on the performance of cross RegionaCollaborative lnnovation:QCA analysis based on 31 provinces and cities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.19629/j.cnki.34-1014/f.210713004</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">East China Econ. Manag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Group perspective and qualitative comparative analysis (QCA): a new path for management research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Beijing</forename><surname>Cciid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">China</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.19744/j.cnki.11-1235/f.2017.06.012</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Manag. World</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="167" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2023. 2017</date>
			<publisher>China Center for Information Industry Development</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>White paper on green development of China&apos;s industry</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What kind of ecosystem for doing business will contribute to city-level high entrepreneurial activity? A research based on institutional configurations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.19744/j.cnki.11-1235/f.2020.0143</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Manag. World</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A statistical significance test for necessary condition analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kuik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1094428118795272</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organ. Res. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="385" to="395" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficiency, legitimacy, and technology implementation in government: an integrative multi method research on government website at the city level in China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Fan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Public Adm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">05</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="187" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building better causal theories: a fuzzy set approach to typologies in organization research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5465/amj.2011.60263120</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acad. Manag. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="393" to="420" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Disentangling combinations and contingencies of generic strategies: a set-theoretic Configurational approach. Long. Range Plan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Greckhamer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gurf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.lrp.2019.101951</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101951</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fenvs.2024.1361598</idno>
		<title level="m">Frontiers in Environmental Science frontiersin.org 13 Meng et</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developing and testing an integrative framework for open government adoption in local governments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Grimmelikhuijsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Feeney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/puar.12689</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Public Adm. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="579" to="590" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The effects of fiscal decentralisation and promotion incentives on urban environmental pollution--An overview of the importance of green appraisal on environmental governance in China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.13239/j.bjsshkxy.cswt.180204</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2023. 2018</date>
			<publisher>Urban Probl</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="35" />
			<pubPlace>New York, NY, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Can pressure of local government performance appraisal lmprove corporate green innovationPerformance?Empirical evidence from dual mediation of environmental</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Key problem and solution about the sustainable developmentof economic and technological development zonesin China: based on research results</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comp. Econ. Soc. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="163" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role classification of overseas subsidiaries and its matching effect with control methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.19744/j.cnki.11-1235/f.2017.10.012</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Manag. World</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="171" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Competition among local governments, environmental regulation and green development efficiency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">An</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">China Popul. Resour. Environ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A study on the influence of green industrial policy on urban green development: based on the empirical data of ecological industrial park pilot construction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/su151310065</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sustainability</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10065</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The internet and homeowner&apos;s collective resistance: a qualitative comparative analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gui</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.19934/j.cnki.shxyj.2009.05.002</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociol. Stud</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An overview of strategic environmental assessment for watershed development planning in China: moving towards more effective involvement in green development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.eiar.2023.107083</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ. Impact Assess. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">107083</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building a monitoring and warning index system of resource and environment carrying capacity of megapolis by taking Chengdu as an example</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.14026/j.cnki.0253-9705.2018.12.012</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ. Prot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research on green performance of GovernmentThe logical bases, model establishment and technical paths:based on a compatible design of green GDP accountin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.15937/j.cnki.issn1001-8263.2014.01.007</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nanjing J. Soc. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The spatial effect of technological innovation on carbon productivity -based on the perspective of industrial structure and external openness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3969/j.issn.1004-6917.2022.04.003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soc. Sci. Guangxi</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of the influence and effect of government subsidies on enterprises&apos; green innovation -based on the perspective of enterprises&apos; motivation for innovation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sub Natl. Fiscal Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circular economy: lessons from China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/531440a</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">531</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="440" to="442" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moving to a circular economy in China: transforming industrial parks into eco-industrial parks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0008125617752692</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Calif. Manage. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="181" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Implementing open innovation in the public sector: the case of Challenge. gov</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Mergel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Desouza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/puar.12141</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Public Adm. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="882" to="890" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The circular economy: an interdisciplinary exploration of the concept and application in a global context</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Skene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Haynes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10551-015-2693-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Bus. Ethics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">140</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="380" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Literature review of information technology adoption models at firm level</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Oliveira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Martins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electron. J. Inf. Syst. Eval</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="110" to="121" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multinational energy utilities in the energy transition: a configurational study of the drivers of FDI in renewables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Patala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Juntunen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lundan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ritvala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.16528/j.cnki.22-1054/f.2013.01.006</idno>
		<idno>doi:10.16528/j.cnki. 22-1054/f.2013.01.006</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Int. Bus. Stud</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="53" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2021. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Econ. Rev. J.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sacirovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ketin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Vignjevic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sacirovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ketin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Vignjevic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Diffusion of innovations</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Mumbai, India</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Free Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Set-theoretic methods for the social sciences: a guide to qualitative comparative analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wagemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.11830/ISSN,1000-5013.2015.06.0698</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">doi:10.11830/,1000-5013.2015.06.0698</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="698" to="703" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012. 2015</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, UK</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>J. Huaqiao Univ. Nat. Sci.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Technical management skills, attention allocation and local government website development. A group analysis based TOE Framew</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Shipan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Craig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Shipan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Volden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Fan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.19744/j.cnki.11-1235/f.2019.0119</idno>
		<idno>doi:10.19744/j.cnki.11-1235/f.2019.0119</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Political Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008. 2008. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The mechanisms of policy diffusion</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The processes of technological innovationl</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tornatzky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Flelscher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Technol Transfer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing relationships of necessity not just in kind but also in degree: complementing fsQCA with NCA</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Vis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0049124115626179</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociol. methods &amp; Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="872" to="899" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the configurations of Chinese SOEs&apos; group control systems: a qualitative comparative analysis of 102 central SOEs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nankai Bus. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="197" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evolution of the control framework China&apos;s central SOEs: is it strategy determined, institution driven, or dependence on the path? An attempt of a quality comparative analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.19744/j.cnki.11-1235/f.2014.12.009</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Manag. World</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Achievements and prospect of China&apos;s national carbon market construction (2024)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lyu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.15918/j.jbitss1009-3370.2024.7182</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Beijing Inst. Technol. Sci. Ed</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Environmental and economic impact assessment of synergistic organic-waste treatment strategies in eco-industrial parks: a pilot-scale case study in Shenzhen</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Duan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Miao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.eiar.2023.107250</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ. Impact Assess. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">107250</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<pubPlace>China</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">China&apos;s development zone management system and practice and thoughts on the innovation of operation mode</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="147" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Can innovation-driven policy reduce China&apos;s carbon emission intensity? a quasi-natural experiment based on the national innovative city pilot policy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/su15054383</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sustainability</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4383</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How to drive strategic green innovation behavior? A qualitative comparative analysis (QCA) based on Chinese manufacturing enterprises</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11356-023-27834-0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77784" to="77797" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social policy diffusion from the perspective of intergovernmental relations: an empirical study of the urban subsistence allowance system in China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Xufeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Hui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/02529203.2018.1414390</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soc. Sci. China</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">2018. 1993-1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How does environmental regulation influence green technological innovation? Moderating effect of green finance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ji</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jenvman.2023.118112</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Environ. Manag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">342</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">118112</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trend prediction and driving forces of ecological industrial park&apos;s green development level</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7631/issn.1000-2243.2017.02.0262</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Fuzhou Univ. Nat. Sci. Ed</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">02</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="262" to="267" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification and prevention and control suggestions of heavy chemical industry risks in the Yangtze River Economic belt</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.12153/j.issn.1674-991X.20210653</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Environ. Eng. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="370" to="379" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why do Chinese enterprises completely acquire foreign high-tech enterprises-a fuzzy set qualitative comparative analysis (fsQCA) based on 94 cases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.19581/j.cnki.ciejournal.2019.04.007</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">China Ind. Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="135" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Qualitative comparative analysis (QCA) in management and organization research: position, tactics, and directions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3969/i.issn,1672</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chin. J. Manag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1312" to="1323" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficiency evaluation and policy matching of environmental protection fiscal expenditure on green development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research on the development of the Suzhou industrial park from the perspective of multiple helix and regional innovation ecosystem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Xing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.19445/j.cnki.15-1103/g3.2023.06.008</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Manag. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of China&apos;s establishment of ecological civilization pilot zones on carbon dioxide emissions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jenvman.2022.116652</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Environ. Manag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">325</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">116652</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Study on the impact of industrial structure upgrading on carbon emissions in China in the context of carbon peaking and carbon neutrality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Qian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inq. into Econ. Issues</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="105" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research on the path of digital economy cultivating zero-carbon industrial parks in western China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Xue</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Technol. Manag. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="240" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantification of green industrial policies and emission reduction effects:A case study of Yangtze River Delta region</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.11870/cjlyzyyhj202311003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Resour. Environ. Yangtze Basin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2254" to="2272" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
