<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of the Transformational Leadership, Work Culture and Work Environment on Teachers&apos; Organizational Citizenship Behavior (OCB)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ahmad</forename><surname>Suriansyah</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master of Education Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitas Lambung Mangkurat</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70123</postCode>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Muhammad</forename><surname>Saleh</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Master of Education Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitas Lambung Mangkurat</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70123</postCode>
									<settlement>Banjarmasin</settlement>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of the Transformational Leadership, Work Culture and Work Environment on Teachers&apos; Organizational Citizenship Behavior (OCB)</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i12-22</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T00:50+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>transformational leadership</term>
					<term>work culture</term>
					<term>work environment</term>
					<term>organizational citizenship behavior The Effect of The Transformational Leadership</term>
					<term>Work Culture and Work Environment on Teachers&apos; Organizational Citizenship Behavior (OCB)</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This study aims to determine and analyze the effect of the principal's transformational leadership, work culture and work environment on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB). This research is a correlational study with a quantitative approach which is formulated into a path analysis model. The research population was 165 with a research sample of 117 people. The data was collected using instruments consisting of the principal's transformational leadership (42 items), work culture (30 items), work environment (24 items), and Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) (30 items) which have been tested for validity and reliability. The researchers used path analysis to analyze the data. The results of the study showed that there was an effect of transformational leadership on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB), transformational leadership on the work environment, transformational leadership on work culture, work environment on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB), work culture on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB), transformational leadership on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) through the work environment, and transformational leadership on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) through the work environment.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>In relation to the management of learning in the classroom and the moral preparedness of teachers to engage in learning, it will be necessary for teachers to continually develop their inventiveness. This increase in creativity is highly dependent on the willingness of teachers to respond to a demand in the world of education in order to achieve specific goals; consequently, it is necessary for teachers to be willing to work beyond their formal obligations which are identified as Organizational Citizenship Behaviors or abbreviated as OCB <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Karyadi et al., 2022)</ref>. Problems related to Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) of teachers in the field, particularly PAUD teachers, include the following: some teachers are still slow in carrying out teaching assignments, there is a lack of helping fellow teachers in filling in blank lessons if a teacher is absent, there are some teachers who don't care about extra activities at school, there is an assumption that activities outside of teaching hours are a waste of time and energy, and some teachers believe that extracurricular activities are a waste of time and energy All of these issues will have an effect on the subpar educational process, which has an effect on school advancement. The leadership component of the professional principle in the teaching and learning process and the dynamics of school activities is anticipated to stimulate teachers and other staff to pursue work accomplishments, not only personal work accomplishments, but also student and school accomplishments. Consequently, if schools are not supervised by experienced principals, the future quality of Indonesian human resources -particularly in the period of globalization -would face significant obstacles. However, if it is managed professionally, the issue of the quality of human resources would be resolved gradually. Society will grant this sector public respect if the OCB results of these experts are approved and acknowledged by all parties in accordance with the slogan Education for all. The success of a school essentially lies in the efficiency and effectiveness of the performance of a school principal <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Wahjosumidjo, 2019)</ref>, while schools as educational institutions are tasked with carrying out educational processes and teaching and learning processes in an effort to educate the nation's life. The principal is given the task of leading the school, the principal is responsible for achieving school goals, so the quality of the principal's leadership determines the success of the school in achieving organizational goals. In addition to the transformational leadership factors that effect teacher OCB, there are also work culture factors. The definition of work culture according to Nawawi (2018) is a habit carried out repeatedly by employees in an organization. Violation of this habit does not have strict sanctions, but morally organizational actors have agreed that this habit is habits that must be adhered to in the context of carrying out work to achieve goals. From the description above that, work culture is a behavior that is carried out repeatedly by every individual in an organization and has become a habit in carrying out work so that later people doing something can do it well. The work environment is another aspect that influences the OCB of teachers. A comfortable work atmosphere will serve as a catalyst for passion and work efficiency, which in turn will increase work output. However, a work setting that exceeds a teacher's creative capacity might have a negative effect on his or her health. Therefore, it is vital to continue pursuing a safe, healthy, and comfortable workplace in order to obtain a healthy working atmosphere and be able to perform effectively and efficiently. For this reason, it is always vital to conduct a work environment assessment as an early warning system for leaders. Noting the importance of transformational leadership, work culture and work environment in improving OCB which teachers have The goal is to create quality education that is continuation is aimed at creating human resources that quality or quality, then in this study will be examined about the effect of transformational leadership of school principals, work culture and work environment on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) PAUD teachers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. METHOD</head><p>The researchers employed a quantitative research with a correlational approach with the path analysis method, namely the research aims to explain the facts and find out how much effect the variables have. The population in this study was 165 PAUD teachers. The sampling technique used was a purposive sampling technique. The number of samples is determined based on the slovin formula as many as 117 people. The data was collected through principal transformational leadership instruments (charisma, inspirational motivation, intellectual stimulus and individual attention), work culture (employee attitudes towards work, employee work behavior at work), work environment (physical environment and non-physical environment), and Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) (altruism, civic virtue, conscientiousness, courtesy, sportmanship) instrument was analyzed by testing the validity and reliability of the collected data descriptions using path analysis to see direct and indirect effects, by first carrying out normality, linearity, and homogeneity tests.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. RESEARCH RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head><p>Based on the results of data analysis using path analysis as described above from the effect, direct and indirect effect coefficients were found as described in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1. Path Analysis Model X, Z1, Z2 and Y Table 1. Summary of Hypothesis Testing Decisions of H1, H2, H3, H4, &amp; H5</head><p>Hypothesis P Decision H1 There is a significant positive effect of transformational leadership on OCB. 0.000 Accepted H2 There is a significant positive effect of transformational leadership on work culture. 0.001 Accepted H3 There is a significant positive effect of transformational leadership on the work environment. 0.000 Accepted H4 There is a significant positive effect of Work Culture on OCB 0.000 Accepted H5 There is a significant positive effect of the work environment on OCB.</p><p>0.000 Accepted There is an indirect positive effect of transformational leadership on OCB through work culture.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="0.465">0.317 Accepted</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H7</head><p>There is an indirect positive effect of transformational leadership on OCB through the work environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="0.465">0.259 Accepted</head><p>Table <ref type="table">1</ref> is a summary of the decisions H1, H2, H3, H4 , and H5 with the criterion of a significance value of less than 0.05, indicating that the hypotheses are all accepted. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref> is a summary of the decision to test the hypotheses of H6 and H7 with the stipulation that if the coefficient of the direct correlation is smaller than the coefficient of the indirect correlation, then the hypotheses are accepted. Based on the results of the analysis in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref> and<ref type="table">3</ref> in this study, the correlation was found between variables which can be explained as follows.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. The Direct Effect of the Principal's Transformational Leadership on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB)</head><p>The results of the analysis of this study indicate that there is a direct effect of the transformational leadership of school principals on teachers' Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB). This corresponds to the path coefficient value of 0.465. These results can be interpreted that there is a direct effect of the principal's transformational leadership on the Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) of PAUD teachers in Lampihong District. As a transforming leader, the principal should be able to move teachers beyond the expected performance through their effect. OCB is an organizational employee behavior that is shown to increase the effectiveness of organizational performance without ignoring individual employee productivity goals <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Titisari, 2014)</ref>. The results of this study are in line with previous research studied conducted by Gunawan (2016); Lamidi, nd; Rahmansyah (2021) who stated that transformational leadership has a direct effect on the Organizational Citizenship Behavior.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. The Direct Effect of the Principal's Transformational Leadership on the Teacher's Work Environment</head><p>The results of this study showed that there is a direct effect of the transformational leadership of the school principal on the work environment of PAUD teachers in Lampihong District, as evidenced by the path coefficient value of 0.544. With these values, it can be concluded that there is a direct effect of the transformational leadership of the school principal on the work environment of PAUD teachers.</p><p>Prior to making decisions at school, the principal asked the teacher's opinion. The teacher would feel trusted to be accountable for carrying out the decisions made by the principal as a result of the teachers' participation. They have the freedom to organize their own workspaces, and they organize theirs to add enthusiasm. The work environment is the conditions and atmosphere in which employees are able to perform their responsibilities and work to the utmost extent. Teachers who are dedicated and disciplined provide a nice working environment for schools, the current work environment is tranquil and pleasant for teachers, and the mutual trust amongst teachers fosters a sense of enthusiasm for their work. A comfortable, clean, and organized workplace creates a pleasant atmosphere for doing teacher tasks. The employee's or teacher's motivation and excitement for work will be greater if the work environment is conducive. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Sedarmayanti (2018)</ref>, if humans are to do their professional duties optimally, the working environment must be healthy, safe, and comfortable. Long-term effects of the work environment's suitability can be felt, whilst a poor work environment can increase labor and time expenditure and hinders the design of an efficient work system. Thus, the work environment is an activity environment in which employees perform work that can influence the fulfillment of corporate goals and facilitate the performance of their duties in a comfortable manner. This research is in line with the results of research study conducted by Susanti (2011) revealed that there is a positive correlation between the work environment and employee effectiveness. It was determined by the degree of strength of the correlation in the form of a correlation coefficient and a coefficient of determination. The results of this study are supported by the theory put forward by Amstrong &amp; Brown (2012) that an enabling environment will create the conditions that encourage high performance and effective discretionary behavior. This is consistent with the results of research of <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bana (2013)</ref> which concluded that there is an effect of transformational leadership on the work environment. Transformational leadership is a very important factor for the correlation between organizations in education in higher education. Transformational leadership is effective if it is able to motivate lecturers to achieve optimal performance and can be learned effectively. Transformational leadership between organizations within an institution and applies universally to all situations and environments. Besides transformational leadership, there is a work environment that can affect lecturer performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. The Direct Effect of Work Culture on Teacher Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB)</head><p>The results of the analysis of this study are that there is a direct effect of work culture on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) teacher, as evidenced by the path coefficient value of 0.506. With this value it can be concluded that there is a direct effect of work culture on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) PAUD teacher in Lampihong District.</p><p>The results of this study are also relevant to research <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Normianti et al., (2019)</ref>. The results showed that head leadership is directly related to teacher Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB). This is evidenced by the path coefficient value of 0.579, which means that there is a moderate correlation between Work Culture and Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) of teachers at Labuan Amas Selatan Elementary School.</p><p>The results of this study are also in line with Agustina's research (2019). The results showed that the average score of Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) of total teachers was 4.08, which means that the Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) of State Elementary School teachers in Kandangan District, Hulu Sungai Selatan Regency was very high. The opportunity to grow subvariables is obtained with the highest average value of 4.20. This value is in the very high category, meaning that the teacher has the support of the school principal to participate in various activities aimed at improving teacher abilities, such as education and training. In addition, the principal also provides convenience for teachers who wish to improve their educational qualifications in the sense that they continue their education to a higher level. According to Normianti et al., (2019), one of the important competencies that a leader must possess is the ability to be able to motivate his subordinates. The principal acts as a motivator for both subordinates and the surrounding environment.</p><p>The amount of effect that a leader has determines what and how a job is carried out in an organization he leads. Work Culture is a type of leadership that is considered capable of fostering Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) of its followers because work culture does not only pay attention to the needs of self-actualization and appreciation but also raises awareness for leaders to do their best by paying more attention to human factors, performance and organizational growth.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. The Effect of the Principal's Transformational Leadership on Teacher Work Culture</head><p>The results of the analysis from this study indicate that there is a direct effect of the school principal's transformational leadership on the work culture of PAUD teachers. This can be seen from the path coefficient value of 0.627. These results can be interpreted that there is a direct effect of the principal's transformational leadership on the work culture of PAUD teachers.</p><p>Based on the results of research on the perceptions of PAUD teachers on the principal's transformational leadership, especially the dimensions on high performance expectations that have effectiveness in helping teachers to achieve school goals. This can be seen from the behavior of school principals who must be able to create high expectations for teachers to work innovatively and professionally in order to create maximum results.</p><p>In addition to establishing high standards of achievement, principals must also construct a shared vision for the school and offer teachers with assistance. This indicates that the principal is able to exercise a style of transformational leadership that can instill in teachers an attitude that fosters the development of mutual trust and concern. In a time when everything is entirely open, the principle's leadership is crucial for giving teachers with direction; therefore, a principal with the ability to empower teachers is required. Principals with supervisory skills require accomplishment, intelligence, assertiveness, self-confidence, and initiative, and they are able to motivate instructors to provide their best effort. The results of this study are also in line with Kailoka's research <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Herminingsih, 2011)</ref> which concluded that transformational leadership has a direct effect on work culture. This means that changes in transformational leadership will lead to an increase in the teacher's work culture. The principal improves student activities, motivates teaching and learning activities, creates a safe and comfortable work atmosphere and works with teachers to improve the quality of learning in schools.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. The Effect of Work Culture on Teachers' Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB)</head><p>The results of the analysis of this study are that there is a direct effect of work culture on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) teacher indicated by the Standardized Coefficients Beta value of 0.506. Based on this it was concluded that there is a direct effect of work culture on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) PAUD teacher. Organizational culture is the values, beliefs and basic principles that are the basis for the management systems and practices and behaviors that enhance and reinforce these principles. Sedarmayanti (2018) stated that organizational culture are the norms and values that direct the behavior of members of the organization (Luthan, 2018). These results support previous research studies Normianti et al., (2019); Sapriansyah &amp; Aslamiah (2022).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F. The Indirect Effect of the Principal's Transformational Leadership on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) is</head><p>Through the Teacher's Work Culture The results of the analysis of this study indicate that there is an indirect effect of the school principal's transformational leadership on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) through the work culture of PAUD teachers in Lampihong District, as evidenced by the product of the path coefficient of the direct effect of the multiplication variable between the beta value of the Principal Transformational Leadership variable (X) on the Work Culture variable (Z1) with the beta value of the Work Culture variable (Z1) on the Organizational Citizenship Behaviors variable (OCB) (Y) namely: .627 x 0.506 = 0.317. This means that there is an indirect effect of Transformational Leadership (X) on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB ) (Y) through Work Culture (Z1) of 0.317.</p><p>The quality of leadership greatly effects the achievement of an effective school. The principal in this case as a formal and factual leader of a school must be able to collaborate and synergize school components. The aim of the principal in the world of education is to create a quality, effective and efficient educational process. Meanwhile, to create a quality, effective and efficient educational process, good teacher OCB is needed. Teacher OCB is an activity carried out by a teacher in learning according to his authority and responsibility. Thus, it can be said that the more conducive the teacher's work environment and the higher the work culture, the higher the OCB.</p><p>The school provides a safe, orderly, and comfortable learning environment so that teaching and learning can occur in an enjoyable manner. Therefore, an efficient school always provides a safe, comfortable, and orderly school environment by looking for aspects that can enhance the environment. This is consistent with studies by <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Normaini &amp; Aslamiah (2022)</ref> indicating that the capacity to influence subordinates is one of the most critical abilities a leader must possess. Principals serve as motivators for subordinates to establish a work culture. Leadership has a significant impact on enhancing OCB since leaders are role models and command subordinates' attention. Therefore, if a company desires to have a high OCB, it must have leadership capable of fostering a productive work environment for subordinates. According to Jarminto &amp; Aslamiah (2022), the purpose of the contact between leaders and subordinates is to modify the behavior of subordinates so that they feel capable of attempting to attain greater and better work performance. Furthermore, Rachmat &amp; Aslamiah (2022) stated that leadership is required to change the attitude and conduct of members/staff.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G. The indirect effect of the Principal's Transformational Leadership on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) through the Teacher Work Environment PAUD in Lampihong District</head><p>The results of the analysis of this study indicate that there is an indirect effect of the Principal's Transformational Leadership on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) through the PAUD Teacher Work Environment in Lampihong District, as evidenced by the beta multiplication of the effect of the variable Transformational Leadership (X) on the Work Environment (Z2) with the beta value of the effect of the Work Environment variable (Z2) on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) (Y), namely: 0.544 x 0.476 = 0.259. This means that there is an indirect effect between the indirect variables of the Principal's Transformational Leadership on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) through the PAUD Teacher Work Environment in Lampihong District of 0.259. The results of this study prove that the indirect factor of the principal's transformational leadership is on Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) through the teacher work environment. Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) and a good work environment can run optimally if the leader in a school has good principal transformational leadership. The quality of leadership greatly effects the achievement of an effective school. The principal in this case as a formal and factual leader of a school must be able to collaborate and synergize school components. The aim of the principal in the world of education is to create a quality, effective and efficient educational process. Meanwhile, to create a quality, effective and efficient educational process, good teacher OCB is needed. Teacher OCB is an activity carried out by a teacher in learning according to his authority and responsibility. Thus it can be said that the more conducive the teacher's work environment and the higher the work culture, the higher the OCB. The school has a safe, orderly and comfortable learning environment so that the teaching and learning process can take place in a comfortable way. Therefore, an effective school always creates a safe, comfortable and orderly school environment by seeking factors that can foster this environment. In this case, the role of the principal is very important. There are several factors that affect a person's work environment, one of which is the existence of a leadership model in an educational institution. This is in line with research <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Normianti et al., 2019)</ref> . The results of the research analysis show that work culture is indirectly related to OCB through the teacher's work environment <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Syarifuddin &amp; Suriansyah, 2022)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. CONCLUSION</head><p>There are direct and indirect effects between transformational leadership, work culture, work environment and Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB). Teachers in the PAUD environment in Lampihong District are advised to always maintain Organizational Citizenship Behaviors (OCB) and work culture by adjusting the subjects arranged with face-to-face loads.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Previous research is supported by the findings of the studies conducted by Aminudin &amp; Suriansyah (2022); Fitroliana &amp; Suriansyah (2022); Lamidi, nd; Adriani &amp; Sulaiman (2022); Novita &amp; Sulaiman (2022).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 2 . Summary of Hypothesis Testing Decisions of H6 and H7</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>hypothesis</cell><cell>Direct</cell><cell>Indirect</cell><cell>Decision</cell></row><row><cell>H6</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The correlation Between Principal Transformational Leadership and Teacher Professionalism through Discipline and Work Climate of State Elementary School Teachers in Tanjung District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Adriani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amr</forename><surname>Sulaiman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-41</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-41" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2313" to="2320" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">International Journal of Social Science And Human Research The Effect of Transformational Leadership of School Principles, Quality Culture and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aminudin &amp; Suriansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i9-47</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i9-47" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2345" to="2353" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Handbook of Human Resources Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Armstrong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Kogan Page</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of Transformational Leadership and Physical Work Environment on Employee Performance with Work Motivation as a Mediating Variable</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bana</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Chemical Information and Modeling</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1689" to="1699" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of Principal Transformational Leadership, Work Discipline, and Emotional Intelligence on Teacher Work Performance at State Elementary Schools, North Banjarmasin District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fitroliana &amp; Suriansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-29</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-29" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2223" to="2229" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of Transformational Leadership on Organizational Citizenship Behavior (OCB) at PT First MArchinery Tradeco Surabaya Branch</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gunawan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AGORA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="66" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Effect of Transformational Leadership on Organizational Culture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Herminingsih</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation between Leadership Transformational Head School, Climate Organization, and Teacher Performance through the achievement motivation of private vocational high school teachers in Banjarbaru</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aslamiah</forename><surname>Jarminto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Suhartono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-106</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-106" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2701" to="2707" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Climate and Work Motivation on Teachers&apos; Organizational Citizenship Behavior in MTsN throughout Hulu Sungai Selatan Regency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Karyadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wahyu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Metroyadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-28</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-28" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2215" to="2222" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The effect of Transformational Leadership on Organizational Citizenship Behavior: with Organizational Commitment Intervening Variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lamidi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.ptonline.com/articles/how-to-getbetter-mfi-results" />
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="37" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Organizational Culture Leadership and Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Nawawi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<pubPlace>Golden</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Work Motivation as an Intermediary Variable in the correlation between Principal Transformational Leadership, School Climate, and Teacher Professionalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Novita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sulaiman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-51</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-51" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2285" to="2291" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effect of Principal Transformational Leadership, Job Satisfaction and Work Motivation on the Performance of Elementary School Teachers in Halong District</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aslamiah</forename><surname>Normaini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-39</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-39" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2297" to="2306" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">correlation of Transformational Leaders of Principal, Teacher Motivation, Teacher Organization Commitments With Performance of Primary School Teachers in Labuan Amas Selatan, Indonesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Normianti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Aslamiah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Suhaimi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.2583734</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.2583734" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Education Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation between Leadership Behavior, Work Stress and Work Motivation on Teacher Performance of SMPN Balangan Regency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rachmat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Aslamiah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-107</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-107" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2708" to="2713" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rahmansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Effect of Transformational Leadership</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">International Journal of Social Science And Human Research The Effect of Organizational Culture and Organizational Climate Through Motivation Work towards Organizational Citizenship Behavior (OCB) Of Elementary School Teachers in Lampihong</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sapriansyah &amp; Aslamiah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Re</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">05</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4331" to="4337" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human Resource Management Bureaucratic Reform and Management of Civil Servants</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sedarmayanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aditama Refika</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The correlation Between Supervision and Work Environment With Work Effectiveness of Regional Office Employees of the Ministry of Religion of North Sulawesi Province</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Susanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.21009/jmp.v2i2.2452</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.21009/jmp.v2i2.2452" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Education Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="327" to="335" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of Principal Instructional Leadership, Work Environment and Job Satisfaction on Teacher Performance in State Elementary Schools in Cempaka District, Banjarbaru City</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Syarifuddin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Suriansyah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-34</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.47191/ijsshr/v5-i6-34" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Science and Human Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2257" to="2266" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Role of Organizational Citizenship Behavior (OCB) in Improving Employee Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Titisari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Media Discourse Partners</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">), which permits remixing, adapting and building upon the work for non-commercial use</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wahjosumidjo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">There is an Open Access article, distributed under the term of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Principal Leadership, Theoretical Review and Problems. King of Grafindo Persada. provided the original work is properly cited</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
