<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Predictors of School Students&apos; Leisure-Time Physical Activity: An Extended Trans-Contextual Model Using Bayesian Path Analysis</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Finland Distinguished Professor (FiDiPro)</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_ZH3ZEGa">
					<orgName type="full">Business Finland</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_kgQDKCk">
					<orgName type="full">Finnish Ministry of Education and Culture</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Juho</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Polet</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIKES Research Centre for Physical Activity and Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Thessaly</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gri th University Menzies Health Institute Queensland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Curtin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jyvaskylan</forename><surname>Yliopisto</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIKES Research Centre for Physical Activity and Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Thessaly</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gri th University Menzies Health Institute Queensland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Curtin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIKES Research Centre for Physical Activity and Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Thessaly</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gri th University Menzies Health Institute Queensland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Curtin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIKES Research Centre for Physical Activity and Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Thessaly</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gri th University Menzies Health Institute Queensland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Curtin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIKES Research Centre for Physical Activity and Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Thessaly</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gri th University Menzies Health Institute Queensland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Curtin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIKES Research Centre for Physical Activity and Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Thessaly</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gri th University Menzies Health Institute Queensland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Curtin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jekaterina</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIKES Research Centre for Physical Activity and Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Thessaly</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gri th University Menzies Health Institute Queensland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Curtin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mary</forename><surname>Hassandra</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIKES Research Centre for Physical Activity and Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Thessaly</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gri th University Menzies Health Institute Queensland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Curtin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Taru</forename><surname>Lintunen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIKES Research Centre for Physical Activity and Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Thessaly</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gri th University Menzies Health Institute Queensland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Curtin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Arto</forename><surname>Laukkanen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIKES Research Centre for Physical Activity and Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Thessaly</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gri th University Menzies Health Institute Queensland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Curtin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nelli</forename><surname>Hankonen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIKES Research Centre for Physical Activity and Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Thessaly</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gri th University Menzies Health Institute Queensland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Curtin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Helsingin</forename><surname>Yliopisto</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIKES Research Centre for Physical Activity and Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Thessaly</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gri th University Menzies Health Institute Queensland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Curtin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mirja</forename><surname>Hirvensalo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIKES Research Centre for Physical Activity and Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Thessaly</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gri th University Menzies Health Institute Queensland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Curtin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tuija</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Tammelin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIKES Research Centre for Physical Activity and Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Thessaly</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gri th University Menzies Health Institute Queensland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Curtin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kyra</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIKES Research Centre for Physical Activity and Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Thessaly</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gri th University Menzies Health Institute Queensland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Curtin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
							<email>mhagger@ucmerced.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LIKES Research Centre for Physical Activity and Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Thessaly</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gri th University Menzies Health Institute Queensland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Curtin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Predictors of School Students&apos; Leisure-Time Physical Activity: An Extended Trans-Contextual Model Using Bayesian Path Analysis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.21203/rs.3.rs-23231/v3</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T19:11+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>autonomous motivation</term>
					<term>self-determination theory</term>
					<term>theory of planned behavior</term>
					<term>self-control</term>
					<term>habit</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The present study aimed to examine effects of motivational and social cognition constructs on children's leisure-time physical activity participation alongside constructs representing implicit processes using an extended trans-contextual model. The study adopted a correlational prospective design. Secondary-school students (N = 502) completed self-report measures of perceived autonomy support from physical education (PE) teachers, autonomous motivation in PE and leisuretime contexts, and social cognition constructs (attitudes, subjective norms, perceived behavioral control), intentions, trait self-control, habits, and past behavior in a leisure-time physical activity context. Five weeks later, students (N = 298) selfreported their leisure-time physical activity participation. Bayesian path analyses supported two key premises of the model: perceived autonomy support predicted autonomous motivation in PE, and autonomous motivation in PE predicted autonomous motivation in leisure time. Both forms of autonomous motivation predicted social cognition constructs and intentions, but did not predict leisure-time physical activity participation. Self-control, attitudes, and past behavior were direct predictors of intentions and leisure-time physical activity participation. Specifying informative priors for key model relations using Bayesian analysis yielded greater precision for some model effects. Findings raise some questions on the predictive validity of the original trans-contextual model, but highlight the value of extending the model to incorporate additional constructs representing non-conscious processes.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Research indicates that low levels of physical activity have deleterious effects on the health of young people <ref type="bibr">(1)</ref>. However, children and adolescents in many nations are not su ciently active to confer health bene ts and reduce disease risk <ref type="bibr">(2)</ref>. As a consequence, national and international health organizations have developed guidelines and national strategies aimed at promoting physical activity in this population <ref type="bibr">(3)</ref>. Given the imperative for promoting physical activity among young people, public health organizations and educators have sought to identify optimally effective strategies to enhance physical activity in this population, and the contexts in which these strategies will have maximal reach.</p><p>Physical education (PE) has been suggested as a potentially useful existing network that can be utilized to deliver interventions promoting physical activity both inside school, and, importantly, outside school, in children and adolescents <ref type="bibr">(4)</ref>. Researchers have, therefore, aimed to explore the potentially e cacious strategies delivered in PE to promote increased physical activity outside of school. Such an endeavor necessitates an understanding of the determinants of children and adolescents' physical activity participation in a PE context and, importantly, also whether those determinants relate to physical activity participation outside of school in students' leisure time <ref type="bibr">(5)</ref>. Understanding how factors linked to engagement in physical activity in school relate to physical activity performed in another context, leisure time, is critical to informing potential strategies delivered in PE that promote physical activity participation in children and adolescents in their leisure time. Such an approach is also consistent with one of the key pedagogical aims of PE to provide young people with the necessary skills to lead an active lifestyle (6).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Trans-Contextual Model</head><p>The trans-contextual model <ref type="bibr">(5)</ref> was developed to provide a theoretical explanation of the constructs and processes that link engagement in physical activity in school PE with physical activity participation in leisure time. The model draws on multiple theories to outline the processes by which school students' motivation toward physical activity in PE relates to their motives and beliefs toward, and actual participation in, physical activity in their leisure time. The model integrates core constructs and processes from self-determination theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, the hierarchical model of intrinsic and extrinsic motivation (8), and the theory of planned behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(9)</ref>. Next, we outline the key premises of the model relating to the determinants of children and adolescents' leisure-time physical activity and the processes involved.</p><p>Based on self-determination theory, the rst premise of the trans-contextual model focuses on the origins of school students' motivation toward activities in PE, and how their motivation relates to their behavior in PE. The model predicts that the social environment in educational settings fostered by social agents and leaders (e.g., PE teachers) will determine the type or form of motivation students experience when performing tasks (e.g., physical activities in PE) and, importantly, their persistence on tasks. Central to the theory is the distinction between autonomous and controlled forms of motivation.</p><p>Autonomous motivation is a form of motivation re ecting self-endorsed reasons for acting and autonomously motivated individuals tend to persist on tasks and exhibit behavioral persistence. Fostering autonomous motivation through the display of autonomy-supportive behaviors by social agents such as PE teachers will promote autonomous motivation toward physical activities performed in PE. Furthermore, students who perceive their PE teacher as displaying behaviors that support their autonomy are more likely to report autonomous motivation toward activities in PE <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(10)</ref>. These predictions form the basis of the rst premise of the trans-contextual model: students' perceived autonomy support from their teachers in PE will relate to their autonomous motivation toward physical activity in a PE context.</p><p>A central prediction of the trans-contextual model is that there will be a trans-contextual relationship between students' autonomous motivation toward physical activities across PE and leisure-time contexts. This prediction is based on Vallerand's (8) hierarchical model, which describes the process by which motivation is transferred across contexts. Vallerand proposed that individuals experiencing autonomous motivation toward activities in one context will also cite autonomous motives toward similar behaviors in other related contexts. This forms the second premise of the trans-contextual model: school students' level of autonomous motivation toward physical activities in a PE context will be related to their autonomous motivation toward physical activities performed outside of school in their leisure time.</p><p>A nal prediction of the trans-contextual model is that autonomous motivation toward physical activities in a leisure-time context will be related to students' beliefs and intentions toward, and future participation in, leisure-time physical activity. If an individual has experienced a behavior as autonomously motivated, it is likely to be internalized and integrated into the individual's repertoire of behaviors that satisfy their psychological need for autonomy. They are therefore more likely to actively seek out opportunities to engage in the behavior in future. To do so, they need to align their system of beliefs and intentions involved in the decision to perform that behavior in future. In the trans-contextual model, this process is modeled by the sets of beliefs from the theory of planned behavior, a leading social cognition theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(9)</ref>. Autonomously-motivated individuals are likely to form positive intentions to perform the behavior in future, and report favorable attitudes, subjective norms, and perceived behavioral control, the immediate belief-based determinants of intentions <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(11)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(12)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(13)</ref>. This forms the third premise of the trans-contextual model: students' autonomous motivation toward physical activity in leisure time will be related to their future participation in leisure-time physical activity mediated by the belief-based social cognition determinants (attitudes, subjective norms, and perceived behavioral control) and their intentions toward participating in leisure-time physical activity in future.</p><p>The key premises of the trans-contextual model have received substantial empirical support (e.g., <ref type="bibr">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">15)</ref>. Furthermore, a meta-analysis of studies applying the model in PE and leisure-time physical activity contexts provides converging evidence supporting model predictions across multiple studies (16).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Extending the Model</head><p>While the trans-contextual model has displayed utility in identifying the determinants of leisure-time physical activity participation, it is not without limitations. One limitation is the exclusive focus on motivational and social cognition determinants of leisure-time physical activity participation without regard for the in uence of implicit beliefs and motives that affect individuals' behavior beyond their awareness <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(17)</ref>. In contrast, dual-process theories of motivation and social cognition propose that individuals' behavior is determined by constructs that re ect conscious, reasoned decision making (e.g., autonomous motivation, social cognition constructs) but also by constructs that re ect implicit decision-making that impact behavior with little reasoned deliberation. Such constructs include implicit attitudes, habits, and individual difference constructs (e.g., <ref type="bibr">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">20)</ref>. Non-conscious processes are adaptive because they lead to effective, e cient decision-making when reasoned deliberation is unnecessary or particularly costly <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(21)</ref>. Constructs re ecting these non-conscious processes are proposed to impact behavior directly without mediation by intentions, independent of the reasoned processes. These constructs may, therefore, account for the additional variance in leisure-time physical activity participation in the transcontextual model and serve to provide a more comprehensive prediction of physical activity motivation and behavior in PE and leisure time.</p><p>Prominent behavioral determinants that re ect non-conscious processes are habit, trait self-control, and affective attitudes.</p><p>Focusing rst on habit, although research on habits has historically considered effects of past behavior as a viable proxy for habitual effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(22)</ref>, recent research has focused on habit as a construct <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">23)</ref>. Theories of habit suggest that habitual behaviors are a function of behavioral experiences in the presence of consistent environmental, situational, or internal cues, and often experienced as automatic, effortless, and highly accessible <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(23)</ref>. These components have been captured by selfreport measures of habit, which are meta-cognitive measures which tap individuals' experience of target behaviors as 'unthinking' and 'automatic' <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(19)</ref>. Such measures have been shown to predict behavior independent of intention-mediated measures, and are also associated with action accessibility and behavioral performance in stable contexts.</p><p>Trait self-control re ects individual differences in capacities and self-regulatory skills that enable individuals to resist impulses and temptations, and engage in sustained, effortful behavior to attain long-term goal-directed outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(24)</ref>. Trait self-control has been consistently related to adaptive behaviors, including physical activity, across multiple contexts and populations <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(25)</ref>. Research has also demonstrated that behavioral effects of trait self-control may be direct, independent of intentions (26). Such effects re ect generalized tendencies to engage in adaptive behaviors without the need for deliberation or consideration. However, a case has also been made for effects of trait self-control on behavior mediated by intentions (26). Such effects re ect situations where individuals have to actively engage in effortful deliberation to overcome a maladaptive behavior, or engage in a new behavior, that requires deliberation. Effects of trait self-control in motivational and social cognition theories may, therefore, relate to behavior via two pathways, directly, and indirectly through intentions. Research incorporating trait self-control in the model has supported these dual effects, with direct and intention-mediated effects on physical activity participation (26).</p><p>There is also research demonstrating that attitudes may predict behavior directly, and such direct effects may also re ect non-conscious decision making <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(27,</ref><ref type="bibr">28)</ref>. The original conceptualization of the theory of planned behavior speci es that attitudes represent cognitive re ections on future participation in a target behavior and should relate to behavior mediated by intentions. However, direct effects of attitudes have been identi ed (28), and have been attributed to the affective or emotional component of attitude. Research separating the cognitive and affective attitude components has demonstrated independent effects. The affective component is proposed to encompass visceral approach or avoidance responses learned through behavioral experience <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(27)</ref>. Direct effects of attitude on behavior may re ect a further spontaneous, automatic process, which affects behavior independent of intentions.</p><p>In the present study, we aimed to extend the trans-contextual model by including these constructs as additional determinants alongside the constructs of the model in a test of the model. This extension is expected to provide additional information on the determinants of leisure-time physical activity behavior, particularly effects of constructs representing non-conscious processes not accounted for in the original model. These constructs are proposed, therefore, to relate to leisure-time physical activity participation directly, independent of effects of the other motivational and social cognition constructs in the model. We also applied the Bayesian analytic approach to test model effects using informative prior values for key model effects derived from a meta-analysis of the model (16). We also capitalized on previous meta-analytic research on self-reported habit <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(29)</ref> and trait self-control <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(25)</ref> to specify informative priors for these parameters in our test of extensions to the model. We expected to see a reduced level of uncertainty in the distributions of the parameters of the model speci ed for the current data when informative priors for key model parameters derived from the meta-analysis are speci ed, re ected in narrowed credibility intervals, compared to the distributions when non-informative priors are speci ed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Present Study</head><p>The current study investigated the determinants of lower secondary school students' leisure-time physical activity participation based on an extended trans-contextual model. The study adopted survey methods and a ve-week prospective design with measures of motivational and social cognition constructs, habit, trait-self-control, and past physical activity participation taken at an initial occasion, and self-reported leisure-time physical activity participation taken at follow-up, ve weeks later. This time period was selected to provide reasonable medium-term prediction, which exceeds typical time frames in model tests <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(30)</ref>. In addition to testing effects of the motivational and social cognition determinants from the transcontextual model on students' intentions toward, and actual participation in, leisure-time physical activity, we also tested direct effects of constructs re ecting non-conscious processes as direct determinants of leisure-time physical activity participation, self-reported habit, trait self-control, and attitudes. The speci c predictions of the proposed model, including direct and indirect effects in the proposed model are summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>. and participants completed self-report questionnaires assessing demographic, psychological, and behavioral measures. The baseline data collection period was followed by the teacher training phase (12 hours over two weeks) and the implementation phase (one month), after which post-intervention data was collected comprising the same self-report questionnaires as at baseline. Follow-up data was further collected one, three, and six months post-intervention. The present study used measures of motivation and social cognition constructs and leisure-time physical activity participation taken at baseline and post-intervention leisure-time physical activity participation controlling intervention effects at baseline. Data for the present study were collected between September and December 2018.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures</head><p>Measures of study constructs were adapted from validated self-report instruments used in previous applications of the trans-contextual model. Measures included in the surveys were: perceived autonomy support from PE teachers <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(32)</ref>; autonomous motivation derived from items measuring self-determined forms of motivation from the perceived locus of causality scales for the PE and leisure-time physical activity contexts <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(33)</ref>; intentions, attitudes, subjective norms, and perceived behavioral control from the theory of planned behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(34)</ref>; self-reported habit <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(19)</ref> and trait self-control <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(35)</ref>; and self-reported leisure-time physical activity participation (36). All self-report measures were translated from English to Finnish using a back-translation process by two bilingual researchers. Full details of the measures used are available in Appendix A (supplemental materials).</p><p>Perceived autonomy support. Students' perceived autonomy support from their PE teacher was measured using items from the Perceived Autonomy Support Scale for Exercise Settings <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(32)</ref>. The scale comprised 13 items (e.g., "I feel that my PE teacher provides me with choices and options to …") with responses provided on seven-point scales (1 = strongly disagree and 7 = strongly agree).</p><p>Autonomous motivation. Autonomous motivation toward in-school and out-of-school physical activities was measured using items from the Perceived Locus of Causality Questionnaire <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(33)</ref>. Two items measured identi ed regulation (e.g., "I do PE/physical activity because it is important to me to do well in PE/physical activity") and two items measured intrinsic motivation (e.g., "I do PE/physical activity because it is fun"). Responses were provided on seven-point scales (1 = not true for me and 7 = very true for me). For each of the PE and leisure-time contexts, a composite autonomous motivation score was computed by averaging scores on the identi ed regulation and intrinsic motivation items.</p><p>Theory of planned behavior constructs. Measures of students' attitudes, subjective norms, perceived behavioral control, and intentions with respect to their future participation in leisure-time physical activity were developed according to guidelines <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(34)</ref>. Attitudes were measured on three items in response to a common stem: "Participating in physical activity in the next ve weeks will be…", with responses provided on seven-point scales (e.g., 1 = unenjoyable and 7 = enjoyable). Subjective norms (e.g., "Most people who are important to me think I should do active sports and/or vigorous physical activities during my leisure time in the next ve weeks"), perceived behavioral control (e.g., "I am con dent I could do active sports and/or vigorous physical activities during my leisure time in the next ve weeks"), and intentions (e.g., "I intend to do active sports and/or vigorous physical activities during my leisure time in the next ve weeks") were measured using two items each with responses provided on seven-point scales (e.g., 1 = strongly disagree and 7 = strongly agree).</p><p>Habit. Habit was measured using automaticity items from the Self-Reported Habit Index <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(19)</ref> which focuses on personal experience of the behavior as 'automatic' and excludes items related to past behavior. The scale comprised four items (e.g., "Physical activity is something I do without thinking") with responses provided on seven-point scales (1 = completely disagree and 7 = completely agree).</p><p>Trait self-control. Students' trait self-control was measured using the 10-item Self-Discipline Scale (e.g., "I tend to carry out my plans") from the IPIP-HEXACO scales <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(37)</ref> with responses provided on four-point scales (1 = not like me at all and 4 = very much like me).</p><p>Behavior. Past leisure-time physical activity at baseline and leisure-time physical activity participation at follow-up was measured using the short form of the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ; 36). The IPAQ comprises four items recording the frequency (number of days) and duration (minutes per day) of engagement in moderate and vigorous physical activity, walking, and sitting over the past seven days. IPAQ data were processed according to established guidelines (38). The procedure gives an estimate of physical activity in MET-minutes per week with higher MET-minute values indicating higher level of physical activity engagement. Full details of calculations used to produce physical activity estimates are presented in Appendix B (supplemental materials). Internal consistency values for the short-form IPAQ exceed guideline cut-off values and scores on the scale demonstrate reasonable agreement with the long form in previous research (36).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Analysis</head><p>The proposed hypotheses of the extended trans-contextual model (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>) were tested using Bayesian path analytic models estimated with the Mplus 8.4 statistical software. Constructs and behavioral variables were manifest variables computed from the mean of the scale items for each construct. We controlled for the effects of the intervention in the model by including effects of a binary variable representing intervention group membership (1 = allocated autonomy support intervention group, 0 = allocated to control group) on follow-up leisure-time physical activity participation. We controlled for effects of gender as a binary variable (0 = female, 1 = male) and age as a continuous variable by estimating effects of these variables on all other constructs in the model. Missing data for the model components were imputed using full information maximum likelihood (FIML) in Mplus.</p><p>The Bayesian path models were estimated using a Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) simulation process using Gibbs' algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(39)</ref>. We speci ed 100,000 iterations of which the rst half were used as a burn-in phase and the remaining posterior draws used to test model inferences. We adopted Gelman and Rubin's (40) criterion to determine the convergence of the Bayesian estimates with a strict potential scale reduction (PSR) value of 1.01. Two models were estimated. The rst was estimated using non-informative prior values for model parameters using the standard default values offered in Mplus for regression coe cients: normal distribution, mean = 0, variance = in nity. In this case the variance is set at a number su ciently large to approximate in nity: ten to the power of ten. The second adopted informative prior values for key parameters in the model derived from three meta-analyses. Priors for relations among the extended trans-contextual model constructs were derived from Hagger and Chatzisarantis' ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) meta-analysis. The prior value for the effect of self-reported habit on leisure-time physical activity participation was taken from Gardner et al.'s ( <ref type="formula">29</ref>) meta-analysis of self-reported habit in physical activity. Finally, the prior value for the effect of trait self-control on leisure-time physical activity participation was taken from de Ridder et al.'s (25) meta-analysis of trait self-control in health behaviors. Non-informative default priors were speci ed for the remaining paths.</p><p>Fit of the Bayesian models was assessed using posterior predictive checking using recommended criteria based on the goodness-of-t chi-square comparing the proposed model with the observed data across the replications in the Bayesian simulation ( <ref type="formula">39</ref>): (a) the 95% con dence interval of the difference in goodness-of-t chi-square values associated with the observed and replicated data, which should have a positive upper bound and a negative lower bound with the interval centered approximately about zero, and (b) the posterior predictive p-value (PPP), which should exceed .05 and preferably approach .50 for a well-tting model. In addition, we also report a series of approximate t indices equivalent to those reported in frequentist path analysis: the comparative t index (CFI), Tucker-Lewis index (TLI), and the root mean square error of approximation (RMSEA) computed at each MCMC iteration and their 90% con dence intervals <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(41)</ref>. Cut-off values of .95 or greater for the CFI and TLI, and .06 for the RMSEA, have been proposed as indicative of good model t.</p><p>Furthermore, the 90% con dence intervals of each index should ideally exceed the cut-off values.</p><p>With respect to model parameters, the Bayesian analysis computes the point estimate and a 95% credibility interval for each proposed model path. The hypothesized effect is considered supported if the posterior credibility interval of the parameter coe cient for the effect does not include zero. In such cases, the posterior probability of a coe cient not including zero is &gt;0.975. In addition, estimates and credibility of indirect effects for the Bayesian models were estimated using Yuan and MacKinnon's (42) method. The Bayesian approach that included informative priors for key relations in the model was expected to improve the precision of the estimates. We therefore computed the extent to which the width of the credibility interval of the parameter estimates decreased in our Bayesian model with informative priors compared to the model with non-informative priors. Data les and Mplus syntax for the analyses are available online: <ref type="url" target="https://osf.io/z8axj/?view_only=b61fabd171a24d36a603810a97fef20d">https://osf.io/z8axj/? view_only=b61fabd171a24d36a603810a97fef20d</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Preliminary Analyses</head><p>Of the participants who completed the initial survey (N = 502), 370 provided complete data at baseline and 298 participants (50% female; M age = 14.51, SD = 0.70) provided data for analysis after the second survey (19.46% attrition rate). Attrition was due to school absences. Percentage of missing data for the psychological constructs over time was low (M = 1.4%; range = 0.0% to 4.0%) and Little's MCAR test (χ 2 = 63.882, df = 70, p = .683) suggested the data were missing at random. In addition, there were no signi cant differences between those who completed study measures at both time points and those who did not on gender distribution, (χ 2 (1) = 0.403, p = .526), age (t(368) = -0.463, p = .643), or baseline physical activity (t(368) = -1.103, p = .271). We also conducted a one-way MANOVA to examine differences in psychological variables between those who completed study measures at both time points and those who did not, which was not signi cant (F(9, 360) = 0.775, p = .639; Wilks' Λ = .981; partial η 2 = .019). All constructs exhibited adequate internal consistency. Means, standard deviations, omega internal consistency coe cients and zero-order intercorrelations among study constructs are presented in Appendix C (supplemental materials).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Path Analyses</head><p>Bayesian path analytic models using non-informative (Bayesian posterior predictive χ  It is important to note that we did not conduct an a priori statistical power analysis for the current study as the main purpose of the study was to test the intervention <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(31)</ref>. Nevertheless, we conducted a posteriori power analysis to check whether we had adequate power to test the current model. Our analysis was based on MacCallum, Browne, and Sugawara's (43) statistical power determination based on the RMSEA. The nal sample size (N = 298), a null hypothesis RMSEA of 0 and a study hypothesis RMSEA of 0.064, alpha set at 0.05, and 16 degrees of freedom were inputs for the analysis, which was conducted using the Webpower package in R <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(44)</ref>. The resulting power estimate of 0.805 indicated that we has su cient statistical power to detect effects of the stipulated size.</p><p>Assuming the selected priors derived from meta-analyses were indicative of the population point estimates and distributions of effects among model constructs, we expected that Model 2 would yield greater precision in model parameter estimates compared to Model 1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(42)</ref>. This was evaluated by examining the extent to which the credibility intervals about each parameter estimate differed across the models (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>). Results indicated that the width of the credibility intervals was narrowed for a few of the effects in Model 2 relative to Model 1, but not by a substantial margin in most cases. The adequate t of both models suggest that including informative priors in the analyses for key model relationships did not have a substantial bearing on the pattern of effects in the model. Nevertheless, given that some parameters were more precise, particularly the direct effects of perceived autonomy support on autonomous motivation in PE and autonomous motivation in PE on autonomous motivation in leisure time, and the indirect effects of autonomous motivation in PE on autonomous motivation in leisure time and intention, we elected to evaluate our hypothesis tests based on the model using informative priors (Model 2). If the posterior distribution for each effect, represented by the credibility intervals about the coe cients, did not include zero, then the effect was considered supported and the posterior probability of a non-zero value for the coe cient is &gt;0.975.</p><p>In terms of direct effects, we found a non-zero effect of perceived autonomy support in PE on autonomous motivation in PE (H 1 ; β = 1.520, 95% CI [1.176, 1.874], p &lt; .001). There was also a non-zero trans-contextual effect of autonomous motivation in PE on autonomous motivation in leisure time (H </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>The purpose of the current research was to examine the determinants of lower secondary school students' leisure-time physical activity participation using an extended version of the trans-contextual model <ref type="bibr">(5)</ref>. Speci cally, the model was augmented to include two constructs that re ected non-conscious processes as predictors of leisure-time physical activity participation, self-reported habit <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(19)</ref> and trait self-control <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(24)</ref>. In addition, attitude was also set as a direct predictor of leisure-time physical activity participation, representing a further non-conscious process <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(27,</ref><ref type="bibr">28)</ref>. Hypothesized relations among the extended trans-contextual model constructs were tested using a two-wave prospective survey design in a sample of lower secondary school students. Data were analyzed using two Bayesian path analytic models: one specifying noninformative priors and one in which informed priors for key relations in the model derived from previous meta-analyses were speci ed. Results indicated adequate t of both models with the data. Perceived autonomy support predicted autonomous motivation in PE and leisure-time contexts, autonomous motivation in PE predicted autonomous motivation in a leisure-time context, and autonomous motivation in a leisure-time context predicted social cognition constructs (attitudes, perceived behavioral control) and intentions toward leisure-time physical activity participation. There were also indirect effects of perceived autonomy support on autonomous motivation in leisure time mediated by autonomous motivation in PE, and of autonomous motivation in PE and leisure time on intentions through the social cognition constructs. In contrast, there were no effects on leisure-time physical activity participation due to effects of intention and perceived behavioral control that were no different from zero. However, attitudes and trait self-control predicted both intentions and behavior. The Bayesian analytic approach demonstrated that the model was tenable with the model incorporating informative prior knowledge demonstrating marginally more precise parameter estimates.</p><p>Overall, current results supported hypotheses relating to the rst two premises of the trans-contextual model, that is, the premises specifying effects of perceived autonomy support on autonomous motivation in PE, and the trans-contextual effects of autonomous motivation across PE and leisure time context <ref type="bibr">(5,</ref><ref type="bibr">16)</ref>. It also provided support for the effects of autonomous motivation in leisure time on intentions to participate in leisure-time physical activity mediated by the attitude, subjective norm, and perceived behavioral control constructs from the theory of planned behavior. However, there was scant evidence for the third premise, due to an intention-physical activity participation relationship that was no different from zero.</p><p>These ndings suggest that, in the current sample, the trans-contextual model is effective in identifying motivational and social cognition determinants of secondary school students' intentions to participate in leisure-time physical activity, and the processes involved, but not their actual participation. We propose four possible interpretations of the current ndings. First, results may raise questions on the effectiveness of the trans-contextual model in identifying the determinants of leisure-time physical activity participation. There have been occasions where studies on the motivational and social cognition constructs in multi-theory, integrated models have failed to yield non-zero effects for the primary predicted determinants of behavior (18, 45). Nevertheless, such occasions are rare, and are contrary to the substantive body of meta-analytic evidence applying the trans-contextual model ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) and other integrated models that have supported effects more broadly and in multiple populations and contexts (46, 47). Therefore, it may be premature to use the current data as a basis for rejecting the trans-contextual model.</p><p>A second interpretation may be that some of the hypothesized effects were attenuated due to contextual factors that affected relations among constructs, particularly the intention-behavior relationship. Certainly, there is evidence that other extraneous constructs may moderate the intention-behavior relationship (48). One possibility is that the current research was conducted in the context of an intervention. However, correlations of the intervention with key model constructs, particularly intentions and follow-up physical activity participation were no different from zero. In fact, the only effects of the intervention on variables from the current study were on perceived autonomy support and attitudes at baseline, and these effects were opposite to the predicted direction and were taken prior to the intervention. Furthermore, we also controlled for intervention effects in the current model, so reported effects were independent of intervention effects. This leaves the possibility of other extraneous constructs attenuating the intention-physical activity participation relationship in the current study. It is possible, for example, that students' intentions were particularly unstable or inconsistent with their subsequent behavior, given research that has con rmed these intention properties moderate these relations (48). However, this possibility remains speculative as we have no data on intention stability or consistency, nor do we have any contextual or demographic information that would explain such inconsistencies.</p><p>A third explanation may be that participation in leisure-time physical activity in the current sample of school students was largely determined by constructs that re ect individual-level non-conscious processes, that is, constructs that impact behavior directly independent of intentions. That the only determinants of leisure-time physical activity participation in the current study were past physical activity participation, attitude, and trait self-control is consistent with this interpretation.</p><p>Focusing rst on the direct effect of trait self-control on behavior, this construct is proposed to re ect non-conscious processes insofar as those endorsing it are purported to exhibit adaptive self-regulatory skills that assist in pursuing goaldirected behaviors and help resist temptations to engage in alternative behaviors that may derail pursuit of the behavior (26, 49). On the surface, such an effect implies that individuals applying such skills must engage in active, effortful decision making to ensure focus on the target behavior and manage distractions, a conscious process. This may be the case for behaviors with which the individual has little experience. However, where the individual has substantive experience and has engaged in such active deliberation over the management of the behavior and application of their skills, they are likely to have well-learned behavioral scripts or schemas stored in memory to manage distractions and maintain behavioral engagement, obviating the need for such conscious deliberation. This is consistent with research suggesting that individuals with good trait self-control are highly effective in managing their environment so as not to be encumbered by distractions and to ensure that the cues to their desired behavior are omnipresent <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(25)</ref>. While this mechanistic explanation is speculative, it may explain the direct effect of trait self-control on behavior in the current model and provides justi cation to explore the role of this constructs within the trans-contextual model.</p><p>A fourth and nal interpretation is that social environmental factors may have contributed to the weak intention-behavior relationship. The high availability of inactive highly-appealing pastimes available to young people (e.g., computer games) and social norms within families and peer groups to engage in inactive pastimes may have contributed to failure of students to engage in physical activity even if they had autonomous motives and intentions to do so. This is consistent with the current data in which students' average intentions to engage in physical activity in their leisure time was above the scale mid-point (M = 5.651, SD = 1.282). The effects of peer norms are especially strong in this age group, so young people with intentions to be active may nd that they are superseded by their need to conform. These premises are consistent with ecological models that stress environmental in uences (e.g., 50), and research suggesting that such in uences are important predictors of behavior beyond social cognition determinants (e.g., 51). Analogously, if a child has low or no intention to participate in physical activity, they may still be compelled to spontaneously do so if their peer groups decides to have a 'kick about' with a football in their local park. The current study did not measure environmental in uences, so such determinants cannot be empirically veri ed from the current data and should be considered speculative. Nevertheless, it points to the potential importance of incorporating constructs that re ect these environmental determinants within integrated models such as the trans-contextual model.</p><p>Turning to the direct effect of attitude on leisure-time physical activity participation, current ndings are consistent with previous research that has found a direct effect of attitude components on behavior in multiple health contexts <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(27,</ref><ref type="bibr">28)</ref>.</p><p>Such effects likely represent spontaneous decisions to engage in a behavior learned through positive or negative affective experiences that coincide with the behavior. As a consequence, the anticipation of rewarding affective responses may be reasons why children and adolescents might spontaneously engage in physical activities outside of school without the need for reasoned decision making. Such an effect has not been identi ed in previous research adopting the trans-contextual model, but has been consistently identi ed in research applying the theory of planned behavior in health behavior contexts, including physical activity (28). These ndings suggest that if out-of-school activities are emotionally appealing to children and adolescents and have been experienced as enjoyable in the past, they may be more likely to spontaneously participate in physical activities in future.</p><p>With respect to the direct effect of past physical activity behavior, current ndings are consistent with research reporting consistent effects of past behavior on subsequent behavior in social cognition theories (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">52)</ref>. This research demonstrates that past behavior accounts for substantive variance in behavior and often attenuates effects of other constructs. The inclusion of past behavior in social cognition models is important as it provides an indication of the su ciency of the theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">52)</ref>. The absence of effects of theory constructs other than past behavior provides an indication that the theory may be inadequate as a means to explain behavior beyond the stability of the behavior itself. Although in the case of the current research, the exclusion of past behavior did not restore effects of other constructs such as intention on behavior.</p><p>So, what might the large-sized effect of past behavior represent? Researchers have suggested that past behavior may model effects of unmeasured constructs in tests of these theories <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">22)</ref>. Given social cognition theories incorporate constructs that re ect reasoned, deliberative processes, past behavior effects may model effects of constructs representing nonconscious processes such as habits and implicit beliefs. The substantive effect of past physical activity behavior on leisuretime physical activity participation in the current study suggests that lower secondary school students' physical activity in their leisure time may be a function of these kinds of constructs. Current ndings suggest, however, that habit may not be among these determinants, given that the independent effect of self-reported habit on leisure-time physical activity participation was no different from zero. Although it must be stressed that the current measure of habit focused exclusively on automaticity, one aspect of habit, and may not have su ciently captured all habitual in uences (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">53</ref>). The current study did not include measures that capture other aspects of habit such as context stability and accessibility of relevant cues to the behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(23)</ref>. In addition, we did not measure other constructs that may re ect these non-conscious processes, such as implicitly held beliefs developed through past experiences of the behavior covarying with evaluations <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(21)</ref>. Research has suggested that measures of implicit beliefs predict behavior, including physical activity participation, independent of intentions (18) and may also mediate effects of past behavior on subsequent behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(54)</ref>. The effects of past behavior in the current study may, therefore, indicate that physical activity behavior in leisure time may be a function of unmeasured constructs re ecting implicit processes, but such an inference is speculative and requires empirical veri cation.</p><p>The current research also illustrates the value of adopting a Bayesian analytic approach to combine prior knowledge of the distributions of model effects with the observed distributions to produce precise estimates and variability among model constructs. This was demonstrated by the narrowing of the credibility intervals about some of the model parameters. Importantly, the data used for the informative priors was highly reliable given they were derived from meta-analyses of multiple studies with large samples sizes. It is, however, also important to note that although the informative priors for the trans-contextual model effects were a meta-analysis of studies on samples of school students with similar pro le to the participants in the current study (16), priors for the effects of the additional variables, self-reported habit and trait selfcontrol were derived from research from multiple populations and mostly adult samples <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">29)</ref>. Therefore, the priors were not directly comparable to the current sample. Nevertheless, current ndings may be of value as a source of informative priors for future applications of the extended trans-contextual model. Consistent with the Bayesian approach, the current study should form part of an ongoing iterative research process that yields increasingly precise estimates of effects in the model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Strengths, Limitations and Recommendations for Future Research</head><p>Strengths of the current study include (1) a focus on the determinants of lower secondary school students' leisure-time physical activity participation, a priority area of research; (2) the application of an extended trans-contextual model, an innovative multi-theory approach that provided a priori hypotheses on the relations among the determinants and leisure-time physical activity participation; (3) adoption of a two-wave prospective design using validated measures of model determinants and behavior; and (4) application of Bayesian analytic procedures that enabled utilization of prior knowledge to arrive at precise estimates of model effects. However, it is also important to note limitations of the current research that may affect interpretation of the ndings and the extent to which they can be generalized.</p><p>While we endeavored to incorporate additional constructs representing non-conscious determinants of leisure-time physical activity participation in the current study, our measures did not encompass a full range of candidate determinants. For example, the current study did not include measures of implicit cognition and motivation with respect to school students' leisure-time physical activity participation. Given that measures of constructs such as implicit beliefs and autonomous motivation have been shown to predict behavior directly independent of intentions in adult samples (18, 54, 55), future tests of the extended trans-contextual model should consider incorporating measures of these constructs as predictors of leisuretime physical activity participation. This is particularly important given the lack of effects of the intentional or motivational constructs on leisure-time physical activity participation in the current study, and inclusion of implicit beliefs may assist in providing an explanation of the effects of past behavior.</p><p>We also did not include the beliefs that underpin the attitude and subjective norm constructs <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(9)</ref>. Their effects on intentions and behavior are typically mediated by the direct attitude and subjective norm measures. Similarly, we did not include constructs related to socioecological environment that may determine behavior, and whose effects on behavior may be mediated by the social cognition constructs in the model <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(50)</ref>. There is precedence for the indirect effect of these beliefs and socio-ecological constructs in the model. Research has demonstrated that beliefs and socio-ecological factors relating to context and environment are related to the social cognition constructs that predict health behavior, and those constructs mediate the effects of the beliefs and socio-ecological factors on behavior (56, 57). While the constructs in the current model are proposed to account for the effects of these variables, such in uences need empirical veri cation and serve as an avenue for future research.</p><p>In addition, current data are correlational, which limits the extent to which we could infer causal relations among the extended trans-contextual model constructs. As with many model tests, including those of the trans-contextual model, causal effects are inferred from theory not the data ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>). Future research should consider the adoption of panel designs that permit modeling of temporal change and direction among trans-contextual model constructs over time through cross-lagged effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(11)</ref>. Such designs should also consider examining measuring model constructs over longer periods of time to test the capacity of the model to account for long-term change in its constructs and physical activity behavior, see Jacobs et al. (58) for an example. In addition, intervention and experimental designs are needed to test the effect of manipulating the constructs found to have a direct effect on leisure-time physical activity participation <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(59)</ref>. For example, interventions targeting attitudes should seek to promote enjoyment and positive affect through positive experiences of physical activity, and interventions targeting self-discipline should seek to provide self-regulatory skills that promote better control over impulses to spend excessive time on leisure-time alternatives to physical activity (e.g., video games, watching television) and identify and manage barriers.</p><p>The purpose of the current research was to examine the determinants of lower secondary school students' leisure-time physical activity participation using an extended version of the trans-contextual model <ref type="bibr">(5)</ref>. Speci cally, the model was augmented to include two constructs that re ected non-conscious processes as predictors of leisure-time physical activity participation, self-reported habit <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(19)</ref> and trait self-control <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(24)</ref>. In addition, attitude was also set as a direct predictor of leisure-time physical activity participation, representing a further non-conscious process <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(27,</ref><ref type="bibr">28)</ref>. Hypothesized relations among the extended trans-contextual model constructs were tested using a two-wave prospective survey design in a sample of lower secondary school students. Data were analyzed using two Bayesian path analytic models: one specifying noninformative priors and one in which informed priors for key relations in the model derived from previous meta-analyses were speci ed. Results indicated adequate t of both models with the data. Perceived autonomy support predicted autonomous motivation in PE and leisure-time contexts, autonomous motivation in PE predicted autonomous motivation in a leisure-time context, and autonomous motivation in a leisure-time context predicted social cognition constructs (attitudes, perceived behavioral control) and intentions toward leisure-time physical activity participation. There were also indirect effects of perceived autonomy support on autonomous motivation in leisure time mediated by autonomous motivation in PE, and of autonomous motivation in PE and leisure time on intentions through the social cognition constructs. In contrast, there were no effects on leisure-time physical activity participation due to effects of intention and perceived behavioral control that were no different from zero. However, attitudes and trait self-control predicted both intentions and behavior. The Bayesian analytic approach demonstrated that the model was tenable with the model incorporating informative prior knowledge demonstrating marginally more precise parameter estimates.</p><p>Overall, current results supported hypotheses relating to the rst two premises of the trans-contextual model, that is, the premises specifying effects of perceived autonomy support on autonomous motivation in PE, and the trans-contextual effects of autonomous motivation across PE and leisure time context <ref type="bibr">(5,</ref><ref type="bibr">16)</ref>. It also provided support for the effects of autonomous motivation in leisure time on intentions to participate in leisure-time physical activity mediated by the attitude, subjective norm, and perceived behavioral control constructs from the theory of planned behavior. However, there was scant evidence for the third premise, due to an intention-physical activity participation relationship that was no different from zero.</p><p>These ndings suggest that, in the current sample, the trans-contextual model is effective in identifying motivational and social cognition determinants of secondary school students' intentions to participate in leisure-time physical activity, and the processes involved, but not their actual participation. We propose four possible interpretations of the current ndings. First, results may raise questions on the effectiveness of the trans-contextual model in identifying the determinants of leisure-time physical activity participation. There have been occasions where studies on the motivational and social cognition constructs in multi-theory, integrated models have failed to yield non-zero effects for the primary predicted determinants of behavior <ref type="bibr">(18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">45)</ref>. Nevertheless, such occasions are rare, and are contrary to the substantive body of meta-analytic evidence applying the trans-contextual model ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) and other integrated models that have supported effects more broadly and in multiple populations and contexts <ref type="bibr">(46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">47)</ref>. Therefore, it may be premature to use the current data as a basis for rejecting the trans-contextual model.</p><p>A second interpretation may be that some of the hypothesized effects were attenuated due to contextual factors that affected relations among constructs, particularly the intention-behavior relationship. Certainly, there is evidence that other extraneous constructs may moderate the intention-behavior relationship (48). One possibility is that the current research was conducted in the context of an intervention. However, correlations of the intervention with key model constructs, particularly intentions and follow-up physical activity participation were no different from zero. In fact, the only effects of the intervention on variables from the current study were on perceived autonomy support and attitudes at baseline, and these effects were opposite to the predicted direction and were taken prior to the intervention. Furthermore, we also controlled for intervention effects in the current model, so reported effects were independent of intervention effects. This leaves the possibility of other extraneous constructs attenuating the intention-physical activity participation relationship in the current study. It is possible, for example, that students' intentions were particularly unstable or inconsistent with their subsequent behavior, given research that has con rmed these intention properties moderate these relations (48). However, this possibility remains speculative as we have no data on intention stability or consistency, nor do we have any contextual or demographic information that would explain such inconsistencies.</p><p>A third explanation may be that participation in leisure-time physical activity in the current sample of school students was largely determined by constructs that re ect individual-level non-conscious processes, that is, constructs that impact behavior directly independent of intentions. That the only determinants of leisure-time physical activity participation in the current study were past physical activity participation, attitude, and trait self-control is consistent with this interpretation.</p><p>Focusing rst on the direct effect of trait self-control on behavior, this construct is proposed to re ect non-conscious processes insofar as those endorsing it are purported to exhibit adaptive self-regulatory skills that assist in pursuing goaldirected behaviors and help resist temptations to engage in alternative behaviors that may derail pursuit of the behavior (26, 49). On the surface, such an effect implies that individuals applying such skills must engage in active, effortful decision making to ensure focus on the target behavior and manage distractions, a conscious process. This may be the case for behaviors with which the individual has little experience. However, where the individual has substantive experience and has engaged in such active deliberation over the management of the behavior and application of their skills, they are likely to have well-learned behavioral scripts or schemas stored in memory to manage distractions and maintain behavioral engagement, obviating the need for such conscious deliberation. This is consistent with research suggesting that individuals with good trait self-control are highly effective in managing their environment so as not to be encumbered by distractions and to ensure that the cues to their desired behavior are omnipresent <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(25)</ref>. While this mechanistic explanation is speculative, it may explain the direct effect of trait self-control on behavior in the current model and provides justi cation to explore the role of this constructs within the trans-contextual model.</p><p>A fourth and nal interpretation is that social environmental factors may have contributed to the weak intention-behavior relationship. The high availability of inactive highly-appealing pastimes available to young people (e.g., computer games) and social norms within families and peer groups to engage in inactive pastimes may have contributed to failure of students to engage in physical activity even if they had autonomous motives and intentions to do so. This is consistent with the current data in which students' average intentions to engage in physical activity in their leisure time was above the scale mid-point (M = 5.651, SD = 1.282). The effects of peer norms are especially strong in this age group, so young people with intentions to be active may nd that they are superseded by their need to conform. These premises are consistent with ecological models that stress environmental in uences (e.g., 50), and research suggesting that such in uences are important predictors of behavior beyond social cognition determinants (e.g., 51). Analogously, if a child has low or no intention to participate in physical activity, they may still be compelled to spontaneously do so if their peer groups decides to have a 'kick about' with a football in their local park. The current study did not measure environmental in uences, so such determinants cannot be empirically veri ed from the current data and should be considered speculative. Nevertheless, it points to the potential importance of incorporating constructs that re ect these environmental determinants within integrated models such as the trans-contextual model.</p><p>Turning to the direct effect of attitude on leisure-time physical activity participation, current ndings are consistent with previous research that has found a direct effect of attitude components on behavior in multiple health contexts <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(27,</ref><ref type="bibr">28)</ref>. Such effects likely represent spontaneous decisions to engage in a behavior learned through positive or negative affective experiences that coincide with the behavior. As a consequence, the anticipation of rewarding affective responses may be reasons why children and adolescents might spontaneously engage in physical activities outside of school without the need for reasoned decision making. Such an effect has not been identi ed in previous research adopting the trans-contextual model, but has been consistently identi ed in research applying the theory of planned behavior in health behavior contexts, including physical activity (28). These ndings suggest that if out-of-school activities are emotionally appealing to children and adolescents and have been experienced as enjoyable in the past, they may be more likely to spontaneously participate in physical activities in future.</p><p>With respect to the direct effect of past physical activity behavior, current ndings are consistent with research reporting consistent effects of past behavior on subsequent behavior in social cognition theories (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">52)</ref>. This research demonstrates that past behavior accounts for substantive variance in behavior and often attenuates effects of other constructs. The inclusion of past behavior in social cognition models is important as it provides an indication of the su ciency of the theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">52)</ref>. The absence of effects of theory constructs other than past behavior provides an indication that the theory may be inadequate as a means to explain behavior beyond the stability of the behavior itself. Although in the case of the current research, the exclusion of past behavior did not restore effects of other constructs such as intention on behavior.</p><p>So, what might the large-sized effect of past behavior represent? Researchers have suggested that past behavior may model effects of unmeasured constructs in tests of these theories <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">22)</ref>. Given social cognition theories incorporate constructs that re ect reasoned, deliberative processes, past behavior effects may model effects of constructs representing nonconscious processes such as habits and implicit beliefs. The substantive effect of past physical activity behavior on leisuretime physical activity participation in the current study suggests that lower secondary school students' physical activity in their leisure time may be a function of these kinds of constructs. Current ndings suggest, however, that habit may not be among these determinants, given that the independent effect of self-reported habit on leisure-time physical activity participation was no different from zero. Although it must be stressed that the current measure of habit focused exclusively on automaticity, one aspect of habit, and may not have su ciently captured all habitual in uences (e.g., 53). The current study did not include measures that capture other aspects of habit such as context stability and accessibility of relevant cues to the behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(23)</ref>. In addition, we did not measure other constructs that may re ect these non-conscious processes, such as implicitly held beliefs developed through past experiences of the behavior covarying with evaluations <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(21)</ref>. Research has suggested that measures of implicit beliefs predict behavior, including physical activity participation, independent of intentions (18) and may also mediate effects of past behavior on subsequent behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(54)</ref>. The effects of past behavior in the current study may, therefore, indicate that physical activity behavior in leisure time may be a function of unmeasured constructs re ecting implicit processes, but such an inference is speculative and requires empirical veri cation.</p><p>The current research also illustrates the value of adopting a Bayesian analytic approach to combine prior knowledge of the distributions of model effects with the observed distributions to produce precise estimates and variability among model constructs. This was demonstrated by the narrowing of the credibility intervals about some of the model parameters. Importantly, the data used for the informative priors was highly reliable given they were derived from meta-analyses of multiple studies with large samples sizes. It is, however, also important to note that although the informative priors for the trans-contextual model effects were a meta-analysis of studies on samples of school students with similar pro le to the participants in the current study (16), priors for the effects of the additional variables, self-reported habit and trait selfcontrol were derived from research from multiple populations and mostly adult samples <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">29)</ref>. Therefore, the priors were not directly comparable to the current sample. Nevertheless, current ndings may be of value as a source of informative priors for future applications of the extended trans-contextual model. Consistent with the Bayesian approach, the current study should form part of an ongoing iterative research process that yields increasingly precise estimates of effects in the model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Strengths, Limitations and Recommendations for Future Research</head><p>Strengths of the current study include (1) a focus on the determinants of lower secondary school students' leisure-time physical activity participation, a priority area of research; (2) the application of an extended trans-contextual model, an innovative multi-theory approach that provided a priori hypotheses on the relations among the determinants and leisure-time physical activity participation; (3) adoption of a two-wave prospective design using validated measures of model determinants and behavior; and (4) application of Bayesian analytic procedures that enabled utilization of prior knowledge to arrive at precise estimates of model effects. However, it is also important to note limitations of the current research that may affect interpretation of the ndings and the extent to which they can be generalized.</p><p>While we endeavored to incorporate additional constructs representing non-conscious determinants of leisure-time physical activity participation in the current study, our measures did not encompass a full range of candidate determinants. For example, the current study did not include measures of implicit cognition and motivation with respect to school students' leisure-time physical activity participation. Given that measures of constructs such as implicit beliefs and autonomous motivation have been shown to predict behavior directly independent of intentions in adult samples (18, 54, 55), future tests of the extended trans-contextual model should consider incorporating measures of these constructs as predictors of leisuretime physical activity participation. This is particularly important given the lack of effects of the intentional or motivational constructs on leisure-time physical activity participation in the current study, and inclusion of implicit beliefs may assist in providing an explanation of the effects of past behavior.</p><p>We also did not include the beliefs that underpin the attitude and subjective norm constructs <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(9)</ref>. Their effects on intentions and behavior are typically mediated by the direct attitude and subjective norm measures. Similarly, we did not include constructs related to socioecological environment that may determine behavior, and whose effects on behavior may be mediated by the social cognition constructs in the model <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(50)</ref>. There is precedence for the indirect effect of these beliefs and socio-ecological constructs in the model. Research has demonstrated that beliefs and socio-ecological factors relating to context and environment are related to the social cognition constructs that predict health behavior, and those constructs mediate the effects of the beliefs and socio-ecological factors on behavior (56, 57). While the constructs in the current model are proposed to account for the effects of these variables, such in uences need empirical veri cation and serve as an avenue for future research.</p><p>In addition, current data are correlational, which limits the extent to which we could infer causal relations among the extended trans-contextual model constructs. As with many model tests, including those of the trans-contextual model, causal effects are inferred from theory not the data (16). Future research should consider the adoption of panel designs that permit modeling of temporal change and direction among trans-contextual model constructs over time through cross-lagged effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(11)</ref>. Such designs should also consider examining measuring model constructs over longer periods of time to test the capacity of the model to account for long-term change in its constructs and physical activity behavior, see Jacobs et al. (58) for an example. In addition, intervention and experimental designs are needed to test the effect of manipulating the constructs found to have a direct effect on leisure-time physical activity participation <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(59)</ref>. For example, interventions targeting attitudes should seek to promote enjoyment and positive affect through positive experiences of physical activity, and interventions targeting self-discipline should seek to provide self-regulatory skills that promote better control over impulses to spend excessive time on leisure-time alternatives to physical activity (e.g., video games, watching television) and identify and manage barriers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>The current research is the rst to test an extended version of the trans-contextual model to identify determinants of leisuretime physical activity participation in lower secondary school students. Results indicate that the traditional motivational and social cognition constructs are effective in predicting leisure-time physical activity intentions, but not actual behavior. However, we found direct effects of trait self-control and attitude on leisure-time physical activity participation, suggesting that students' physical activity participation was determined by constructs representing non-conscious processes. A further innovation of the current research is the application of a Bayesian analytic approach to update the effects and variability estimates of model parameters based on previous meta-analytic ndings. Results raise questions over the effectiveness of the original trans-contextual model constructs in determining leisure-time physical activity participation, at least in the</p><note type="other">Figures Figure 1</note><p>The  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>using informative priors); PAS = Perceived autonomy support; Aut. mot. = Autonomous motivation; PE = Physical education contexts; LT = Leisure-time context; PBC = Perceived behavioral control; Sub. norm = Subjective norm; Phys. act = Self-reported leisure-time physical activity participation; Past. Beh. = Past leisure-time physical activity behavior. * p &lt; .05 ** p &lt; .01 *** p &lt; .001</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>hypothesized relations among constructs of the extended trans-contextual model.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 Parameter</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2</figDesc><graphic coords="25,28.00,405.00,557.00,273.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Summary of Hypothesized Direct and Indirect Effects in the Extended Trans-Contextual Model Finland with support from the City Education Department. The University institutional review board and Education Department approved the study protocol prior to data collection. Informed consent was sought from the head teacher of each school, and, subsequently, PE teachers and eligible students' parents or legal guardians via the schools' online administration and communication software or via email or post. Opt-in consent was sought from the head teachers and PE teachers, while opt-out consent was sought from students' parents and legal guardians. Quali ed fulltime PE teachers teaching regular PE lessons in lower secondary schools were eligible to participate in the study and were</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">Hypothesis (H) Independent variable Dependent variable</cell><cell>Mediator(s)</cell><cell cols="2">Informative priors</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>β</cell><cell>σ 2</cell></row><row><cell>Direct effects</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H 1</cell><cell>PAS</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (PE) a</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.42</cell><cell>0.10</cell></row><row><cell>H 2</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (PE)</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT) a</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.56</cell><cell>0.17</cell></row><row><cell>H 3</cell><cell>PAS</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT) a</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.29</cell><cell>0.18</cell></row><row><cell>H 4</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Attitude a</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.60</cell><cell>0.12</cell></row><row><cell>H 5</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Subjective norm a</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.26</cell><cell>0.26</cell></row><row><cell>H 6</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>PBC a</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.19</cell></row><row><cell>H 7</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Intention a</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.31</cell><cell>0.13</cell></row><row><cell>H 8</cell><cell>Attitude</cell><cell>Intention a</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.68</cell><cell>0.09</cell></row><row><cell>H 9</cell><cell>Subjective norm</cell><cell>Intention a</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.42</cell><cell>0.25</cell></row><row><cell>H 10</cell><cell>PBC</cell><cell>Intention a</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.63</cell><cell>0.28</cell></row><row><cell>H 11</cell><cell>Habit</cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>H 12</cell><cell>Self-control</cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>H 13</cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell>Phys. act. a</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.60</cell><cell>0.20</cell></row><row><cell>H 14</cell><cell>Attitude</cell><cell>Phys. act. a</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.43</cell><cell>0.21</cell></row><row><cell>H 15</cell><cell>PBC</cell><cell>Phys. act. a</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.43</cell><cell>0.21</cell></row><row><cell>H 16</cell><cell>Habit</cell><cell>Phys. act. b</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.43</cell><cell>0.13</cell></row><row><cell>H 17</cell><cell>Self-control</cell><cell>Phys. act. c</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.26</cell><cell>0.09</cell></row><row><cell>H 18</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Phys. act.</cell><cell></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>H 19</cell><cell>Past behavior</cell><cell>Phys. act.</cell><cell></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Indirect effects</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H 20</cell><cell>PAS</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (PE)</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>H 21</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (PE)</cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell>Attitude Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>H 22</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (PE)</cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell>Sub. norm. Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>H 23</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (PE)</cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell>PBC Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>H 24</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (PE)</cell><cell>Phys. act.</cell><cell>Attitude Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H 25</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (PE)</cell><cell>Phys. act.</cell><cell>Sub. norm. Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H 26</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (PE)</cell><cell>Phys. act.</cell><cell>PBC Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H 27</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (PE)</cell><cell>Phys. act.</cell><cell>PBC Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>H 28</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell>Attitude</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>H 29</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell>Sub. norm.</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>H 30</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell>PBC</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>H 31</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Phys. act.</cell><cell>Intention Attitude</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>H 32</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Phys. act.</cell><cell>Intention Sub. norm.</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>H 33</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Phys. act.</cell><cell>Intention PBC</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">Note. PAS = Perceived autonomy support; Aut. mot. = Autonomous motivation; PE = Physical education</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">context; LT = Leisure-time context; PBC = Perceived behavioral control; Sub. norm = Subjective norm;</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">Phys. act = Self-reported leisure-time physical activity participation; Past. Beh. = Past leisure-time physical</cell></row><row><cell>activity behavior.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Method</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Participants</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>included the .95 cut-off value. This index penalizes models of high complexity, indicating a relative lack of parsimony in the model. Parameter estimates and 95% credibility intervals for the analysis with non-informative priors (Model 1) and the analysis including informative priors for key model relationships (Model 2) are presented in Table2 and Fig2.Note. †Parameters with informative priors. Model 1 = Bayesian path model with non-informative priors; Model 2 = Bayesian path model including informative priors; H = Hypothesis; β = Parameter estimate; 95% CrI = 95% credibility interval of path coefficient; %diff = Percent difference in 95% credibility interval of path coefficients of path analysis including informative priors for specified model relationships compared to analysis using non-informative priors (negative numbers indicate a narrowing of credibility intervals when</figDesc><table><row><cell>H H 32 Aut. mot. Independent variable (LT)</cell><cell cols="2">Dependent variable Phys. act. Sub. norm. Mediator(s) Intention</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>Model 1 -0.001 0.001</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>Model 2 -0.001 0.001 0.00 %diff</cell></row><row><cell>(LT) H 33 Aut. mot.</cell><cell cols="2">Intention Phys. act. PBC</cell><cell>β 0.000</cell><cell>95% CrI LL UL -0.005 0.005</cell><cell>β 0.000</cell><cell>95% CrI LL UL -0.005 0.005 0.00</cell></row><row><cell>Direct effects</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H 1 PAS</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (PE) †</cell><cell>-</cell><cell cols="2">2.683 *** 1.850 3.457</cell><cell cols="2">1.520 *** 1.176 1.874 -56.57</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">Table 2 H 2 Aut. mot. (PE) Parameter Estimates (β) with 95% Credibility Intervals for Hypothesized Effects from the Bayesian Path Aut. mot. -0.683 *** 0.516 0.887 0.609 *** 0.476 0.772 -20.22 (LT) † Analyses of the Extended Trans-Contextual Model for Leisure-time Physical Activity H 3 PAS Aut. mot. (LT) † -0.190 ** 0.034 0.378 0.363 *** 0.166 0.626 33.72</cell></row><row><cell>H 4 Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Attitude †</cell><cell>-</cell><cell cols="2">0.432 *** 0.342 0.521</cell><cell cols="2">0.434 *** 0.346 0.523 -1.12</cell></row><row><cell>H 5 Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Sub. norm †</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.163 *</cell><cell>0.007 0.320</cell><cell>0.166 *</cell><cell>0.010 0.320 -0.96</cell></row><row><cell>H 6 Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>PBC †</cell><cell>-</cell><cell cols="2">0.220 *** 0.119 0.321</cell><cell cols="2">0.222 *** 0.121 0.323 0.00</cell></row><row><cell>H 7 Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Intention †</cell><cell>-</cell><cell cols="2">0.411 *** 0.305 0.517</cell><cell cols="2">0.403 *** 0.298 0.507 -1.42</cell></row><row><cell>H 8 Attitude</cell><cell>Intention †</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.165 **</cell><cell>0.058 0.274</cell><cell cols="2">0.182 *** 0.076 0.288 -1.85</cell></row><row><cell>H 9 Sub. norm</cell><cell>Intention †</cell><cell>-</cell><cell cols="2">0.118 *** 0.058 0.178</cell><cell cols="2">0.118 *** 0.059 0.178 -0.83</cell></row><row><cell>H PBC</cell><cell>Intention †</cell><cell>-</cell><cell cols="2">0.325 *** 0.228 0.422</cell><cell cols="2">0.323 *** 0.227 0.420 -0.52</cell></row><row><cell>H Habit</cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.057</cell><cell>-0.029 0.143</cell><cell>0.058</cell><cell>-0.028 0.143 -0.58</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">H Self-control Intention</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.216 *</cell><cell>0.032 0.400</cell><cell>0.215 *</cell><cell>0.031 0.399 0.00</cell></row><row><cell>H Intention</cell><cell>Phys. act. †</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-0.001</cell><cell>-0.062 0.060</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>-0.061 0.061 0.00</cell></row><row><cell>H Attitude</cell><cell>Phys. act. †</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.092 **</cell><cell>0.033 0.151</cell><cell>0.093 **</cell><cell>0.034 0.152 0.00</cell></row><row><cell>H PBC</cell><cell>Phys. act. †</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-0.030</cell><cell>-0.086 0.026</cell><cell>-0.029</cell><cell>-0.085 0.026 -0.89</cell></row><row><cell>H Habit</cell><cell>Phys. act. †</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-0.005</cell><cell>-0.051 0.041</cell><cell>-0.004</cell><cell>-0.050 0.042 0.00</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">H Self-control Phys. act. †</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.104 *</cell><cell>0.002 0.207</cell><cell>0.107 *</cell><cell>0.007 0.208 -1.95</cell></row><row><cell>H Aut. mot.</cell><cell>Phys. act.</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-0.017</cell><cell>-0.079 0.045</cell><cell>-0.019</cell><cell>-0.081 0.043 0.00</cell></row><row><cell>(LT)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H Past beh. (LT)</cell><cell>Phys. act.</cell><cell>-</cell><cell cols="2">0.676 *** 0.521 0.829</cell><cell cols="2">0.673 *** 0.518 0.829 0.97</cell></row><row><cell>Indirect effects</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H PAS</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (PE)</cell><cell cols="2">1.827 *** 1.113 2.733</cell><cell cols="2">0.922 *** 0.625 1.324 -56.85</cell></row><row><cell>H Aut. mot. (PE)</cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell cols="2">0.048 ** 0.016 0.090</cell><cell cols="2">0.047 *** 0.019 0.084 -12.16</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Attitude</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H Aut. mot. (PE)</cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>0.012 *</cell><cell>0.000 0.031</cell><cell>0.011 *</cell><cell>0.001 0.027 -16.13</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Sub. norm.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H Aut. mot. (PE)</cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell>Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell cols="2">0.048 *** 0.022 0.085</cell><cell cols="2">0.043 *** 0.021 0.074 -15.87</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>PBC</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H Aut. mot.</cell><cell cols="2">Phys. act. Aut. mot.</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>-0.003 0.003</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>-0.003 0.003 0.00</cell></row><row><cell>(PE)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(LT)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Attitude</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H Aut. mot.</cell><cell cols="2">Phys. act. Aut. mot.</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>-0.001 0.001</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>-0.001 0.001 0.00</cell></row><row><cell>(PE)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(LT)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Sub. norm.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H Aut. mot.</cell><cell cols="2">Phys. act. Aut. mot.</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>-0.003 0.003</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>-0.003 0.003 0.00</cell></row><row><cell>(PE)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(LT)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>PBC</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H Aut. mot.</cell><cell cols="2">Phys. act. Aut. mot.</cell><cell>-0.004</cell><cell>-0.015 0.004</cell><cell>-0.004</cell><cell>-0.013 0.004 -10.53</cell></row><row><cell>(PE)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(LT)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>PBC</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell>Attitude</cell><cell cols="2">0.071 ** 0.024 0.123</cell><cell cols="2">0.078 *** 0.032 0.131 0.00</cell></row><row><cell>H Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell cols="2">Sub. norm. 0.018 *</cell><cell>0.001 0.043</cell><cell>0.019 *</cell><cell>0.001 0.044 2.38</cell></row><row><cell>H Aut. mot. (LT)</cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell>PBC</cell><cell cols="2">0.070 *** 0.035 0.114</cell><cell cols="2">0.071 *** 0.036 0.114 -1.27</cell></row><row><cell>H Aut. mot.</cell><cell cols="2">Phys. act. Attitude</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>-0.005 0.005</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>-0.005 0.005 0.00</cell></row><row><cell>(LT)</cell><cell></cell><cell>Intention</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><p>2 95% CI = [-25.520, 58.347]; PPP = 0.224; CFI = 0.987, 90% CI = [0.968, 1.000]; TLI = .953, 90% CI [0.881, 1.000], RMSEA = 0.048, 90% CI [.000, .076]) and informative priors for key model relationships (Bayesian posterior predictive χ 2 95% CI = [-17.857, 67.360]; prior PPP = 0.389; CFI = 0.982, 90% CI = [0.961, 0.999]; TLI = .918, 90% CI [0.825, 0.996], RMSEA = 0.064, 90% CI [.013, .093]) exhibited</p>adequate goodness-of-t with the data, although it should be noted that the 90% con dence intervals for the TLI were wider than desirable and</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>.034, 0.152], p = .001), trait self-control (H 17 ; β = .107, 95% CI [0.007, 0.208], p = .018), and past physical activity participation (H 19 ; β = .673, 95% CI [0.518, 0.829], p &lt; .001) on leisure-time physical activity participation at follow-up, while effects of intention (H 13 ), perceived behavioral control (H 15 ), habit (H 16 ), and autonomous motivation in leisure time (H 18 ) were no different from zero. All effects were small-to-medium in size.Focusing on the indirect effects, we found non-zero effects of perceived autonomy support on autonomous motivation in leisure time mediated by autonomous motivation in PE (H 20 ; β = .922, 95% CI [0.625, 1.324], p &lt; .001). There were also non-</figDesc><table><row><cell>zero effects of autonomous motivation in PE on intentions mediated by autonomous motivation in leisure time and attitude</cell></row><row><cell>(H 21 ; β = .047, 95% CI [0.019, 0.084], p &lt; .001), subjective norms (H 22 ; β = .011, 95% CI [0.001, 0.027], p = .019), and perceived</cell></row><row><cell>behavioral control (H 23 ; β = .043, 95% CI [0.021, 0.074], p &lt; .001). Similarly, there were also non-zero indirect effects of</cell></row><row><cell>autonomous motivation in leisure time on intentions mediated by attitude (H 28 ; β = .078, 95% CI [0.032, 0.131], p &lt; .001),</cell></row><row><cell>subjective norms (H 29 ; β = .019, 95% CI [0.001, 0.044], p = .019), and perceived behavioral control (H 30 ; β = .071, 95% CI</cell></row><row><cell>[0.036, 0.114], p &lt; .001). However, indirect effects of autonomous motivation in the PE (H 24 -H 27 ) and leisure-time (H 31 -H 33 )</cell></row><row><cell>contexts through the social cognition constructs on leisure-time physical activity participation were no different from zero</cell></row><row><cell>because the intention-behavior relationship was also no different from zero. Finally, effects of the intervention on leisure-</cell></row><row><cell>time physical activity participation, and effects of age on model constructs, were no different from zero. However, we found</cell></row><row><cell>non-zero effects of gender on autonomous motivation in PE (β = -.462, 95% CI [-0.795, -0.138], p = .002), with girls</cell></row><row><cell>experiencing higher levels than boys, and leisure time (β = .243, 95% CI [0.018, 0.463], p = .017), and attitudes (β = .210, 95%</cell></row><row><cell>CI [0.017, 0.404], p = .016).</cell></row><row><cell>2 ; β = .609, 95% CI [0.476, 0.772], p &lt; .001), and perceived autonomy</cell></row><row><cell>support in PE also had a non-zero effect on autonomous motivation in leisure time (H 3 ; β = 0.363, 95% CI [0.166, 0.626], p &lt;</cell></row><row><cell>.001). We also found non-zero effects of autonomous motivation in leisure time on attitudes (H 4 ; β = .434, 95% CI [0.346,</cell></row><row><cell>0.523], p &lt; .001), subjective norms (H 5 ; β = .166, 95% CI [0.010, 0.320], p = .018), and perceived behavioral control (H 6 ; β =</cell></row></table><note><p>.222, 95% CI [0.121, 0.323], p &lt; .001). We also found non-zero effects of attitudes (H 8 ; β = .182, 95% CI [0.076, 0.288, p &lt; .001), subjective norms (H 9 ; β = .118, 95% CI [0.059, 0.178], p &lt; .001), and perceived behavioral control (H 10 ; β = .323, 95% CI [0.227, 0.420], p &lt; .001) on intentions. Moreover, there were non-zero effects of autonomous motivation in leisure time (H 7 ; β = .403, 95% CI [0.298, 0.507], p &lt; .001) and trait self-control (H 12 ; β = .215, 95% CI [0.031, 0.399], p &lt; .001) on intentions, but the effect of habit on intention (H 11 ) was no different from zero. We found non-zero effects of attitude (H 14 ; β = .093, 95% CI [0</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We thank <rs type="person">Pauliina Hietanen</rs>, <rs type="person">Noora Kilpeläinen</rs>, <rs type="person">Sampsa Löppönen</rs>, <rs type="person">Stina Seppänen</rs>, and <rs type="person">Miika Tuominen</rs> for their assistance with data collection. We are grateful to <rs type="person">Jari Villberg</rs> for his assistance with the data analysis.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><head>Funding</head><p>This project was funded by grant from the <rs type="funder">Finnish Ministry of Education and Culture</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">OKM/62/626/2016</rs>) and a <rs type="funder">Finland Distinguished Professor (FiDiPro)</rs> award from <rs type="funder">Business Finland</rs> (grant no. <rs type="grantNumber">1801/31/2105</rs>).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_kgQDKCk">
					<idno type="grant-number">OKM/62/626/2016</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_ZH3ZEGa">
					<idno type="grant-number">1801/31/2105</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Availability of data and materials</head><p>Data le, analysis syntax, and output for the present study are available online: <ref type="url" target="https://osf.io/z8axj">https://osf.io/z8axj</ref>.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>current societal context in which the physical environment may not support engagement in physical activity and offers various competing, non-active alternatives (e.g., video games). However, current ndings highlight the potential of including additional constructs representing non-conscious processes. However, these data should not be considered unequivocal evidence to support rejection of the model as unmeasured moderator variables may have affected model effects. Further replication of the extended trans-contextual model predictions in larger samples is warranted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Declarations Ethics approval and consent to participate</head><p>The study protocol was approved by the research ethics committee of the University of Jyväskylä (ref no. 2017/12/13).</p><p>Written informed consent was obtained from participating students and their parents prior to data collection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Consent for publication</head><p>All participants provided consent for their deidenti ed data to be used in research reports and publications arising from this study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Competing interests</head><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary Files</head><p>This is a list of supplementary les associated with this preprint. Click to download.</p><p>STROBEchecklistrevised.doc Supplementalmaterial.docx</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Physical activity and sedentary lifestyle towards teenagers&apos; overweight/obesity status</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Kurdaningsih</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sudargo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lusmilasari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Comm Med Pub Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="630" to="635" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Level of physical activity among children and adolescents in Europe: A review of physical activity assessed objectively by accelerometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Guinhouya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Samouda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>De Beaufort</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pub Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="301" to="311" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Raising an active and healthy generation: A comprehensive public health initiative</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Pate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dowda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exerc Sport Sci Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increasing physical activity levels in primary school physical education: The SHARP Principles Model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Powell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wood Eld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nevill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prev Med Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The processes by which perceived autonomy support in physical education promotes leisure-time physical activity intentions and behavior: A trans-contextual model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nld</forename><surname>Chatzisarantis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Culverhouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sjh</forename><surname>Biddle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Educ Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="784" to="795" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Physical education, school physical activity, school sports and academic performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Trudeau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Shephard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vallerand RJ. Towards a hierarchical model of intrinsic and extrinsic motivation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Deci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv Exp Soc Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="360" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985. 1997</date>
			<publisher>Plenum Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Intrinsic motivation and self-determination in human behavior</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The theory of planned behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ajzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organ Behav Hum Decis Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="211" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceived autonomy support, behavioural regulations in physical education and physical activity intention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bsc</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ckj</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol Sport Exerc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reciprocal relations between autonomous motivation from self-determination theory and social cognition constructs from the theory of planned behavior: A cross-lagged panel design in sport injury prevention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dkc</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Asy</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol Sport Exerc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101660</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thøgersen-Ntoumani C. The effects of social identity and perceived autonomy support on health behaviour within the Theory of Planned Behaviour</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nld</forename><surname>Chatzisarantis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ckj</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using the construct of perceived autonomy support to understand social in uence within the theory of planned behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nld</forename><surname>Chatzisarantis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Brickell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol Sport Exerc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Broadening the trans-contextual model of motivation: A study with Spanish adolescents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>González-Cutre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Á</forename><surname>Sicilia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Beas-Jiménez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scand J Sci Med Sport</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="306" to="e319" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Urban adolescents&apos; exercise intentions and behaviors: An exploratory study of a transcontextual model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mccaughtry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contemp Educ Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="841" to="858" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The trans-contextual model of autonomous motivation in education: Conceptual and empirical issues and meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nld</forename><surname>Chatzisarantis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rev Educ Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="360" to="407" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Re ective and impulsive determinants of social behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Strack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Deutsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pers Soc Psychol Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="220" to="247" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting sugar consumption: Application of an integrated dualprocess, dual-phase model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Trost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Keech</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dkc</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appetite</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="156" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Re ections on past behavior: A self-report index of habit strength</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Verplanken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Orbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Appl Soc Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1313" to="1330" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">the transtheoretical model of change, and exercise: A neo-socioanalytic integration of trait and social-cognitive frameworks in the prediction of behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bogg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Conscientiousness</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="775" to="802" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rede ning habits and linking habits with other implicit processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol Sport Exerc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101606</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Habit and intention in everyday life: The multiple processes by which past behavior predicts future behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ouellette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Habit in personality and social psychology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pers Soc Psychol Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="403" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High self-control predicts good adjustment, less pathology, better grades, and interpersonal success</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Tangney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Baumeister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Boone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="324" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Taking stock of self-control: A meta-analysis of how trait self-control relates to a wide range of behaviors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dtd</forename><surname>De Ridder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lensvelt-Mulders</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Finkenauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stok</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Baumeister</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pers Soc Psychol Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trait self-control, social cognition constructs, and intentions: Correlational evidence for mediation and moderation effects in diverse health behaviors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hankonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E-M</forename><surname>Kangro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lintunen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pagaduan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Polet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl Psychol Health Well Being</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="407" to="437" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Desire or reason: Predicting health behaviors from affective and cognitive attitudes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lawton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Conner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mceachan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of affective attitudes and anticipated affective reactions in predicting health behaviors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Conner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mceachan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O'</forename><surname>Hara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lawton</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="642" to="652" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systematic review and meta-analysis of applications of the self-report habit index to nutrition and physical activity behaviours</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gardner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G-J</forename><surname>De Bruijn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lally</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Behav Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="174" to="187" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The reasoned action approach applied to health behavior: Role of past behavior and test of some key moderators using meta-analytic structural equation modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Polet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lintunen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soc Sci Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">213</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Using physical education to promote out-of school physical activity in lower secondary school students -A randomized controlled trial protocol</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Polet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hassandra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lintunen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Laukkanen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hankonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hirvensalo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>BMC Pub Health</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">157</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The perceived autonomy support scale for exercise settings (PASSES): Development, validity, and cross-cultural invariance in young people</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nld</forename><surname>Chatzisarantis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Hein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pihu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Soós</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Karsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol Sport Exerc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="632" to="653" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceived locus of causality and internalization: Examining reasons for acting in two domains</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Connell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pers Soc Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="749" to="761" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Constructing a TPB questionnaire: Conceptual and methodological considerations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ajzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://people.umass.edu/~aizen/pdf/tpb.measurement.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-09-01">2002 updated September 1, 2002</date>
			<pubPlace>Amherst, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Massachusetts</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Self-discipline scale from the NEO-PI-R</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ipip</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://ipip.ori.org/newNEOKey.htm#Self-Discipline" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">International physical activity questionnaire: 12-country reliability and validity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Craig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sjostrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bauman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Booth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ainsworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Sci Sports Exerc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1381" to="1395" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The IPIP-HEXACO scales: An alternative, public-domain measure of the personality constructs in the HEXACO model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ashton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Goldberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>Pers Individ Diff</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1515" to="1526" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<ptr target="http://www.ipaq.ki.se/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The IPAQ group. International Physical Activity Questionnaire</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian structural equation modeling: A more exible representation of substantive theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Muthén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Asparouhov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="335" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inference from iterative simulation using multiple sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Rubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="511" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Advances in Bayesian model t evaluation for structural equation models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Asparouhov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Muthén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.statmodel.com/download/BayesFit.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian mediation analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mackinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="301" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Power analysis and determination of sample size for covariance structure modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Maccallum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Browne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sugawara</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psych Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="130" to="149" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Practical statistical power analysis using Webpower and R</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K-H</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>ISDSA Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Granger, IN</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting fruit and vegetable consumption in long-haul heavy goods vehicle drivers: Application of a multi-theory, dual-phase model and the contribution of past behaviour</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Morrissey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appetite</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="326" to="336" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrating the theory of planned behaviour and self-determination theory in health behaviour: A meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nld</forename><surname>Chatzisarantis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Health Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="302" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Testing a model of physical activity among mothers and fathers of young children: Integrating self-determined motivation, planning, and theory of planned behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Sport Exerc Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="124" to="145" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moderation of cognition-intention and cognition-behaviour relations: A meta-analysis of properties of variables from the theory of planned behaviour</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cooke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sheeran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Soc Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="186" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-control and health-related behavior: The role of implicit self-control, trait self-control, and lay beliefs in self-control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gucciardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Turrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Health Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="764" to="786" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changing behavior using ecological models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Salmon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hesketh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Arundell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Downing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sjh</forename><surname>Biddle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hankonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lintunen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The handbook of behavior change</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="250" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adolescent sugar-sweetened beverage consumption: An extended health action process approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mc-Y</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appetite</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104332</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The in uences of continuation intentions on the execution of social behaviour within the theory of planned behaviour</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nld</forename><surname>Chatzisarantis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Phoenix</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Soc Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="551" to="583" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The subjective experience of habit captured by selfreport indexes may lead to inaccuracies in the measurement of habitual action</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rebar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mullan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Lipp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nld</forename><surname>Chatzisarantis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Psychol Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="296" to="302" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reasoned and implicit processes in heavy episodic drinking: An integrated dual process model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Gibbs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Keech</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Health Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="209" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Older adults&apos; physical activity: The integration of autonomous motivation and theory of planned behaviour constructs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Arnautovska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fleig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>'callaghan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aust Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="54" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of socio-structural variables in the theory of planned behavior: A mediation model in multiple samples and behaviors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antecedents of children&apos;s physical activity intentions and behaviour: Predictive validity and longitudinal effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nld</forename><surname>Chatzisarantis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sjh</forename><surname>Biddle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Orbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="391" to="407" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Testing an integrated model of the theory of planned behaviour and self-determination theory for different energy-balance related behaviours and intervention intensities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Jacobs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Streukens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>Bourdeaudhuij</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Claes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Health Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hagger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hankonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lintunen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The handbook of behavior change</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
