<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Determination of The Direct and Indirect Effects of Feed Characteristics on the Metabolizable Energy of Natural Pasture Hay</title>
				<funder ref="#_PHwyTRf">
					<orgName type="full">Turkish Ministry of Agriculture and Forestry</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Cem</forename><surname>Tirink</surname></persName>
							<email>cem.tirink@gmail.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Samanı</forename><surname>Mera</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yem</forename><surname>İçin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Metabolize</forename><forename type="middle">Edilebilir</forename><surname>Özelliklerinin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Üzerine</forename><surname>Enerjisi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Analizi</forename><forename type="middle">Cem</forename><surname>Path</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Tirink</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zehra</forename><surname>Sariçiçek</surname></persName>
							<email>zehra.saricicek@ankara.edu.tr</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hasan</forename><surname>Önder</surname></persName>
							<email>honder@omu.edu.tr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Ankara Üniversitesi Ziraat Fakültesi Zootekni Bölümü</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ankara</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Ondokuz Mayıs Üniversitesi Ziraat Fakültesi Zootekni Bölümü</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Samsun</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anadolu</forename><surname>Tarım</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bilimleri</forename><surname>Dergisi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Araştırma Makalesi / Research Article</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Geliş Tarihi</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Iğdır Üniversitesi Ziraat Fakültesi Zootekni Bölümü</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Iğdır</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Determination of The Direct and Indirect Effects of Feed Characteristics on the Metabolizable Energy of Natural Pasture Hay</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">1308-8769</idno>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.7161/omuanajas.980656</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 9 Ağustos / August 2021 Kabul Tarihi / Accepted: 17 Aralık / December 2021</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T19:12+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Correlation</term>
					<term>Path Analysis</term>
					<term>Path Coefficient</term>
					<term>Direct Effects</term>
					<term>İndirect Effect Korelasyon</term>
					<term>Path Analizi</term>
					<term>Path Katsayısı</term>
					<term>Doğrudan Etki</term>
					<term>Dolaylı Etki</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The aim of this study is to examine the direct, indirect and total effects of nutrient content properties on metabolizable energy contents of natural pasture feeds using path analysis. For this aim, the relationship between metabolizable energy and eight feed nutrient characteristics such as acid detergent lignin (ADL), acid detergent fiber (ADF), neutral detergent fiber (NDF), crude fiber, crude protein, ether extract, ash, and the nitrogen-free extract (NFE) was used for 48 grassland plants samples obtained from natural pastures of Ankara. According to the results of path analysis, the most significant effects on metabolizable energy were reported in crude fiber, acid detergent lignin, crude protein, ash, and nitrogen-free extract. In addition, both acid detergent lignin and neutral detergent fiber had a negative and significant impact on metabolizable energy. As a result, acid detergent lignin and neutral detergent fiber can be presented as prediction criteria to predict metabolizable energy.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The general aim of animal nutrition is to provide nutrients that will increase the productivity of the livestocks. Feed intake is one of the most important factors that will increase the productivity of animals. Variation in feed quality due to a variety of factors such as genetic structure of feed material, season, differences in storage conditions, and sampling errors of feed material used can have a significant impact.. As a result of the evaluation of all these factors, it is difficult to find the standard feeding values of feeds. There are many factors affecting the quality of feed that this will increase the quality of livestock. These factors, such as acid detergent lignin (ADL), acid detergent fiber (ADF), neutral detergent fiber (NDF), crude fiber (CF), crude protein (CP), ether extract (EE), ash (A) and nitrogenfree extract (NFE), metabolizable energy (ME) can affect the productivity and the quality of food from animal origins.</p><p>There is a close relationship between the nutrient content of feeds and energy. ADF and NDF affect the digestibility of feeds. Thus, they also affects energy values. ADF and NDF can be determined in a short amount of time. In addition, relative feed value (RFV) can be calculated by ADF and NDF which help to determine the feed quality of roughages as given below <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Rohweder et al. 1978)</ref>.</p><p>Dry matter intake (DMI)=(LiveWeight=LW%)=120/(NDF%)</p><p>(1)</p><p>Dry matter digestibility (DMD)(%)=88.9-(0.779×ADF%) (2)</p><p>Relative Feed Value (RFV)=(DMD×DMI)/1.29</p><p>In most cases, those with higher potential for these factors are chosen as feed materials. Therefore, it is necessary to determine the factors affecting these features, which play a crucial role in the selection, and the effect levels of these factors.</p><p>In statistical models with two or more variables, cause-effect relationships are generally emphasized, and if there is a functional relationship between variables, the degree and functional form of the relationship are tried to be determined. To determine these effects of factors, many statistical methods such as regression and correlation analysis can be used <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Onder and Abaci, 2015)</ref>. The common method to determine these relationships is correlation analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Gul et al., 2019)</ref>. It is not always possible to explain the relationships between the factors affecting the feature under consideration with a simple correlation coefficient. Because the relationship between two variables can be affected by a third variable or more variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Gul et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Tahtali et al., 2011)</ref>. These effects, which are defined as direct and indirect effects, need to be determined. Path analysis was used to determine the direct and indirect effects between variables more accurately <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Alpar, 2013)</ref>. Path analysis differs from other multivariate methods in that it considers not only direct but also indirect effects in order to determine the effects and artificial effects <ref type="bibr">(Isci Guneri et al., 2016)</ref>.</p><p>When the literature is examined, no other study has been found that examines the direct and indirect effects on the relationships between feed nutrient contents and metabolizable energy. For this reason, the aim of this study was to determine direct and indirect effects of the feed nutrient content characteristics such as acid detergent lignin, acid detergent fiber, neutral detergent fiber, crude fiber, crude protein, ether extract, ash, and nitrogen-free extract, and metabolizable energy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">MATERIAL AND METHODS</head><p>The feed material used in the study consists of natural pasture feeds taken from various parts of Ankara province in Turkey <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Saricicek, 2020)</ref>. Plant samples from natural meadows were taken every 15 days in May, June, July and August and analyzed. Plant nutrient analysis (CP, ash, EE, CF) were performed according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">AOAC (1990)</ref>.</p><p>Metabolic energy value was determined for ruminants according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Menke et al. (1979)</ref> using the following formula. ME,MJ / kgDM = 2.20 + 0.136GP + 0.057CP + 0.002859EE 2 (4)</p><p>where; GP: 24 h net gas production (ml/200mg DM), CP: Crude protein (%), EE: Ether extract (%).</p><p>NEL value was determined using the formula MJ / kgDM = 0.101GP + 0.051CP + 0.11EE for ruminants, according to <ref type="bibr">Menke and Steingass (1988)</ref>. In addition, ADF, NDF and ADL analysis were made according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Van Soest et al. (1991)</ref> by using Ankom device.</p><p>Determining the relationship between metabolic energy and other nutrient contents is important for the preparation of the correct ration formulation. Multivariate statistical methods can be used to determine this relationship. There are many multivariate statistical tecniques such as regression analysis, correlation analysis. Investigating the relationship and the degree of this relationship is within the scope of correlation analysis. The correlation coefficient obtained, one of the variables being the result and the other being the explanatory variable, appears as a measure that also expresses the level of influence of these variables on each other. However, even in this case, it is not possible to determine the relationship between the two variables completely. However, there are also nonlinear relationships apart from linear relationships between variables. The process of analysis and interpretation of nonlinear relationships is difficult. Therefore, a path analysis technique, in which all relationships are considered linear, is proposed according to this assumption <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Kayali, 2013)</ref>.</p><p>The path coefficient, whose formula is given below where Y and X used as a dependent variable and independent variable respectively, was proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Wright, 1921)</ref>. Path analysis is a multivariate technique that enables to estimate direct and indirect effects between explanatory and response variables in the model <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Mitchell, 1992)</ref>. There are two main components of path analysis, which are namely the path coefficients representing the mathematical part and the path diagram representing the visual part <ref type="bibr">(Isci Guneri et al., 2016)</ref>. The standardized regression coefficient found by Wright, which is also a path coefficient, was used to calculate the direct and indirect effects of the correlation coefficient.</p><p>(5)</p><p>The path coefficient including direct and indirect effects can be shown with the path diagram. The important and hardest part of path analysis is to logically construct a path diagram. Even if there is no need for a path diagram in practical studies, it would be useful to find direct and indirect effects, from the type of correlation, between explanatory and response variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Pedhazur, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr">Isci Guneri et al., 2016)</ref>. If there is a path coefficient greater than 1 in the path diagram, this situation indicates that there is a balancing mechanism (negative effect) in the system. Path coefficients greater than 1 are not unilaterally significant due to this negative effect <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Li, 1975;</ref><ref type="bibr">Isci Guneri et al., 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> shows that a path diagram to reveal direct and indirect effects between some feed characteristics and metabolizable energy content. In Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>, direct and indirect effects are shown as a one-way arrow and two-way arrow, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1. Path diagram of metabolizable energy and other feed nutrient content characteristics</head><p>The path equations for the path diagram in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> showing the relationship between ME and feed properties are as follows.</p><p>All statistical analysis were performed by using R software (R Core Team, 2020). For descriptive statistics "psych" package were used <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Revelle 2020)</ref>. The package for path analysis was used "lavaan" and the related packages for drawing path diagrams, "semPlot" and "lavaanPlot" were used <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Rosseel, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Epskamp, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Lishinski, 2018)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head><p>Shapiro-Wilk normality test was used to test of normality of the variables. All the variables were determined to be normally distributed (p&gt;0.05). Descriptive statistics for data set were given in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 1. Descriptive statistics of the data</head><p>Pearson correlation coefficients and significance level of correlation coefficients between whole variables are given in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 2. Pearson correlation coefficient between feed characteristics and metabolizable energy of feed nutrient contents</head><p>Table <ref type="table">2</ref> shows that the correlation coefficients between all variables, with the exception of ether extract, and between crude protein and ether extract, NFE and ether extract, metabolizable energy and ether extract, ash and ADF, were statistically significant (p&lt;0.05). Among the significance correlations, the coefficients between crude fiber and ADF (r= 0.939**) were determined to be the highest, whereas the coefficients between ash and NDF (r= 0.291*)were found to be the lowest.</p><p>Direct, indirect and total effects calculated between each explanatory variable and ME are shown in Table <ref type="table">3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 3. Direct and indirect effect of the feed nutrient contents characteristics on metabolizable energy</head><p>According to Table <ref type="table">3</ref>, when the direct effects are examined, it is seen that all variables except for ether extract have negative effects. Ether extract has a positive direct effect on metabolizable energy with a value of 0.077 and the p-value of this effect is 0.181. NFE has a negative direct effect on metabolizable energy with a value of -1.533.</p><p>In the present study, path analysis was used to determine the direct and indirect effects for the feed nutrient contents characteristics such as ADL, ADF, NDF, CF, CP, EE, A and NFE and ME. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Li (1975)</ref> and Isci Guneri et al. ( <ref type="formula">2016</ref>), path coefficients greater than 1 are not unilaterally significant due to the negative effects of the mechanism. Other negative direct effects between feed characteristics and metabolizable energy are ADF, NDF, ADL, crude protein and ash with the values of -0.806, -0.365, -0.020, -0.328, -0.923, respectively. Of these negative direct effects, only ADF and NDF were found to be statistically significant (p&lt;0.05). There is no study about the naturel pasture hay within the scope of path analysis. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Sayan et al. (2004)</ref> reported the correlations between ME and in vitro characteristics such as A, CP, EE, CF, NFE, ADF and NDF. The highest and the most significant correlations are between EE(0.783), CF(-0.851), ADF (-0.892) and NDF (-0.760), respectively. However, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Sayan et al. (2004)</ref> emphasized that according to <ref type="bibr">Menke and Steingass (1988)</ref>, it would be more appropriate to consider the amount of NDF or ADF compared to EE, CF, A in meeting the roughage fiber needs of ruminants, therefore, ADF and NDF are more important parameters. Furthermore, ADF and NDF affect the digestibility of feeds. Thus, it also affects energy values. ADF and NDF can be determined in a short time. In addition, in the present study, there is a significant indirect effect on metabolizable energy for ether extract, crude fiber, ADL, crude protein, ash and NFE (p&lt;0.05). <ref type="bibr">Canbolat and Kahraman (2009)</ref> compared the in vitro gas production, metabolizable energy (ME), organic matter digestibility (OMD), relative feed values (RFV) for the legume forages and they reported the relationship between ME and CP (0.756), EE (0.353), ADF (-0.832), NDF (-0.795) within the scope of correlation analysis, respectively. Of these relationships, only EE was found to be statistically insignificant (p&lt;0.01).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">CONCLUSION</head><p>In vivo digestion trials are expensive and require a long time to determine the metabolizable energy (ME) value in feed. However, it is very important that the parameters to be used in determining the ME values of feed materials such as roughages and industrial residues are reliable and that they are obtained economically and practically. For this reason, researchers have conducted many studies on which parameters are more important in predicting ME.</p><p>According to the results, ADF and NDF have the highest effect on metabolizable energy in the feed evaluation process. In addition to the direct effects of ADF and NDF on metabolizable energy, other feed properties have indirect effects through ether extract, crude fiber, ADL, crude protein, ash and NFE. Especially in the literature, NDF or ADF amounts instead of crude protein, ether extract, crude fiber are shown as reliable parameters to estimate metabolizable energy. Therefore, researchers interested in animal nutrition should take into account that ADF and NDF are important selection criteria in their work to predict metabolizable energy. The RFV method developed for quality control in roughage is used. The ADF and NDF contents of feeds are used to calculate the RFV value. RFV is currently an important guide in marketing and determining the quality of roughage. In this way, ADF and NDF, which are among the nutrient contents of the feed, support the results as important criteria as feed evaluation criteria.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="6,70.87,163.56,325.98,255.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="8,68.29,424.28,322.76,191.91" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>https://doi.org/10.7161/omuanajas.980656</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>Cem TIRINK, Zehra SARIÇİÇEK, Hasan ÖNDER https://doi.org/10.7161/omuanajas.980656</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>This work was supported by the <rs type="funder">Turkish Ministry of Agriculture and Forestry</rs> as a <rs type="grantNumber">TAGEM-16 / ARGE-13</rs> project.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_PHwyTRf">
					<idno type="grant-number">TAGEM-16 / ARGE-13</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Alpar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Applied Multivariate Statistical Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Detay Anatolia Yayıncılık</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Sample Preparation (950.02) Official Methods of Analysis, Association of Official Analytical Chemists</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Aoac</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990. 1990</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="222" />
			<pubPlace>Washington DC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>15 th edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of in Vitro Gas Production, Organic Matter Digestibility, Relative Feed Value and Metabolizable Energy Contents of Some Legume Forages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Canbolat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Karaman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Agricultural Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="188" to="195" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">semPlot: Path Diagrams and Visual Analysis of Various SEM Packages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Epskamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=semPlot" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Output. R package version</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Path Analysis of the Relationship Between Weaning Weight and Some Morphological Traits in Awassi Lamb</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Keskin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Guzey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Behrem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Gunduz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Kahramanmaras Sutcu Imam University Journal Of Agriculture and Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">Suppl 2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="435" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Path analysis and determining the distribution of indirect effects via ANAJAS</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Statistics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Isci</forename><surname>Guneri</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Goktas</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kayali</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1181" to="1210" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012. 2016. 2022</date>
			<publisher>IBM Corp. Released</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Cilt</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Path analysis and a simulation study about the distribution of indirect effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Kayali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Mugla Sitki Kocman University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">MSc Thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Path Analysis a Primer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<publisher>The Boxwood Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Pacific Grove, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">lavaanPlot: Path Diagrams for Lavaan Models via DiagrammeR</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lishinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=lavaanPlot" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>R package version 0.5.1.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The estimation of the digestibility and metabolizable energy content of ruminant feeding stuffs from the gas production when they are incubated with rumen liquor in vitro</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Menke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Raab</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Salewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Steingass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Agricultural Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="222" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation of the Energetic Feed Value Obtained from Chemical Analysis and in vitro Gas Production Using Rumen Fluid</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Menke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Steingass</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Animal Research and Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Testing evolutionary and ecological hypotheses using path analysis and structural equation modelling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Functional Ecology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Path Analysis for Body Measurements on Body Weight of Saanen Kids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Onder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Abaci</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Faculty of Veterinary Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="354" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Kafkas University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Multiple Regression in Behavioral Research: Explanation and Prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pedhazur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<publisher>Harcourt Brace College Publishers</publisher>
			<pubPlace>FortWorth, TX</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">R: A language and environment for statistical computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Team</forename><surname>Core</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.R-project.org/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">R Foundation for Statistical Computing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Vienna, Austria</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Revelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=psychVersion=2.0.12" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<pubPlace>Evanston, Illinois, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Procedures for Personality and Psychological Research, Northwestern University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proposed hay grading standards based on laboratory analysis for evaluating quality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rohweder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Jorgensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Animal Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="747" to="759" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">lavaan: An R Package for Structural Equation Modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Rosseel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.jstatsoft.org/v48/i02/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Statistical Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determination of botanical composition, nutrient content, feed value and quality parameters in between May-August months of natural grasslands of Ankara province</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Saricicek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Black Sea Journal of Agriculture</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of the parameters using for determination of metabolizable energy value of the roughages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Sayan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ozkul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alcicek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Coskuntuna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Onenc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Polat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Agriculture Faculty of Ege University</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="175" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determination of Effective Factors for Milk Yield of Brown Swiss Cattle Using by Path Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tahtali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sahin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ulutas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sirin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Abaci</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Faculty of Veterinary Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="859" to="864" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Kafkas University</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Path analysis of honey yield components using different correlation coefficients in caucasian honey bee</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Topal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Emsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dodologlu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Animal and Veterinary Advances</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1440" to="1443" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Methods for dietary fiber, neutral detergent fiber, and nonstarch polysaccharides in relation to animal nutrition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Soest</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Dairy Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3583" to="3597" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation and causation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Agricultural Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="557" to="558" />
			<date type="published" when="1921">1921</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
