<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A minimalist computational model of slice hippocampal circuitry based on Neuronify™ for teaching neuroscience</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">CNPq -Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cientí co e Tecnológico</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">CAPES -Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior foundation. INNT -Instituto Nacional de Neurociência Translacional</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lucas</forename><surname>Longo</surname></persName>
							<email>lucas.longo@unifesp.br</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurology and Neurosurgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Escola Paulista de Medicina</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Universidade Federal de São Paulo</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>São Paulo</settlement>
									<country>Brazil;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">João</forename><forename type="middle">A F</forename><surname>Brogin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mechanical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">São Paulo State University (UNESP)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>São Paulo</settlement>
									<country>Brazil;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jean</forename><surname>Faber</surname></persName>
							<email>jean.faber@unifesp.br</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Universidade Federal de São Paulo</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>São Paulo</settlement>
									<country key="BR">Brazil</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A minimalist computational model of slice hippocampal circuitry based on Neuronify™ for teaching neuroscience</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.32388/4T2NIN</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-14T19:29+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The hippocampal (HP) formation is a vital component of the central nervous system in processing memory, learning, and spatial navigation. Existing methods are obsolete to address new emerging questions as our understanding of HP circuits and its connections advances. Hence, there is a need for new techniques with an accessible approach for visualizing and understanding the inner connections and circuitry. Research requires a quick update of textbooks and a better integration of new media to facilitate the teaching of these neural structures, which until recently, was an issue due to availability of limited resources. For example, understanding the dynamics of neural circuits' activities is a great challenge in the teaching of neuroscience, because by only using pictures, drawings, and diagrams, it is not possible to express the complete structural and functional effects that each circuit imparts. One solution to this challenge might be the use of computational models adapted to these diverse contexts. The construction of simple computational models can be an excellent alternative in teaching these complex dynamics since they reduce the use of animal models, amplify and simplify structural relationships, promote quick and easy visualization, and uncover possible functional and structural interventions. This interactivity is crucial for a better understanding of the causal relationships between nuclei and neural circuits. Conversely, it is important that computational models aimed at teaching are simple so that any student, regardless of their mathematical background, can understand and manipulate the structures and dynamics of interest. Further, software packages that do not require programming knowledge for its use are indispensable. However, generally this limitation also restricts the structural and dynamic representations possible for study. Here, we demonstrate the use of Neuronify™ software, which uses simple functional Qeios qeios.com</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>representations of neurons and circuits. We represent the most important pathways and connections of the HP formation by building a simpli ed model that shows the main known relations between the subregions [Cornus Ammonis (CA)1, CA2, CA3, and CA4] and afferent nucleus (subiculum and dentate gyrus).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>The eld of education in neuroscience (RAMIREZ, 2020) faces many speci c challenges that differ from other areas of science because of its particularities. Speci cally, the requirement of a special set of pedagogic strategies and materials, the limited range of tools available for investigation (e.g., electrophysiological recordings, behavioral index, biochemical markers), and the complex technical language of area of study <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(WILLINGHAM, 2009)</ref>. The resources required to teach the different aspects of the brain function are limiting due to various factors, e.g., books show a static view of the brain and fail to show the dynamics in a didactic way, and animal models demand technical skill and thorough dedication as they are dif cult to manipulate and need to be used responsibly. In comparison, computational models are an interesting alternative solution since they bypass many issues <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(JIRSA et al., 2014)</ref>, such as forcing students to learn by simple gures and euthanizing animals, thus supporting initiatives like the 3Rs (replace, reuse and re ne) <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(PRESCOTT and LIDSTER, 2017)</ref>. Computational models offer a fun, easy and interactive way of studying and understanding the complexity of neural circuits and physiological processes.</p><p>However, computational models present a series of limitations. The most common is that they generally require knowledge of programming logic <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(ROGALSKI and SAMURÇAY, 1990)</ref>. Additionally, since the mathematical descriptions can be too abstract, researchers investigating biological basis use it minimally.</p><p>A few software packages exist that propose simple biological representations with userfriendly interfaces, thus allowing anyone to manage and construct their own biological system <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(KIPARISSIDES et al., 2011)</ref>. Here, we use the free software Neuronify™ (NORTHCUTT, 2021), an intuitive platform with a user-friendly interface that does not require expertise in any programming language. Also, many other applications exist that allow the construction of different types of computational models of biological systems, which are not restricted to neuroscience, such as PhET™, a simulator for physics, chemistry and biology <ref type="bibr">(WIEMANet al., 2008)</ref>, "portal SESI educação" from Brazil, MERLOT Biology™, and Atomify™. These simulators have a simple interface and are used for education purposes.</p><p>Despite the simple biological representations and some functional limitations offered by Neuronify™, we were able to build the complex inner circuitry of hippocampal (HP) formation using only excitatory and inhibitory leaky integrate-and-re neurons, adjusting them in speci c patterns of connectivity to express their real dynamics. For instance, we represented the main pathways of the trisynaptic circuit <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(JEFFREY and MICHAEL, 2016)</ref> and highlighted its sub elds. By using the virtual sensors provided by the application, we could show the temporal patterns related to the action potential of speci c neurons of each HP sub eld.</p><p>Considering the HP formation neuroarchitecture <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(KEINATH et al., 2020)</ref>, this model preserved the disposition of semicircular-like complementary structures from dentate gyrus (DG), going through the sub elds of Cornu Ammonis (CA3, CA2 and CA1) to the subiculum (SUB), yielding a comprehensive view of the circuit connections <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(SHIMBO et al., 2021)</ref>. Additionally, we were able to construct a simpli ed qeios.com doi.org/10.32388/4T2NIN version of the whole HP circuitry by reducing and emphasizing its main nucleus and path connections. Since this circuitry reduction maintains the same physiological activity outputs, it can be an important educational approach to teach how the brain uses redundancies and 'motifs blocks' to process information <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(WOMELSDORF et al., 2014)</ref>.</p><p>In summary, we show how computational models might be useful for teaching neuroscience. We propose an easy way to understand brain networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(CLEMENT and LOVAT, 2012)</ref> through the construction of a HP network, its main features and connections, using Neuronify™. This work helps the study and understanding of the HP formation, making it easy to observe the response of its parts to stimuli in different conditions determined by the experimenter, simplifying and dynamizing the teaching-learning process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p>The computational model describes the main circuits of the hippocampus and its correlations considering its input-output information. By a motif-based approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(BRAGANZA et al., 2018)</ref> of subregions in HP formation, patterns of recursion, inhibition, and propagation of input signals were established, thus setting the connections between these microcircuits. The motif representation uses the minimum number of neurons (excitatory and inhibitory) and synapses, hence emphasizing its main structural connections and functional relationships. This representation makes the model description more intuitive, and morphologically accurate to a HP slice. We used the software Neuronify™ since it is user-friendly with simple features built speci cally for educational purposes <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(ELBEZ et al., 2018)</ref>. The software's interface is a simple "grab and drop" system, where the users only need to select the components, they want to display on the screen. In the simulator, glutamatergic and cholinergic neurons were labeled as excitatory, and GABAergic as inhibitory. Additionally, the mossy bers (MF), perforant path (PP) and Schaffer collaterals (SC) were plotted as neurons, and not axons. The information ow crossing these paths were maintained under the same environmental conditions. Therefore, by representing these bers as neurons, we were able to control the cell parameters needed to hold the concomitant ow of discharge.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>qeios.com</head><p>doi.org/10.32388/4T2NIN Furthermore, the sensors and current sources provided by the software allowed a simultaneous testing process, which made it possible to improve the model during its construction. These sensors offer vast possibilities for analyzing the model, by measuring the activity in any neuron or group of neurons when the input has a speci c chosen characteristic (Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>).</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>: General portrait of Neuronify™ main features. This assembly shows some of the most important components of the software: the option for creating, opening and saving les; the appearance of the neurons, both excitatory and inhibitory, when plotted and connected; the options for sensors that measure the nodes ring by different kinds of plot, such as voltmeter, ring rate plot, spike detector, and a loudspeaker that emits a noise when the selected neuron res; and the current sources, with a variety of possibilities for stimulating the network by direct or alternating current and generators of spike with regular, irregular or user-de ned activation (by using a camera or touching the generator).</p><p>The HP circuit has many redundancies and is essentially constructed by links between smaller circuits called motifs <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(HANGYA et al, 2014)</ref>. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Braganza and Beck (BRAGANZA and BECK, 2018)</ref>, a circuit motif is "a conserved anatomical pattern of connections between speci c cell types. " Since motifs are the basic blocks of HP circuitry, understanding these blocks is critical in the implementation of any equivalent computational model. To construct the whole HP circuitry, a total number of 226 excitatory and inhibitory neurons were used and displayed in patterns according to reviewed literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(THOMPSON et al., 2008)</ref>. This construct allowed the analysis of activity of each sub eld and component of the HP circuit (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref>).</p><p>We identi ed and separated HP formation to determine the speci c functionalities of each part <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(KRAGEL et al., 2021)</ref>. The ve main features of the sub elds can be understood as follows: rst, sparsity of DG, i.e., less intensity of output compared to the input; second, the recurrence of stimulation of the CA3 with strong and localized inhibition; third, selectivity of excitatory output by inhibitory feedback of CA2; fourth, the information cadenced ow with collateral excitation of CA1; fth, the relative temporal synchronization of spikes as output through simultaneous excitation coupled to inhibitory feedback of SUB <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(DE BRIGARD, 2014)</ref>.</p><p>The six motifs were set to match these features. We selected alternative motifs, as follows, that could be incorporated in the network to generate the effects of interest only by using a combination of excitatory and inhibitory neurons: a) Simple Feedforward Excitation: motif relates to the simple and forward propagation of an excitatory signal, causing it to arrive at downstream structures. b) Simple Feedback Inhibition: motif responsible for inhibiting activity on a upstream neuron in a network, preventing it from ring as much as it was previous to excitation of the feedback inhibition network. c) Simple Feedforward Inhibition: similar to 'Simple Feedback Inhibition' where the inhibition occurs on a downstream neuron instead of an upstream neuron. d) Recurrent Excitation: a motif characterized by a postsynaptic excitatory neuron that feeds back to the presynaptic one, therefore reinforcing the signal that it receives. e) Simple Feedback Excitation: similar to 'Recurrent Excitation' where the signal ampli ed by the recursion between two excitatory interneurons induces a robust representation of a given attribute. f) Global Feedback Inhibition: promotes a selective pattern of activation of the excitatory postsynaptic neurons. An inhibitory neuron selectively chooses which of the neurons are going to re by varying its synaptic weights while the other neurons remain "silent. " qeios.com doi.org/10.32388/4T2NIN Figure 2: Main circuit-motifs used. This list of constructions shows the motifs needed for building this model. These motifs are useful in computational neuroscience since they simplify complex structures by logical pieces with a not speci c anatomic correspondence that is repeated through an area of the nervous system. a) This motif known as "simple feedforward excitation" relates to linear propagation of the signal from one cell to another. Computational mechanism: signal propagation. Computational / behavioral function: linear propagation of information. b) This motif known as "simple feedback inhibition" is characterized by inhibitory feedback that limits the maximum excitation of a neuron and may represent a way to control the output of the structure in network. A variation of this motif was also used, in which the presynaptic neuron was inhibited instead of the neuron that stimulates the inhibitory neuron but resulting in the same effect. Computational mechanism: output normalization. Computational / behavioral function: controlling maximum output / sparsity. c) This motif known as "simple feedforward inhibition" basically plots an inhibitory neuron, which is able to limit the range of activation of another cell by amplifying the possible levels of excitability the next cell will be exposed to. Computational mechanism: input normalization. Computational / behavioral function: increasing the dynamic range. d) This motif known as "simple feedback excitation" contains a postsynaptic neuron exciting the presynaptic neuron, reinforcing the arriving signal by its repetition between the cells. Computational mechanism: repetition. Computational / behavioral function: reinforcement of the signal. e) This motif known as "recurrent excitation" is made of excitatory neurons stimulating each other in order to amplify the signal, generating a robust representation of a determined feature. Computational mechanism: ampli cation. Computational / behavioral function: robust feature representation. f) This motif known as "global feedback inhibition" presents a characteristic connectivity between its components, with a row of excitatory neurons establishing synapses with an inhibitory cell that feedbacks them, causing an effect called "k-winners take all. " It means that the "k" selected cells that receive a less intense inhibitory feedback will re while the rest of the neurons will stay inactive, being an effective way to discriminate a pattern of interest to a network. Computational mechanism: k-winners take all. Computational / behavioral function: pattern discrimination.</p><p>The above motifs are attributed to every structure of the HP formation. DG has a wide presence of simple feedforward excitation and inhibition as well as feedback inhibition. CA3 has feedforward excitation and inhibition, feedback excitation and inhibition, and recurrent excitation. CA2 has feedforward excitation, and simple and global feedback inhibition. CA1 has feedforward excitation, feedback excitation and inhibition, and recurrent excitation. SUB has feedforward excitation and feedback inhibition. Thus, each constructed region shows the peculiarities in its organization similar to a HP slice.</p><p>We emulated the regions on Neuronify™ using only excitatory and inhibitory neurons. The current sources and sensors were tested during and after each region was composed. We maintained default neuron settings (threshold, resting potential, refractory period, membrane resistance and membrane capacitance) for easy manipulation of the network. Alternatively, we implemented a de ciency of a voltage-dependent sodium channel by changing the membrane's threshold potential <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(HEYNE et al., 2020)</ref>, while maintaining other properties to equalize every neuron feature. These networks highlighted the spike patterns in relation to the structural connectivity of the cells.</p><p>Model building started with characterizing the activity of each portion of HP formation followed by determining the motifs present in in vivo models. Small and enough arti cial neurons were connected according to the selected motifs emulating the robust features in a topologically accurate network. To emphasize the educational purpose of the network, we created connections similar to that of a histological HP slice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref>).  neuroarchitecture of hippocampal formation could be preserved whereas its activity could be well demonstrated. Basically, and classically, the information arrives from the EC II and EC III, ows through the "gate, " which is the DG by PP up to the CA3 -that receives its afferences mainly by the MF, processes and conducts the information together to the CA2 and CA1 and, in the SUB, shapes the signals directed to neocortex, rstly received in the EC V.</p><p>The medial entorhinal cortex (MEC), subregions II (EC II) and III (EC III), was represented by a row of excitatory neurons composed of six sources of input. This row of neurons received connections from current sources chosen by the researcher. These represent the main pathways by which signals arrive at the HP formation in DG <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(TATU and VUILLIER, 2014)</ref>. These six excitatory neurons were designed to project efferent to the DG, CA3 and CA1. A feedforward excitation motif allowed the efferents to receive versatile types of input from the current sources provided by Neuronify™.</p><p>In DG, the neurons were arranged into a C-shape form with alternating excitatory-inhibitory-excitatory three-layer structure similar to the actual cytoarchitecture of the archicortex <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(MORAIS et al., 2020)</ref>. The structure had a total number of 16 excitatory neurons which was the minimum number of cells suf cient to emulate HP functions, while, creating an easy-to-view network. Experimentally, the number of neurons demonstrated the expected performance without compromising the delity of the activity. Similar logic was extended to represent other subregions. The second layer strongly inhibits the others, letting only three neurons, adjacent to the superior limit of the DG representing mossy neurons, without inhibitory input, with 12 inhibitory neurons and a large number of synapses. In turn, the excitatory neurons connect with other excitatory neurons positioned laterally or frontally and at least to one inhibitory neuron that feeds back to them. The last layer consists of 16 excitatory neurons including three mossy neurons. Through the layers, feedforward excitation, feedback inhibition and feedforward inhibition can be observed.</p><p>In our model, eight excitatory neurons represent the anatomical input from the "mossy neurons" from the DG to the CA3 sub eld, such that four neurons each represent the bers and the receivers of the input. Additionally, we used two neurons in the inferior part of the DG representing input from the SC. For the connections from EC II, we used two neurons directly connected from the PP, which are the main pathway of bers from the neocortex to HP formation <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(AMANI et al., 2021)</ref>.</p><p>Further, the sub elds' inner connections were randomly plotted, with 12 excitatory neurons and 3 inhibitory ones showing SC stimulation to each other with a strong aspect of inhibition. However, they qeios.com doi.org/10.32388/4T2NIN</p><p>were organized in a way that allowed any amount of input signals to be ltered by the inhibitory neurons, strategically connected to afferent neurons and excitatory interneurons. This characteristic is better observed in its portion adjacent to DG, almost located in its hilus, where CA4 can be found <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(EZAMA et al., 2021)</ref>.</p><p>Another important feature of this part of the hippocampus is the recursion observed between the MF from the DG and the rst afferent pyramidal cells in CA3. This recursion corresponds to the reinforcement of arriving information that will be only processed into the hippocampus by the action of biochemical and electrophysiological mechanisms, thus enhancing the learning <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(BARTSCH and WULFF, 2015)</ref>. To represent this recursion, we used the motifs feedforward excitation and feedback excitation coupled to inhibitory feedback in CA3 to limit the excitability of the signal-receiver cells.</p><p>Next, we represent the connections between CA2 and CA3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(DING, L. et al., 2020)</ref>. We used four afferent cells from CA3 connecting to the surrounding neurons in a pattern characterized by inhibitory feedback that limits the excitability of these cells and the other ones connected to them. Therefore, one of these pyramidal neurons' synapses onto one inhibitory cell and the other three pyramidal neurons synapse onto two inhibitory neurons each. Also, these afferents establish connections to one excitatory neuron to keep the information owing to the CA2. Computationally, a greater number of connections between both excitatory and inhibitory neurons were required to generate the huge activation attached to a high level of inhibitory feedback in CA2. This structure required a total number of 11 excitatory and 4 inhibitory neurons.</p><p>Furthermore, we must consider that CA3's border with CA2 is not precise since these sub elds are not anatomically well established <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(MAHZER and HASSAN, 2021)</ref>. However, a "transition area" that is still a part of CA3 shows a gradual regularization of motifs more related to CA2. This area also has efferents directly to CA1. Assuming the role of SC, we placed three neurons between the area and CA1 to mediate these connections. Hence, the way out CA3 leads information to CA2 by three layers of neurons connected in a pattern of feedforward excitation coupled to feedback inhibition, maintaining the pseudounidirectional propagation of information <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(SUN et al., 2021)</ref>. The boundary of the transition area is immediately after the last (upper) excitatory cell, where the SC is present. Here, SC was modeled by ten excitatory and six inhibitory neurons disposed in connectivity patterns that mix the partially randomly plotted CA3 neurons with great recursion and limitation of excitability paired to the continuous propagation and inhibitory feedback typically seen in CA2.</p><p>qeios.com doi.org/10.32388/4T2NIN</p><p>Furthermore, CA2 has a feature of global feedback inhibition <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(MCHUGH et al, 2021)</ref>, by which it selectively enhances synapses according to the stimulus provided <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(NAVAKKODE et al, 2022)</ref>. In our model, this feature was represented by a feedback system of three neurons, one from each layer to the same inhibitory neurons where synapses might have their weights changed to strengthen few connections over others, thus composing the global feedback inhibition motif.</p><p>In CA1, 23 neurons were used to maintain proportional numbers in the sub elds of the three-layer structure. This con guration was suf ciently large to conduct experiments even in a non-scienti c computer, while also including the pattern of linear propagation feedforward excitation and inhibitory feedback mechanisms.</p><p>In our model, CA1 also received input directly from EC III by PP, showing a different pattern of organization. This pattern was represented as a row of excitatory neurons that stimulate itself located before the SUB layer <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(BÖHM et al., 2018)</ref>. The con guration was adopted to maximize the stimulation of the network since beyond the SUB layer the information will ow from the HP formation to the neocortex.</p><p>In summary, a total number of 15 excitatory and 15 inhibitory neurons were plotted, where 27 of them were designed to keep the feedforward excitation coupled to feedback inhibitions. The last three excitatory neurons denote recurrent connections, thus stimulating each other to enhance the activation of the organized region and start the relative temporal synchronization of the signal.</p><p>The SUB structure was designed to be a continuation of the three-layer architecture, but the layers are less independent. Here, the propagation of the signal takes collateral direction and is not linear as seen in CA2 and CA1. Each neuron is con gured to stimulate two other neurons in the following row until the end of the SUB, projecting its efferents to the three terminal neurons labeled as entorhinal cortex V (EC V) which is a part of the lateral entorhinal cortex (LEC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(NILSSEN et al., 2019)</ref>. The LEC receives three to ve spikes from SUB sequentially and spreads the information to the adjacent neocortex <ref type="bibr">(YU et al., 2021)</ref>. Considering the con guration of this area, 18 excitatory and 18 inhibitory neurons were plotted maintaining this connectivity pattern of inhibitory feedback and forward and collateral excitation (using the motifs of feedback inhibition and feedforward excitation).</p><p>qeios.com doi.org/10.32388/4T2NIN</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>Using this computational model, we propose a simple platform that allows the study of the structural con guration and functional activities of each sub eld of the HP formation, and their relationships. By placing the virtual sensors on each subregion, it was possible to observe the interdependence and the type of information processing that each region performs with respect to the other, and relative to the whole HP circuit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HP sub eld formations and their dynamics</head><p>The signal rst arrives at the DG of the HP formation. The pattern of eliciting action potentials is sparse and wide-distributed around the structure, because the granular cells (excitatory neurons) are exposed to intense inhibition. Information gets to DG through PP from EC II and EC III and its activity clearly shows fewer spikes in comparison to that of its neighborhood <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(PIATTI et al., 2013</ref>; Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>). From DG, information ows to CA3 through the axons of mossy glutamatergic neurons in MF. Since Neuronify™ cannot build an autapse, MF were plotted as excitatory neurons receiving feedforward input from DG and feedback input from pyramidal neurons of CA3 to simulate an autapse of CA3 pyramidal neuron. This motif is based on a learning rule <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(BECKER, 2005)</ref> according to the synchronization of spikes of postsynaptic and presynaptic neurons as a regulator for strengthening an associative memory.</p><p>It is possible to observe recurrent excitation and feedback inhibition (with feedforward excitation, feedback excitation, recurrent excitation, feedforward inhibition and feedback inhibition motifs) between the pyramidal and basket cells in CA3, which is part of the hippocampus proper and located on the fornix <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(BENEAR et al., 2020)</ref>. They can be found all over the hippocampus in circuits of feedback inhibition, and hilar interneurons, propagating signals in convergent and divergence patterns (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref>). Besides these main components, CA3 receives information directly from EC II and shows two main outputs: CA2, continuing from the fornix, and CA1, through SC <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(CACUCCI et al., 2017)</ref>, composing the well-studied trisynaptic circuit (DG, CA3, CA1, SUB).</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>: Activity of Cornus Ammonis (CA) 3. A considerable variety of patterns of spikes are observed as a result of the different kinds of connections, inputs, and types of cells in this eld. The portion next to dentate gyrus (DG) shows randomized patterns of connectivity that respect the purpose of softening the signal since the following part receives the main and stronger input. Thereafter, a region in the "curve" mixes these characteristics with the features of CA2, with a simpler propagation of the information attached to a simple inhibitory feedback system. qeios.com doi.org/10.32388/4T2NIN CA2 connections followed a basic pattern with three layers of inner pathways representing linear propagation and feedback inhibition <ref type="bibr">(Figure 4;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">HIRASE et al, 2003)</ref>. Its pathways have been well characterized recently and data suggests that this structure is important for social memory <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(TZAKIS et al., 2019)</ref>.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>: Activity of Cornus Ammonis (CA)2. The linear propagation of information is easily observed by the voltage sensor as the spikes occur almost simultaneously between the layers and with a relatively huge temporal separation provided by the individual inhibitory feedback (that is given by the inhibitory neurons). Besides these, the feature of global inhibitory feedback practiced by two inhibitory neurons that plays the role of "gates, " functioning as nodes that decide which neurons will re by the weights of their efferent synapses are notable.</p><p>The last part of hippocampus proper is CA1, whose circuitry was designed partly in continuity with CA2 and partly mixed with the components of SUB in a more complex con guration of afferents and efferent. The sub elds CA1 receives input directly from EC III by PP (Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>). It works as an information integrator, being a fundamental part of hippocampus in processing memory, learning, and spatial navigation. Spatial navigation is especially relevant due to the molecular particularities of some of its cells (grid cells and place cells) responsible for mapping the world around us <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(SOLTESZ and LOSONCZY, 2018)</ref>.</p><p>Despite the widely accepted notion that CA3 connects to CA1, recent studies <ref type="bibr">(SHI et al., 2013)</ref>  bidirectional propagation between CA3 and CA1, where the path from CA3 to CA1 is much more developed. Hence, we plotted only a portion of partial random synapses, so that the signals from CA1 could ow to CA3. Since the literature is unclear whether the recurrent excitation between some neurons of CA1 exists, we plotted it only once.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref>: Activity of CA1. Features of feedforward propagation are combined with feedback inhibition between the three neuronal layers, besides a bidirectional spreading of the signal in singular and random excitatory neurons (one every layer), which coupled with recursion between three neurons next to the subiculum (SUB), gives this region the main role in the processing of information by a spectacular variety of connections</p><p>The output coming from HP formation is forwarded to SUB, whose connections look less random than CA3 but is equally complex, with feedforward propagation applied to excitatory convergence and feedback inhibitory <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(STAFSTROM, 2005)</ref>. The normalized output reaches LEC in EC V, spreading itself to the neocortex around (Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>).  Not all features of inputs and outputs of hippocampus could be modeled. Yet, the spike activity in each of the sub elds by sensors provided by the software match well when compared with biological HP slices <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(REYES-GARCIA et al., 2018)</ref>. Thus, his simple model aids in the discussion and understanding of structural connections and its associated activities. The difference seen between the model and biological sample is a good opportunity to discuss the universality and redundancies of the neural circuits. Therefore, throughout the process of building the simple model, it is even possible to formulate predictions and hypotheses using solely the structural and functional modi cations (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">9</ref>) of the circuit.</p><p>qeios.com doi.org/10.32388/4T2NIN  <ref type="figure">2</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref><ref type="figure">5</ref><ref type="figure">6</ref><ref type="figure">7</ref>. It is possible to visualize the "entire pathway" of the main circuit: information coming from the medial entrohinal cortex (EC) II and EC III and passing through the whole hippocampal formation until it arrives again at the neocortex by EC V.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Computational simpli cation of HP circuitry</head><p>The establishment of circuit motifs allowed a subsequent construction of a simpler version of the HP circuitry. We observed a broader view of the ow of information in the structure, thus making it easier to visualize the HP activities <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(WOMELSDORF and EVERLING, 2015)</ref>. Here, we were able to reproduce most of the complex HP activities and preserve its main recurrent connections, motifs con gurations, while using only 31 cells, 21 excitatory and 10 inhibitory (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">10</ref>).</p><p>By turning the complex network into a simpler one, we asked whether it is possible that the brain uses redundancies between neural connections, perhaps for code protection? Reducing the structures and connection rules of HP circuitry can be an interesting educational strategy since it can simplify the understanding of its functional aspects. This model's simpli cation shows how effective the motif-approach is. Specially in context of limited computational power, simpli ed models like this can be of great applicability depending on the purpose of the experimenter. Additionally, they indicate the effectiveness of neural redundancies since they tend to appear in structures according to their functionalities <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(INGALLS et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">GOOGLE QUANTUM IA, 2021)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>Despite the simpli cation of the proposed model, it demonstrates high accuracy related to the neuroarchitecture and functional correspondence with real HP circuitry (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">11</ref>). We believe this type  The simplicity of the platform and biological structures provides anyone a highly accessible way to study this model using basic computers, tablets or even cell phones. Also, it overcomes the limitation of books that fail to demonstrate the cell dynamics.</p><p>Computational models like the one proposed here are an interesting alternative for teachers and students interested in understanding the function and structure of the hippocampus or any other brain region. The teaching and learning dynamics open many possibilities not offered by traditional lessons. The model allows for interacting with each structure, manipulating it with different input sources, measuring sensors, changing electrical properties of cells or even varying the position and connectivity of neurons in any region of interest, all through a simple screen and easy mechanism without harming any animals. While computational models are useful for education in neuroscience, they have some key limitations. For example, we need to determine how to faithfully represent a realistic and complex HP formation in Neuronify™. Despite it being a user-friendly and stable platform, there are limited options to modify the biophysical aspects of cells. To solve this problem, we cluster a variety of cell types into only two categories: (1) every neuron related to a neurotransmitter capable of inducing a depolarization in the cell membrane of a postsynaptic neuron was plotted as excitatory, and (2) every neuron with the opposite effect on postsynaptic membrane potential were designed as inhibitory. Moreover, other neuronal biophysics features including resting potential, membrane capacitance, resistive current were standardized such that discharge patterns were generated via circuit motifs. Thus, modeling using the circuit motifs approach successfully represent the HP circuitry. The approach allowed the simultaneous prediction of computation effects and construction by only organizing the structure. The choice of the right motifs was crucial, since they determine the functional aspects of each region represented individually and together. In case of DG, we implemented the sparsity described in this region. Instead of only minimizing the relative ring rate between the output and the input, we also needed to limit the number of inhibitory cells without creating many synapses between an inhibitory and excitatory neuron. To x this problem, a proportion of 8:3 was set between the excitatory and inhibitory cells to balance the number of cells and the required properties.</p><p>Similarly, in CA3, the challenges included representing the afferent pathways from MF with the strong recurrent connections and coupling these afferent neurons to its inhibitory mechanism. Furthermore, the rst signal of action potentials is propagated, processed, and directed to CA2, precisely through the excitatory-inhibitory neural process. To implement this, we de ned motifs to properly t to the dynamics and partially randomize the cell positions. Thus, they could keep their effects even without being restricted to a single and particular organization, but also be able to work in alternative scenarios, e.g., -conditions where the environmental variables could not be fully captured by a simpli ed model.</p><p>The representation of the CA2 sub eld addressed selective activation mechanism using the global feedback inhibition motif, which enabled an acceptable level of selectivity that can be virtually modulated by the user. The implementation of this mechanism emphasized the importance of motifs as modular units for building neural circuits.</p><p>The CA1 subregion was one of the hardest to implement since it represents different features and speci c connections that must be well described. The rst portion of CA1 in this model was characterized by the cadence of the signal while the second portion was characterized by a recursion mechanism through which the signal is ampli ed before arriving at SUB. These characteristics could be implemented because we conjugated the motifs of feedforward excitation and recurrent excitation with feedback inhibition.</p><p>Lastly, the SUB region's biggest challenge was to implement the related synchronization of action potentials, so they could represent constructive interference patterns. The solution was to couple the simple feedforward excitation linearly and collaterally to the simple feedback inhibition motif. Thus, the neurons could start ring simultaneously, triggering three to ve action potentials per stimuli as qeios.com doi.org/10.32388/4T2NIN described by the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(AGGLETON et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">XU et al., 2016)</ref>. Considering all these points, one of the main limitations of this model is its physiological simplicity. Physiological details such as cell types and speci c potentials of each neuron could not be fully addressed mainly due to the features of Neuronify™. Nevertheless, this simplicity can be seen as an interesting feature, since the model is more intuitive and easier to manipulate during the learning process. Another limitation to consider is the output measurements. The sensors only allow individual neuron measures, not neuronal populations. Particularly it measures only extracellular spike-train activities and does not allow local eld potential measurements <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(VINCK et al., 2012)</ref>. Additionally, the stimulation of the network is limited to six options provided by the software that act directly on a selected neuron, without being able to cause an extracellular-like stimulation that simultaneously excites a group of neurons next to an electrode.</p><p>Despite these restrictions, the platform and the model itself present many possibilities for analyzing the signals in each node of the network. We believe this model can be a good object for teaching hippocampus circuitry and its correspondent dynamics. It can even work as an initial step for research on HP disorders based on modifying the connections of the subregions and balancing the functions of each region.</p><p>One of the most interesting achievements through this computational model was the demonstration of circuit redundancy, where we were able to reproduce the main aspects of HP circuitry using a motif approach. It provides a good opportunity for students to discuss the arrangement of complex brain networks and how to improve the ef cacy of information processing while maintaining energy consumption.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>Using the Neuronify™ computational platform we were able to implement a model of the hippocampus circuit. The model primarily satis ed the structural architecture encompassing the pathways between the main subregions. Despite the limitations of the platform, such as the use of only excitatory and inhibitory neurons and the restricted biophysical modulation of the cells, we reproduced the main mechanisms of activity modulation using speci c circuit blocks. This implementation by block, known as motifs, was fundamental to better understand the structural relations between each subregion and to qeios.com doi.org/10.32388/4T2NIN</p><p>reproduce their activities.</p><p>The model proved to be very robust and at the same time malleable for virtual interventions such as synaptic interruption, short circuit construction, and stimulation. The simplicity of the computation model, along with the user-friendly interface of the platform, makes it important in interactive teaching and learning of neuroscience concepts. This model can potentially contribute to studying other similar dynamics, thus is capable of enriching and assisting the teaching process inside and outside the experimental laboratories.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Hippocampus in human brain, mouse hippocampal slice, schematic hippocampal formation, and complete portrait of the computational model of hippocampal formation. a) Schematic representation of the location of the two hippocampi inside a rat brain. Cellular and Molecular Neurophysiology, fourth edition. Elsevier, 2015. Copyright™. b) Drawing of a transversal slice of the hippocampus by Ramon y Cajal, 1911. c) The illustration simply represents the main structures of hippocampal formation, with the most relevant efferences indicated by the blue arrows. EC II: entorhinal cortex II; EC III: entorhinal cortex III; PP: perforant path; DG: dentate gyrus; MF: mossy bers; CA1-3: Cornu Ammonis; SC: Schaffer collaterals; SUB: subiculum; EC V: entorhinal cortex V. d) Hippocampal slice in the brain of a wistar rat in a coronal section stained with cresyl violet. (Own source) e) By plotting 226 neurons with a complex machinery of synapses, the</figDesc><graphic coords="9,88.90,57.75,427.68,479.19" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure4: Activity of dentate gyrus. The signal coming from the medial entorhinal cortex (EC) II is processed in a way that sparsity (less spikes in the output when compared with the input) is widely observed, not because of a greater number of inhibitory neurons, but by the number of synapses they establish with the granular (excitatory) ones.</figDesc><graphic coords="13,88.90,359.80,427.68,214.54" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8: Activity of SUB and the output. Beyond a linear propagation of the signal (restricted to feedforward neurons of only its own layer a divergent pattern by which the spikes gradually and partially synchronize up to the nal portion of subiculum (SUB) is observed, leading the information to medial entrohinal cortex (EC) V with clustered spikes, in series of three to ve shoots every stimulus.</figDesc><graphic coords="17,88.90,57.75,427.68,219.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9: Portrait of full hippocampal activity. Wide view of the complete model working, with the behaviors of each eld of hippocampal formation being shown smaller than in Figures 2-7. It is possible to visualize the "entire pathway" of the main circuit: information coming from the medial entrohinal cortex (EC) II and EC III and passing through the whole hippocampal formation until it arrives again at the neocortex by EC V.</figDesc><graphic coords="18,88.90,57.75,427.68,225.13" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10: Simpli cation of the model of hippocampal circuitry a) With 31 neurons, it was possible to emulate the main activity of each subregion of hippocampal formation by this motif-driven model (by comparing these recordings with the ones in Figures 5-9 it is possible to nd a good compatibility level). b) The activity of each subregion and the reason for these speci c ring patterns are described in the article.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 11 :</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11: Comparison between activity of the general model and its simpli cation. a) Activity of dentate gyrus of the general model. b) Activity of dentate gyrus of the simpli ed model. c) Activity of Cornus</figDesc><graphic coords="21,88.90,57.75,427.68,606.23" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="7,88.90,57.75,427.68,378.27" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="14,88.90,348.51,427.68,214.54" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="15,88.90,153.73,427.68,217.37" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="19,88.90,57.75,427.68,320.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>qeios.com doi</head><label></label><figDesc>.org/10.32388/4T2NIN of model and modeling practice can be very useful for teaching and learning neuroscience, such as studying the HP formation, connectivity between neural networks, and electrophysiological properties of neuronal cells.</figDesc><table><row><cell>qeios.com</cell><cell>doi.org/10.32388/4T2NIN</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>qeios.comdoi.org/10.32388/4T2NIN</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>This work was partially funded by <rs type="funder">CNPq -Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cientí co e Tecnológico</rs> and to the <rs type="funder">CAPES -Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior foundation. INNT -Instituto Nacional de Neurociência Translacional</rs>. We would also like to thank <rs type="person">Prof. Vinicius Rosa Cota</rs> and <rs type="person">Heitor Terra</rs> for the important discussions about the model.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <ref type="bibr">XU, X. et al.</ref> <p>Noncanonical connections between the subiculum and hippocampal CA1. The Journal of Comparative <ref type="bibr">Neurology, v. 524, n. 17, p. 3666-3673, Dec 2016. YU, X. et</ref>  </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The subiculum: the heart of the extended hippocampal system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Aggleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Christiansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/bs.pbr.2015.03.003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Progress in Brain Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">219</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<pubPlace>maio</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid Aging in the Perforant Path Projections to the Rodent Dentate Gyrus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Amani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2376-20.2021</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2301" to="2312" />
			<date type="published" when="2021-03-10">10 Mar 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The hippocampus in aging and disease: From plasticity to vulnerability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bartsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wulff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2015.07.084</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-11-19">19. Nov 2015</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier Neuroscience</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">309</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A computational principle for hippocampal learning and neurogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/hipo.20095</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hippocampus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="722" to="738" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dissecting the Fornix in Basic Memory Processes and Neuropsychiatric Disease: A Review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Benear</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ngo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Oslon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1089/brain.2020.0749</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Connectivity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="354" />
			<date type="published" when="2020-09">Sep 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Routes to, from and within the subiculum</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Böhm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00441-018-2848-4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell and Tissue Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">373</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="557" to="563" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-05">May 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Circuit Motif as a Conceptual Tool for Multilevel Neuroscience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Braganza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Beck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.32388/4T2NIN</idno>
		<ptr target="qeios.comdoi.org/10.32388/4T2NIN" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Press Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018-03">Mar 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hippocampus Activity-Driven Maturation of Neural Circuits for Navigation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cacucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Salinas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cub.2017.04.006</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Press Current Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="428" to="430" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-06">Jun 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neuroscience and Education: Issues and Challenges for Curriculum</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Clement</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lovat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1467-873X.2012.00602.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curriculum Inquiry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="534" to="557" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>De Brigard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/scientificamericanmind0514-39</idno>
		<title level="m">What Does the Hippocampus Do? Scienti c American Mind</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-05">May 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural Correlates of CA2 and CA3 Pyramidal Cell Activity in Freely-Moving Mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0099-20.2020</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5797" to="5806" />
			<date type="published" when="2020-07-22">22 Jul 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neuronify: An Educational Simulator for Neural Circuits. eNeuro</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S. -A</forename><surname>Dragly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1523/ENEURO.0022-17.2017</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visualization Techniques in SNN Simulators. 3rd International Conference on Multimedia Information Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-03-09">9 Mar 2017. 2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional connectivity of the hippocampus and its sub elds in resting-state networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ezama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41593-020-0705-8</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The European Journal of Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-09-14">5 May 2021. 14 Sep 2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1444" to="1452" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Circuit and molecular architecture of a ventral hippocampal network</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Hippocampus Anatomy, Pathophysiology, and Regenerative Capacity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Giap</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/00001199-200006000-00003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Head Trauma Rehabilitation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="875" to="894" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exponential suppression of bit or phase errors with cyclic error correction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Google</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41586-021-03588-y</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">595</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="383" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="2021-07">Jul 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From circuit motifs to computations: mapping the behavioral repertoire of cortical interneurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hangya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1126/scitranslmed.aay6848</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science Translational Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-06-12">Jun 2014. 12 Aug 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Predicting functional effects of missense variants in voltage-gated sodium and calcium channels</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploiting stoichiometric redundancies for computational ef ciency and network reduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hirase</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3233/isb-140464</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In Silico Biology, v</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">424</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-07-31">31 Jul 2003. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Nature</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mature Granule Cells of the Dentate Gyrus -Passive Bystanders or Principal Performers in Hippocampal Function?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Jeffrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Michael</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jirsa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.32388/4T2NIN</idno>
		<ptr target="qeios.comdoi.org/10.32388/4T2NIN" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroscience &amp; Biobehavioral Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2210" to="2230" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-08">03 Mar 2016. Aug 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Brain</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DG-CA3 circuitry mediates hippocampal representations of latent information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Keinath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41467-020-16825-1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3026</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Closing the loop&apos; in biological systems modeling -From the in silico to the in vitro</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kiparissides</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.automatica.2011.01.013</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-06">Jun 2011</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier Automatica</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1147" to="1155" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid coordination of effective learning by the human hippocampus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kragel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1126/sciadv.abf7144</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science Advances</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021-06-18">18 jun. 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open Source Software Tools for Teaching Neuroscience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Latimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Undergraduate Neuroscience Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018-09-03">3 Sep 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development of Neural Circuits in Adult Hippocampus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Mu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Topics in Developmental Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CA2 inhibition reduces the precision of hippocampal assembly reactivation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mahzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hassan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Histological</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mchugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.neuron.2021.08.034</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">histochemical, and immunohistochemical studies of hippocampus in male New Zealand rabbits</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021-02-17">Feb 2021. 17 Nov 2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">304</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3674" to="3687" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Neuron</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cytoarchitecture and myeloarchitecture of the entorhinal cortex of the common marmoset monkey (Callithrix jacchus)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L A</forename><surname>Morais</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>De G</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/cne.24814</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Comparative Neurology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">528</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1307" to="1320" />
			<date type="published" when="2020-06">Jun 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhanced long-term potentiation and impaired learning in mice lacking alternative exon 33 of CaV1.2 calcium channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Navakkode</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41398-021-01683-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Translational Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022-01-10">10 Jan. 2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neurons and networks in the entorhinal cortex: A reappraisal of the lateral and medial entorhinal subdivisions mediating parallel cortical pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Nilssen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/hipo.23145</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hippocampus, v</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1238" to="1254" />
			<date type="published" when="2019-12">Dec 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cooperative Group Learning in Undergraduate Neuroscience: Using Simulations to Complement Problem-Solving Assignments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Northcutt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Undergraduate Neuroscience Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021-06-19">19 Jun 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neurogenesis in the dentate gyrus carrying the message or dictating the tone</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Piatti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ewell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Leutgeb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fnins.2013.00050</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013-04-04">4 Apr 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving quality of science through better animal welfare: the NC3Rs strategy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Prescott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lidster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/laban.1217</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lab Animal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="152" to="156" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Undergraduate neuroscience education: Meeting the challenges of the 21st century</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ramirez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.32388/4T2NIN</idno>
		<ptr target="org/10.32388/4T2NIN" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-11-20">20 Nov 2020</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier Neuroscience Letters</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">739</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Different patterns of epileptiform-like activity are generated in the sclerotic hippocampus from temporal lobe epilepsy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Reyes-Garcia</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41598-018-25378-9</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Scienti c Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7116</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018-05-08">8 May 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Acquisition of Programming Knowledge and Skills</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rogalski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Samurçay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/B978-0-12-350772-3.50015-X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier Psychology of Programming</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="174" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bidirectional Global Spontaneous Network ActivityPrecedes the Canonical Unidirectional Circuit Organization in the Developing Hippocampus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/cne.23528</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Comparative Neurology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">552</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2192" to="2208" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-06-15">15 Jun 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scalable representation of time in the hippocampus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shimbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E. -I</forename><surname>Izawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fujisawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1126/sciadv.abd7013</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science Advances</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2021-02-03">3 Feb 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CA1 pyramidal cell diversity enabling parallel information processing in the hippocampus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Soltesz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Losonczy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">493</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018-04">Apr 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Role of the Subiculum in Epilepsy and Epileptogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Stafstrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1535-7511.2005.00049.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epilepsy Currents</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-07">Jul 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Frequency-Dependent Synaptic Dynamics Differentially Tune CA1 and CA2 Pyramidal Neuron Responses to Cortical Input</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0451-20.2021</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8103" to="8110" />
			<date type="published" when="2021-09-29">29 Sep 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure and vascularization of the human hippocampus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tatu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Vuillier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1159/000356440</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers of Neurology and Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-04-16">16 Apr 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Genomic Anatomy of the Hippocampus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.neuron.2008.12.008</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-12-26">26 Dec 2008</date>
			<publisher>Neuron Cell Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1010" to="1021" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social Memory and the Role of the Hippocampal CA2 Region</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tzakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Holahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fnbeh.2019.00233</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Behavioral Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved measures of phase-coupling between spikes and the Local Field Potential</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vinck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10827-011-0374-4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computational Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-08">Aug 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PhET: Simulations That Enhance Learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Wieman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Perkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1126/science.1161948</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">322</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="682" to="683" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-10-31">31 Oct 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three problems in the marriage of neuroscience and education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Willingham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cortex.2008.05.009</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cortex</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="544" to="545" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-04">Apr 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic circuit motifs underlying rhythmic gain control, gating and integration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Womelsdorf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nn.3764</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1031" to="1039" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-07-28">28 Jul 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Range Attention Networks: Circuit Motifs Underlying Endogenously Controlled Stimulus Selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Womelsdorf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Everling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Long-</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.32388/4T2NIN</idno>
		<ptr target="qeios.comdoi.org/10.32388/4T2NIN" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ScienceDirects Trends in Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="682" to="700" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-11">Nov 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
