<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">This is a repository copy of Networking Capability in Supplier Relationships and its Impact on Product Innovation and Firm Performance</title>
				<funder ref="#_FJhyFM5 #_X5s6SMm #_HuJ5WJD #_cqSyPcm #_PYd9HXx #_WN9rBBs #_jxjagES #_jrPWv7j #_YxeV8Vc #_Ys6KEwb #_qXTQrNh #_fD9ATmJ #_Tp5SSpg #_s9X6n8T">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">This is a repository copy of Networking Capability in Supplier Relationships and its Impact on Product Innovation and Firm Performance</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">0144-3577</idno>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1108/IJOPM-11-2014-0517</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.1" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T23:55+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This study proposes and empirically investigates the concept of Networking Capability (NC)    for the management of supplier relationships and their dynamics in order to leverage product innovations. NC in the context of supplier relationships is conceptualized based on dynamic capabilities aimed at relationship initiation, relationship development, and relationship ending.</p><p>Furthermore, the study tests the interaction of NC with relationship proclivity as an organizational feature, and analyzes latent classes of NC affecting product innovation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Design/methodology/approach</head><p>This study brings together prior research on company routines related to inter-firm networking, the dynamic capability approach to strategy, and literature on inter-firm innovation. The study utilizes multiple-informant survey data gathered from 156 firms operating in the automotive parts industry in Iran. Data are analyzed with partial least square structural equation modeling (PLS-SEM), as well as latent class analysis using finite mixture modeling (FIMIX PLS).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Findings</head><p>This research provides evidence for the positive influence of NC with respect to supplier relationships on firm product innovation, as well as overall firm performance. Relationship proclivity is shown to amplify this effect. At the same time, the research illustrates that NC may be applied in different combinations in the context of supplier relationship portfolio</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reuse</head><p>Items deposited in White Rose Research Online are protected by copyright, with all rights reserved unless indicated otherwise. They may be downloaded and/or printed for private study, or other acts as permitted by national copyright laws. The publisher or other rights holders may allow further reproduction and re-use of the full text version. This is indicated by the licence information on the White Rose Research Online record for the item.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Takedown</head><p>If you consider content in White Rose Research Online to be in breach of UK law, please notify us by emailing eprints@whiterose.ac.uk including the URL of the record and the reason for the withdrawal request.</p><p>management. Two mechanisms are tentatively identified: firms using 'static optimization' focus mainly on supplier relationship development capabilities, while those using 'dynamic optimization' utilize supplier relationship initiation and ending capabilities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research limitations/implications</head><p>This research focuses on one setting (i.e. the automotive parts industry in Iran). Further studies need to broaden these findings to other industries and countries, specifically those which show a different cultural make-up from Iran. Furthermore, this research indicates the existence of two distinct mechanisms as to how different aspects of NC impact product innovation. While it is reasonable to identify these mechanisms as networking 'strategies', this study does not clarify whether this represents intended strategies by firms or relates to emerging capability patterns.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Practical implications</head><p>Our study contributes to managerial knowledge by illustrating the need for a dynamic approach with regard to networking-related routines in supplier relationships in the context of product innovation. This study suggests that managers should devote equal attention to strengthening existing supplier relationships as well as to initiating new supplier relationships (e.g. screening for promising partners and signaling firm's relationship value to attract new counterparts) and managing non-performing supplier relationships (e.g. by developing routines to exit from those supplier relationships).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Originality/value</head><p>The paper contributes to a better understanding of dynamic approaches to networking with suppliers and their impact on product innovation from the perspective of the focal firm. It furthermore provides a fine-grained understanding of different latent classes of firms in terms of how they utilize networking capabilities.</p><p>Networking Capability in Supplier Relationships and its Impact on Product Innovation and Firm Performance</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Successfully managing supplier relationships, including overall supply portfolios, has been shown to increase the purchasing and manufacturing efficiency of firms by streamlining resource acquisition and optimizing operational costs <ref type="bibr">(Da Silveira and Arkader, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ketchen and Hult, 2007)</ref>. Having close relationships with firms in the supply chain has also been discussed as being instrumental for firms' innovation activities through joint research and product development <ref type="bibr">(Szwejczewski et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Johnsen, 2011)</ref>. Innovation is often the outcome of collaborative work between partners pooling their resources rather than the result of isolated firms exploiting their own resources <ref type="bibr">(Chesbrough, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr">Smart et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Azadegan et al., 2013)</ref>. Suppliers constitute important providers of such resources (e.g. technologies, knowledge, skills), which firms may lack in their innovation activities. Therefore, supply chain management as well as innovation literature posit the management of supplier relationships as a key mechanism for increasing a firm's innovativeness (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Wognum et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zirpoli and Caputo, 2002)</ref>. Besides managing individual supplier relationships, there is also the need to constantly re-shape the overall innovation partner portfolio <ref type="bibr">(Smart et al., 2007)</ref>, as mature portfolios could become stale, limiting product design and development <ref type="bibr">(Capaldo, 2007)</ref>. For example, over time the portfolio of supplier relationships may not provide access to the resources necessary to accomplish successful product innovation as a result of changing customer requirements, new regulations, or different technological possibilities <ref type="bibr">(Hauser et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Bohlmann et al., 2013)</ref>. Hence, to enhance innovation success, managing supplier relationships as part of an overall portfolio is a key managerial challenge and requires specific strategies and capabilities <ref type="bibr">(Smart et al., 2007</ref><ref type="bibr">, Johnsen, 2011)</ref>.</p><p>While the majority of the extant literature has focused on issues around supplier selection and relationship development activities in isolation <ref type="bibr">(Wu et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sjoerdsma and van Weele, 2015)</ref>, research on relationship portfolios suggests the importance of an integrated approach. This includes the management of initiating, developing and ending business relationships <ref type="bibr">(Reinartz et al., 2004)</ref>. In this context, less research has so far been conducted on how to deal with problematic collaborative relationships <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Wognum et al., 2002)</ref>. For example, some supplier relationships may have inherent dysfunctional features from the beginning due to wrong partner selection <ref type="bibr">(Lavie, 2007)</ref>. Such relationships may become a burden for the firms involved, hampering their innovation activities <ref type="bibr">(Håkansson and Ford, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Capaldo, 2007)</ref>.</p><p>Thus, supplier relationships may degenerate over time and create opportunity costs. Therefore, managing supplier portfolios effectively to drive innovation requires an integrative approach to relationship initiation, development and ending.</p><p>Relatively little research exists on the business capabilities that underpin and enable supplier relationship and portfolio management. A recent study by <ref type="bibr">Forkmann et al. (2016)</ref> has outlined the importance of supplier relationship management capability for supply base performance improvement. Studies using a capability perspective in the context of relationship portfolios and innovation are rarely partner-specific, do not focus on capabilities specific to the relationship stages that allow for dynamic management of the composition of portfolios, or do not consistently understand capabilities as organizational processes and routines <ref type="bibr">(Ritter 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ritter et al., 2002)</ref>. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Ritter and</ref><ref type="bibr">Gemünden (2003, 2004)</ref> assess the importance of network competence for innovation success, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Walter et al. (2006)</ref> stress the role of network capabilities for the success of entrepreneurial firms, and <ref type="bibr">Zaefarian et al. (2016)</ref> assess the impact of relationship ending capability on product innovation success, however, no integrated study of dynamic capabilities enabling supplier relationship management exists in the context of product innovation.</p><p>Therefore, the starting point for our study relates to a dynamic approach to supplier relationship management <ref type="bibr">(Aláez-Aller and Longás-Garcia, 2010)</ref>. We argue that while developing relationships is important for innovation, some supplier relationships cannot be sustained and should be ended. On the other hand, firms must be able to sense future beneficial supplier relationship opportunities and initiate new partnerships to enhance their innovativeness <ref type="bibr">(Moeller et al., 2006)</ref>. We follow <ref type="bibr">Mitrega et al.'s (2012)</ref> suggestion that such a dynamic orientation towards supplier relationship management can be conceptualized as networking capability (NC), which is defined as the "set of activities and organizational routines which are implemented at the organizational level of the focal company to initiate, develop, and terminate business relationships for the benefit of the company" (p. 741). In their study, <ref type="bibr">Mitrega et al. (2012)</ref> provide only general evidence as to the performance-enhancing effect of NC without empirically testing the detailed mechanisms or potential contingency factors. This has recently been addressed in a study by <ref type="bibr">Forkmann et al. (2016)</ref>, but only in the context of supply base performance improvements. We argue that networking capabilities are important for innovation, however, they do not alone guarantee superior performance outcomes, but require an appropriate organizational context, such as relationship proclivity, i.e. the extent to which firms value business relationships as an important driver of their success <ref type="bibr">(Johnson and Sohi, 2001)</ref>. Overall, the research objective of this study is to understand how firms can utilize NC and its components to improve firm performance through product innovation.</p><p>This study uses a sample of 156 firms in the Iranian automotive supplier industry to test the relationship between NC, product innovation and firm performance as well as the role of relationship proclivity. This study contributes to the literature in several ways. First, based on a theoretical grounding in the relational view of the firm and the dynamic capability theory, we show how supplier relationship management from a portfolio perspective is related to product innovation. For this purpose, we introduce the concept of networking capability (NC) to the supplier context, based on an understanding of supplier relationship dynamics, and provide evidence of its positive effect on product innovation. The concept of NC is informed by a portfolio perspective and captures three important relationship stages that allow for a dynamic portfolio management, i.e. initiation, development and ending. This extends the current literature, which has either singled out isolated relationship stages or focused on network management activities in general. Furthermore, our conceptualization of NC as a dynamic capability constitutes organizational routines and practices that can be developed by firms to manage their supplier portfolios. Secondly, this study contributes to the ongoing discussion about the importance of the organizational context in the effective deployment of capabilities by showing that relationship proclivity amplifies the positive effect of NC. This shows that capabilities with respect to supplier relationships need to go hand in hand with the organizational attitudes within the firms deploying them. Thirdly, this study demonstrates the differential effects of the individual components of NC, i.e. initiation, development and ending. Furthermore, it identifies latent classes of firms that exemplify two different mechanisms of how firms utilize NC components to achieve product innovation. We find that both of these mechanisms are equally successful and represent alternative supplier portfolio management strategies in the context of product innovation. This allows firms to choose NC approaches that are best aligned with their characteristics as well as their business environment.</p><p>The article is structured as follows. We first ground the NC conceptualization in a theoretical framework. Next, we discuss the literature on aspects of NC, i.e. business relationship initiation, development and ending, and derive specific hypotheses with regard to product innovation. We then present our research design, which is followed by a discussion of our analyses and results. Finally, the findings of the study as well as their theoretical and managerial implications are outlined, and limitations and directions for further research are introduced.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Conceptual Background and Development of Hypotheses</head><p>We couch our argument in the resource-based view of the firm, or RBV <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Barney, 1991)</ref> and the relational view of the firm, or RV <ref type="bibr">(Dyer and Singh, 1998)</ref>. The RBV argues for the importance of valuable as well as non-imitable and rare resources, which are combined into capabilities that lead to firm-specific advantages such as efficient operations or superior product quality <ref type="bibr">(Das and Teng, 2000)</ref>. The RV extends this view by emphasizing the importance of business relationships in mobilizing and combining such resources from external partners, leading to relationship-specific advantages, such as the collaborative development of unique technologies <ref type="bibr">(Eisenhardt and Martin, 2000)</ref>.</p><p>Our research follows the RBV as well as the RV and argues for the importance of relationships with suppliers to access and develop resources such as technologies, knowledge, and skills <ref type="bibr">(Mesquita et al., 2008)</ref>, which are critical for product innovation. Regarding the management of such relationships, we argue that successful firms require a dynamic approach going beyond existing supplier relationships. This is supported by research that has shown that an overly strong focus on existing relationships may decrease firms' innovative potential <ref type="bibr">(Lavie and Rosenkopf, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Capaldo, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Smart et al., 2007)</ref>. Adopting a dynamic perspective, our study suggests that supplier relationship management in the context of product innovation relates to a combination of organizational efforts to benefit as much as possible from resources dedicated to existing partnerships (e.g. exchanging knowledge with strategic suppliers) as well as efforts to avoid getting stuck in unprofitable partnerships. This can be achieved by anticipating threats embedded in the current portfolio of supplier relationships, and by searching for promising opportunities via new supplier relationships. Therefore, we combine the RBV and RV with the dynamic capabilities approach as an important theoretical framework applied in general management (e.g. <ref type="bibr">Easterby-Smith et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Protogerou et al., 2012)</ref> and in the operations and supply chain management literature (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Azadegan et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">Perunovic et al., 2012)</ref>.</p><p>The dynamic capability approach (DC) to firm strategy <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Teece et al., 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zollo and Winter, 2002)</ref>, which also builds on the RBV, suggests that firms should continuously transform themselves by reshaping resource configurations to establish and sustain their competitive advantage. Such configurations may combine resources and capabilities possessed by the firm itself or mobilized through its partners in the supply chain. DC suggests developing organizational routines and processes that enable firms to adjust to changes in their external business environment, i.e. to cope with emerging threats and to seize arising opportunities.</p><p>Following this DC perspective, we argue that firms can accomplish such resource reconfigurations by implementing systematic processes for reconfiguring their supplier relationship portfolio, e.g. initiating new supplier relationships, developing existing ones, as well as ending those that are performing sub-optimally. Mitrega and colleagues (2012) offer the concept of networking capability to capture such dynamic capabilities. While networking capability (NC) as a supplier relationship management capability <ref type="bibr">(Forkmann et al., 2016)</ref> and as business relationship process management (Mitrega and Pfajfar, 2015) has been empirically tested in the context of supplier performance improvements, the relationship between NC and firm innovativeness remains unknown.</p><p>NC implies that the locus of innovation success is situated within the network or portfolio of firms' business relationships <ref type="bibr">(Gulati, 1999)</ref> rather than in any single partnership, because every partnership may sooner or later lose its rent-generating function. This corresponds with concepts of knowledge networks <ref type="bibr">(Powell et al., 1996)</ref> and innovation networks <ref type="bibr">(Dhanaraj and Parkhe, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Smart et al., 2007)</ref>, according to which firms systematically increase their partnership experiences, utilize their absorptive capacity and mobilize network resources through the dynamic management of their inter-organizational links to improve product innovation. However, in contrast to prior studies on innovation business networks <ref type="bibr">(Capaldo, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Schilling and Phelps, 2007)</ref>, this study does not focus on the structural characteristics of the supplier network in which a firm is embedded (e.g. centrality or density, direct and indirect ties) but is instead devoted to studying the networking capabilities (i.e. organizational routines) of the firm that help to actively shape the supplier relationship portfolio to maximize its product innovation potential.</p><p>Prior research in the area of networking-related capabilities is fragmented, with most research focusing on activities to develop already existing relationships or without clear distinctions between activities implemented by firms to start, develop and end business relationships <ref type="bibr">(Lorenzoni and Lipparini, 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ritter, 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kale et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kale and Singh, 2007)</ref> although they are acknowledged as crucial in managing relationship life cycles <ref type="bibr">(Ozcan and Eisenhardt, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ritter and Geersbro, 2011)</ref>. In line with the DC perspective, we position our research within the existing literature by following the conceptualizations of NC by <ref type="bibr">Mitrega et al. (2012)</ref> and focus on dynamically managing supplier relationships specific to their lifecycle phase, in line with <ref type="bibr">Reinartz et al.'s (2004)</ref> suggestions for portfolio management. <ref type="bibr">Mitrega et al. (2012) and</ref><ref type="bibr">Forkmann et al. (2016)</ref> posit that NC in supply relationships has three distinctive components, i.e. those behavioral routines aimed at initiating; those aimed at developing; and those aimed at terminating business relationships. The following will outline these components of NC and their relationships with firms' product innovation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Supplier Relationship Initiation Capabilities (SRIC)</head><p>The RV emphasizes business relationships as the source of inter-firm learning and increased innovativeness <ref type="bibr">(Chesbrough, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr">Cheng and Huizingh, 2014)</ref>, because such relationships create the appropriate atmosphere that fosters cooperation and collaboration while mitigating opportunism <ref type="bibr">(Dyer and Singh, 1998)</ref>. To this end, the RV also stresses the necessity to identify and evaluate partners as the building block of inter-firm competitive advantage, and thus provides, together with DC, the underpinning for Supplier Relationship Initiation Capabilities (SRIC) as the first NC component. SRIC focuses on organizational routines to utilize the potential of new supplier relationships for product innovation. While some literature covers supplier selection criteria, there is no extensive literature on how firms navigate the relationship initiation stage <ref type="bibr">(Edvardsson et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">La Rocca et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Tóth et al., 2015)</ref>.</p><p>Supplier relationship initiation may be used by firms to exploit the potential of new supplier partnerships within their portfolio for product innovation <ref type="bibr">(Hennart et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mesquita et al., 2008)</ref>. We posit, in line with suggestions by <ref type="bibr">Mitrega et al. (2012)</ref>, that SRIC is composed of two sub-components, i.e. selecting new suppliers as well as attracting new suppliers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.1.">Supplier Selection Capability</head><p>Selecting new supply partners requires screening potential suppliers and acquiring knowledge about potential partners <ref type="bibr">(Mitrega et al., 2012)</ref>. However, the literature does not offer a clear picture with regard to factors or processes that are most important in screening and selecting suppliers for collaborative innovation projects (e.g. <ref type="bibr">Birou and Fawcett, 1994)</ref>.</p><p>Research by <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Wagner and Hoegl (2006)</ref> shows that R&amp;D managers expect supply partners to possess both 'hard skills' as well as openness and credibility as a reflection of 'soft skills'.</p><p>Firms tend to assess new business partners through various channels, such as word-of-mouth, managers' personal ties <ref type="bibr">(Gulati, 1998)</ref>, or other partners outside of their immediate business network <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Beckman et al., 2004)</ref>. Therefore, we argue that successful firms use various information sources to find and subsequently assess new suppliers for collaborative innovation relationships (e.g. suppliers' online presence, professional social media, and professional and personal relationships with other network actors).</p><p>Successful partner selection minimizes the risk of supplier opportunistic behavior (e.g. appropriation of knowledge by the supplier), and creates the potential for resource synergies (e.g. successful collaborative new product development projects). However, developing business relationships is an interactive process based on the cognition and behavior of all networking firms <ref type="bibr">(Forkmann et al., 2012)</ref> and all actors, including suppliers, aiming to select the best partners <ref type="bibr">(Håkansson and Ford, 2002)</ref>. Thus, besides being able to select an appropriate new supply partner, firms should also be able to attract selected suppliers for relationship initiation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.2.">Supplier Attraction Capability</head><p>Attracting new supply partners for collaborative innovation relies on signaling, which refers to activities informing the selected partner that a firm is open to forging business relationships, e.g. for collaborative product innovation activities, or for sharing knowledge <ref type="bibr">(Fontana et al., 2006)</ref>. Such signaling activities could include various features such as cues focusing on financial and non-financial benefits, costs, trust and dependency <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Tóth et al., 2015)</ref>. Proposing a staged process of buyer-seller relationship development, <ref type="bibr">Dwyer et al. (1987)</ref> suggest that business partners might be attracted by demonstrating similarity of values and complementarity of resources. Thus, we argue that attracting supply partners in order to enhance product innovation comprises informing the environment, and in particular suppliers, about relevant focal firm features, including technological capabilities, trustworthiness, and relationship propensity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.3.">SRIC and Product Innovation</head><p>We argue that SRIC may help firms to innovate in two ways. First, carefully selected new supply partners will reveal appropriate supplier behavioral intentions <ref type="bibr">(Ramsay et al., 2013)</ref>, such as a willingness to get involved in collaborative new product development projects as well as minimizing possible opportunism during such projects <ref type="bibr">(Yam and Chan, 2015)</ref>. Furthermore, such selection will also identify suppliers with important resources for innovation. Secondly, being able to effectively attract selected partners allows innovationrelated resources to be accessed and may potentially shorten new product development times <ref type="bibr">(King and Penlesky, 1992)</ref>. Based on the RV, SRIC will allow firms to be able to find (selection capability) and bond with (attraction capability) supply partners with complementary and synergistic resources and technologies <ref type="bibr">(Dyer and Singh, 1998)</ref>. In line with Mitrega et al.'s (2012) conceptualization, these two aspects are independent sub-components of SRIC.</p><p>However, complementary to the RV and based on RBV arguments, firms may also exploit SRIC to benefit from short-term knowledge acquisitions during the early relationship stagesan approach entitled 'creaming-off' <ref type="bibr">(Lavie, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mesquita et al., 2008)</ref>. We argue that knowledge and resources accumulated during initial interactions with potential suppliers strengthen firms' resource base (e.g. technological or market knowledge) by adding currently inaccessible resources, thereby contributing to their innovativeness. Thus, based on the considerations regarding SRICs' ability to initiate potentially important supplier relationships for collaborative product innovation, and due to the creaming-off benefits of SRIC, we hypothesize:</p><p>H1a -SRIC is positively related to Product Innovation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Supplier Relationship Development Capabilities (SRDC)</head><p>Supplier Relationship Development Capabilities (SRDC) is the second NC component and follows the logic of the RV <ref type="bibr">(Dyer and Singh, 1998)</ref>. It refers to actions routinized at the firm level to strengthen relationships with supply partners. Strong or deep relationships are usually based on specific assets dedicated to the relationships (e.g. mutually adapted processes and technologies) in order to enhance collaborative product innovation <ref type="bibr">(Jean et al., 2014)</ref>.</p><p>Several pivotal factors were discussed in prior research, which help firms to strengthen their supply relationships: strategic integration with suppliers (Johnson, 1999), supplier development programs <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Wagner, 2006)</ref>, or collaborative communication and supplier control <ref type="bibr">(Joshi, 2009)</ref>. These studies concentrate generally on procedures and systems implemented at the inter-organizational level; however, business relationships are also operating via social ties, i.e. the inter-personal levels <ref type="bibr">(Granovetter, 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr">Håkansson and Ford, 2002)</ref>. Consequently, we recognize inter-personal and inter-organizational aspects as important sub-components with regard to supplier relationship development.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1.">Inter-organizational SRDC</head><p>For the development of supplier relationships aimed at product innovation, often various inter-firm adjustments and relationship-specific investments are necessary, which cannot easily be re-deployed as part of other supplier relationships <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Bensaou and Anderson, 1999)</ref>. Safeguarding such relationship-specific assets against opportunism as well as enhancing product innovation benefits requires effective communication and information sharing <ref type="bibr">(Eckerd and Hill, 2012)</ref>. In line with the RV (Dyer and Singh, 1998), we argue that inter-organizational relationship development capabilities in the context of supply partnerships aim at creating relationship-specific assets and formal governance mechanisms, which take the form of resource links and mutual adjustments as well as improved communication and information sharing between supply partners. This strengthens supplier relationships and has been shown</p><p>to have a positive effect on product innovation activities, for example through increased knowledge exchange and risk mitigation <ref type="bibr">(Cheng and Huizingh, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Jean et al., 2014)</ref>, or through technology transfer <ref type="bibr">(Lawson et al., 2015)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2.">Inter-personal SRDC</head><p>The inter-personal aspects of supplier relationship development have received increased attention in recent years and were conceptualized as the foundation of supply chain relational capital <ref type="bibr">(Cousins et al., 2006)</ref>, in particular in the context of product innovation <ref type="bibr">(Lawson et al., 2009)</ref>. The importance of building inter-organizational relationships through inter-personal ties was suggested not only in studies grounded empirically in Eastern business cultures <ref type="bibr">(Michailova and Worm, 2003)</ref> but also in studies conducted in Western countries <ref type="bibr">(Hutt et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lawson et al., 2009)</ref>. Inter-personal aspects of SRDC are also emphasized in the RV <ref type="bibr">(Dyer and Singh, 1998)</ref> where they are treated as fundamental for creating informal and self-enforcing relational governance mechanisms, such as trust and commitment, which in turn drive communication and knowledge exchange <ref type="bibr">(Morgan and Hunt, 1994)</ref>. Therefore, we treat inter-personal aspects as inherent elements of SRDC, with similar positive effects on product innovation as inter-organizational SRDC <ref type="bibr">(Lawson et al., 2015)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.3.">SRDC and Product Innovation</head><p>We argue that the positive effect of SRDC on firm innovativeness is based on the positive influence of SRDC on inter-firm trust, commitment, and relationship-specific assets, which in turn work as a relationship governance mechanism by mitigating threats of opportunistic behavior and by creating the appropriate climate for collaborative projects (e.g.</p><p>sharing ideas via open communication) <ref type="bibr">(Cheng and Huizingh, 2014)</ref>. Such mechanisms were illustrated by <ref type="bibr">Dyer and Hatch (2006)</ref> in the context of the automotive industry, where manufacturers that provide more assistance in collaborative projects also benefit more from their supply chain relationships. SRDC increases both: occasions for joint new product development (e.g. organizing inter-firm meetings for offering development, stimulating procedural adjustments with suppliers) <ref type="bibr">(Jean et al., 2014)</ref>, as well as appropriate partner attitudes for joint new product development (e.g. through organized socialization) <ref type="bibr">(Lawson et al., 2009</ref><ref type="bibr">(Lawson et al., , 2015))</ref>. This results in the improved availability and development of supplier-based innovation resources through stronger and more collaborative business relationships <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Takeishi, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Azadegan et. al., 2013)</ref>, especially in cases in which such resources are expensive or unavailable via the initiation of new supplier relationships. Thus, we hypothesize: H1b -SRDC is positively related to Product Innovation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Supplier Relationship Ending Capabilities (SREC)</head><p>The RV, as an important rationale for business networking, in general does not suggest implementing any systematic actions at the firm level that would help eventually end some selected relationships <ref type="bibr">(Dyer and Singh, 1998)</ref>. In fact, as partnering usually requires "nonrecoverable investments" <ref type="bibr">(Dyer and Singh, 1998, p. 663)</ref>, the RV implicitly discourages managers from ending relationships. However, the ending of business relationships is becoming a more important research area <ref type="bibr">(Tähtinen and Halinen, 2002)</ref> and is perceived as a building block of supplier relationship management <ref type="bibr">(Moeller et al., 2006)</ref>. Diminishing performance from mature supplier relationships as well as from mature supplier portfolios is well documented (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Wagner, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Capaldo, 2007)</ref>, and negative effects on product innovation have been outlined <ref type="bibr">(Moeller et al., 2006)</ref>. The process of relationship-ending is compatible with the DC perspective that sees sources of competitive advantage as temporary, thereby emphasizing a systematic reconfiguration of firms' strategic focus <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Teece, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zaefarian et al., 2016)</ref>. In line with the DC, this research treats Supplier Relationship Ending Capabilities (SREC) as the actions or behavioral routines implemented at the firm level oriented towards the systematic withdrawal of supplier relationships that are hampering innovation. Consequently, such suppliers are deliberately eliminated from the supply portfolio even if they may be re-engaged in future interactions. We argue in line with Zaefarian et al.</p><p>(2016) that, in the context of supplier relationships, ending management comprises two components: ending preparation (i.e. selecting non-performing supplier relationships by evaluating their value and identifying sub-optimal ones) and ending processes (i.e. establishing procedures for how to phase out or end sub-optimally performing supplier relationships).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1.">SREC Preparation</head><p>Without selection routines in place, firms may be affected by what is known as supplierswitching inertia and therefore become locked into non-performing supplier relationships, with stifling effects on product innovation <ref type="bibr">(Moeller et al., 2006)</ref>. Such non-performing supplier relationships are therefore binding resources while not providing adequate product innovation benefits; these resources could otherwise be used in a more optimal manner for product innovation. Systematic supplier evaluation has been discussed as a tool to assess partner contribution in business relationships and therefore to identify those relationships with a deficient value <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Wagner, 2006)</ref>. Implementing firm routines oriented at identifying nonperforming supply partners provides an appropriate basis for further actions, including minimizing collaborative projects or downsizing relationships to more transactional levels <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Wagner, 2006)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.2.">SREC Process</head><p>We build on the few recent studies that have treated relationship dissolution as an organizational competence <ref type="bibr">(Ritter and Geersbro, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Havila and Medlin, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mitrega et al., 2012)</ref>, and we argue in line with <ref type="bibr">Zaefarian et al. (2016)</ref> that successful business networking demands not only monitor non-performing supplier relationships in order to improve them <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Wagner, 2006)</ref> but also develop concrete routines (e.g. assessing costs of ending, exploiting specific supply contract elements) devoted to relationship dissolution. These may be utilized after existing supply partners have been carefully evaluated and deemed as non-performing for product innovation activities. Such processes and routines would allow for a disengagement from supply partners and therefore the freeing of resources otherwise bound up in these supplier relationships <ref type="bibr">(Moeller et al., 2006)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.3.">SREC and Product Innovation</head><p>Studies on the effects of relationship-ending capabilities in the context of supplier relationship management are rather scarce and not often related directly to product innovation <ref type="bibr">(Ritter and Geersbro, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Havila and Medlin, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mitrega et al., 2012)</ref>. A notable exception is <ref type="bibr">Zaefarian et al. (2016)</ref>, who show the importance of relationship ending capabilities for product innovation success. Utilizing SREC in relation to collaborative product innovations does not question the idea that some investments dedicated to supplier relationships are not retrievable <ref type="bibr">(Dyer and Singh, 1998)</ref>. We acknowledge that some, but not all, innovation-related benefits may be lost if firms end certain non-performing relationships.</p><p>However, we argue for the existence of positive influences from SREC on product innovation based on two main reasons. First, supplier evaluation helps to identify non-performing supplier relationships but, combined with feedback to suppliers, also motivates those suppliers to improve their relationship performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Wagner, 2006)</ref>. Thus, non-performing supplier relationship assessment should have a positive impact on supplier relationships that are oriented towards innovation activities because they motivate non-performing partners to increase their collaborative activities and decrease opportunistic behavior <ref type="bibr">(Yam and Chan, 2015)</ref>. Furthermore, this safeguards against suppliers appropriating collaborative innovation outcomes, i.e. being able to withdraw from such relationships before such an appropriation by the supplier happens <ref type="bibr">(Noordhoff et al., 2011)</ref>. Secondly, we argue for a positive impact of SREC on firm product innovation via freeing certain organizational efforts as well as such retrievable resources (e.g. skills of specialists employed by the firm that are dedicated to the collaboration with a specific supply partner), which can be used for alternative supplier relationships (i.e. initiating partnerships with new prospective suppliers, or deepening other well-performing existing supplier relationships) to improve product innovation <ref type="bibr">(Zaefarian et al., 2016)</ref>. This mechanism reflects a DC approach in the context of inter-firm networking because it assumes that firms systematically reconfigure resource bundles <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Teece et al., 1997)</ref> through 'making space' in the supplier relationship portfolio for collaborative projects with new partners focused on product innovations. Thus, we hypothesize: H1c -SREC is positively related to Product Innovation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Higher-order NC and Product Innovation</head><p>Based on our considerations regarding the different NC components, i.e. initiation (SRIC), development (SRDC), and ending capabilities (SREC), and their respective positive effect on product innovation, a higher-order conceptualization can be derived. All three NC components are independent of each other, as they are aimed at different supplier relationship phases. However, together they form the dynamic networking capability that allows firms to re-configure their supplier relationship portfolio and optimize their product innovation performance. Thus, in line with DC, we provide an overall higher-order hypothesis: H1 -NC is positively related to Product Innovation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.">Moderation Effects through Attitudinal Relationship Proclivity</head><p>As our conceptualization of NC is grounded in the dynamic capabilities view of strategy <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Teece et al., 1997)</ref>, it relates to actions and behaviors that are learned and institutionalized within firms and are oriented towards their supplier relationships. The literature suggests that such actions are grounded in (or moderated by) firms' make-up, which in turn affects the prevailing organizational attitudes <ref type="bibr">(Henneberg et al., 2010)</ref>. This mechanism (i.e. attitudes moderating behaviors) has been documented in several studies, e.g. <ref type="bibr">Ritter (1999)</ref> found that firms' ability to develop technologies through business relationships is influenced by the extent to which attitudes of an entrepreneurial spirit and openness towards the business environment exist within such firms.</p><p>We use the construct of relationship proclivity to capture the attitudes held by firms regarding managing relationships with suppliers. Specifically, in line with Johnson and Sohi (2001), we treat relationship proclivity as the "...strength of the general tendency held by a firm to seek out, engage in and make close partner-style IFRs [interfirm relationships] as opposed to conducting interfirm interaction at arm's-length" (p. 302). Consequently, if the firm's top management introduces product innovation projects in collaboration with suppliers, such projects are likely to experience implementation barriers when there exists a lack of relationship proclivity within the organization (i.e. there is a lack of institutional willingness to share knowledge in relationships, or to develop interdependencies).</p><p>We argue that relationship proclivity works in similar ways for all processes and routines related to reshaping the supplier relationship portfolio, i.e. it positively amplifies the effect of supplier relationship initiation, development, as well as ending capabilities and therefore NC as a whole on product innovation. For example, a firm's capabilities for identifying non-performing supply partners may not be used effectively, if the firm does not perceive supply partnering as important for their innovation activities. Thus, problems with fading relationships are ignored until they become demonstrably disturbing for the firm's innovation objectives. In the same spirit, low levels of relationship proclivity will hinder firm programs oriented at initiating new, or developing existing supplier relationships. Intuitively, if firm attitudes persist which treat firm-internal proprietary knowledge and skills as the sole source of innovation success, such organizations will be resistant to engage with and learn from suppliers in collaborative innovation projects.</p><p>Thus, we hypothesize a positive moderating effect of relationship proclivity on the effect of NC with regard to product innovation: H2 -Relationship Proclivity positively moderates the relationship between NC and Product Innovation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.">Product Innovation and Firm Performance</head><p>We follow <ref type="bibr">Ritter and Gemünden (2003)</ref> and argue that firms' innovativeness includes introducing new effective solutions in two main areas: a firm's offerings and its operations.</p><p>Specifically, our research is focused on product (offering) innovations as the key innovation outcome of a firm's interactions with its suppliers. Product innovation has been established in the management and strategy literature as an important driver of firm performance <ref type="bibr">(Han et al., 1998)</ref>. Thus, our hypothesis is: H3 -Product Innovation is positively related to Firm Performance.</p><p>The overall nomological model, which will be tested in our research is presented in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INSERT FIGURE 1</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Research Design</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Sample</head><p>To test the proposed model, we collected data from a sample drawn from the Middle East, specifically the Iranian automotive parts industry. Iran's economy, alongside that of many other Middle Eastern countries, is growing. Iran's automotive industry (i.e. car manufacturers and parts suppliers) is its second largest and most established industry after the oil and gas industry. The automotive industry's growth in Iran is reported to be around 25% between 1995 and 2005, with total yearly car sales of more than $8.7bn. The automotive industry overall accounts for 10% of Iran's GDP <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Azar et al., 2009)</ref>. Today, this industry is led by a number of public and privately owned car manufacturers that annually produce more than 1.6 million vehicles in Iran. The size of the Iranian automotive market, as well as that of the entire Middle East, has attracted the attention of major international car manufacturers as well as automotive parts suppliers to this previously untouched market. The demand for cars has pushed the automobile industry in the Middle East to also enter into joint ventures with international car manufacturers and automotive parts suppliers who are interested in systematically increasing their market share in the region. The resulting mutual benefits have led to the signing of several joint venture agreements such as Peugeot, Citroen (France), Volkswagen (Germany) and Kia Motors (South Korea) in Iran; Land Rover (UK) in Jordan; and BMW (Germany), Nissan (Japan) and Hyundai (South Korea) in Egypt <ref type="bibr">(Killing, 2012)</ref>. As a result of these joint ventures, the competition in the automotive industry in Iran and other Middle Eastern countries is increasingly fierce, and the supplier relationships in this sector are an important factor of innovativeness and firm competitiveness, both for automotive manufacturers as well as their parts suppliers. NC with respect to the supply chain plays a vital role in firms' long-term success in such a setting, specifically in the context of product innovation.</p><p>We collected data from the automotive parts industry in Iran for which questionnaires were initially developed in English and then translated into Persian. In order to increase conceptual and translational equivalence between the two versions, the Persian questionnaires were back-translated into English <ref type="bibr">(Brislin, 1970)</ref>. As a result of this process, a small number of questions were re-worded to increase the precision of the translation. As a final step, faceto-face interviews were conducted with ten CEOs of automotive parts suppliers in Iran in order to pre-test the translated questionnaires, ensure their comprehensibility, as well as gauge ideal key informants for the specific content of the questionnaire, i.e. aspects related to supplier relationship management and innovation.</p><p>As a result of the pre-test, a multiple-key-informant approach was chosen to collect data from automotive parts firms regarding their supplier relationship management as well as their performance. Data regarding antecedent (NC), moderator (relationship proclivity) and final outcome (firm performance) constructs of our proposed model were collected from purchasing managers. Data regarding the central mediator construct (product innovation) were collected from R&amp;D managers. Such a research design based on collecting data regarding independent and dependent variables from different respondents was chosen to mitigate against common method bias (Podsakoff et al., 2012) in addition to increasing the knowledgeability of respondents, as indicated in the pre-test.</p><p>The purchasing and R&amp;D managers of 500 parts suppliers of major Iranian car manufacturers were contacted by phone and asked to participate in the survey. As such, we utilized a cross-sectional study design in line with prior studies on dynamic capabilities <ref type="bibr">(Drnevich and Kriauciunas, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Vanpoucke et al., 2014)</ref>. 340 firms indicated their willingness to participate and we mailed the respective questionnaires separately to the purchasing and R&amp;D managers of those firms. Initially, we received 143 matched questionnaires back (i.e. including both purchasing and R&amp;D responses). After a reminder phone call, we received another 51 matched questionnaires, totaling 194 matched firm responses (i.e. 388 questionnaires), resulting in a response rate of 38.8%. Responses from firms that only returned one of the questionnaires (either purchasing or R&amp;D) were excluded from further analyses.</p><p>In order to verify each respondent's knowledge, and to increase the validity of our findings, we added the following items to the purchasing and R&amp;D questionnaires respectively:</p><p>"To what extent do you feel knowledgeable about issues relating to the performance of your firm" (purchasing questionnaire) and "To what extent do you feel knowledgeable about issues relating to the innovativeness of your firm" (R&amp;D questionnaire). Both items were measured on seven-point bipolar scales anchored at poor knowledge (1) and excellent knowledge (7).</p><p>Firms for which either one of the two respondents indicated knowledgeability below the midpoint of four on the seven-point scale were removed from further analyses, thereby arriving at a purified sample size of 156 firms (i.e. 312 questionnaires) with an adjusted response rate of 31.2%.</p><p>The large majority of respondents have been with their firms in their current position for more than two years (90.6%) (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). Half of the respondents are in senior-level positions at their firms (48.5%) while the other half are middle-level managers (51.5%). While 70.7% of the firms are small and medium sized, 29.3% have more than 250 employees. All of the firms appear to be well established in the market, with 74.5% operating for more than 10 years. The vast majority of the firms surveyed are pure manufacturing firms (92.6%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INSERT TABLE 1</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Non-response and Common Method Bias</head><p>To assess potential non-response bias within our sample, we first follow <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Armstrong and Overton (1977)</ref> and compare early versus late respondents across various firm and respondent characteristics as well as central constructs in our model. Therefore, responses received after the reminder phone call were treated as late responses and compared with those received before the reminder, which served as early responses. Chi-square and t-tests did not show any significant differences between those two groups, suggesting that late-response bias is not an issue. Next, a short telephone survey about our key constructs was conducted with 50 firms randomly chosen from those firms of the initial sample that did not respond to the questionnaire. No significant differences between respondent firms and actual non-respondent firms were detected, providing further evidence that non-response bias is not a problem.</p><p>We controlled for common method bias through our multiple informant research design <ref type="bibr">(Podsakoff et al., 2012)</ref>. Also, various other research design procedures suggested by <ref type="bibr">Podsakoff et al. (2003)</ref> were used in order to reduce ex-ante the risk of common method bias: random question order, neutral wording, assurance of the respondents' anonymity, and data confidentiality. In addition to these preventive procedures, we followed several steps to assess ex-post whether common method bias is problematic within our data. First, we used Harman's single factor test. Common method variance is problematic if either a single factor emerges from the exploratory factor analysis (EFA) or if a single factor accounts for the large majority of the explained variance. According to the results of the unrotated EFA, the biggest factor explains only 33.61% of the variance, while all factors with Eigen values above one altogether account for 68.32% of the explained variance. As an alternative to Harman's one-factor test, Chang et al. (2010) suggest using a confirmatory factor analysis (CFA). Following their suggestions, we restrained all items to load on only one factor in a CFA. The fit statistics (RMSEA (&lt;0.08) = 0.129; NFI (&gt;0.9) = 0.473; CFI (&gt;0.9) = 0.544; IFI (&gt;0.9) = 0.555;  2 = 1767.117 (DF=495);  2 / DF (&lt;2) = 3.570) did not show good fit, indicating that a single factor does not account for all the variance in the data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Construct Operationalization</head><p>The focal constructs of the proposed model are measured using existing and already tested multi-item measurement models that are based on seven-point Likert scales (anchored at 1 "strongly disagree" and 7 "strongly agree"). As suggested by <ref type="bibr">Mitrega et al. (2012)</ref>, the NC components of supplier relationship initiation, development, and ending capabilities were operationalized as second-order formative constructs <ref type="bibr">(Diamantopoulos, 2008)</ref>. Supplier relationship initiation capability was composed from the two conceptually distinct but interconnected sub-components of selection and attraction. Similarly, supplier relationship development capability was constructed from the two distinct sub-components of interorganizational and inter-personal supplier relationship development. Finally, the third NC componentsupplier relationship ending capabilitywas formed by the two conceptually distinct sub-components of ending preparation and process.</p><p>In line with the theoretical argument, initiation, development and ending are conceptually non-overlapping but interrelated components of NC <ref type="bibr">(Jarvis et al., 2003)</ref>. Thus, NC itself is operationalized accordingly as a third-order formative construct. As a composite variable, increases and decreases of NC can thus be either caused by the components independently or jointly <ref type="bibr">(Diamantopoulos and Winklhofer, 2001)</ref>. The items used for all first order constructs of supplier relationship initiation (i.e. selection and attraction), development  <ref type="formula">2001</ref>). The moderating construct of relationship proclivity was measured using scales from <ref type="bibr">Johnson and Sohi (2001)</ref>. Firm performance as our focal outcome variable was measured according to <ref type="bibr">Reinartz et al. (2004)</ref>. Table <ref type="table">2</ref> provides an overview of the item wordings. We also included the availability of alternative supply partners, firm size, and firm age as control variables.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INSERT TABLE 2</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Assessing Measurement Models</head><p>Before estimating the proposed model, we first assess the reliability and validity (i.e. convergent and discriminant validity) of the measurement model. According to the EFA results (oblique/non-orthogonal rotation using Direct Oblimin with principle components extraction method; SPSS 17.0), the two sub-components of supplier relationship development capability (i.e. inter-organizational and inter-personal) load together on one common factor (see Table <ref type="table">3</ref>). This suggests that they are not conceptually distinct sub-components as theoretically argued by We adopt the emerged factor structure moving forward and all items of the final measurement model load on their respective factor, with most loadings consistently above 0.6 and no cross-loadings above 0.3. According to our analysis, both the average variance extracted (AVE) as well as the scale composite reliabilities (SCR) for all constructs are above the thresholds of 0.5 and 0.6 respectively in support of convergent validity (see Table <ref type="table">4</ref>). Also, the square root of the AVE for each construct is larger than their respective correlations with the other constructs in the model in support of discriminant validity <ref type="bibr">(Fornell and Larcker, 1981;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hair et al., 2009)</ref>. Finally, we performed a CFA of the overall measurement model in LISREL 8.80 <ref type="bibr">(Jöreskog and Sörbom, 2006)</ref>. The CFA results indicate adequate fit (RMSEA (&lt;0.08) = 0.064; NFI (&gt;0.9) = 0.917; CFI (&gt;0.9) = 0.965; IFI (&gt;0.9) = 0.965;  2 = 780.868;  2 / DF (≤2) = 1.672).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INSERT TABLES 3 AND 4 4. Analysis and Findings</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Main Model Analysis and Moderation Effects</head><p>We used the partial least square structural equation modeling (PLS-SEM) technique to test the proposed model. PLS-SEM has been increasingly popular in business and management research <ref type="bibr">(Hair et al., 2012a</ref><ref type="bibr">(Hair et al., , 2012b))</ref>. PLS-SEM is advantageous for relatively small sample sizes and complex models <ref type="bibr">(Fornell and Cha, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr">Reinartz et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hair et al., 2012a;</ref><ref type="bibr">2012b;</ref><ref type="bibr">Henseler et al., 2014)</ref> and allows the testing of models that simultaneously use formative and reflective measurement as well as hierarchical models <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Becker et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hair et al., 2012b)</ref>, which makes this a particularly useful analysis technique for our hypothesized model.</p><p>As empirically demonstrated in the EFA and discriminant validity analysis, the firstorder factors of supplier relationship initiation (i.e. selection and attraction) and ending (i.e. preparation and process) capabilities are distinct and non-overlapping constructs. In line with our theoretical argument that those first-order factors form important independent subcomponents of their higher-order constructs, we operationalize supplier relationship initiation and ending capabilities as a reflective-formative hierarchical latent variable model using the repeated indicator approach with Mode A as the mode of measurement on the second-order construct, and by applying the path-weighting scheme. The first-order constructs show strong and highly significant links with their higher-order constructs. The path coefficients for selection and attraction on supplier relationship initiation capability are 0.476 (t-value=9.083) and 0.748 (t-value=11.525) respectively. The path coefficients for ending preparation and process capabilities on supplier relationship ending capability are 0.518 (t-value=22.160) and 0.593 (t-value=20.838) respectively. Furthermore, NC is operationalized as a reflective-formative-formative hierarchical latent variable model using the repeated indicator approach with Mode A as the mode of measurement on the third-order construct and by applying the path-weighting scheme. The corresponding regression weights for SRIC, SRDC and SREC on NC are 0.289 (t-value=11.500), 0.397 (t-value=13.320), and 0.457 (t-value=17.019) respectively, indicating that NC is appropriately measured by the three components <ref type="bibr">(Hair et al., 2012b)</ref>. As suggested for formative measurement models, we assess multi-collinearity <ref type="bibr">(Diamantopoulos and Winklhofer, 2001)</ref>. The variance inflation factors (VIF) for all constructs show values well below 5 (highest VIF=2.070), suggesting that multi-collinearity is not an issue <ref type="bibr">(Hair et al., 2012a)</ref>. SmartPLS 3.0 <ref type="bibr">(Ringle et al., 2014)</ref> was used to test the hypothesized model. We follow the suggestion of <ref type="bibr">Hair et al. (2012a)</ref> and test our main model using a path-weighted procedure with a maximum of 300 iterations. A bootstrapping procedure with 5000 bootstrap samples was used to compute the t-statistics. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">5</ref> provides an overview of the PLS results for the main model testing H1, H2, and H3. According to Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">5</ref>, this model explains 29.0% and 29.4% of the variance in firm product innovation and firm performance respectively. Also, Stone- <ref type="bibr">Geisser, 1974;</ref><ref type="bibr">Stone, 1974)</ref> indicates good predictive validity of the model for both firm product innovation (0.118) and firm performance (0.191). A blindfolding procedure with an omission distance of 9 (to ensure that the number of observations divided by omissions distance is not an integer) was used to compute the cross-validated redundancies <ref type="bibr">(Hair et al., 2012a)</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Geisser's Q 2 (</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INSERT TABLE 5</head><p>According to the results, NC has a strong and positive effect on product innovation (β=0.332, t-value=3.716) in support of H1. Further, the results show that product innovation has a strong and positive effect on firm performance (β=0.297, t-value=3.552) in support of H3. The results also show a significant positive direct effect of NC on firm performance (β=0.211, t-value=2.394). Thus, the effect of NC on firm performance is partially mediated by product innovation. The indirect effect of NC on firm performance can be computed as 0.332×0.297=0.099. The total effect can then be calculated as the sum of the direct and indirect effects (0.211+0.099=0.310). The variance accounted for (VAF) through the mediation is 0.099/0.310=0.318, which suggests that product innovation success mediates 32% of the effect from NC on firm performance. In a further step, we analyzed the moderation effect of relationship proclivity (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">5</ref>). The results provide evidence in support of H2, i.e. that relationship proclivity positively moderates the effect of NC on product innovation (β=0.119, t-value=2.122). In our model, we controlled for the effects of firm size and firm age as well as the availability of alternative supply partners on product innovation and firm performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Disaggregated NC and Latent Class Analysis</head><p>In order to test H1a, H1b, and H1c (i.e. the sub-hypotheses which disaggregate H1 into separate hypotheses relating to the three components of NC), we model the direct effects of the NC components, i.e. supplier relationship initiation, development, and ending capabilities, on product innovation. According to the results (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">6</ref>, row 'overall'), supplier relationship development capability (H1b; β=0.324, t-value=2.600) has a significant and positive effect on product innovation in support of H1b. However, the effects of supplier relationship initiation (H1a; β=0.043, t-value=0.630) and ending (H1c; β=0.135, t-value=1.407) capabilities on product innovation are not significant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INSERT TABLE 6</head><p>To understand the robustness of these results with regard to the components of NC, i.e. supplier relationship initiation, development, and ending capabilities, a latent class analysis was conducted using finite mixture modeling in PLS (FIMIX PLS) <ref type="bibr">(Hair et al., 2012a</ref><ref type="bibr">, Money et al., 2012)</ref>. This analysis allows detecting whether any meaningful segments exist within the sample for which the strength, direction, as well as statistical significance differ for the estimated model. It represents a homogeneity test as overall results often mask more finegrained details <ref type="bibr">(Hair et al., 2012a)</ref>. In particular, the latent class analysis is aimed at understanding whether the non-significant results for H1a and H1c are a result of such a 'masking' and thus spurious, or if they are replicated in a rigorous FIMIX analysis. To determine the appropriate number of segments, a range of indices are used; most importantly the Akaike's Information Criterion (AIC) and Bayesian Information Criteria (BIC) should be minimized, while the entropy statistic <ref type="bibr">(Ramaswamy et al., 1993)</ref>, measuring the degree of separation between the estimated individual cluster probabilities (defined between 0 to 1), should be maximized <ref type="bibr">(Hair et al., 2012a)</ref>. In addition, Sarstedt and Ringle (2010) suggest that in order to avoid "unreasonable FIMIX-PLS results, a useful indicator is the small size of additional segments" (p. 1303). Table <ref type="table">7</ref> shows the different index values for solutions with two to five clusters, altogether pointing to the existence of two dominant segments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INSERT TABLE 7</head><p>In Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">6</ref>, we contrast the PLS results of the NC component path model between the two segments (n=27) and (n=129). The sample size of segment 1 is relatively small, however, PLS permits path modeling with smaller sample sizes, but the results need to be interpreted tentatively <ref type="bibr">(Hair et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">2012a</ref><ref type="bibr">, 2012b)</ref>. Our comparison shows that the impact of supplier relationship initiation (β=0.250, t-value=2.431) and ending capabilities (β=0.426, t-value=3.812) on product innovation are strong positive and significant for segment 2, while that of supplier relationship development capability is insignificant (β=-0.082, t-value=1.020).</p><p>Vice versa, segment 1 shows a strong positive and significant effect of supplier relationship development capability on product innovation (β=0.740, t-value=5.259), while the effects of supplier relationship initiation (β=-0.216, t-value=1.357) and ending capabilities are insignificant <ref type="bibr">(β=-0.192, t-value=1.022)</ref>. The observed differences in the effects of the three NC components on product innovation are significantly different . The effect of product innovation on firm performance is positive and significant for both segments (segment 1: β=0.355, t-value=2.378; segment 2: β=0.524, t-value=7.605) and not significantly different between the two segments (t-value=1.045), which is in line with the findings for the overall sample. The FIMIX results therefore indicate the existence of two groups of firms in the automotive parts industry in Iran, which use different combinations of the components of networking capability to leverage their product innovations through supply relationships.</p><p>To further investigate the two segments as well as explore their consequence, we carry out a further FIMIX analysis, first in terms of the performance of the segments with respect to our focal constructs, i.e. firm performance and product innovation, and secondly in terms of control variables in particular firm size, firm age, and the availability of alternative supply partners. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">8</ref> provides an overview of our findings. The results show that there is no significant difference between the two segments for firm performance and product innovation.</p><p>These results indicate that both approaches present viable (equifinal) manifestations of NC with regard to fostering product innovation success and achieving higher firm performance. Furthermore, we were not able to detect any significant difference between the two segments in terms of firm size, firm age, or the availability of alternative supply partners.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INSERT TABLE 8</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Discussion and Theoretical Contributions</head><p>This study uses a sample of 156 firms in the Iranian automotive supplier industry to test the relationship between NC, product innovation, and firm performance as well as the role of relationship proclivity. The results for the overall sample show that NC has a positive effect on product innovation. Furthermore, relationship proclivity amplifies the positive effect of NC on product innovation. A more detailed analysis at the NC component level reveals that overall only NC routines oriented at developing existing supply relationships influence product innovations. However, these results are further qualified by a more detailed latent class analysis, which identifies two subgroups among the surveyed firms: in one subgroup product innovation results purely from relationship development capabilities, while in the other (larger) subgroup initiation and ending capabilities are positively related to product innovation, with development capabilities showing no significant impact. We therefore provide evidence of a 'masking effect' when analyzing the overall sample <ref type="bibr">(Hair et al., 2012a)</ref>.</p><p>This study informs research on supplier networks <ref type="bibr">(Harland and Knight, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mills et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Smart et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Johnsen, 2011)</ref> by introducing a dynamic capability framework that provides an understanding for how firms can manage the composition of their supplier portfolio. We argue that such dynamic supplier relationship management allows firms to continuously align their resource base with their innovation resource needs. We extend existing knowledge about such networking-related capabilities (e.g. <ref type="bibr">Ritter et al., 2002</ref><ref type="bibr">Ritter et al., , 2003</ref><ref type="bibr">Ritter et al., , 2004;;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mort and Weerawardena, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Walter et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mitrega and</ref><ref type="bibr">Pfajfar, 2015, Forkmann et al., 2016)</ref> by empirically illustrating their importance with respect to supplier relationships, in particular for product innovation, which mediates around one third of the effect of NC on firm performance. Furthermore, we empirically show that distinct components of NC suggested by <ref type="bibr">Mitrega et al. (2012)</ref>, namely relationship initiation capability, relationship development capability, and relationship ending capability, have different performance implications for product innovation. While in the overall sample, only the effect of relationship development capabilities on product innovation is significant, our more fine-grained FIMIX analysis found that this result masks two underlying mechanisms, suggesting that firms may use two different 'recipes for success' in supplier relationship management <ref type="bibr">(Dittrich and Duysters, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mesquita et al., 2008)</ref>, both of which can be equally successful (equifinality). Thus, NC and its three components provide firms with 'ingredients' which can be combined in different 'recipes', i.e. NC configurations, as part of choosing how to use them.</p><p>Our results further indicate that the organizational attitudes moderate the effect of NC on product innovation. We specifically show how relationship proclivity amplifies the effectiveness of NC. Thus, if external partnerships are perceived as important drivers of firm success, networking capabilities are utilized better, while low relationship proclivity dampens the effectiveness of NC. This result is in line with research in management that suggests the importance of alignment between organizational attitudes and capabilities for firm performance <ref type="bibr">(Schein, 2010)</ref>. Our research thus extends the literature on networking-related capabilities (e.g. <ref type="bibr">Ritter 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mitrega et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Forkmann et al., 2016)</ref> by examining an important contingency factor for their deployment.</p><p>The results of our FIMIX analysis provide tentative support for the thesis that firms may implement distinct networking capabilities in different ways to achieve product innovation and ultimately firm performance. The two resulting clusters of firms identified in our research seem to be based on very different supplier portfolio management mechanisms. In the first cluster of firms, which represents a small proportion of our empirical dataset (n=27), product innovation success is driven by NC routines aimed at existing collaborative supply partnerships, i.e. these firms leverage their product innovation within the boundaries of their current supplier relationship portfolio. We call this mechanism 'static optimization'. In the second and larger cluster (n=129), firms benefit mainly from implementing NC routines aimed towards reconfiguring their supplier relationship portfolios by terminating selected partnerships and initiating new ones. We call this mechanism 'dynamic optimization'. Our exploratory latent class analysis research results do not explain if these two optimization mechanisms are intentionally chosen by those firms or not.</p><p>However, the overall results provide a contribution in the area of dynamic capabilities aimed at managing supply relationship portfolios by suggesting that not only supplier development with existing partners within the portfolio contribute to success <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Wagner, 2006)</ref> but that also the dynamic reconfiguration of the supplier relationship portfolio itself may be an effective strategy in supply chain management. We see our research results in line with the 'exploitation' versus 'exploration' approaches previously discussed in research on interorganizational learning <ref type="bibr">(Lavie and Rosenkopf, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mesquita et al., 2008)</ref> as well as collaborative innovation <ref type="bibr">(Dittrich and Duysters, 2007)</ref>. Both of these networking approaches are fostering product innovation, but exploitation is status-quo-oriented, usually taking the form of technology refinement in existing (inter-)organizational settings, whereas exploration is dynamic and demands new resources and competences (e.g. to enable radical new product designs), which might be acquired by forming new supplier relationships <ref type="bibr">(Lavie and Rosenkopf, 2006)</ref>. Our research results suggest that such an orientation towards forming new supply partnerships as well as ending non-performing ones is indeed a valuable strategic option for firms. In fact, our analysis shows that firms utilizing a dynamic optimization approach can be as successful as firms utilizing a static optimization approach.</p><p>In sum, our research results provide evidence for the positive influence of networking capabilities on product innovation, as well as overall firm success. At the same time, the research illustrates that such capabilities may be applied in various combinations in the context of supplier relationship portfolio management, as well as highlights the key role of organizational attitudes regarding the importance of relationships for firm success. We believe that our research also corresponds with the need to make today's supply chains more agile <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Van Hoek et al., 2001)</ref>, thereby facilitating the adjustment and flexibility of the supply chain with regard to turbulent environments. As all business relationships lose, sooner or later, their value and become costs <ref type="bibr">(Capaldo, 2007)</ref>, the most successful firms may need to maneuver over time between various approaches to using NC in supply relationships.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Managerial Contributions</head><p>Our study contributes to managerial knowledge by illustrating the need for a selective approach with regard to networking-related routines in a product innovation context. As distinct networking mechanisms for supply relationship portfolio management emerge from our analysis, this study suggests that managers should devote equal attention to strengthening existing relationships on the supply side as well as to initiating new partnerships (e.g. screening for promising partners and signaling their firms' relationship value to attract new counterparts) and managing fading relationships (e.g. by developing routines to exit from sub-optimal relationships). Additionally, as relationship termination processes are often neglected in management practice, partly due to the mind-set embedded in some organizational cultures <ref type="bibr">(Ritter and Geersbro, 2011)</ref>, our study calls for greater managerial interest in concrete organizational routines that may be useful for disengaging from those supply relationships that are no longer fruitful in terms of their impact on product innovation. In this context, firms should also heed the fact that capabilities themselves are only one aspect of successful management but that certain attitudes, in our case relationship proclivity, are important success factors in utilizing these capabilities. It is therefore pivotal to provide training, education and incentives to instill a management mindset, which embraces business relationships but also allows for a flexible dealing with under-performing relational partners.</p><p>Our results show two different mechanisms of how firms utilize NC for supply relationship management. The results indicate that most firms in our dataset do not follow a static approach of exploitation with regard to supplier relationship management. A practical implication of equifinal NC configurations regarding supplier relationship management implies that a 'one-size-fits-all approach' for enhancing product innovation does not exist. Thus, firms can choose which of the NC configurations fits best with their characteristics as well as their business environment</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Limitations and Future Research</head><p>Our research is focused on one setting (i.e. the automotive industry in Iran). Therefore, while such a specific research design allows us to control for many parameters, it limits the generalizability of the findings. Further studies need to broaden our findings to other industries and countries, specifically those which show a different cultural make-up from Iran. It also needs to be noted that after the data collection period, the Iranian automotive industry suffered considerably from more stringent sanctions, with car/bus production falling to just under 800,000 units in 2015 (from a high of over 1.5m in 2011) (Ministry of Industry, <ref type="bibr">Mine and Trade, 2016)</ref>. Therefore, our findings (relating to a period of growth in the industry) are not representative for the downturn and contraction period. However, as sanctions have again been lifted in 2016, it can be expected that the Iranian car industry will return to a growth trajectory.</p><p>Our research design also has some advantages and disadvantages. Our sample of firms is not very large but is adequate in relation to the size of the automotive supply industry in Iran <ref type="bibr">(Azar et al., 2010)</ref> and larger in comparison to other studies in this area (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Wagner, 2006)</ref>.</p><p>We also provide evidence that non-response bias was not a problem in our research. Using cross-functional survey data is always problematic but we tried to mitigate against such risk by applying a multiple-informant research design. We also controlled for this problem by testing common method variance. Taking into consideration that we concentrated on cross-sectional data and phenomena that are not directly observable, our analyses were not causal in a rigorous sense <ref type="bibr">(Iacobucci, 2009)</ref>. Furthermore, our findings indicate the existence of two distinct mechanisms as to how different aspects of NC impact product innovation. While it is reasonable to identify these mechanisms as networking 'strategies', it is unclear whether or not these are intended by those firms or are emerging <ref type="bibr">(Mintzberg and Waters, 1985)</ref>. Additionally, our analysis through PLS-FIMIX did not reveal any descriptive and explanatory variables, which can be used to understand the differences between the firm clusters better. Thus, further research needs to ascertain if supply chain managers intentionally choose to focus on certain aspects of NC as part of supplier relationship portfolio management, and what the contingencies for such strategies are. For example, further research may test the relative influence of networking capabilities on a wider set of supply chain performance measures, including operational and purchasing costs, and supply chain agility, or the appropriateness of different NC configurations for radical versus incremental product innovations.  Geisser, S., <ref type="bibr">(1974)</ref>. "A predictive approach to the random effects model". Biometrika, 61(1), 101-107.</p><p> Granovetter, M., <ref type="bibr">(1985)</ref>. "Economic action and social structure: The problem of embeddedness". American Journal of Sociology, 91(3), 481-510.</p><p> Gu, F.F., Hung, K, &amp; Tse, D.K., <ref type="bibr">(2008)</ref>. "When does Guanxi matter? Issues of capitalization and its dark sides". Journal of Marketing, 72(4), 12-28.</p><p> Gulati, R., <ref type="bibr">(1998)</ref>. "Alliances and networks". Strategic Management Journal, 19(4), 293-317.</p><p> Gulati, R., <ref type="bibr">(1999)</ref>  Ramaswamy, V., DeSarbo, W.S., Reibstein, D.J., &amp; Robinson, W.T., <ref type="bibr">(1993)</ref>. "An empirical pooling approach for estimating marketing mix elasticities with PIMS data". Marketing Science, 12(1), 103-124.</p><p> Ramsay, J., <ref type="bibr">Wagner, B., &amp; Kelly, S., (2013)</ref>  Stone, M., <ref type="bibr">(1974)</ref>. "Cross-validatory choice and assessment of statistical predictions".</p><p>Journal of the Royal Statistical Society, 36(2), 111-147.</p><p> Szwejczewski, M., <ref type="bibr">Lemke, F., &amp; Goffin, K., (2005)</ref>. "Manufacturer-supplier relationships:</p><p>An empirical study of German manufacturing companies". International Journal of <ref type="bibr">Operations &amp; Production Management, 25(9), 875-897.  Tähtinen, J., &amp; Halinen, A., (2002)</ref>. "Research on ending exchange relationships: A categorization, assessment and outlook". Marketing Theory, 2(2), 165-188.  To what degree do you agree with the following statements (Strongly Disagree (1) -Strongly Agree (7)):</p><p>Our company has established a formal system to identify Supply partners where key performance indicators or agreed milestones are not met. .758</p><p>Our company has a formal system in place to assess the profit and cost associated with existing Supply partners relationships.</p><p>.842</p><p>We systematically rank our Supply partners according to their performance.</p><p>.841</p><p>We analyse the direct and indirect costs involved in terminating a business relationship with our Supply partners (e.g. searching for new Supply partners, new investments, penalties, etc.).</p><p>.823 To what degree do you agree with the following statements (Strongly Disagree (1) -Strongly Agree ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>)):</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplier</head><p>Our company has established formal procedures for how to discontinue relationships with unwanted Supply partners.</p><p>.806</p><p>Our company formalizes termination conditions within the contracts between us and our Supply partners.</p><p>.868</p><p>If we have to terminate a relationship with a Supply partner, we first try to achieve a mutual understanding of the situation and reasons leading to the partnership's discontinuation.</p><p>.822</p><p>Our company has established procedures for how to phase out business relationships with Supply partners that are not desirable any more.</p><p>.878 <ref type="bibr">et al., 2012 (adapted)</ref> VE = 62.627 α = .795</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Product Innovation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Shu</head><p>To what degree do you agree with the following statements (Strongly Disagree (1) -Strongly Agree (7)):</p><p>Our company continuously improves the quality of its products.</p><p>.679</p><p>Our company continuously introduces new products and develops markets.</p><p>.779</p><p>We care a great deal about the new technology breakthroughs.</p><p>.854</p><p>The company is a pioneer in developing new markets.</p><p>.841</p><p>The number of new products introduced in the past three years increased steadily.</p><p>-</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Relationship Proclivity</head><p>Johnson and <ref type="bibr">Sohi, 2001 (adapted)</ref> To what degree do you agree with the following statements (Strongly Disagree (1) -Strongly Agree (7)):</p><p>Closer partner-type relationships with Supply partners offer a major advantage in doing business.</p><p>.808   </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(i.e. inter-organizational and inter-personal) and ending (i.e. preparation and process) capabilities were adapted from Mitrega et al. (2012) to the supplier context. The mediating construct of product innovation was measured with scales from Shu et al. (2012) based on Li and Atuahene-Gima (</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Mitrega</head><label></label><figDesc><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">et al. (2012) and</ref> Forkmann et al. (2016), but rather jointly reflect one common construct of supplier relationship development capability. We attribute this finding to the specific context of our study (i.e. Iranian automotive industry). The business culture in the Middle East (i.e. Iran) often does not exhibit a clear distinction between inter-personal and inter-organizational relationship management. This is expected as Iran tends strongly towards the collectivist end on the cultural continuum of individualism-collectivism(House et al.,   2004). In such a context, top managements' personal networks become a key competitive advantage for the firm, since many of the key decisions are made through lobbying within such personal networks. Similar observations can be made in the business cultures in Far East Asia, i.e. Guanxi in China(Gu et al., 2008). Furthermore, while Mitrega et al. (2012) did not find any empirical support for their original conceptualization of relationship ending capability as being two-dimensional in nature, our EFA results suggest that respondents distinguished between the ending preparation and the ending process in line with findings by Forkmann et al. (2016) and Zaefarian et al. (2016), thereby justifying the existence of two distinct sub-components for relationship ending. Our findings differ from Mitrega et al. (2012) as we specifically sample purchasing managers similarly to Forkmann et al. (2016) and Zaefarian et al. (2016). The more general sampling frame of Mitrega et al. (2012) may have masked the dimensionality of the construct.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Birou, L.M., &amp; Fawcett, S.E., (1994). "Supplier involvement in integrated product development: A comparison of US and European practices". International Journal of PhysicalDistribution &amp; Logistics Management, 24(5), 4-14. Bohlmann, J. D., Spanjol, J.,Qualls, W. J., &amp; Rosa, J. A., (2013). "The interplay of customer and product innovation dynamics: An exploratory study". Journal of Product Innovation Management, 30(2), 228-244. Brislin, R.W.,(1970). "Back-translation for cross-cultural research". Journal of Crosscultural Psychology, 1(3),185-216.    Capaldo, A., (2007). "Network structure and innovation: The leveraging of a dual network as a distinctive relational capability". Strategic Management Journal, 28(6), 585-608. Chang, S.-J.,Van Witteloostuijn, A., &amp; Eden, L., (2010). "From the editors: Common method variance in international business research". Journal of International Business Studies, 41(2), 178-184.  Cheng, C. C. J., &amp; Huizingh, E. K. R. E., (2014). "When is open innovation beneficial? The role of strategic orientation". Journal of Product Innovation Management, 31(6), 1235-1253.  Chesbrough, H.W., (2003). "The era of open innovation". MIT Sloan Management Review, 44(3), 35-41.  Cousins, P.D., Handfield, R.B., Lawson, B., &amp; Petersen, K.J., (2006). "Creating supply chain relational capital: The impact of formal and informal socialization processes". Journal of Operations Management, 24(6), 851-863.  Da Silveira, G.J., &amp; Arkader, R., (2007). "The direct and mediated relationships between supply chain coordination investments and delivery performance". International Journal of Operations &amp; Production Management, 27(2), 140-158.  Eckerd, S., &amp; Hill, J.A., (2012). "The buyer-supplier social contract: Information sharing as a deterrent to unethical behaviors". International Journal of Operations &amp; Production Management, 32(2), 238-255.  Edvardsson, B., Holmlund, M., &amp; Strandvik, T., (2008). "Initiation of business relationships in service-dominant settings". Industrial Marketing Management, 37(3), 339-350.  Eisenhardt, K.M., &amp; Martin, J.A., (2000). "Dynamic capabilities: What are they?". Strategic Management Journal, 21(10/11), 1105-1121.  Fontana, R., Geuna, A., &amp; Matt, M., (2006). "Factors affecting university-industry R&amp;D projects: The importance of searching, screening and signaling". Research Policy, 35(2), 309-323.  Forkmann, S., Wang, D., Henneberg, S.C, Naudé, P., &amp; Sutcliffe, A., (2012). "Strategic decision making in business relationships: A dyadic agent-based simulation approach". Industrial Marketing Management, 41(5), 816-830.  Forkmann, S., Henneberg, S. C., Naudé, P., &amp; Mitrega, M., (2016). "Supplier relationship management capability: A qualification and extension". Industrial Marketing Management, 57, 185-200  Fornell, C., &amp; Cha, J., (1994). "Partial least squares". in: Advanced Methods of Marketing Research, R.P. Bagozzi (ed.), Oxford: Blackwell, 52-78.  Fornell, C., &amp; Larcker, D.F., (1981). "Evaluating structural equation models with unobservable variables and measurement error". Journal of Marketing Research, 18(1), 39-50.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. "Network location and learning: The influence of network resources and firm capabilities on alliance formation". Strategic Management Journal, 20(5), 397-420. Hair, J.F., Black, W.C., Babin, B.J., &amp; Anderson, R.E.,(2009). Multivariate Data Analysis (7th ed.). New York: Prentice Hall. Hair, J.F.,Ringle, C.M., &amp; Sarstedt, M., (2011). "PLS-SEM: Indeed a silver bullet". Journal of Marketing Theory and Practice, 19(2), 139-152.  Hair, J.F., Sarstedt, M., Ringle, C.M., &amp; Mena, J.A., (2012a). "An assessment of the use of partial least squares structural equation modeling in marketing research". Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science, 40(3), 414-433.  Hair, J.F., Sarstedt, M., Pieper, T.M., &amp; Ringle, C.M., (2012b). "The use of partial least squares structural equation modeling in strategic management research: A review of the past practices and recommendations for future applications". Long Range Planning, 45(5-6), 320-340. Håkansson, H., &amp; Ford, D., (2002). "How should companies interact in business networks?". Journal of Business Research, 55(2), 133-139. Han, J. K., Kim, N., &amp; Srivastava, R.K.,(1998). "Market orientation and organizational performance: Is innovation a missing link?". Journal of Marketing, 62(4), 30-45. Hauser, J.,Tellis, G., &amp; Griffin, A., (2006). "Research on innovation: A review and agenda for marketing science". Marketing Science, 25(6), 687-717.  Jean, R.-J., Sinkovics, R.R., &amp; Hiebaum, T.P., (2014). "The effect of supplier involvement and knowledge protection on product innovation in customer-supplier relationships: A study of global automotive supplier in China". Journal of Product Innovation Management, 31(1), 98-113.  Johnsen, T.E., (2011). "Supply network delegation and intervention strategies during supplier involvement in new product development". International Journal of Operations &amp; Production Management, 31(6), 686-708.  Johnson, J.L., &amp; Sohi, R.S., (2001). "The influence of firm predispositions on interfirm relationship formation in business markets". International Journal of Research in Marketing, 18(4), 299-318.  Johnson, J.L., (1999). "Strategic integration in industrial distribution channels: Managing the interfirm relationship as a strategic asset". Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science, 27(1), 4-18.  Jöreskog, K.G., &amp; Sörbom, D., (2006). LISREL 8.80 for Windows [Computer software]. Lincolnwood, IL: Scientific Software International.  Joshi, A.W., (2009). "Continuous supplier performance improvement: Effects of collaborative communication and control". Journal of Marketing, 73(1), 133-150.  Kale, P., Dyer, J.H., &amp; Singh, H., (2002). "Alliance capability, stock market response, and long-term alliance success: The role of the alliance function". Strategic Management Journal, 23(8), 747-767.  Kale. P., &amp; Singh, H., (2007). "Building firm capabilities through learning: The role of the alliance learning process in alliance capability and firm-level alliance success". Strategic Management Journal, 28(10), 981-1000.  Ketchen, D.J., &amp; Hult, G.T.H., (2007). "Bridging organization theory and supply chain management: The case of best value supply chains". Journal of Operations Management, 25(2), 573-580.  Killing, P., (2012). Strategies for Joint Venture Success (RLE International Business) (Vol. 22): Routledge.  King, B.E., &amp; Penlesky, R.J., (1992). "Impediments to timely delivery of new products at an industrial products firm". International Journal of Operations &amp; Production Management, 12(10), 56-65.  La Rocca, A., Ford, D., &amp; Snehota, I., (2013). "Initial relationship development in new business ventures". Industrial Marketing Management, 42(7), 1025-1032.  Lavie, D., &amp; Rosenkopf, L., (2006). "Balancing exploration and exploitation in alliance formation". Academy of Management Journal, 49(4), 797-818.  Lavie, D., (2007). "Alliance portfolios and firm performance: A study of value creation and appropriation in the US software industry". Strategic Management Journal, 28(12), 1187-1212.  Lawson, B., Petersen, K.J., Cousins, P.D., &amp; Handfield, R.B., (2009). "Knowledge sharing in interorganizational product development teams: The effect of formal and informal socialization mechanisms". Journal of Product Innovation Management, 26(2), 156-172.  Lawson, B., Tyler, B.B., &amp; Potter, A., (2015). "Strategic suppliers' technical contribution to new product advantage: Substitution and configuration options". Journal of Product Innovation Management, 32(5), 760-776. Li, H., &amp; Atuahene-Gima, K.,(2001). innovation strategy and the performance of new technology ventures in China". Academy of ManagementJournal, 44(6), 1123Journal, 44(6),  -1134.  .   </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. "Purchase offering quality: The effects of buyer behaviour on organizational supplying behavior". International Journal of Operations &amp; Production Management, 33(10), 1260-1282.  Reinartz, W., Krafft, M., &amp; Hoyer, W.D., (2004). "The customer relationship management process: Its measurement and impact on performance". Journal of Marketing Research, 41(3), 293-305.  Reinartz, W., Haenlein, M., &amp; Henseler, J., (2009). "An empirical comparison of the efficacy of covariance-based and variance-based SEM". International Journal of Research in Marketing, 26(4), 332-344.  Ringle, C.M., Wende, S., &amp; Becker, J.M., (2014). Smartpls 3. Hamburg: SmartPLS.  Ritter, T., (1999). "The networking company: Antecedents for coping with relationships and networks effectively". Industrial Marketing Management, 28(5), 467-479.  Ritter, T., &amp; Geersbro, J., (2011). "Organizational relationship termination competence: A conceptualization and an empirical test". Industrial Marketing Management, 40(6), 988-993.  Ritter, T., &amp; Gemünden, H.G., (2003). "Network competence: Its impact on innovation success and its antecedents". Journal of Business Research, 56(9), 745-755.  Ritter, T., &amp; Gemünden, H.G., (2004). "The impact of a company's business strategy on its technological competence, network competence and innovation success". Journal of Business Research, 57(5), 548-556.  Ritter, T., Wilkinson, I.F., &amp; Johnston, W.J., (2002). "Measuring network competence: Some international evidence". Journal of Business &amp; Industrial Marketing, 17(2/3), 119-138.  Sarstedt, M., &amp; Ringle, C.M., (2010). "Treating unobserved heterogeneity in PLS path modeling: A comparison of FIMIX-PLS with different data analysis strategies". Journal of Applied Statistics, 37(8), 1299-1318.  Schein, E.H., (2010). Organizational Culture and Leadership (Vol. 2): John Wiley &amp; Sons.  Schilling, M.A. and Phelps, C.C., (2007). "Interfirm collaboration networks: The impact of large-scale network structure on firm innovation". Management Science, 53(7), 1113-1126.  Shu, C., Page, A.L., Gao, S., &amp; Jiang, X., (2012). "Managerial ties and firm innovation: Is knowledge creation a missing link?". Journal of Product Innovation Management, 29(1), 125-143.  Sjoerdsma, M., &amp; van Weele, A., (2015). "Managing supplier relationships in a new product development context". Journal of Purchasing &amp; Supply Management, 21(3), 192-203.  Smart, P., Bessant, J., &amp; Gupta, A., (2007). "Towards technological rules for designing innovation networks: A dynamic capabilities view". International Journal of Operations &amp; Production Management, 27(10), 1069-1092.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIGURE 1 Nomological Model</figDesc><graphic coords="52,117.65,127.20,360.00,244.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE 1 Overview of Sample Characteristics</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Share</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 5 PLS Estimation of Structural Model</head><label>5</label><figDesc>β, b t, *** p&lt;0.01, ** p&lt;0.05, * p&lt;0.1</figDesc><table><row><cell>Main Effects</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>NC  Product Innovation</cell><cell>0.332 a ***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(3.716) b</cell></row><row><cell>Product Innovation  Firm Performance</cell><cell>0.297***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(3.552)</cell></row><row><cell>NC  Firm Performance</cell><cell>0.211**</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(2.394)</cell></row><row><cell>Relationship Proclivity  Product Innovation</cell><cell>0.020</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.303)</cell></row><row><cell>Interaction Effects</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>NC × Relationship Proclivity  Product Innovation</cell><cell>0.119**</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(2.122)</cell></row><row><cell>Control Variables</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Availability of Alternative Supply Partners  Product Innovation</cell><cell>0.198**</cell></row><row><cell>Success</cell><cell>(2.487)</cell></row><row><cell>Availability of Alternative Supply Partners  Firm Performance</cell><cell>0.173**</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(2.428)</cell></row><row><cell>Firm Size  Product Innovation</cell><cell>0.105*</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.774)</cell></row><row><cell>Firm Size  Firm Performance</cell><cell>0.062</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.277)</cell></row><row><cell>Firm Age  Product Innovation</cell><cell>0.082</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.367)</cell></row><row><cell>Firm Age  Firm Performance</cell><cell>0.077</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.541)</cell></row><row><cell>R 2 (Product Innovation)</cell><cell>0.290</cell></row><row><cell>R 2 (Firm Performance)</cell><cell>0.294</cell></row><row><cell>Q 2 (Product Innovation)</cell><cell>0.118</cell></row><row><cell>Q 2 (Firm Performance)</cell><cell>0.191</cell></row></table><note><p>a</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>TABLE 6 PLS Estimation of NC Components Structural Model and Corresponding FIMIX Results of Two Latent Segments</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Overall</cell><cell>FIMIX</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Segment 1 (N=27)</cell><cell>Segment 2 (N=129)</cell><cell>t[W-S]</cell></row></table><note><p>a β, b t, *** p&lt;0.01, ** p&lt;0.05, * p&lt;0.1; t[W-S] = Welch-Satterthwait t-value for multi-group comparison test.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>TABLE 8 FIMIX Segment Characteristics</head><label>8</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Overall Segment 1</cell><cell>Segment 2</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(N=27)</cell><cell>(N=129)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Firm Performance</cell><cell>5.30</cell><cell>4.94</cell><cell>5.37</cell><cell>t=-1.233</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>p=0.228</cell></row><row><cell>Product Innovation</cell><cell>5.52</cell><cell>5.51</cell><cell>5.52</cell><cell>t=-0.038</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>p=0.970</cell></row><row><cell>Number of Employees 10 or less</cell><cell>2.7%</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>3.3%</cell><cell>Χ 2 =3.785</cell></row><row><cell>11-25</cell><cell>10.2%</cell><cell>7.7%</cell><cell>10.7%</cell><cell>pexact=0.698</cell></row><row><cell>26-50</cell><cell>19.7%</cell><cell>26.9%</cell><cell>18.2%</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>51-250</cell><cell>38.1%</cell><cell>30.8%</cell><cell>39.7%</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>251-750</cell><cell>22.5%</cell><cell>30.8%</cell><cell>20.7%</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>751-5000</cell><cell>6.1%</cell><cell>3.8%</cell><cell>6.6%</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>5001 or above</cell><cell>0.7%</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>0.8%</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean</cell><cell>292.73</cell><cell>215.92</cell><cell>309.23</cell><cell>t=-0.711</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>p=0.478</cell></row><row><cell>Company Age 0 -&lt;2</cell><cell>2.7%</cell><cell>3.8%</cell><cell>2.4%</cell><cell>Χ 2 =4.072</cell></row><row><cell>2 -&lt;5</cell><cell>7.4%</cell><cell>3.8%</cell><cell>8.1%</cell><cell>pexact=0.540</cell></row><row><cell>5 -&lt;10</cell><cell>15.4%</cell><cell>23.1%</cell><cell>13.8%</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>10 -&lt;20</cell><cell>34.2%</cell><cell>42.3%</cell><cell>32.5%</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>20 -&lt;50</cell><cell>38.9%</cell><cell>26.9%</cell><cell>41.5%</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>50 or more</cell><cell>1.4%</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>1.6%</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean</cell><cell>17.66</cell><cell>16.04</cell><cell>18.00</cell><cell>t=-0.779</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>p=0.437</cell></row><row><cell>Availability of Alternatives</cell><cell>4.59</cell><cell>4.52</cell><cell>4.61</cell><cell>t=-0.229</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>p=0.820</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div><p><rs type="person"> Das</rs>, T. K., <rs type="person">&amp; Teng</rs>, B.-S., (2000). "A resource-based theory of strategic alliances". Journal of Management, 26(1), <rs type="grantNumber">31-61</rs>.   <rs type="person"> Dhanaraj</rs>, <rs type="person">C.</rs>, <rs type="person">&amp; Parkhe</rs>, A., (<rs type="grantNumber">2006</rs>), "<rs type="projectName">Orchestrating innovation networks". Academy of Management Review</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">31</rs>(3), <rs type="grantNumber">659-669</rs>. <rs type="person"> Diamantopoulos</rs>, <rs type="person">A.</rs>, <rs type="person">&amp; Winklhofer</rs>, H.M., (2001). "Index construction with formative indicators: An alternative to scale development". Journal of Marketing Research, 38(2), <rs type="grantNumber">269-277</rs>. <rs type="person"> Diamantopoulos</rs>, A., (2008). "Formative indicators: Introduction to the special issue". Journal of Business Research, 61(12), <rs type="grantNumber">1201-1202</rs>. <rs type="person"> Dittrich</rs>, K., &amp; Duysters, G., (2007). "Networking as a means to strategy change: The case of open innovation in mobile telephony". Journal of Product Innovation Management, 24(6), <rs type="grantNumber">510-521</rs>. <rs type="person"> Drnevich</rs>, P.L., <rs type="person">&amp; Kriauciunas</rs>, A.P., (2011). "Clarifying the conditions and limits of the contributions of ordinary and dynamic capabilities to relative firm performance". Strategic Management Journal, 32(3), <rs type="grantNumber">254-279</rs>. <rs type="person"> Dwyer</rs>, F.R., Schurr, P.H., <rs type="person">&amp; Oh</rs>, S., (<rs type="grantNumber">1987</rs>). "Developing buyer-seller relationships". Journal of Marketing, 51(2), <rs type="grantNumber">11-27</rs>. <rs type="person"> Dyer</rs>, <rs type="person">J.H.</rs>, <rs type="person">&amp; Singh</rs>, H., (1998). "The relational view: Cooperative strategy and sources of interorganizational competitive advantage". Academy of Management Review, 23(4), <rs type="grantNumber">660-679</rs>. <rs type="person"> Dyer</rs>, <rs type="person">J.H.</rs>, <rs type="person">&amp; Hatch</rs>, N.W., (<rs type="grantNumber">2006</rs>). "Relation-specific capabilities and barriers to knowledge transfers: Creating advantage through network relationships". Strategic Management Journal, 27(8), <rs type="grantNumber">701-719</rs>.  Easterby-Smith, M., Lyles, M.A., <rs type="person">&amp; Peteraf</rs>, M.A., (2009). "Dynamic capabilities: Current debates and future directions". British Journal of Management, 20(s1), <rs type="grantNumber">1-8</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_FJhyFM5">
					<idno type="grant-number">31-61</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_X5s6SMm">
					<idno type="grant-number">2006</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Orchestrating innovation networks&quot;. Academy of Management Review</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_HuJ5WJD">
					<idno type="grant-number">31</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_cqSyPcm">
					<idno type="grant-number">659-669</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_PYd9HXx">
					<idno type="grant-number">269-277</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_WN9rBBs">
					<idno type="grant-number">1201-1202</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_jxjagES">
					<idno type="grant-number">510-521</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_jrPWv7j">
					<idno type="grant-number">254-279</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_YxeV8Vc">
					<idno type="grant-number">1987</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_Ys6KEwb">
					<idno type="grant-number">11-27</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_qXTQrNh">
					<idno type="grant-number">660-679</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_fD9ATmJ">
					<idno type="grant-number">2006</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_Tp5SSpg">
					<idno type="grant-number">701-719</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_s9X6n8T">
					<idno type="grant-number">1-8</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p> Harland, C.M., &amp; Knight, L. <ref type="bibr">A., (2001)</ref>. "Supply network strategy: Role and competence requirements". International Journal of <ref type="bibr">Operations &amp; Production Management,</ref><ref type="bibr">21(4)</ref>, 476-489.</p><p> Havila, V., &amp; Medlin, C.J., <ref type="bibr">(2012)</ref>. "Ending-competence in business closure". Industrial Marketing <ref type="bibr">Management,</ref><ref type="bibr">41(3)</ref>, 413-420.</p><p> Hennart, J.F., <ref type="bibr">Roehl, T., &amp; Zietlow, D.S., (1999)</ref>. "'Trojan horse' or 'Workhorse'? The evolution of US-Japanese joint ventures in the United States". Strategic Management Journal, 20(1), 15-29.</p><p> Henneberg, S.C., Naudé, P., &amp; Mouzas, S., <ref type="bibr">(2010)</ref>. "Sense-making and management in business networks -Some observations, considerations, and a research agenda". Industrial Marketing Management, 39(3), 355-360.</p><p> Henseler, J., Dijkstra, T.K., Sarstedt, M., Ringle, C.M., Diamantopoulos, A., Straub, D.W., Kecthen Jr., D., Hair, J.F., Hult, G.T., &amp; Calantone, R.J., <ref type="bibr">(2014)</ref>. "Common beliefs and reality about PLS: Comments on Rönkkö and Evermann (2013)". Organizational Research Methods, 1-28.</p><p> House, R.J., Hanges, P.J., Javidan, M., Dorfman, P.W., &amp; Gupta, V., <ref type="bibr">(2004)</ref>. Culture, leadership, and organizations: The GLOBE study of 62 societies: Sage publications.</p><p> Hutt, M.D., <ref type="bibr">Stafford, E.R., Walker, B.A., &amp; Reingen, P.H., (2000)</ref>. "Case study: Defining the social network of a strategic alliance". MIT Sloan Management Review, 41(2), 51-62.</p><p> Iacobucci, D., <ref type="bibr">(2009)</ref>. "Everything you always wanted to know about SEM (structural equations modeling) but were afraid to ask". Journal of Consumer Psychology, 19(4), 673-680.</p><p> Jarvis, C.B., <ref type="bibr">MacKenzie, S.B., &amp; Podsakoff, P.M., (2003)</ref>. "A critical review of construct indicators and measurement model misspecification in marketing and consumer research". <ref type="bibr">Research, 30(2), 199-218.  Lorenzoni, G., &amp; Lipparini, A., (1999)</ref>. "The leveraging of interfirm relationships as a distinctive organizational capability: A longitudinal study <ref type="bibr">". Strategic Management Journal, 20, 317-338.  Mesquita, L.F., Anand, J., &amp; Brush, T.H., (2008)</ref>  Mitrega, M., &amp; Pfajfar, G., <ref type="bibr">(2015)</ref>. "Business relationship process management as company dynamic capability improving relationship portfolio". Industrial Marketing <ref type="bibr">Management, 46, 193-203.  Moeller, S., Fassnacht, M., &amp; Klose, S., (2006)</ref>. "A framework for supplier relationship management (SRM)". Journal of Business-to-Business Marketing, 13(4), 69-94.  To what degree do you agree with the following statements (Strongly Disagree (1) -Strongly Agree ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>)):</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Journal of Consumer</head><p>Our company has a formal system for identifying which of the potential Supply partners are attractive to us.</p><p>.858</p><p>We rank order and short-list potential Supply partners based on their potential to us.</p><p>.911</p><p>We develop a formal list of preferred features of potential Supply partners.</p><p>.749</p><p>We systematically gather and review publicly available information to identify potential Supply partners.</p><p>-We evaluate the resources and capabilities of potential Supply partners.</p><p>-</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplier Relationship Initiation Capability (SRIC) -Attraction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mitrega et al., 2012 (adapted)</head><p>To what degree do you agree with the following statements (Strongly Disagree (1) -Strongly Agree ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>)):</p><p>We promote our company's successes with previous/current Supply partners.</p><p>.788</p><p>We systematically build the image of our company as a "reliable business partner".</p><p>.859</p><p>We systematically inform potential Supply partners about our company's offering.</p><p>.868</p><p>We systematically use recommendations from our existing Supply partners to attract new ones.</p><p>.837</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplier Relationship Development Capability (SRDC) -Inter-company &amp; Inter-personal development</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mitrega et al., 2012 (adapted)</head><p>To what degree do you agree with the following statements (Strongly Disagree (1) -Strongly Agree ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>)):</p><p>We try to customize cooperation with our Supply partners (e.g. technology/product/process adaptations).</p><p>.846</p><p>We try to "lock in" our Supply partners in cooperation with us.</p><p>.799</p><p>We work closely with our Supply partners when developing our offerings.</p><p>.696</p><p>We provide our Supply partners with valuable information that can help them better serve their customers.</p><p>-We continuously communicate with our Supply partners regarding mutual expectations.</p><p>-Our company regularly organizes social events involving representatives from our Supply partners.</p><p>.811</p><p>Our company motivates us to create close personal business ties with representatives from our Supply partners.</p><p>.844</p><p>Our company motivates us to socialize with representatives from our Supply partners at networking events (e.g. trade shows, professional training conferences).</p><p>.813 VE = 66.343 α = .828 Teaming up and working closely with Supply partners allows us to be more effective.</p><p>.874</p><p>It is appropriate to share proprietary information with our Supply partners if it is useful to do so.</p><p>.825</p><p>Most often Supply partners can be trusted to meet their obligations.</p><p>.746</p><p>Most of the time, Supply partners will not take advantage of us.</p><p>-</p><p>The less any Supply partners know about how we do things, the better off we are.    </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic supplier management in the automotive industry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Aláez-Aller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Longás-García</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Operations &amp; Production Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="312" to="335" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating nonresponse bias in mail surveys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Armstrong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Overton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="396" to="402" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design creativity: Static or dynamic capability?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname> Azadegan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bush</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dooley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Operations &amp; Production Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="636" to="662" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The influence of R&amp;D partnerships on innovation in manufacturing firms: The moderating role of institutional attachment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname> Azadegan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Napshin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Oke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Operations &amp; Production Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="248" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship between supply chain quality management practices and their effects on organisational performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Azar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kahnali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Taghavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Singapore Management Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Firm resources and sustained competitive advantage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hierarchical latent variable models in PLS-SEM: Guidelines for using reflective-formative type models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wetzels</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Long Range Planning</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5-6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="394" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Beckman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Haunschild</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Friends or strangers? Firmspecific uncertainty, market uncertainty, and network partner selection</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="275" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Buyer-supplier relations in industrial markets: when do buyers risk making idiosyncratic investments?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bensaou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organization Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="460" to="481" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bridging inter-and intra-firm boundaries: Management of supplier involvement in automobile product development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Takeishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Strategic Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="433" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic capabilities and strategic management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Teece</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pisano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shuen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Strategic Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="509" to="533" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding configurations of relational attractiveness of the customer firm using fuzzy set QCA</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Tóth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Thiesbrummel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Henneberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Naudé</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="723" to="734" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring agile capabilities in the supply chain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Van Hoek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Christopher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Operations &amp; Production Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1/2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="126" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developing supplier integration capabilities for sustainable competitive advantage: A dynamic capabilities approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Vanpoucke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vereecke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wetzels</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Operations Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7/8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="446" to="461" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Involving suppliers in product development: Insights from R&amp;D directors and project managers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hoegl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Industrial Marketing Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="936" to="943" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A firm&apos;s responses to deficient suppliers and competitive advantage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="686" to="695" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of network capabilities and entrepreneurial orientation on university spin-off performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Walter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Auer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ritter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Venturing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="541" to="567" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Balanced relationships: Management of client-supplier relationships in product development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wognum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fisscher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Weenink</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technovation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="351" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Firm Performance FPerf1 .759 FPerf2</title>
		<idno>895 FPerf3 .764 FPerf4 .770</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
